A Boy and His Girl

One o’clock. Then two. Then three. In the library at the head of the stairs, through the limping hours, Mrs. Vivian sat. But now the front door opened and closed. Presently there was the sound of ascending steps.

Mrs. Vivian stood up. “Alfred!”

At the entrance, in evening clothes, a good-looking boy appeared. “Why, mother?” he surprisedly exclaimed.

Mrs. Vivian nodded. “Yes, I can sit up until two, but at three I think everybody ought to be in bed. Perhaps you will be civil enough to agree with me.”

“Certainly, mother, but—”

Mrs. Vivian nodded again. “Very good then, make a soiled breast of it. Who is she?”

In speaking she looked him up and down. Though forty, she appeared twenty-eight. A widow and a rich one, she was handsome, arrogant, commanding and taller, both mentally and physically, than her son.

The boy twisted. “Suppose I tell you tomorrow.”

“It’s tomorrow now.”

“But you don’t know her, and it would take so long to explain.”

“Of course I don’t know her. If I did I would not ask, but I know at least that she is not an old woman, and I know, too, that no decent young woman would keep you up—”

“Mother,” the boy got in, “we had supper and we were talking.”

Mrs. Vivian sniffed. “You had supper at twelve, I suppose, and you have been talking ever since. But no man ever talks to a girl for three hours unless he keeps saying the same thing all the time.”

She paused, half-turned and threw out: “And that thing decent young women don’t listen to.”

“She is perfectly decent,” the boy angrily protested. “She—”

“She’s an angel,” Mrs. Vivian interrupted. “I know the air. But since you don’t seem to be able to tell me who she is, I assume that you can show me her picture. Probably you have it with you now—next to your heart.”

At the suggestion and the sneer of it, the boy flushed, fumbled and fished out a card-case from which he produced a photograph that, for a moment, Mrs. Vivian contemptuously considered.

“A chorus girl, isn’t she?” she asked. “If not she ought to sue the photographer for libel. What’s her name? Mamie? Tottie?”

“Mother!” the boy indignantly corrected. “She is a Miss Pelham.”

“For short, no doubt. But actually Miss Pelham-Clinton or Miss Pelham-Cavendish. That’s it, isn’t it? The daughter of a hundred bankrupts. Where does she live?”

Like a goaded calf, Alfred tossed his head. “She is as good a New Yorker as any of us.”

“And she lives?”

“At The Amsterdam.”

“On eighteen a week?”

“Well, she has an uncle who is quite well off.”

Mrs. Vivian smiled. “Such uncles usually have to be. In addition to the uncle, she has a very innocent young man. How long are you to keep this up?”

Alfred straightened. “I should have told you already. Miss Pelham has consented to do me the honor to become my wife.”

Mrs. Vivian’s smile deepened. “And very condescending of her that is. Now how do you propose to support her?”

“I counted on you.”

“And she also?”

“She is above mercenary considerations.”

“With an uncle such as hers she may well be. But you need not count on me any more than you can on him.”

Boldly Alfred bluffed. “Very good then, I’ll work my fingers to the bone for her. I’ll carve out a future for us both.”

Mrs. Vivian laughed. “You had best go to bed and forget it.”

“But mother,” the boy tormentedly pleaded, “when you know her, when you see what a splendid, glorious girl she is—”

“Yes, when I do. Meanwhile don’t be lyrical. Besides, if you won’t go to bed I shall. I have heard enough.”

In a moment she had gone. Alfred was alone. So also was his mother. In a room that gave on upper Fifth Avenue she locked out at the night. It was very black. For a week she had suspected. For a week she had seen her son look, not wickedly contented but ingenuously disturbed and, from other indicia, she had feared just some such stupidity as this.

Mrs. Vivian was not a snob, nor was she oppressively aristocratic. Against chorus girls as a class she had no prejudices whatever. Moreover, in other circumstances she might have been on the stage herself, and a very good actress she would have been. But her husband, in departing this life, had made her his sole legatee and, while he was at it, enormously wealthy. Since then English lords and Italian princes had competed for her. In the great matrimonial hurdle-race she was a prize. But she had not been won; and now her son was bagged—almost, but as yet not quite. It was not the principle of the thing to which she objected, it was the money. At sight of the picture, at mention of the uncle, instantly she had known what it was that the creature was after.

Now, as she looked out at the night, she realized that if she opposed her son, he might take the bit in his teeth, in which case she would either have to give in or else buy the girl off, unless she could alarm her away. Yet how?

But the night, it is said, brings counsel. It brought some to her which later, at luncheon, she omitted to mention.

Instead, when the servants had gone and she and her son were alone in a great room which in Europe would have been called baronial, she patted a yawn and asked:

“This is Friday, isn’t it?”

Alfred who had been looking down, looked up, but he looked too as though he had not slept very well. His eyes were heavy and about his mouth there was a droop.

“Friday, mother? Yes, I think so. I am not quite sure.”

“No matinée then?”

“None that I know of. Why? Were you thinking of going to one?”

Mrs. Vivian compressed her lips. “Don’t try to translate me. You will only fail. But now, since you know of no matinée, do you know of any rehearsal?”

“Oh!” said Alfred deeply, for he had got it. “I think not.”

Mrs. Vivian nodded. “In that case you might bring her here.”

“Why, mother!” Alfred, half-rising, exclaimed.

Mrs. Vivian gestured at him. “Don’t keep saying ‘mother’ every minute. It is so tiresome. And do sit still. You get on my nerves. Heavens! I can’t sit up until all hours and not feel it. But now since you propose to marry this er—this girl, it may seem to you only becoming that I should meet her.”

“You consent then?” Alfred, almost with a whoop, got out.

Mrs. Vivian patted another yawn. “What else can I do? But I do not approve of it. You are far too young. At your age matrimony is so respectable and disillusioning. In a week you will be sick to death of her.”

“Never,” the boy proudly proclaimed.

“Well, in three months then. At your age that is the limit—that is matrimony. Three months of adoration, three months of cogitation, thirty years of toleration, with the children to repeat the process. I ought to know. You will too. You are your father all over—minus his brains.”

“Thank you,” said Alfred who laughed as he said it. His spirits had risen, his color too; the droop from his mouth had gone. “You are the very best mother in all the world. I knew you would give in. I told Sadie so.”

Frostily Mrs. Vivian smiled. “And Sadie agreed with you, I suppose. Well, she must be the ideal ingénue. Now run and fetch her.”

In speaking she stood up and passed into a room that was fitted gravely, with infinite taste. There, at a piano, she seated herself and began on the “Meditation” from “Thais.” But it did not suit her mood. It was too harmonious. She abandoned it and attacked one of Borodin’s belligerent surprises.

Before she had finished, the portières parted and, followed by her son, there entered a young woman who had the full face of a doll and the tight mouth of a vixen.

Violently perfumed and dressed quite modishly as though for a fancy ball, the girl paused uncertainly. She had expected gold and glitter. The subdued surroundings awed her. At the moment, with suspicious defiance, she looked at Mrs. Vivian, who had risen and who was advancing to greet her.

But Mrs. Vivian’s manner was very thawing. “And this is Miss Pelham,” she said, and she said it as though she were eating nougat. At once, taking the girl’s hand, she turned to her son. “Run and play and come back in half an hour.” With a gesture she dismissed him and drawing the girl to a chair caressingly resumed: “Sit down, my dear, and let us have a nice little chat.”

Already with the one imperceptible glance with which the mondaine judges and classifies, she understood the girl, understood her possibilities, her impossibilities rather, and in her opulent corsage, her high color, her doll-like and inane face, understood too the wholly-physical attraction which she had for her son.

“The imbecile!” she thought, but she said: “Did your ears burn last night? Alfred was telling me of you. He was quite poetic. Are you fond of poetry? But you are. I can see that. And who is your favorite? Swinburne or Tennyson?”

Sadie moistened her lips. “I would not like to say.”

“No, of course not,” Mrs. Vivian with charming affability rejoined. “Any decided view seems so superficial, don’t you think? But I can see that in addition to poetry you are fond of pretty clothes. But not too many of them, of course. Did you ever hear of Miss Flora McFlimsey?”

“What is she driving at?” Sadie wondered. But she said: “There was a Flora in the ‘Ring Around the Rosie’ show, but I don’t remember her last name.”

“Well, that could hardly have been this Flora. This Flora was very unhappy because she had nothing to wear. Now instead of being unhappy she would be very fashionable. But I am forgetting myself. Won’t you let me give you a cup of tea?”

Mrs. Vivian touched a bell and added, “Or a glass of champagne?”

“Don’t wake me,” thought Sadie. But she said: “I don’t mind if I do.”

“Champagne!” Mrs. Vivian told a manservant who then appeared, and who could not credit his ears.

“Champagne, mem?” he repeated.

But Mrs. Vivian had turned again to the girl. “There’s nothing like it, is there? Particularly in the afternoon. Oh, we have so many tastes in common, or perhaps I should say so many common tastes. Alfred did not begin to tell me how famously we shall get on. It’s going to be perfectly splendid, isn’t it?”

“Pinch me,” thought Sadie, who, precisely as she had expected gold and glitter, had expected, too, airs, hostility, the disdain of a very rich woman for a working-girl. Instead of which she was being treated “like a lady.” At the consciousness and sheer satisfaction of it she laughed. “This is too easy,” she told herself.

On that, for emphasis, there came a pop! The manservant, reappearing, was filling glasses on a wonderful tray which he placed on a table that he had conjured before her. It was not only easy, it was grand, for now the man had gone, and here was this party drinking her health.

“Yes,” said Mrs. Vivian, “to you and to Alfred! But you have not told me. What are your plans? Don’t you agree with me that long engagements are a mistake? Long engagements make people sick and tired of each other, and that only ought to come afterwards.”

“She’s dotty,” thought Sadie. But she said: “You’re dead right.”

The glass which Mrs. Vivian held and which she had barely touched, she put down. “There! I was sure you would think so. Now why don’t you and Alfred get married at once?”

“Hurray for Sadie!” thought the girl, who answered: “That’s what Mr. Vivian says.”

“And how natural that is! But in the circumstances is not ‘Mr. Vivian’ a bit formal?” Comfortably the girl drained her glass. The uncertainty, the awe, the stabbing fear that she had of this fool of a woman, where were they now? Then roguishly she smiled. “Between you and me and the bedpost, I call him Fredikins.”

“Fredikins!” Mrs. Vivian with an enraptured air repeated. “Why that was his pet name when he was a baby! So amusing he was, too. Since then he has become very tedious. But tedious men make such excellent husbands, and that brings me back to what I was talking about. Why don’t you and he get married at once? If you will let me, I will give you the wedding.”

“I should worry,” thought Sadie, who said: “That will be elegant.”

“And every wish for your happiness.”

“That suits yours truly,” thought the girl, and she said it.

“And then, as Fredikins expressed it, and very manly he was—but then he is his father all over—he can carve out a future for you both.”

“Eh?” Sadie whinnied.

“Yes, wasn’t it manly of him? Reared as he has been in what I think I have seen described as the lap of luxury, isn’t it noble? It made me so proud. But that is not all. Without the slightest trace of conceit, but in a quiet, resolute way he has that way, you know, he got it from his father—he said that for you he would work his fingers to the bone.”

Sadie was bristling. Her tight mouth tightened. Had the champagne, she wondered, gone to the old cat’s head?

“And here is something else,” Mrs. Vivian, dropping her voice as though imparting a great confidence, continued. “When I die he will have six hundred a year. He won’t need it, of course, He will make millions. But, in case of a rainy day, there it will be for you both.”

“But—” Sadie fiercely exploded. At the moment her thoughts stammered. The monosyllable was all that she could get out.

Yet Mrs. Vivian seemed to appreciate, for enthusiastically, as though very much pleased with everybody and everything, she ran on; “And meanwhile, there is your ability and profession for him to fall back on.”

“Well, of all the gall!” thought Sadie. “See here—”

“My dear, I am an old woman,” interrupted Mrs. Vivian, who at the moment looked younger than the girl. “It is a month of Sundays since I have been to the theater, where, I am sure, you are as much of a success as that young French lady who was here last year—what was her name? Ah, yes, I have it and a quotation, too. ‘Consider the lilies of the field!’ Solomon in all his glory was not arrayed like Gaby des Lys.”

“Gaby nothing,” Sadie furiously cut in. “See here—”

Apologetically Mrs. Vivian half-raised a hand. “But it is not for her that my boy is to work his fingers to the bone; it’s for you, yet with such an admirable example as hers before you—I am told that when under our flag she just Stars and Strips, and that I think shows so much tact—I am sure the dear boy won’t have to.”

“You can bet your life on that,” said Sadie, who not only thought it but meant it, and who in saying it stood up, shook herself and glared. “See here. Your son told me he had your consent.”

Ingratiatingly Mrs. Vivian smiled and nodded. “So he has.”

“And what else?” Sadie, stamping a foot, threw at her.

With an air of surprise that succeeded in being both infinite and sympathetic, Mrs. Vivian took it up. “But what more did you expect?”

“What?” Sadie snapped. “Why with him letting himself go like a prince of the blood, and everybody saying how rich you are, whatever I expected it wasn’t false pretenses, for that’s what it is.”

Mrs. Vivian arose. “But, my dear child, except the prince part it is all of it true.”

At that Sadie faced her. “You want this marriage?”

“But don’t you know,” Mrs. Vivian in a voice of gentle reproach replied, “don’t you know that it is my dearest wish?”

Mentally Sadie fanned herself. “I have you now,” she thought. But she said: “Then you’ve got to divvy up.”

Mrs. Vivian smiled her sweetest. “I would just love to. But Fredikin’s father wanted him to make his own way, and with a dear child like you he is sure to.”

“Do you hear that!” Sadie gnashed. “Then listen to this. Unless a man can support me in style, it’s another dear child for him.”

“There he is now!” Mrs. Vivian, with the same sweet smile, exclaimed. “Alfred,” she called, “you are just in time to take Miss Pelham home.”

But that young lady’s lip had lifted like a dog’s when about to bite. “Not on your life,” she cried. “We’ll finish this right here.” Twisting, she fronted the boy. “I have been giving your mother the straight goods, and watch out now for the jolt for you.”

“Dearest!” the wretched youth protested. “What do you mean?”

But with great dignity Sadie now was making her exit. “I mean that I’m done with you, you little shrimp. Get out of my way.”

She passed, the hall engulfed her, the outer door closed, and furiously Alfred turned on his mother.

“You must have been taking things with a very high hand.”

Mrs. Vivian gave a shrug. “Probably. I have to take them from where I am.”

But the piano was before her. Seating herself she began anew on the harmonious “Meditation.” She felt in the mood for it then. She felt that definitely and decisively she had settled the boy and his girl.

A Business Man

In the ornate and brilliant room, when the songbirds had flown, the musicians had departed and the last guest, had gone, Duncan dropped into a chair, lit a cigar and looked at his daughter—a slim, low-breasted beauty.

To all New York, to all at least that counts, which numerically is not enormous, she had been hostess that night. Only Effingham had been absent. At thought of him a dizziness seized her, and as Duncan lit and looked, silently she crumpled. In that ornate and brilliant room she fell to the floor, her arms outstretched. It was as though death had touched her. She was ashen.

Duncan started. Old, cynical, astute, he loved her. Except for his millions, she was all he had. But now, before he could reach her, she turned, moaned. In a moment, assisted by him, she got to her knees, then to her feet.

“I’ll send for Sturgis,” he told her.

A hand to her head, she shook it, moved away.

“But Kate! You have never fainted before. You must see a doctor.”

She had reached the door. “No, I’ll go to bed. I suppose I am tired.”

But she spoke without conviction. Duncan followed her to the wide tapestry-hung hall, saw her to the lift. Then, entering the library, he took up the telephone, called for the physician, got him, asked him to come.

Barring “Poor’s Manual” and the “Financial Chronicle,” the library was bookless. Yet not otherwise empty. The furniture and woodwork had come from the Grand Canal. One great chair was dogian. Before it, on a vast table was a winged figure, a Mercury, the work of Benvenuto Cellini, that bandit who had the hands of a fairy. It was not priceless, since Duncan had bought it, but it was in keeping with the rest of this house which gave on upper Fifth Avenue.

Now, it was not the Mercury that occupied him, but his daughter. Since childhood and its multitudinous ills, always he had seen her active, ardent, alert, the picture of health and beauty. And yet, two minutes since, after an evening not more tiresome than any other, she had fainted. For the moment he could but hope that she was not in for anything serious.

The year before she had come out. At once there were aspirants. Among others, Jack Scarlet, a young man abominably good-looking, but with nothing else to his credit and no credit elsewhere.

“No man can have my daughter, with my consent, unless he can support her,” Duncan had told him, at which, Scarlet, after securing a berth in Wall Street, had returned to the charge. But Kate, who had laughed and danced with him, apparently wished to do nothing but that.

Meanwhile Solférino had put his modern, entirely authentic and equally non-existent principality at her feet. Hohenzolras had asked that she share with him the title of Serene Highness. Finsbury had offered the strawberry leaves.

In each instance the girl had laughed and refused. “I don’t want to be duchess, I don’t want to be princess,” she told her father. “I want to be happy.”

“That is the most selfish wish in the world,” Duncan replied.

But the point of view pleased him. With his endless millions he had acquired the interior of palaces, the gems of galleries, the manuscripts of seers. Though a financier, he had taste and he had flair. But crowns and coronets he did not regard as assets, and what assets were he knew. What is more notable, everybody knew that he knew. In the old boom days a tip from him was a fortune, and so clearly that when Scarlet secured the berth in Wall Street, he got it by whispering, confidentially of course, that as Duncan’s future son-in-law he would be provided and amply with just such tips.

Duncan, who knew all that was going on and a good deal that was not, learned of the trick. The effrontery of it amused him. But it hardly heightened the young man in his esteem.

Now, as he sat in the library, he pressed a button. A footman appeared.

“Dr. Sturgis will be here in a moment. When he comes, take him to Miss Duncan and say with my compliments that I would like a word with him before he goes.”

“Thank you, sir.”

Duncan was again alone, but his thoughts were many. He had scented that the time to buy had come. Stocks, after their long agony, might go lower. But he never tried to get in at the bottom, precisely as he never waited to unload at the top. Presently stocks would, he felt, be selling at double their present quotations and his instinct regarding them was due to a prescience that had enabled him to foresee in a harlequinade at Washington, the panic, rebound and slump that ensued. He had been a bear ever since. Now that everything was at its blackest, he saw the light.

“Dr. Sturgis, sir,” the footman announced.

Duncan, without rising, nodded. “Nothing wrong upstairs, eh?”

The confessor of all New York—of all, that is, that counts—Dr. Sturgis had a pointed beard and a manner which if not ecclesiastic was at least sedate.

“Nothing abnormal,” he replied.

Duncan smiled. He had hoped as much. “And what did you prescribe?”

Sturgis plucked at his beard. “There is no need for any prescription—at present.”

“At present!” Duncan surprisedly repeated.

Sturgis turned. “Good night, Mr. Duncan.”

The hall engulfed him. It was long and wide. Before he reached the outer door, Duncan was telephoning to Kate.

In her stead, a maid answered. Miss Duncan had gone to bed.

But though the girl had gone to bed, she had not gone to sleep. Sleep, latterly, had been long in coming. Not until morning would it take her, lull her, free her from herself, from the knowledge of that which was and of that which was to be.

At Newport, that summer, love had swum into her life. Hitherto she had but laughed and danced while awaiting the heart’s desire which happiness is and which then Effingham had brought her.

Effingham was a widower with no tombstone to show. His wife, dead to him, to the world and to herself, was insane. But the fact had little weight with Kate, and prudence as much meaning as it has for children and for gods. There might have been a hundred Mrs. Effinghams. Love in swimming into her heart swept every other consideration away. Now and again in thinking of it all, she recalled a picture which she had somewhere seen. Entitled “Le Vertige,” it showed men and women in a ballroom, and behind a slender screen, two others embracing. Their vertige had been hers—and his. Only—some day, the screen must fall away.

Now, on this night, after Sturgis had appeared, questioned and gone, she saw another picture, one that had come to her just before she had fainted, the vision of a man with the face of a soldier and the eyes of a poet, that irresistible compound of the resolute and the magnetic which was Effingham’s.

Then her father had telephoned. The picture faded, another surged—an engraving in a Victorian novel which represented an old man standing on a threshold and bidding a huddling girl begone!

Meanwhile, below, in the bookless library, her father sat. He too had his pictures. Kate’s mother who had died long since. Kate as a child, Kate as a young girl, Kate as a débutante, Kate dismissing Scarlet, Kate renouncing coronets, Kate refusing the strawberry leaves, Kate wanting only to be happy. There were these. There were others. In particular, a Newport vista in which together stood Kate and Effingham. Now the silent collapse, the ambiguousness of Sturgis and at once with that insight which had made Duncan what he was, he knew. The front door had not closed on Sturgis before he saw it all.

Passionless as algebra, devoid of nerves, accustomed in any crisis to think and to act, he rang, gave directions, had himself lifted to his rooms, from which, the next morning, mentally armed, he descended to the library again.

Always in Wall Street before the opening, he had intended on this morning to be there earlier still. There were brokers to be summoned, orders to be given, details to be arranged. Instead of which, telephoning to his office that he might not be down that day, he sent for Kate.

When presently, languid and lovely in a honey-colored gown, she appeared, he got up, motioned to the chair in which a doge had throned, closed the door, took another seat, looked at the girl and smiled.

“How did you sleep?”

Kate, settling herself, answered absently: “Fairly well, father. And you?”

“Oh, as usual. Now I want to have a talk with you.”

Kate who had been looking down, looked up. “About what, father?”

“About myself, of course. What do people ever want to talk about? But incidentally a little too about you. Now Kate, things have not been going very well lately, have they?”

Kate flushed. “In what way do you mean?”

“I mean that when things do not go well, ignorant people always blame some one else, sensible people blame themselves and wise people blame nobody. A wise man knows that whatever happens, happens because it had to happen and because it could not happen otherwise. Do you follow me?”

Confusedly Kate sat back. “Yes—no. I mean not quite.”

Duncan nodded at her. “I will put it more clearly then. We all make mistakes. You may have also made them. In that case I shall not blame you. On the contrary. The only punishment a father should inflict is forgiveness.”

Kate turned uneasily. Was it possible, she wondered, that he knew—and already! “But punishment for what?” she got out.

“Well—for remaining single. Now I want you to marry and to marry Scarlet. Will you?”

Kate straightened. “Certainly not.”

“It will be a bit awkward then. It will mean going abroad and for the moment I had other plans.”

Kate now was crimson. She knew he knew. In miserable protest she halfraised a hand. “But—”

“Oh,” he got in. “I know you don’t care for Scarlet. He is a damned scoundrel. It is for that reason I selected him.”

“But—”

“Precisely. He will treat you badly. You can leave him. I will get you a divorce and afterward it may be that you will meet some one with whom you can be happy and for me at least it is not selfish to want you to be that.”

“But—”

“There! I understand how you feel. Leave it all to me. I am a business man. But in every business man’s stock-in-trade there is, or ought to be, honesty and my honesty in regard to you will surprise Scarlet. But he is blackguard enough to thank his stars for even that opportunity of getting a quid pro quo in cash.”

Kate had shriveled. Pay a man to marry me! she tormentedly thought. But before she could protest again, nervously she started.

At the door a tap had come, low and discreet, and a footman appeared with a card on a tray which he brought to Duncan.

Duncan took the card, looked at it, looked again and from it looked at the footman.

“Where is he?”

“In the drawing-room, sir.”

Duncan turned to Kate. “ ‘Poor’s Manual’ is at your elbow. It is one of the most diverting books ever printed. You might occupy yourself with it until I return.”

As he spoke, he got up, followed the servant, crossed the wide tapestried hall and entered the ornate, but now less brilliant room, in the center of which stood Effingham.

In similar circumstances there are fathers who would have reviled him, struck him, thrown him from the house. In places less ornate, he might have been cowhided, strangled, shot.

Duncan asked him to be seated. But the asking was accompanied by a look which was chill and pointed as a rapier.

With unswerving eyes, that look Effingham returned. “Mr. Duncan, I am sorry to trouble you. In coming here I asked for Miss Duncan. I was told she was engaged.”

Duncan nodded. “Well, what of it?”

For a second Effingham considered the question. Then out the answer came. “Mr. Duncan, I am here to ask your daughter—”

Instantly Duncan got it. But what he said was: “We are not in Salt Lake.”

Effingham made a gesture. “Forgive me. I should have told you. Mrs. Effingham died yesterday. Though in her condition she has been dead so long that—”

On with it he rambled. Duncan had ceased to hear, ceased rather to listen. The large fact occupied ham. It overshadowed Scarlet, Europe as well, besides being just the thing. Mentally he waved it. But he said and simply enough: “And you want my daughter, is that it?”

Effingham bowed. “A year’s delay is usual I know, but in the circumstances—”

Duncan, hastily swallowing something, caught him up. “Am I to understand that my daughter has already encouraged you?”

It was but a sprat for a mackerel, which at once Effingham produced.

“Not at all, sir. On the contrary. Moreover I have not been in a position to expect encouragement. But I had thought that with a divorce—one which death has unexpectedly granted—I might ask.”

You are a cool customer, Duncan thought. Yet the decency of it appeased him. “Well?” he threw out.

“I believe you knew my father,” Effingham resumed.

But that was coals to Newcastle. Duncan had not only known him, he knew practically to a dime how much he had left.

“I am quite able to support your daughter,” Effingham continued. “If—”

There shall be no ifs, Duncan decided. But he said: “There is an if in everything. My daughter has refused many offers, some perhaps more advantageous than yours. But I do not believe in interference.”

“I have your consent then?”

Duncan stood up, took out his watch, looked at it, put it back and looked at Effingham.

“You will find my daughter in the library. But I have to go. It is after the opening and I am a business man.”

A Maid of Modern Athens

“It was this way,” she said, and as she spoke she stooped and flicked a speck of dust from her habit. “It was this way: The existence which I lead in the minds of other people is absolutely of no importance whatever. Now wait: I care a great deal whether school keeps or not, but in caring I try chiefly to be true to myself. I may stumble; I may not. In any event I seek the best. As for the scandal of which you speak, that is nonsense. There is no criterion. That which is permissible here is inhibited yonder, and what is permissible yonder is inhibited here. Scandal, indeed!”

There was something about her that stirred the pulse. She was fair; the sort of girl whose photograph is an abomination, and yet in whose face and being a charm resides, a charm intangible and coercive, inciting to better things. A Joan of Arc in a tailor-made gown.

“You remember how it was when we were younger—You—well, there is no use in going into that. You had a mother to think for you; I had no one. I had to solve problems unassisted. The weightiest of all was marriage, and that, in my quality of heiress, I found perplexing to a degree. But how is it possible, I asked myself, how can a girl pledge her life to a man of whom she knows absolutely nothing? For, practically speaking, what does the average girl know of the man whose name she takes? It may be different in the country, but in town! Listen to me; a girl ‘comes out,’ as the saying is; she meets a number of men, the majority of whom are more or less agreeable and well-bred—when she is present. But what are they when she is not? At dinners and routs, or when she receives them in her own house, they are at their best; if they are not they stay away. It is not so difficult to be agreeable once in awhile, but to be so always is a question not of mask but of nature. It seems to me that when an intelligent woman admires her brother it is because that brother is really an admirable man. Has she not every opportunity of judging? But what opportunity is given to the girl whom a man happens to take in and out at dinner, or whom she sees for an hour or two now and then? You must admit that her facilities are slight. That was the way it was with me, and that was the way I fancied it would continue to be, and I determined that it was better to remain spinster forever than to take a man on trust and find that trust misplaced. Suspicious? No, I am not suspicious. When your husband bought this property did you think him suspicious because he had the title searched? Very good; then perhaps you will tell me that the marriage contract is less important than the conveyance of real estate? Besides, my doubts on the subject of love would have defied a catalogue. When I read of the follies and transports of which it was reported to be the prime factor, I was puzzled. It seemed to me that I had either a fibre more or a fibre less than other girls, I could not comprehend. No man I had ever met—and certainly I had met many—had ever caused me so much as a fleeting emotion. There were men with whom I found speech agreeable and argument a pleasure, but, had they worn frocks instead of trousers, such enjoyment as I experienced would have been unimpaired. You see, it was purely mental. And when—there, I remember one man in particular. As Stella said of Swift, he could talk beautifully about a broomstick. He knew the reason of things; he was up in cuneiform inscriptions and at home with meteorites; he was not prosy, and, what is more to the point, he never treated a subject as though it were a matter of life and death. He was not bad-looking, either, and he was the only man of my acquaintance who both understood Kant and got his coats from Poole. That man I liked very much. He was better than a book. I could ask him questions, a thing you can’t do even of an encyclopaedia. One fine day the personal pronoun cropped out. We had been discussing Herbert Spencer’s theory of conceivability, and abruptly, with an inappositeness which, now I think of it, would have been admirable on the stage, but which in the drawing-room was certainly misplaced, he asked me to take a walk with him down the aisle of the swellest church in the commonwealth. I mourned his loss, as we say. But wasn’t it stupid of him? But what does get into men? Why should they think that, because a girl is liberal with odd evenings, she is pining for the marriage covenant?”

With the whip she held she gave the hem of her habit a sudden lash.

“That episode gave me food for thought. H’m. By-and-by the scene was occupied by a young man who was an authority on orchids, and wrote sonnets for the Interstate. My dear, a more guileful little wretch never breathed. When my previous young man disappeared, I felt that I had been hasty. I desired nothing so much as an increase in my store of knowledge, and I determined that if another opportunity occurred I would not be in such a hurry to shut the door on entertaining developments. Consequently, when my poet turned up, I was as demure as you please. He was a fox, that man. He began with the fixed purpose of irritating me into liking him. The tactics he displayed were unique. He never came when I expected him, and when he did come he was careful to go just when he thought he had scored a point. If any other man happened in, he first eclipsed him and then left him to me. I saw through that game at once. He understood perfectly that if I preferred the other man I was all the more obliged to him for going, and if I preferred him to the other man I was the sorrier to see him leave. In addition to this, whatever subject I broached, he led it by tangential flights to Love. That Machiavelli en herbe knew that to talk love is to make love. And talk of love he did, no, but in the most impersonal manner. To hear him discant you would have thought his wings were sprouting. Love, as he expressed it, was a sentiment which ennobled every other; a purifying and exalting light. It was the most gracious of despots. It banished the material; it beckoned to the ideal. It turned satiety into a vagabond that had not where to lay its head. It was the reduction of the world, creation, and all the universe to a single being. It was an enchanted upland, inhibited to the herd. It was a chimera to the vulgar, a crown to the refined. ‘A perfect lover,’ he said, ‘must needs be an aristocrat.’ And if you will believe me, I actually thought he meant what he said. In spite of myself, I was becoming interested. There were new horizons before me. I seemed to discern something hitherto unseen. My dear, for the moment I felt myself going. I was at the foot of his enchanted upland. I was almost willing to take him for guide. At first I had been merely amused. Once, even, when he quoted the ‘Two souls with but a single thought,’ I suggested that that must mean but half a thought apiece. The quiet dignity which he then displayed almost fetched me. He had the air of a prelate in whose presence an oaf has trampled on a crucifix. He kept up that sort of thing for two months. To me his sincerity was beyond peradventure. Not once did he speak in a personal way. I was beginning to wonder when he would stop beating about the bush, and I not only wondered, I believe I even wished that he would be a little more enterprising and a trifle less immaterial. Presently I detected a symptom or two which told me that the end of the beginning was in sight. I suppose my manner was more encouraging. In any event, one evening he took my hand and kissed it. From nine-and-ninety men out of a hundred I should have thought nothing of such a thing. In Europe it is an empty homage, a pantomime expressive of thanks. As I say, then, in any other man I should not have given it a second thought, but he had never done it before.

“The next day I lunched with Mrs. Bunker Hill. I mentioned his name; I suppose it was running in my mind. And then, my dear, Fanny began. Well, the things she told me about that transcendental young man were of such a nature that when he next called I was not at home. He came again, of course. And again. He sent me a note which I returned unopened. That, I confess, was a foolish thing to do. It showed him that I was annoyed. I might better have left it unanswered. After all, there is nothing so impenetrable as silence. Finally, he got one of his friends to come and reconnoitre. Indeed, he did not desist until I had an opportunity of cutting him dead. I was angry, I admit it. And it was after that little experience that I determined, the next time I felt myself going, I would make sure beforehand where I was going to. H’m. I wonder what his sister thought of him? You see, it was not that I had fallen in love; the word was as unintelligible to me as before, but I had fancied that, through him, I might intercept some inkling of its meaning, and I was put out at having been tricked. Ach! diese Männer!”

Beneath descending night the sky was gold-barred and green. In the east the moon glittered like a sickle of tin. The air was warm and freighted with the odors of August. You could hear the crickets hum, and here and there was the spark of a fire-fly gyrating in loops of flame. From across the meadows came the slumbrous tinkle of a bell.

She raised a gloved hand to her brow and looked down at the yellow road. To one who loved her, the Helen for whom the war of the world was fought was not so fair as she. And presently the hand moved about the brow, and, resting a second’s space on the coil just above the neck, fell again to her side.

“Well,” she continued, “you can see how it was. Even before the illusion, disillusionment had come. That winter I went with the Bunker Hills to Monaco. Were it not for the riff-raff, that place would be a paradise in duodecimo. We had a villa, of course. One evening, shortly after our arrival, we went to the Casino. For the fun of the thing I put some money on the Trente et Quarante. I did nothing but win. It was tiresome; I would rather have lost; I had to speak to the dealer, and that, as you can fancy, was not to my liking. There was a great crowd. One little old woman put money wherever I did. She won a lot, too. But one man, whom I could not help noticing, backed red when I was on black, and vice versa. He did it persistently, intentionally, and he lost every time. Finally one of the croupiers told me that my stake was above the maximum, and asked how much I would risk. I was tired of answering his questions, and I turned away. A lackey followed me with a salver covered with gold and notes—the money I had won. I didn’t want it; I had not even a pocket to put it in, and the purse which I held in my hand would not have held a fraction of it. It was a nuisance. I turned it over to Bunker, and presently we all went out on the terrace that overhangs the sea. It was a perfect night. In the air was a caress, and from the Mediterranean came a tonic. While I was enjoying it all, a beggar ambled up on a crutch and begged a franc. I took from Bunker the money I had won and gave him thirty thousand. You should have heard Bunker then. I actually believe that if I had been his wife instead of his guest he would have struck me. I suppose it was an absurd thing to do. But the next time you are in search of a new sensation do something of the same sort. The beggar became transfigured. He looked at the gold and notes, and then at me. I do not think I shall ever forget the expression in his face. Did you ever see a child asleep—a child to whom some wonderful dream has come? It was at once infantile and radiant. And all the while Bunker was abusing me like a pickpocket. The beggar gave me one look, dropped on his knees, caught the hem of my skirt, kissed it, threw away his crutch, and ran. I burst out laughing, and Bunker, in spite of his rage, burst out laughing too. Fanny called us a pair of idiots, and said that if I was as lavish as that it would be better and wiser, and far more Christian, to keep my money for indigent and deserving Bostonese, than to bestow it as a premium on Monacean vice and effrontery. Just as she was working herself into big words and short sentences, the man whom I had noticed at the tables came along. He had met her before, and now, as he expressed it, he precipitated himself to renew the expression of his homage. Fanny, after introducing him to me, began at once on the tale of my misconduct. He had a complexion of the cream-tint order, and a moustache blacker than hate. He was a Florentine, I discovered, a marquis with a name made up of v’s, sonorous o’s, and n’s. We had found a table, and Bunker ordered some ices. The night was really so perfect, and the ice so good, that, like Mme. de Staël over her sherbet in moonlit Venice, I almost wished it were a sin to sit there. The marquis was in very good form and inclined to do the devoted on the slightest provocation.

“ ‘Is mademoiselle,’ he asked me, ‘is mademoiselle as disdainful of the heart as she is of gold?’

“ ‘Absolutely,’ I answered—a remark which may have sounded snobbish, but still was wholly true.

“ ‘Ah!’ he exclaimed, ‘there are birds that do not sing untaught.’

“ ‘You are beginning well,’ I thought.

“The next day he lunched with us, and came again in the evening. In addition to his marquisate, he had a fluty tenorino voice; what they call a voix de salon. He sang all sorts of things for us, and he sang them very well. When the air was lively he looked at Fanny, when it was sentimental he looked at me. Thereafter I saw a great deal of him. One day we would make up a party for Nice, on another we would go to San Remo, or else back in the mountains, or to Grasse. Of course, as you know, customs over there are such that he had no opportunity of being alone with me, even for a second; but he had an art of making love in public which must have been the result of long practice. It was both open and discreet. It was not in words; it was in the inflection of the voice and in the paying of the thousand and one little attentions which foreigners perform so well. Now, to me, a tiara might be becoming, but it is an ornament for which I have never felt the vaguest covetousness. Moreover, I had no intention of marrying an Italian, however fabulous the ancestry of that Italian might be. And, besides, the attentions of which I was the apparent object were, I knew, addressed less to me than to the blue eyes of my check-book. The Florentine nobleman who is disposed to marry a dowerless American is yet to be heard from. This by the way. However, I accepted the attentions with becoming grace, and marked the cunning of his tricks. One evening he did not put in an appearance, but at midnight, I heard, on the road before my window, the tinkle of a guitar. I did not need to peer through the curtains to know from whom it came. First he sang a song of Tosti’s, and then the serenade from “Don Pasquale:”

‘Com’ è gentil, la notte in mezz’ Aprile.

Poi quando sarò morto, tu piangerai
Ma ritornarmi in vita, tu non potrai.’

“Sentimental? Yes, sentimental to the last degree. But on the Riviera, in spring, and at night, one’s fancy turns to that sort of thing with astounding ease. I listened with unalloyed pleasure. It was like a Boccaccian echo. And as I listened I wondered whether I should ever learn what love might be. The idea of taking a course of lessons from a man who strummed on a guitar in front of my window never entered my head. The next day Fanny came to me in a state of great excitement. The guitarist, it appeared, had, with all proper and due formality, asked leave to place his coronet at my feet. Ce que j’ai ri!

“You can hear Fanny from here. She accused me of flirting with the man. ‘You have no right,’ she said, ‘to treat him as though he were a college boy at Mt. Desert.’ What he had done to make her so vicious I never discovered. It must have been the title, a title always went to her head. Poor Fanny! That evening, when he came, she declined to be present. I had to see him alone. My dear, he was too funny. He had prepared a little speech which he got off very well, only at the end of it he lapsed into English. ‘We will loaf,’ he said, ‘we will be always loafers.’ He meant, of course, to assert that we should love and be always lovers, but the intricacies of our pronunciation were too much for him. I could have died, it was so amusing. I managed, however, to keep a straight face. ‘Marquis,’ I said, ‘I am deeply honored, but your invitation is one that I am unable to accept.’ A more astounded man you never saw. He really thought that he had but to ask, and it would be given. He declined to take No for an answer. He said he would wait. Actually, he was so pertinacious that I had to drag Fanny up to Paris. He followed us in the next train. There was no getting rid of him at all. If he sent me one note he sent me a hundred, and notes ten pages each, at the very least. Finally, as you heard, he tried the dramatic. One afternoon, while I was out shopping, he bribed a waiter at the hotel where we lodged. When I returned, there he was, waiting for me. ‘At last,’ he cried, ‘at last we are face to face. You think I do not love. Cruel one, behold me! I love as no mortal ever loved before. See, I die at your feet!’ And there, before my very eyes, he whipped out a pistol, pulled the trigger, tumbled over and seemed fully disposed to carry out the programme to the end. He had shot himself; there was no doubt about that; but he had shot himself in such an intelligent manner, that, though there was blood enough to frighten a sensitive young person out of her wits, yet of danger there was none at all. Talk to me about comedians! When I discovered the farce which had been enacted with the sole object of stirring my sympathies into affection, I was flabbergasted at the wiles of man.

“It was after that episode that I returned to Beacon Street. It was there that what you are pleased to call the scandal began. Fanny, whose desire to marry me off was simply epic, one day caught an Englishman; young, so she said, and good-looking. And that Englishman, she made up her mind, I should ensnare. Fanny, as you know, was possessed with an ungratified desire to pay annual visits to swell country houses on the other side. Hence, I suppose, her efforts. Having caught the Englishman, the next step was to serve him up in becoming form. To that end she gave a tentative dinner. I got to it late; in fact, I was the last to arrive. Fanny, I could see, was in a state of feverish excitement. She presented to me one or two men, whose names I did not catch, and a moment later one of them gave me his arm. When we were seated at table, and while he was sticking a chrysanthemum in his button-hole, I glanced at the card on his plate. It bore for legend Lord Alfred Harrow. It was then I took my first look at him. My dear, he was the ugliest man I have ever seen; he was so ugly that he was positively attractive. His mouth was large enough to sing a duet, but his teeth were whiter than mine.”

As she spoke she curled her lips.

“There was no hair on his face, and his features were those of a middle-aged wizard. But about him was the atmosphere of health, of strength, too, and his hands, though bronzed and sinewy, were perfect. I knew he was a thoroughbred at once. ‘And how do you like the States?’ I asked. He was squeezing some lemon on an oyster, and I noticed that when some white wine was offered him he turned the glass upside down. ‘Very much,’ he answered; ‘and you?’ There was more of that sort of thing, and finally I asked him if, like other Englishmen, he thought that Boston suggested one of his provincial towns. ‘There seems to be some mistake,’ he said. ‘I was going into the Somerset five minutes ago when Hill coralled me. He told me that his wife was giving a dinner, and that at the last moment one of the bidden had wired to the effect that he was prevented from coming. Whereupon Mrs. Hill had packed him off to the club, with instructions to bring back the first man he met. I happened to be that man.’ He took up the card. ‘Lord Alfred is, I fancy, the delinquent. My name,’ he added, ‘is Mr. Stitt—Ferris Stitt,’ he continued, as though apologizing for its inconsequence.

“After that we got on famously. In a day or two he came to the house. When he left the world was larger. He knew nothing about poetry. He had never so much as heard of Fichte. Herbert Spencer was to him a name and nothing more. The only works of ornamental literature which he seemed to have read were the Arabian Nights, which he had forgotten, and something of Dickens, which had put him to sleep. He did not know one note of music from another. But he had hunted big game in Africa, in Bengal, and he had penetrated Thibet. He had been in Iceland and among the Caribs. No carpet knight was he.

“My dear, I had not seen him five times before I felt myself going. I think he knew it. But I had been cheated before, and so well that I held on with all my strength. While I was holding on, he disappeared. Not a word, not a line, not even so much as a p. p. c. In the course of time, through the merest accident, I learned that he was in Yucatan. Six months later I caught a glimpse of him in the street. Presently he called.

“At once, without so much as a preamble, he told me he had gone away that in absence he might learn whether I was as dear to him as he thought. He hesitated a moment. ‘Will you let me love you?’ he asked. ‘You have been prudent,’ I answered; ‘let me be prudent, too.’ Then I told him of my disenchantments. I told him how difficult I found it to discover what men really were. I told him, as I have told you, that it seemed to me, if an intelligent girl admired her brother, it was because that brother was assuredly an admirable man. And I added that I would accept no man until I had the same opportunities of judging him as a sister has of judging her brother. Besides, I said, I have yet to know what love may be. It was then that we made the agreement of which you disapprove. After all, it was my own suggestion, and, if unconventional, in what does the criterion consist? I was acting for the best. You do not imagine, do you, that I regret it?”

And to her lips came a smile.

“I took Mary, who, you must admit, is respectability personified, and whom I had long since elevated from nurse to sheep dog—I took Mary, and, together, all three of us, we went abroad. It is in travelling that you get to know a man. Each evening, when he said good-night, my admiration had increased. From England, as you know, we went straight to India. It was a long trip, I had heard, but to me it seemed needlessly brief. During the entire journey I studied him as one studies a new science. I watched him as a cat watches a mouse. Not once did he do the slightest thing that jarred. During the entire journey he did not so much as attempt to take my hand in his. He knew, I suppose, as I knew, that if the time ever came I would give it unasked.

“One evening, on going to my stateroom, I found I had left my vinaigrette on deck. Mary was asleep. I went back for it alone. It was very dark. On the way to where I had sat I heard his voice; he was talking to one of the passengers. In spite of myself I listened to what he was saying. I listened for nearly an hour. Not one word was there in it all that he could not have said to me. When I got back to my cabin I wondered whether it might not be that he knew I was standing there. Yes, I admit, I was suspicious; but circumstances had made me so. Oh! he has forgiven me since.”

She smiled again complacently to herself, and, tucking the whip under her arm, she drew off a glove; on one finger was a narrow circle of gold. She looked at it and raised it to her lips.

“When we landed our journey had practically begun. You see, I was still unassured. Yet he was irreproachable and ever the same. Well, the details are unimportant. One day, at Benares, he heard that leopards had been seen in the neighborhood of a lake some fifteen or twenty miles out. At once he was for having a crack at them. I determined to accompany him. He was surprised at first, and objected a little, but I managed, as I usually do, to have my own way. It was night when we got there. We left the horses with the guide, and, noiselessly as ghosts, we stole through a coppice which hid the lake from view. Almost at the water’s edge we crouched and waited. The stars were white as lilies and splendid as trembling gems. The silence was as absolute as might. How long we waited I cannot now recall. I think I dreamed a bit with open eyes. Then dimly I became conscious of something moving in the distance. The moon had risen like a balloon of gold, and in the air was the scent of sandal. Slowly, with an indolent grace of its own, that something neared the opposite shore. As it reached the water it stopped, arched its back, and turned. I saw then that it was a leopard. No, my dear, you can form no idea of the beauty of that beast. And then suddenly it threw its head back and called. It lapped the water, and then, with its tongue, gave its forepaw one long, lustrous lick, and called again; a call that was echoless, yet so resonant I felt it thrill my finger-tips. In a moment its mate sprang from the shadows. If the first comer was beautiful, then this one was the ideal. There they stood, caressing each other with amber, insatiate eyes. It was like a scene in fairyland. And as I watched them, I felt a movement at my side. I turned. He had taken aim and was about to fire, but, as I turned, he turned to me. Those beasts, I told myself, are far too fair for death; yet I said not a word. My dear, he read my unuttered wish, he lowered the gun, and then—then, for the first time, I knew what love might be. … There’s the dogcart now. Come over and dine to-morrow. If you care to, Ferris will show you the gun.”

A Transaction in Hearts

An Episode

“Pour estre bien aimé,
Il faut aimer bien peu.”

Ronsard.

I

The quiet of the morning was punctuated by a housemaid who, aware that the master was astir, was singing, for his benefit, “Jesus loves me,” in a treble of irritating insistence. Already the carriage had arrived, and as Gonfallon drew on his gloves he wondered by what token he should recognize the sister of his wife. He had the vaguest memory of her, a slip of a girl who years before had sat opposite him at dinner, the eyes lowered, the hair in pendent plaits. And as his thoughts went back to earlier days, Ruth called to him from the floor above, “If you don’t see her at once, ask the captain: she is in his charge.”

Gonfallon was not a whit more unselfish than the best of us, yet that morning, his routine upset, his coffee undigested, the paper barely skimmed, and, paramount of all, Ruth’s neuralgia which forced him to the wharf alone, made him conscious that, momentarily, for all of him, in the captain’s charge the girl might remain.

But he assented smilingly, as was his wont; and when, after a long sweep down the Avenue and a brisk drive through hideous little streets, he caught a sniff of salt water, his equanimity returned, and as the carriage rolled into the domed and creaking peninsula the momentary annoyance was forgot.

Already the Bourgogne was in the offing, and Gonfallon had but a few moments in which to kick his heels before the great ship was moored and the gangplank let down. As the vessel swung round he had gazed up at the faces that lined the rail, trusting to his own intuition to recognize the girl unprompted; but as yet among the passengers he saw no one that in any way resembled the shy little maid whom he had come to meet.

“H’m,” he mused, “I dare say she has recognized me and is too timid to make a sign.” And, reflecting that after all, in view of his cloth, it would be more dignified to make inquiry of someone than to stand staring women out of countenance, he descended in the caverns of memory and recovered a sentence in French.

“Where is the purser to be found?” he asked of an official at his side.

“Le voilà,” the man answered, not over-suavely, and nodded towards an individual bebraided with gold who stood within hailing-distance.

Gonfallon turned to the person thus designated, and presently succeeded in catching his eye. “Would you be good enough—” he began, and, as the purser leaned forward the better to catch his speech, Gonfallon added, “I am looking for Miss Bucholz.”

The purser lifted his arms and assumed an expression of the civilest and most amiable perplexity. “Really, sir, I regret, perhaps—” And as he shrugged his shoulders and bowed, as who should say, “It is a grief that I cannot serve you,” a young man dressed Piccadilly-fashion touched him on the arm.

“I beg pardon: Dr. Gonfallon, I believe. My name is Mr. Yarde. Miss Bucholz is yonder.”

And as Gonfallon, in obedience to the summons, turned again, he heard the purser, presumably to a sympathetic ear, exclaim, “Ah, çà! Does he think I have his Miss Bucholz in my pocket?”

But Gonfallon had no opportunity of meditating on the variation of demeanor which is peculiar to the French: a moment or two later the guide which Providence or his sister-in-law had sent, had led him through coils of descending passengers to a corner of the deck, which, so nearly as his vision permitted him to discern, was occupied by but one person, a pouting, good-looking lad, such as one may see any day at Eton during term-time, who stood leaning against the back of a steamer-chair in such a manner that only the head and shoulders were visible.

“Here,” said the guide, greatly to Gonfallon’s astonishment, “here is your quest.—Miss Bucholz, can I be of further assistance?”

Immediately the pout disappeared, and a hand gloved in Suede was extended. “Is Ruth not with you?”

And then for the first time Gonfallon realized that he was in the presence of her whom he sought.

“Yes,” he answered—“no, I mean. She is at the house—” In amusement at his own surprise, he smiled a little. “I have a carriage, though—”

The girl turned to the young man who had introduced himself as Mr. Yarde. “You may go,” she said, abruptly, and to her lips the pout returned.

The young man made as would he speak, but evidently he thought better of it, and, raising his hat, took himself off. As he moved away, Gonfallon glanced at him, and as he glanced there bubbled within him that unmotived, instinctive dislike of which antipathy is born.

“Detestable little cad!” the girl muttered, and issued from her barricade.

Gonfallon eyed her curiously. Whatever manner of gown she wore was covered by an ulster. On her head was a sailor-hat, about her neck was a high white collar, the ends bent, and beneath it was a scarf such as is worn by men. She was worse than pretty. In her skin was the hue of that white rose which has a sulphur heart. Her features had the surety of an intaglio, her head was small, the brow low; in her hair, which was short and curled, was the glisten of gold-leaf shown to the sun. Her eyes were of porcelain-blue, the under lids retreating and shorter than the upper. The effect of her mouth, now that the pout had gone, was that of lips untouched and unaware of love. In height she was a trifle taller than the average New York girl. She held herself with the erectness of one accustomed to the saddle. And when again she spoke, Gonfallon felt the charm of that undulant intonation which is the sweetest heritage of English speech.

“Father, I suppose, was too busy to meet me, was he not?” she asked.

Too busy, indeed! Gonfallon thought of the sodden mortal he had seen the week before ambling down a side-street, the estray of millions and of health, and then, remembering that Claire was as yet uninformed of the successive disasters in which he had foundered, he nodded cheerily and smiled.

“Yes, yes, of course. Ruth would have come too, but she is a martyr—no, but really a martyr, you know.” For a second he paused, as though in some dumb fashion he might console the girl for the absence of those she loved. “You had a pleasant trip, I hope?” he added. “If you will come with me I will put you in the carriage and see to your traps. Have you the keys?”

An hour later, without further incident necessary of record, the house was reached, and Gonfallon, leaving the girl to her sister’s ministrations, went to his study to sandpaper an address for the morrow. But, whether because his routine had been disturbed, or because he was personally out of trim, certain it is that he felt in no mood for the chastening of homilies that noon. For a little while he still fingered the manuscript, striving to coerce his thoughts, until, conscious of the futility of the endeavor, he abandoned further effort and lounged back into the past.

At the time contemporaneous to the episodes with which these pages have to deal, Christopher Gonfallon was in his fortieth year. Across his forehead was a sabre-cut which thought had dealt, near the temples was a suspicion of gray, on either side of his nostrils were the beginnings of furrows, but otherwise the years had been gentle. In his face and bearing was the fragrance of the fields. He wore no beard, his lip was unmoustached. His eyes were of that green-black which is noticeable in dysodile coal. His profile suggested sensitiveness, the full-face strength. Lavater would not have praised his chin. At first sight you would have taken him for a maker of songs and of laws, but his coat betrayed him. By profession he was an ecclesiastic, a priest of the Episcopal Church.

On the conferment of orders he had accepted a call at Bronx, a somnolent New England hamlet, and there during an entire decade he had wasted his fervors on a collection of cattle, surreptitiously beloved the while by a procession of parochial maids.

Throughout the parish, however, there was at most but one person capable of appreciating the imageries of his speech, and that person, the Countess of Cinq-Cygne, was deaf. To this lady his subsequent and metropolitan success was indirectly due.

The countess, born a Chisolm-Jones, lived in a great stone house that overlooked the village and patches of the surrounding country as well. And this stone house each summer and autumn she was accustomed to populate with detachments and reinforcements of guests. The winter she passed in meditation, though not, presumably, of the count. For de Cinq-Cygne, who had enjoyed the formidable reputation of being the handsomest member of the Jockey, had, after marrying the heiress of Bronx, as the countess was known in her youth, and promenading her through the Tuileries, returned with her to the New England hamlet from which he one day disappeared companioned by his wife’s nearest friend. It was rumored that he had returned to the Tuileries and the Jockey Club. But from the countess no mention of him could be wrung. After Sedan she put on black, and it was taken for granted that the count had fallen with the eagle and the imperial bees. Of the fate of the companion of his flight her kinsfolk never asked.

During the last months of winter Gonfallon was a frequent guest at the house on the hill. The countess was too infirm to attend services with any satisfaction to herself, but she was devout, and the visits of the pastor were grateful to her. She was appreciative, and, despite her encroaching deafness, pleasant and intelligent of speech. She had a smile of singular indulgence, and, though her beauty was that of a city raised from the ground, still, you divined among the vestiges the seductions of earlier charm. By repute she had been indeed a belle; and as for her manner, time had coped with it in vain: she was still the high-bred woman who had shown the pinchbeck maréchales and marchionesses of the Tuileries how to walk, and who, when the Emperor on learning that her baptismal name was Helen had exclaimed, “Ah that I were Paris!” had answered, “Sire, you are France.”

Of connections she had many, yet of relations but one, a nephew, Mr. A. B. Fenwick Chisolm-Jones by name, familiarly known as Alphabet, a young gentleman of literary promise which thus far he had failed to fulfil. To the aunt in the sultriness of the summer months the nephew came, and with him anyone else who could be lured that way. But in the winter the great house was almost uninhabited; and so it came about that in the soundless dusks the one man in the village who could speak English correctly was made welcome there and at home.

The countess, as has been intimated, was devout. In the old cosmogony she had the amplest faith. To her, heaven was just beyond the stars, and hell beneath the ferrule of her crutch. To the truth of any miracle she would have testified on oath. Had anyone so much as hinted before her that the precepts of the synoptic gospels were due to Socrates and the Socratics, she would have routed the blasphemer with the sign of the cross. It was rumored that in youth she had been less orthodox. But with age religion held her like a vice; it was her ultimate refuge; and as Gonfallon penetrated its abysses he fell to wondering whether his own creed might not be as futile as was hers. Yet to argue with her would have been profitable as the chiding of a river. As a consequence, he held his peace, perplexed at times, but endeavoring in the saddle, in long stretches over bleak, unfrequented roads, to starve his thoughts into submission and sponge his mind of doubt.

Meanwhile, the tenor of his discourses remained unchanged. Long since he had discovered that to move his congregation he needed not spirituality of metaphor, but powder and shot; and yet, through that obstinacy which inhibits the poet from writing to the crowd, he continued to preach, not to his listeners, but to the lintels above. And to them his lessons bore no trace of the dogmatic. Now and then would come a warning, but the detached and terrible maledictions in which the provincial divine delights were never voiced by him. It was to souls he did not see he spoke, and in his speech were exhortations to virtue and pictures of the perfect peace of conscience at rest. His weapons were parables; the groundwork of his instruction was built on compassion. Did he plead, it was for patience, for abnegation of self; did he exhort, it was to charity, to forgiveness of sin.

Christopher Gonfallon did not preach to the lintels wholly in vain. One green afternoon in June, while he was engaged with the litany, a little man, rather stout, rather pompous, yet shrewd of eye, an individual unknown to the villagers, entered the church and dropped into the first convenient pew, the which, thereupon, apparently interested him no further. During the services he remained apathetic; during the sermon that followed he did not once take his eyes from the preacher. And when, to the accompaniment of the usual “Let your light so shine,” the warden handed him, tentative fashion, the plate, that gentleman was bewildered at the receipt, not of the fraction of a dollar which he had expected, but of the most majestic contribution which he had as yet borne to the rail.

In a village a bit of gossip seems rather to permeate the air than to circulate from mouth to mouth: it reaches the sojourner whether he will it or not. Before teatime that evening every one in Bronx knew that the little man was Bucholz the monopolist, a visitor, with his daughters, at the house on the hill, piloted there, it was rumored, by the countess’s nephew, Alphabet Jones.

To the house on the hill that evening Christopher Gonfallon was bidden. In summer it was the custom of the countess not to sup, but to dine; and when the doors of the semi-baronial hall were thrown open and a servant announced that her ladyship was served, Gonfallon discovered that it was his privilege to lead to the repast one of the two daughters of the monopolist alluded to. She was, he presently observed, a very fetching young woman. Her skin was eburnean in its clarity, her eyes of iserine, and in her features something there was that suggested a pastel of a politer age, an Eve on a fan. Across the table her sister sat, an undeveloped slip of a girl, at whom Gonfallon glanced but once. It was to the elder that he gave his attention, and it took him but a moment to perceive that that attention was not thrown away. She was breezy of speech, though not of manner, and she was garmented in a mode and texture which her neighbor did not remember to have remarked before. When he addressed her, he detected her thought running just in advance of his own, completing it as it were with little embroideries of home manufacture; and when in turn she led the talk, she seemed, in comparison to his parochial dames and damsels, the visitant from a larger world. Beside her he felt himself the rustic: for a little space he fancied that he must seem awkward, a fancy which did not tend to an increase of confidence, and when, later on, he journeyed over the yellow road to the parsonage, he noted with a pang of mortification that unconsciously he had been envying the easy assurance of Alphabet Jones.

The Bucholz family disappeared noiselessly as they had arrived; and when the stifle of summer disappeared as well, one of that family was still remembered in Bronx. Now and then, in some leaf-bound quietude that was stirred if at all but by the call of some ruffian bawling to the cows, Gonfallon had caught himself wishing for the wider spheres that lay beyond the hills and musing through fringes of melancholy on the desolateness of his life. Thus far the feminine had been apart from his existence. In the first fervors of the calling which he had adopted, the celibacy of the priesthood in the Mother Church had seemed to him obligatory on whomso devoted his energies to Christ, and unprompted he had paraphrased a familiar dictum—a cleric married is a cleric marred. As an adolescent he had been of too shy and vibrant a nature to consort in comfort with the combustible maidens of the Massachusettsian town in which his boyhood had been passed, and at the university the mysticism of the spirit had dulled the virility of the flesh. But now the first fervors had gone. He had weighed the Mother Church; her laws had no hold on him. The mysticism with which he had spurned the earth had faded like spilt wine; while of his energies, nothing, apparently, had resulted. In his pastorate he was not disliked, but he was not appreciated. His predecessor had been oafish as his charges, and by that very oafishness the good will of the parish had been won—he had been of themselves; whereas Gonfallon was of a clay so fine that they felt him above them, a fact which in itself was a reproach. Moreover, he was a bachelor: save his mother, their womenfolk had no one to receive them did they perpetrate a contribution-party, and about the stove in the village store the misdeeds of unmarried divines to which the press gave prominence had been chuckled over with envious and suspicious glee.

Presently the summer spent itself, the stifle departed; but before the earliest frost had used its palette on the leaves there came an invitation from the metropolis beyond. The Church of Gethsemane—nicknamed that of the Holy Bilk—that edifice which from the corner of Fifty-Second Street and Fifth Avenue projects sheer up into carolling azure the brownest and steepest of steeples, was in need of a new incumbent. The former rector—an exegete and eschatologist of more than passing note, a scholar possessed of rare controversial ability, and, parenthetically, English by birth, a man whose mere attitude and manner were pervasive with a seduction so alluring that through it depopulated pews had been repeopled and filled—suddenly had come to grief. In spite of the wage, ten thousand a year paid quarterly and in advance, he had managed to run up a hillock of debts which if not fabulous in size had been noisy and unseemly of utterance. At the initial clamor there had been a hush, then a murmur and an effort to suffocate the scandal in its cradle, but inarticulate whispers floated the facts abroad, the rector vanished, and Gethsemane, dubbed there and then the Church of the Holy Bilk, witnessed a procession of clerics ascending and descending the pulpit stair. But apparently no one of them had more than momentarily pleased. Then a call, prompted by Bucholz, had been voiced in Gonfallon’s ears. If he hesitated, not even his mother knew it. The dust of Bronx he shook from him. He came, he preached, and when the benediction was given, the rectorship was his.

At the hour when that intelligence was conveyed to him he escaped into solitude and with a finger beat a tattoo on his teeth. During that tattoo his thoughts went forward and back. He reviewed the negligent years, he interrogated the future. Behind him were bundles of baseless appearances, the mysticism which had shrouded his youth, the akosmism into which Berkeley had led him, then the long halt, the lintels of the village church; but now Fifth Avenue lay at his feet, beyond were the insignia of the episcopate, while in him pulsed that strength which brings the strophium to the conqueror. And as he peered at the stranger that was himself, anyone who had chanced that way would have discerned, not a man, but an aim. That day he called on Bucholz, and, not finding him at home, gave an hour to his daughter Ruth.

Gonfallon’s metropolitan success was immediate. He made no attempt to theorize with history; he did not meddle with Paul; the expounding of the gospels he left to others. With a set of people that fancied themselves in possession of advanced views and were still in the Middle Ages, he achieved the impossible: he not only consoled, he flattered, he persuaded and fascinated as well. In a word, he detained attention, not with home truths, however, but with issues and questions which few have energy enough to probe for themselves, and of which every one wishes to be informed. And therewith he could be austere, stern even, and he could wield an epigram like a glaive. He was in earnest, too.

It was towards the close of a political contest that he first donned the rector’s gown. On that occasion the President happened to be in the middle aisle. Gonfallon, however, with an apposite text for foreword, took up the question at once. For three-quarters of an hour he held the most indifferent congregation in New York with the topic for which they cared the least. And at the close, with a gesture that swept the church, “Not politics,” he cried, “but religion is the nation’s soul.” It was in this wise that the congregation was won.

Incidentally he did not neglect Bucholz, nor yet Bucholz’ daughter. The girl was shyly willing; as for Gonfallon, he was wholly in love. The dream of celibacy faded, as dreams ever do. He asked, and with sweet reluctance it was given. His mother, who had migrated with him from Bronx, departed to the Massachusettsian homestead; and after the brief honeymoon he settled down to his pastorate charge.

Meanwhile, Bucholz’ younger daughter, Claire, had been sent abroad in search of masters of foreign arts and tongues; and abroad for four years she remained—in fact, until Bucholz, caught in a mousetrap which that arch-hunter Jerolomon had set for him, saw the amassments of his own booty, twenty million at least, evaporate in a night. Six weeks later Claire landed in New York.

And now, the morning of her arrival, as Gonfallon lounged back through the past, the episodes of his career paraded unsummoned before him. He saw himself on the singing sands of the Beverly coast, he saw the elms of the village street, he heard the unprompted prayers of his youth and the sound of his own voice vibrating for the first time through the aisles of Gethsemane. Faces long forgotten returned to him and smiled. Incidents that were trivial ousted others that were grave—the trick the countess had of polishing the handle of her crutch, the vividness of certain dreams, one in particular that had haunted him, sporadically, for years—the idea that he had ascended the pulpit in pajamas and was unable to hide—the tennis-match in which Ruth had played, and which, a sunstroke and a check of perspiration aiding, had resulted in the neuralgia which kept her to her room.

At the thought of her he drew a breath that resembled a sigh. For Ruth, in her enforced seclusion, seemed to have resigned herself to invalidism and the matter-of-fact. The breeziness which had won him to her had gone, gone too the impromptu of her speech, the savors that had so allured. Three years of marriage, and in place of the sensitive, high-strung girl there was a languid woman who each day at stated intervals consumed a furtive pill. His love for her, that love which he had accounted measureless, and which in the earliest transports of the unexpected had thrown him at her feet, impelling him in the belief there was none that could fill his life as she, and prompting him in the utterance, Non hodie solum, sed in aeternum te adorabo—that love which in the possibilities of its expansion had seemed a contingent of the infinite had narrowed into an unsuggestive bond. Where is the Vandal that invented marriage? Gonfallon put to himself no such query. Unquestionably he was happy in his household; but to the happiest of households there comes a moment of regret.

II

Claire transplanted took root at once. It was only now and then, in a bow not from the neck but from the waist, in an intonation, in a haphazard phrase, that you divined the foreign-bred girl. A month had not spent itself before she was in possession of a list. Each day was marked by scrawls from people she had met no one knew how or when. In the evening and in the late afternoons the sitting-room of the rectory, a room which Gonfallon in the earliest awkwardness of prosperity had fitted in that lovable Latin fashion which excludes everything but the necessary and inhibits every adornment introduced for ornament’s sake—the bare tableless sitting-room, with its infrequent chairs and pedestalled lamps, was peopled with guests astonished enough to find themselves in so sedate a home. Mrs. Manhattan, on the wing from Newport to New Jersey, had happened in twice, a signal mark of favor from one as socially occupied as she. And with her, or without her, yet inevitably in her train, were other ladies of lesser note—Miss Nevers, for instance, a young woman who had preferences for everybody and attractions for none; Miss Pickett, whom Claire had encountered in that vague region which is known as Abroad; Mrs. Usselex, a parishioner of Gonfallon’s, the bride of a year, more familiarly known as Eden; the Pondirs, mère et fille, recruiting, as usual, for their musicales; Miss Raritan, with whom scandal had been busy and who ignored that scandal as only the virtuous may; the Duchesse de la Dèche, born a Wainwaring, very fetching in her widow’s weeds, now courted, it was rumored, by Mr. Incoul. And with these ladies there was a contingent of men—Dugald Maule, a young lawyer who dreamed of the bench, famous for the art with which he abandoned a sweetheart and preserved her good will; Harry Tandem, a youth of such lively taste in dress that the previous winter on asking Nicholas Manhattan to suggest a costume that he might wear to the Amsterdams’ fancy-ball he had been answered, “Go as you are, Harry; you are fancy enough as it is;” George Rerick, a young man so vacuous of expression that he had been nicknamed It; Trement Yarde, Claire’s fellow-passenger on the voyage over, a scion of the house of Yarde and Company, bankers; and, last and least, Alphabet Jones the novelist.

The sudden infatuation of these people for his sister-in-law was a phenomenon which Christopher Gonfallon was at a loss to explain. Everything about her, the innocence of her eyes, the purity of her lips, the atmosphere which she exhaled, everything, even to the ripple of her laugh, seemed at variance with such as they. That she should be admired was a thing which he accepted as a matter of course: she was, he had already discovered, admirable in manifold respects. But she was not a catch; the recent disasters of her father must have bespattered her not a little; she was not, never had been, and in all probability never would be, in what is colloquially known as the swim; and yet, seemingly, without an effort on her part, a bouquet of the flowers of the upper four was claiming her as its own. Truly he could not make it clear. Now and then on returning to the rectory he had loitered a second at the sitting-room door, surprised at the murmur of voices, the hum of a conversation that seemed to flutter from ear to ear, interrupted, if at all, by a laugh, or the click of a fan furled suddenly; and through it he would catch Claire’s intonation, undulatory yet vibrant as a child’s, and he would see her, behind the teacups, in her face the flush of the rose, in her expression the guilelessness of one too young to be aware of wrong.

Once only, on the impulse of the moment, he had ventured in, but his cloth must have jarred, for immediately there had been an escape, delayed only by Mrs. Manhattan’s superior tact, which had led him into a corner and forced him into platitudes on the subject of the Bond of Hope, a benevolent institution for deserving poor, over which as rector he presided.

Ah, yes, the Bond of Hope was doing famous work. And even as he asserted it he remembered a smothered scandal of the month before—Ah, yes, the Bond of Hope indeed! But as he smiled assuringly he caught in Mrs. Manhattan’s congratulations an inflection which told him she was not the fool she looked; and when Mrs. Manhattan had taken her Directoire coat away and the other visitors had departed, he himself had lingered, refreshed by Claire’s limpid smile, the guilelessness of her face.

Guileless she was—so guileless, so pure and chaste of face and way, that a day or two later, when Gonfallon, outwearied with the effort of setting new thoughts into archaic frames, dropped his pen, determining, if need were, that he would exhume a sermon from the package he had brought from Bronx, the charm was upon him. Already he had discerned in her something of the confidence of a flower, a flexibility which a passing wind might disarray, that innocence which a breath will tarnish and which it was for him who stood quasily in loco parentis to preserve unsullied by the world. For a moment he pondered on the possibility of mating her to some earnest young cleric, Mr. Qualms, for instance, one of his own assistants, a recent graduate of Trinity, a sturdy servant of Christ who possessed a look of feverish determination and trousers that bagged at the knee. Yet, somehow, the idea seemed incongruous and unpleasant; this thought took a tangential flight, and he fell to musing as to what Claire could have in common with her guests and they with her.

So far as the feminine element was concerned, little there was to be said. Mrs. Manhattan was indeed a butterfly of fashion—rather mature and stout, but still a butterfly—yet did she not each Sunday occupy a pew that fronted the pulpit, under the very drippings of the sanctuary as were, and was not her husband warden of the church? Miss Nevers, he understood, had been taxed with inconsequences; but society he knew to be censorious. Besides, was she not the originator of the Girls’ Friendly Aid Association?—and, moreover, when after some sudden peroration he had extended his arm, with that gesture with which all New York was familiar, and asked the congregation, as though it embodied a unit, Are you one of those miserable sinners? he had watched Miss Nevers and marked that not so much as an eyelid had quivered at the taunt. With Miss Pickett no fault whatever could be found: her attendance at communion had the exactitude of an eclipse. And so far as the duchess was concerned, albeit on marrying a Frenchman she had renounced the Episcopal Church, was there not, poor, errant lamb, a chance of winning her back to the fold?

But of the men he was by no means so sure. Jones, certainly, apart from the ribaldry of his fiction and a mania he had for collecting plots, was harmless as a strawberry festival, and an old friend to boot. Maule was of a different class: he had a coarse mouth, and his reputation was sour. Rerick was not a bit better. Tandem he dismissed with an epithet—popinjay. But Yarde detained his thoughts. Concerning him he had obtained information—information which the young man’s appearance refuted, for he was fragrant, colorful, and grateful to the eye, evidence, however, which Gonfallon was not inclined to accept in his favor. And in declining he was logical; for if Satan be not seductive how can he ever enthrall?

As he thought of Yarde his perplexity increased. He was welcomed from one end of Fifth Avenue to the other. Outwardly he was not ill-behaved, a little effeminate perhaps, but not actually offensive, and yet about him was an atmosphere which Gonfallon could not breathe. It seemed to him that beneath the affectations of a peacock he concealed the beak and talons of a bird of prey—the sort of man that ought to have the danger-signal hoisted wheresoever he went. But still, if Claire chose to receive him, what manner of complaint could be made? Because he himself happened to be of the cloth there was little reason why he should expect his wife’s sister to be exclusive as a nun. Were the girl under any other roof than his own, no form of remonstrance could be voiced. Nevertheless he felt that some remonstrance should be forthcoming. That afternoon he had seen Yarde’s brougham at the door; he had seen it there the day previous, and the day before that. He felt vexed at Claire, at himself—the more so, perhaps, in that he was unable to put his finger on the exact cause of the vexation and display it guardian-wise to her. The only plank that drifted to him seemed to inhibit speech. Claire was so evidently innocent-minded that did he venture to warn her, either she would not understand, in which case explanations would be impossible, or in comprehending she might feel herself aggrieved. In consequence, but one course seemed open to him—to speak to Ruth and ask her to catechise the girl in his stead.

Despite the lancinating neuralgia which imprisoned her for days at a stretch, Ruth preserved the disposition of a sundial: it was only serene hours of which she took count. There was nothing dolent in her tone; her manner, if languider than before, was unwarped by pain. About her husband, the parish, everything in fact, down to the minutiae of domestic economy, she was still alert. The servants adored her. In moments when the agony of her temples was acute enough to turn each individual hair above them red, when a pang would scatter through the cheekbones, loiter under the teeth, and then distend in zigzags and spirals through every nerve of the face, a moan might come from her, but never a complaint. Dr. McMasters, who attended her—a physician who had passed his prime among the poor, and whom the resuscitation of a stockjobber encountered by chance had lifted from the purlieus of Abingdon Square to the precincts of Fifth Avenue—expressed full confidence in her recovery; but meanwhile he marvelled not alone at her self-control, but at the solicitude which she was able to maintain in those of his indigent patients whom he had not the heart to abandon, and whose sufferings, if less acute than her own, poverty rendered more poignant. In these, as in many others, Ruth’s interest was unrelaxing, and her assistance life. While as to her pleasures, the which indeed had become scanty of late, the greatest, the uniquest of all was the touch of her husband’s hand. To her he was always the perfect lover whose charm had won her heart and the attention of all New York. She was proud of him as only a woman can be whose love has idealized a man into something more than flesh. And when, with the selfishness of those who know themselves adored, he would come to her in some momentary depression, it was joy to her to encourage him anew. To her individualism rarely an allusion did she make, and then so casually that you would have thought her discussing the momentary malaise of some stranger whose indisposition rumor had brought to her, or else so hopefully that you expected on the morrow to find her with health restored. Indeed, she was self-abnegatory, fretting only at the imprisonment which kept her from her husband’s side, supervising from her chair everything, even to the coal in the cellar, and in her darkened room clairvoyant as a nyctalope and weariless in thoughts and devices for him.

And this evening as he entered the room, “Chris!” she murmured, “it is so good of you!”

In her smile, in her gesture, in the expression which her lips took on, there was an ambient gratitude, a welcome, and a delight.

“You are better, are you not?”

“All day I thought if I could only get away from the pain; but see, you come, and the wish is fulfilled. Yes, I am better now. you? Were you at the Bond today?”

“I was; and as I came from it I saw Yarde’s brougham at the door. What does Claire have him for?”

“Really, Chris, it is not her fault. He insists on coming. But if you object I will speak to her.”

“It is she that should object, not you, nor I.”

“Yes, Chris, it is for us. Claire!—why, she is a child yet: anyone can see that. Besides, she does not like him: she told me so.”

“H’m! she has an odd way of showing it, then.”

“Do you know, Chris, she really does dislike him? When she met him in Paris, she was taken, oh! just a little, as a girl might be—it appears that there are no young men in Paris—and so, as he seemed nice and agreeable, she was a little flattered, and, I suppose, just a little bit pleased as well. It is so easy to please a young girl! Well, from what she told me, he did not act right. He met Miss Pickett, Claire even introduced him, and then, how ever it came about I don’t know, but the attention which he had previously given to Claire he bestowed on her friend. He sees his mistake now, that is evident; but Claire will have none of him.”

“She has him here every day.”

“Chris, really, I think she hates him. She admitted as much the other night. When he comes here she snubs him. On the ship she was barely civil.”

“He hasn’t enough reputation to last overnight. Jones told me any number of things about him. It is an outrage that he should pursue her here. As for hating him, that’s all stuff and nonsense: she is too sweet-tempered to hate anyone. Besides, even if she did, it would only show that she was dead in love with him.”

“That is not like you, to be cynical.” And into Ruth’s face a sudden sadness came.

“There, sweetheart, forgive me. I am irritated today. I would not vex you: you know that. I will speak to Claire myself.” As he spoke, he took her hand in his, and Ruth, comforted by the caress and by the title, smiled anew.

“Yes, Chris, speak to her; and I will speak to her too.”

For a while husband and wife sat together, discussing matters of common interest, the illness of the bishop, the condition of Ruth’s father, the possibility that before the winter set in she herself would be able to assume the duties in the sphere to which she had been called; and when at last he rose to go, she declared that every ill had vanished. When a woman loves a man, his mere presence is a tonic.

As Gonfallon descended the stair, however, his thoughts were not of his wife. The brougham which had stood before the rectory that afternoon had in departing carried his fancy afar. It had roamed in and out of the possibilities of that young man’s career, and it had not roamed with approval.

According to Jones, Trement Yarde was hardly such an one as a young girl should know. Among women he had the reputation of a freebooter; the men, Jones asserted, were more lenient. But, then, are not men always that? Provided their own family be secure from attack, at deeds of a certain kind they were apt to wink, and approvingly too. Moreover, though the young man had a number of zeros behind him, those zeros were fronted with figures. The house of Yarde and Co. was, with that of Usselex, foremost in the Street. Of course the men were lenient—and the women as well. Gonfallon was not a fool. He knew that everything, virtue, genius, beauty—everything can be talked away, but never wealth. He had not lived under the shadow of the Bleeckers for nothing. But now, as he descended the stair, even that was forgot. One thing was present with him—his antipathy to Yarde, and the warning he must give. That young man, he decided, might disport himself wheresoever he listed, but Claire he should not approach. And with this decision, to which, since his conversation with Ruth, he made certain the girl would concur, he entered the room where she sat.

Claire was lounging on one of those sofas in which the occupant can fall asleep without being preached to. At Gonfallon’s entrance she looked up, and a book which she held fell from her. Her head was on one cushion and her feet on another.

Leïlah swinging in a hammock in a garden of Ispahan was less clothed, perhaps, but not more indolent, than she. At sight of her he seemed to catch some echo of ghuzlas and cithars. From above the lamplight shuttled her curls. On one ankle which the negligent fold of her frock disclosed, glittered a gold thread, the clockwork of the stocking. As he approached there came to greet him the clean odor of acorns and of pines.

Suddenly the curtain must have claimed his attention, for for a moment he busied himself with it. Then he turned again to where she lay.

“Did you ride this morning?” he asked, and, without waiting for an answer, he added at once, “You don’t get this Indian summer over there, do you? H’m. Rather close, though, don’t you think? By the way,”—he had been talking at the wall, but now he looked at her—“by the way, Claire, whose trap was that at the door this afternoon? Rather neat, I thought.”

And Claire, with that inappositeness which constitutes one of the crimes which the law cannot reach, murmured from the tips of her lips, “I say, would you mind lowering that wick?”

Gonfallon did as he was bidden, adding, as he moved to the lamp, “That brougham, I mean. The man on the box had two pair of reins; I counted them.”

“Is Ruth coming down?”

“I think not. She is expecting McMasters. Whose affair did you say it was?”

“The_brougham, you mean?—bottle-green, with yellow wheels? Yarde’s, I fancy.”

“Ah, yes—that young fellow that crossed in the steamer with you. I thought—h’m—however—Claire, do you know he is not at all the kind of a man for you to know? Someone happened to speak of him the other day. To oblige Ruth and myself, I wish the next time he calls you would send word you are not visible. You see—”

The girl interrupted him with a yawn: “It was that lamp over there I meant.” And as she spoke she covered her mouth with her hand.

“You see, Claire,” Gonfallon continued, after he had attended to her behest—“you see, while I presume that this young man is not in any way personally offensive, yet, er—well, he is not of a class that we care to have you associate with.”

“Ah?”

“Not of that class at all.”

Claire raised herself a little on the lounge and looked up at Gonfallon. “And what class is it that you prefer?” she asked.

“H’m. Well, Claire, this Mr. Yarde is notoriously a loose fish. It is unnecessary that I should particularize; but we prefer that you only see men whose intentions are honorable.”

Claire laughed. “There aren’t any,” she answered, and let her head fall back on the cushion.

III

For a moment Gonfallon stared, open-mouthed, astonished as a yokel at a thimble-rigger. And as Claire picked up the book which she had dropped at his entrance, he stood quite still, groping among the obscurities of her speech. But it was impossible, he told himself, that a girl so fragrant of innocence should wittingly make a remark as paradoxically unanswerable as was that. It was a mistake; he had not heard her words aright, or else she had uttered them as a child utters haphazard a phrase caught up and retained. But something in her attitude, the manner in which she turned the page, the carriage of her head, the abandonment of the body, the indiscretion of a foot uptilted on a cushion, the contraction of the under lip betokening a smile suppressed and suggestive of merriment aroused not by the book she held but by some picture which memory had just disclosed—these things, intercepted in a glance, revealed a Claire unknown and wholly undivined.

Noiselessly as he had entered he turned and left the room. Across the hall was his study; and as he sank on the ample lap of an easy-chair in which it was his custom to scaffold his homilies, suddenly his pulse was stirred. At the moment he made no attempt to dominate, he sat in wonder at himself, the will refractory and perverse. But presently he was on his feet again, his teeth set, and in his eyes that expression which the horseman has when he masters with curb and with knee.

On the mantel before him was a mirror, a convenience serviceable on those occasions when, surprised by some unawaited visit, it was necessary to filch a reflection for the adjustment of neckcloth or of hair. But now in the surprise at a visitant such as he had never encountered before he fronted the mirror, his teeth still set, the jaw unrelaxed; and as he stood the rumor of the inward conflict moved his lips. “Ah, Tartufe!” he muttered, “is it for this you toiled?”

In his ears a ripple of laughter still rang, a laugh that was sylvan, the laugh of a young faun made merry by the sorceries of spring. “Ah, Tartufe!” he repeated. And still the ripple continued, insistent, insinuating, jubilant in wantonness, clear and heady as the upper notes of a flute. “Is it for this?”

With the grimace of a hound at a vagabond he glared at his image. He was angered and distraught at the intussusception of a presence more terrible than that which Luther outfaced in his cell. “Do you think,” he cried in menace at himself, “do you think that I have fear of you?” At the unanswering mirror he raised his hand. “What have you to do with her, or she with you?” And as his arm fell again to his side some fume of disgust must have mounted to his brain, for he added, in a murmur, “I am as a Jesuit: I argue with myself.”

“Did you call, Chris?”

Gonfallon turned with a start of a subject awakening from a trance. In the doorway was Ruth.

“Did you call?” she repeated.

He blinked, but made no answer. And Ruth, gazing at him from the doorway, one hand on the woodwork, the other upholding the curtain, her eyes full of interrogations, her lips just parted, her head nimbused with the jonquil of her hair, had about her a suggestion of that grace with which Boucher pleasured the Pompadour. To one as myope as her husband, the lines that extended from the edge of the nostril, the circles that shadowed the cheekbones like inverted circumflexes over an i, were unperceived. Through the saffron shade of the lamp she appeared younger, more tentative, than she had for months, and in her voice which now seemed to reach him across inordinate distances was the caress he had loved so well. But he was still imprisoned in himself. He shook his head and blinked as one does who passes from darkness into light.

“No,” he said, at last, “no—”

“Oh, Chris, you are composing your sermon! Forgive me: I did not mean to interrupt.”

With a finger she threw him an apology and a kiss. The curtain fell again, and she was gone.

Sermon, indeed! The sermon was in that patient face that just had disappeared. He sat down again on the chair, and let his thoughts roam back again to Bronx and the wooing of his wife. When first she had put her hand in his it was as though life were fulfilled to its tips: he had conceived no greater earthly joy than the possibility of calling her his own, to his after-days she had brought the blithest airs, and now, after three years of marriage, if nothing remained save that friendship which is born of love and which the fabulist has declared to be better than love itself, if of the ardors which he had believed inextinguishable only cinders remained, was the fault his own? Surely he had been sincere. It is a maxim in law that against a promise to do something in the future no charge of fraud can lie. And if the maxim hold good in law, why not in love as well? When before God and man he had promised to love her always, had he not as fully intended to keep that promise as the honest trader does who makes a note? If bankruptcy intervene and the note be protested, it is humiliating, no doubt, but conscience at least is undisturbed. And yet an elenchicism such as this one with which, as was his duty, he would have dulled the remorse of any parishioner who had come to him in similar strait, left him rudderless and derelict. Truly the advice we give is rarely that to which we hold. Gonfallon sounded its sophistry with a sneer. He would have given hope itself to be able to touch Ruth’s hand and feel again the electricity which it had once communicated, that spasm which in days gone by had seized him between the shoulder-blades and gone pulsing down the spinal cord, leaving him during the moment that followed quasi-dumb, and ineffectual of speech; indeed he would have given much could the old thrill have outlasted satiety, and, though it were through the very force of love that satiety had been begot, he wondered could the fault be nature’s, not his own.

To Ruth he had brought his firstfruits, and in the bringing he had deemed them imperishable as the apples of the Hesperides. He had revelled in the offering of them; he had laid them glistening at her feet; he had marvelled at the blossoms with which she crowned the gift; he had thought them both enduring as the stars; he would have staked his soul that their twin hearts made one would mount, inseparate, into those realms no eye has scanned, but which the gracious Christ, his Master, has vouchsafed to whomso does believe in Him. These things had been the securest tenets of his marriage-pact. And then, as sometimes happens with those mated over-hastily, he awoke one day to the knowledge that it was the woman he had loved, not the individual—the bottle, not the wine.

Of sweeter than she, one fairer and more gentle, a woman kindlier, juster, yet more debonair, it was not within his power to conceive. She was still to him admirable in each respect, a woman whom as sister he would have adored, as another’s sister he would have envied, but who as wife left him as marble is, unmalleable, and chilling to the touch. Where had the emotions gone? Where were the roses of the yesteryear? Where was the vision he had sought to clasp? Though the flutter of her kiss still hovered, ambient, in the air, he told himself that her love had departed like his own, that between them but one thing subsisted—the sanctity of the marriage-vow, unbreakable by either. Of her, in that regard, he had, of course, no fear. And it was perhaps that very confidence, that security and facility in love, that had brought him to his present pass. Whoso has nothing to desire has nothing left to dread. But for himself he had trembled indeed. Claire had exhaled an atmosphere headier than the headiest breath of spring. There was about her an attraction, undiscerned till that night, but which, latent perhaps for days gone by, had suddenly enveloped and coerced him with its force. But now that too was gone.

Ah, yes, it was gone indeed; and he cracked the joints of his fingers in testimony to his deliverance from its spell. For a second he had been weaker, more unstable than water; and now, as he smiled a trifle grimly at the remembrance, he bethought him of the legends of the saints, of Saint Anthony, Saint Dominick, Saint Maur. It was a disaster which overtook all men. But it needed strength to combat—he would have added faith, but something choked the utterance down—it needed strength; and that strength was his. Again he smiled. He would have no need to cope again. Yet, for the moment, he wondered what sudden invocation of the flesh could have oppressed him so. Nothing, he could have sworn, in connection with that girl that lay sprawled on the sofa across the hall. No, it was not that: it was one of those ills which had afflicted and would continue to afflict many another more steadfast than he. Besides, independent of that, what had he of all men to do with such a thing? aside from his cloth, were not his temples gray? and, save spectacles, what better guarantee against love can there be?

In thought he had really tried to trick himself, but in an instant he was at the mirror again. At school, at the seminary, even so recently as the preceding summer, he had been spoken of as That Handsome Gonfallon. And as he sprang from his seat he remembered a bit of gossip that had been brought him, an anecdote culled in the vestibule of the church, a conversation overheard and apposite to the infatuation of his parishioners, in which the first speaker was reported to have said something about Dr. Gonfallon’s congregation, while the second, interrupting, had interjected a remark unreportable here.

But now, as he stood again before the glass, it was as though it pictured not the present alone but the past as well. He saw a lithe, dark-eyed lad, clear of feature and of mind, hurrying to some distant goal, arrested by a mirror that showed him back not youth, but age.

Through the window a moon luminous as sulphur shone. Beyond, the spires of Gethsemane pierced the night. The street was quiet. From afar came the accent of the Elevated, rushing, dragon-wise, in midair, lulling the neighborhood with the strain of its incessant surge. After a dusk in dead rose, the sky had become visibly blue.

And as he stood, interviewing the night, determining that the pulses should subside with years, from the hall came the rustle of a dress. For a second’s space he clutched at the wainscot. The glass gave him forty years, his blood nineteen. Then at once he was at the door, drawing the curtain on its rings aside.

“H’m,”—he affected a little cough, and held himself as though an accident had brought him there—“h’m, Claire, is that you? I thought you had gone to bed.”

“Going,” the girl answered, negligently, and yawned as she spoke. “One has to come to New York to go to bed early.”

Then, something that he could not afterwards explain, some one of those unanalyzed causes that transform the gentle to the brute, claimed him as its own. His cloth, his vows, the rectory itself, everything, even to the presence of Ruth on the floor above, vanished as had they never been. With a spring his arm was about her neck, his lips were on hers, the odor of her hair, of her face, the moisture of her mouth, were his, and just as he strove to clasp her closer yet, with an undulant movement the girl slipped from his embrace.

“There, don’t hurt a fellow,” she exclaimed; and as she retreated, smiling yet breathless, to a step beyond his reach, she added, with her faun-like ripple, “I say, Chris, you seem to like the breed.”

From strength to weakness there is but a kiss. During the moments that followed, Gonfallon felt as were he astride a runaway horse. At first, as he plunged through unimagined thickets, striving as best he could with knee and curb to stay the flight, a stirrup went, then another; the beast had got its head, and as with ever-increasing speed it bore him over quagmires, obstacles, and intervales, at last his own brain caught fire, and he urged with incitements of spur and of whip. In the distance was everything he had held most dear, the route was strewn with his illusions, gone were his unprompted vows, the truths that had been savors of life unto life fell from him undetained, the white assumptions of conscience at rest vanished with retiring landmarks. And, still in fancy propelled, suddenly he discerned a sense of that freedom which is the synonyme of joy. It was good to feel one’s self untrammelled, delivered of the compunctions of the herd; with every breath he drew came a foretaste of larger life, his lungs expanded with fresh odors, beyond was a new horizon, brutally beautiful, wholly solid, dreamless and real, and in it, fairer than the desire of a fallen god, was Claire, her arms outstretched.

IV

The morrow was a blank. Gonfallon attended to his duties with the air of a somnambulist. In the morning at the meeting of the Church-Workers, in the afternoon at the Friendly Aid, the echo of Claire’s laughter rippled through the tidings which it was his office to proclaim; and when the last rite had been performed he shook from him a young licentiate who fain would have passed a moment in Christian converse, and strode out into the gathering dusk and on to the outlying regions of the Park.

Above him was a sky of zinc. Beyond, to the west, the sun had slashed the horizon with belts of amber and agonizing green. The air was chill: he raised the collar of his coat, and as he hurried on unimpressed, unobservant even of the salutations of acquaintances whom he chanced to encounter, never yet had he felt more averse to his cloth. Yet did he relinquish it, what was there left? He was too old to begin life afresh he lacked that energy which permits and even forces some men to turn from one calling to another; he had a wife to support, and down in a Massachusettsian village was his mother dependent on his wage. Truly it was easier to keep up a brave face and draw ten thousand per annum than to pull a wry one and advertise in the papers for an occupation suited to a man of scholarly attainments. If Bucholz had not gone under, there, indeed, would be a different guitar: he could have leaned on him, he could have entered, if need were, into his employ. As it was, instead of the opulence which Ruth might one day have inherited, it seemed not improbable that he would be called upon to contribute to Bucholz’ support. Not later than the previous day a whisper, a breeze that loiters, had told him that his father-in-law passed his hours in extracting, and not painlessly, either, small loans from former companions of his banditti-days.

No, that dream had gone. There was no one to whom he could turn. However unfitted he might be, the pastorate was a refuge still. Yet, even supposing, for argument’s sake, he relinquished it and another cleric mounted the pulpit in his stead, would the congregation be bettered by the change? He knew his parishioners through and through. Half of them were superstitious as ballads, the other half sceptical as himself. There were those who sat very erect and said “Amen” to impress their neighbors, and there were those who allowed themselves to be impressed thereby; there was a collection of boys and girls to whom the church was indeed a meetinghouse, there was also an assortment of neurosthenes; and did he leave these people, in what manner would their salvation be affected?

The mere query was puerile. He shrugged his shoulders in annoyance at himself. Eastward, a splatter of stars, some livid, some as lights seen through canvas slit, betokened the advance of night. He turned, and, musing still, retraced his steps. When he reached the rectory his eyes were eager and his face was flushed.

The hall was silent, the sitting-room untenanted. He put his hat and coat aside, and ascended the stair. To the left was Claire’s room, the door ajar. At the threshold he lingered a moment and listened. Then, hearing no sound, he pushed the door and entered in.

On the sofa some raiment was strewn—a gown, a petticoat, a corset; from the latter a white string hung pendent, the steel tip idling on the floor. At his feet a rose had fallen. On a table beneath the gas-jets utensils were scattered, instruments for the hands in stained ivory, brushes with silver backs, quaint little boxes, curious of form, a rumpled sachet, stamped Cordova leather, four bonnet-pins, a curling-iron, and a collar. In the air was the aroma which women exhale.

Beyond was a bed, the coverlet smooth as an anapest, surmounted by monogrammed pillows. It was white, virginal as its owner, alluring as spring; and as Gonfallon gazed at it the flush on his face increased. “What am I doing here?” he mused, and held his head as one who listens, fearful of surprise. From afar came the rumble of the Elevated, but the house itself was dumb. For a moment he loitered, his eyes fumbling the counterpane, his pulse fluttering like a bird ensnared, and presently, as he stole from the room, he was conscious of that elation of spirit which had visited him in his youth when on the Beverly sands he had crouched close, yet never close enough, to the swoon and the surge of the sea.

That evening Gonfallon broke bread in solitude. Claire had been bidden somewhere—to Miss Pickett’s, the housemaid thought; and Ruth, whom neuralgia had seized again, was lying in darkness, waiting the release of sleep. By his plate was a telegram, which he pushed aside, his thoughts occupied with other things; but when the maid removed the dishes he opened it and read the message it contained:

“We are sorely visited,” it ran. “The Bishop entered into rest this noon. Your brother in Christ, Jabez Foan.”

The yellow slip fell from him undetained. It was so pregnant with intimations that the restless current of his thought was changed. For the time being he forgot all things, even to Claire, and sat, one finger just separating the lips, staring after the retreating past and far out into the chartless morrow. The bishop he had known well. He was one of the few whom he had really revered, a man simple and sincere, earnest for the best, indulgent to the worst, a man who had but one creed, Charity, but one text, Goodwill—a man whose face was so luminous with spiritual reflections that whoso saw him thought he truly walked with God. And now he was gone. The grave would open and close again: tomorrow he would be forgot.

“I wonder,” mused Gonfallon, “that He who made space for the infinite and eternity for time should not have created a being capable of mounting sheerly to some fringe of His mantle of stars, instead of a groping phantom incompetent to leave behind so much as a shadow on a wall. I wonder—”

And as he mused he was visited by an idea which at first he repulsed and then beckoned back. It was that however ephemeral life might be, it was yet clothed with radiant possibilities. Throughout the length and breadth of the diocese there was no ecclesiastic more prominent than himself: it was he who would be nominated for the bishopric. While he still mused, the door opened, and Claire appeared.

“Did you miss me, Chris?”

She was in street-costume, a trim skirt, a cloth jacket descending to her waist, her hands cased in Suede, her face unveiled, and on her head a low-crowned hat of felt.

“Did you miss me, Chris?”

As she spoke, her lips parted as a flower opens to the sun: he could see the edges of her teeth, and in the lamplight they seemed to reflect the rose of her mouth and tongue.

“And Ruth? Is she no better?”

Her hat she removed and tossed pin-pierced aside. Her jacket she had already unbuttoned, and as she raised her arm to divest herself of it Gonfallon sprang to her aid.

“There, let me help you,” he said.

As he caught at the sleeve, he touched her wrist. From her hair came the clean smell of acorns and of pines that had greeted him the night before; and as he bent to aid her, there was a cleft in her neck which might have tempted a saint.

“I didn’t hear you come in,” he added.

“Thanks, put it anywhere. Oh, didn’t you? I have a key, you know. Pickett came in this afternoon and wanted me to dine with her: her people have gone to Lakewood, and she was alone. What of Ruth?”

She had turned to Gonfallon, who stood, her jacket in his hand. At the question he made a gesture indicative of discouragement.

“Give it me,” she continued. “I will go to her now.” And as she stretched her hand, Gonfallon caught it in his own.

“Sit with me a moment, Claire.”

“I might have a cigarette, don’t you think? Pickett,”—and she ushered a memory with the ripple of her laugh—“Pickett was afraid to have me smoke, on account of the servants.”

She moved from him and drew out a case, a toy of fair gold, on the mirror-like surface of which she glanced at her own reflection.

“Try one,” she added, and extended the case.

“No, Claire, I do not smoke, nor should you. But there,” he continued, hastily, for on the girl’s lips a sudden pout had appeared. “Do as you will.”

“What’s gone wrong? The ten commandments are gayer than you, sir.” And to her lips, from which the pout had retreated, a smile returned.

“You were not annoyed at me last night, were you, Claire?” And as the girl, answering nothing, stood gazing at him, her virginal eyes a trifle dilated, her lips just parted, her head drawn back, he added, huskily, “You know I love you,” and hesitated—for encouragement, perhaps, or else rebuke.

Then, as she seemed about to move from him, he detained her with a gesture that was at once an apology and a plea, the gesture of a mendicant accustomed to rebuff. “Claire, let me tell you. I know, none better, that it is wrong for me to speak to you as I do. I have no excuse. Yet when you came—see, it is but a month ago—you brought a gladness and a sorcery. At first I did not understand, but last night it was as a sense recovered: I knew that all my life I had hungered for you. You were the odor of a feast at which I had longed to sit, the shadow of a hope which I had dreamed to claim. Claire, listen to me. It is not years that make our age: I was old at twenty, I am young today, and it is youth that loves best and most. Let me love you. There, I will ask nothing in return, but I have such need of you! Each emotion I compressed expands to you, every illusion that I lost you can restore. You are to me the fulfilment of an anterior promise, the requital of an earlier mistake. Were I free I would speak to you less gravely, but I am bound as never Tantalus was. I can ask nothing, I can take nothing, I can only give. And there the misery of it is; for my power of giving is slight indeed. Were I master of fate instead of slave, and had you a wish, like a spaniel that wish should nestle at your feet. But this is idle speech; forgive it me. The fact remains, I love you, not alone with all my heart, but as no other has loved you yet, as no other can love you now.”

The initial phrases of this address had come from Gonfallon haltingly, but as he warmed to the work they fell from him in rounded periods, as they were wont to when he preached. And that magnetism which was in him, the electricity which he diffused and which had made him what he was, the foremost ecclesiastic in the largest of provincial cities, seemed now to be coercing the girl, despite herself, to his mood. Her eyes drooped, her lips were compressed, in her cheeks the color rose and subsided, vacillating as it were with retroacting and contending currents. And Gonfallon, as he scanned her face, felt an exultant throb. With a movement of the arm that would have encircled an oak he caught her in his embrace. The jacket had gone from her, the gold toy had disappeared. For a second that was an eternity he was conscious of her emollient mouth on his, his fingers intertwisted with her own. In that second he really lived—perhaps he really loved.

Undulantly she disengaged and freed herself. She stooped for her jacket, and when she stood up again there was no sign of vacillation in her face. The back of her hand she drew across her lips, but whether to brush away the kiss that had been placed on them, or the smile that hovered in their moisture, Gonfallon was unable to decide. She had retreated a little, and he made a step to her, but as he moved she retreated yet farther away.

“Claire—” he murmured.

“Oh, I say, Chris,” she interrupted, “drop all that.” The curtain parted, and she had gone.

In a second he was in the hall, but already she had reached the floor above, and, foreseeing the futility of pursuit, he entered his study and threw himself on a chair.

For a while he sat palpitant in alternations of elation and remorse. His path, doubtless, was straight, but it was by no means clear. The mystic penumbra of accepted tenets was still about him, yet through them shone the wonder of landscapes undivined. He was as one who awakes at dawn and finds the night still there. And as he alternately detained and dismissed now elation, now regret, he was aware of that confusion of purpose which visits those that puzzle over a problem they are in haste to solve. The signification of his own attitude was that which stirred him most. At the moment it seemed to him impossible that he should have acted to the girl as he had, and not impossible alone, but cowardly as well. Of the two, was not he the stronger? was it not for him to guide, to protect her, if need be, even from herself? And yet, without even the excuse of celibacy, without receiving from her so much of an invitation as can be conveyed in the quiver of an eyelid, he had performed the most ignoble role that man can play. Had it been love that had impelled him, some excuse might there be. But it was not that. Love would have slit his lips to the ears rather than let him touch her own. There would have been no elation then, no remorse, only an abandonment in spirit, the escape of a dream that might have come true, and then oblivion which is the novitiate of death. But no; it was not that. He needed no one to prompt him that in his heart were none of those choirs which love awakes; not a hymn had been summoned, not a harmony evoked. No, it was not that; it was the beast that is in us all, lashed down, kept cowering and hidden in the deepest cavern of our being, till in the inadvertent moment it leaps into light and claims its prey at last.

Through the silence of the house he heard a door open and another shut. From above, overhead, came the faint fall of moving feet. She had left Ruth, he knew; she had gone to her room. Now she had latched the door; now she was at the window, he heard the shutters close. The footfalls seemed to cross the room, and for the moment he pictured her standing as he had seen her once, before the glass, her arms raised, the fingers interlocked behind her head. What was it, after all, he wondered, that had impressed him so? It was not the refinement of her nature: there were times when he thought her almost coarse. Her mind was a rendezvous of platitudes; and as for her beauty, he could have sent a prayerbook skimming from the pulpit and in whatever aisle of Gethsemane it chanced to fall would be a girl fairer, more feminine, more appetizing yet, than she. But would there, though?

An almost imperceptible footfall from the room above aroused him from his revery. The sound was fainter than before; the feet that stirred were unshod, stockingless perhaps. Their faint tinkle ushered a fresh vision into the chambers of his mind: he saw her in a fabric so delicate of texture that it could be drawn through a ring, a garment immaterial as a moonbeam, her neck uncovered, and about her half-closed eyes and red moist lips the subtle smile of a faun.

In anger at himself he sprang to his feet. On the table before him was a heap of the manufactures of rationalist, of sophist, and of sage. Every one of those who have taken the nimbus from a god and pointed to an eternal grave had left a textbook there. For some time they had been accumulating on back bookshelves; but the day before, with some sermon in view, he had got them within reach. It is good to be valiant in the pulpit, it is good to confute; and the privilege of demolishing any doctrine that conflicts with Christianity, particularly when there is not the slightest danger of being answered back, is a pleasure in itself. But each time Gonfallon had handled a materialist, zest in his own creed declined. An Englishman, Clifford, who described the universe as an immense Sir Roger de Coverley, in which the dancers were atoms and the ballroom space, had the power to take him into an abyss so dank that the candle of faith was snuffed. A Frenchman, Flavet, had shown him the provenance of the parables. In Assyro-Accadian myth, Schrader, a German, had displayed to him the fabric of the Pentateuch.

An idle task, Voltaire has said, an idle task it is, this pulling down of enchanted castles. It is better far to examine truths than lies. But where are the truths? Gonfallon had asked himself the same thing not once, but many times. As yet no answer had been vouchsafed.

And now, in anger at himself, in an effort to banish Claire, he picked up the book that lay nearest to his hand. “Comprends,” it shouted at him, “comprends que tu portes ton paradis et ton enfer en toi-même.”

“Perhaps,” he muttered.

He put the book down and took another. It happened to be one of Renan’s melodious fumisteries; and as he opened it a phrase jumped out and stabbed him in the eyes: “La vertu est une suprême illusion.”

“Perhaps,” he repeated.

A third volume, a summary of German metaphysics, lay within reach. “The heavens are void,” it insisted. “There has been nothing, there is nothing, there will be nothing, save a constant evolution, a continuous development, with death for a goal.”

“Nothing?”

He left the table and its blasphemies, and turned to the window. His anger had gone, his thoughts of Claire as well, and in their train seemed to have departed the strength—or the weakness, was it?—which had visited him the preceding night. Yet as he looked up into the taciturn sky, something must have rebelled within him; for he groaned to the stars, “O Chaos, take that Nothing back and give us Satan in its stead!”

V

Decidedly the days were shorter. As Gonfallon let himself in with a latchkey, it was barely five, yet already night had come. The hall was dark; and as he drew off his gloves, straightening and folding them methodically as was his custom, he told himself that Jane must have forgotten the gas.

From the sitting-room came a murmur, and through the portière a thread of light. “It is Ruth,” he reflected. For that morning she had appeared at breakfast, declaring that she had rested well, and that for the time being at least she was free of pain. “It is Ruth and some visitor,” he reflected—Mr. Qualms, perhaps—and he made to enter the room, but at once he drew back. The glimpse which he caught had shown him not Ruth, but Claire, and at her side Trement Yarde. They were standing a little apart from each other, their backs turned to the door, and for a moment Gonfallon hesitated, his hand on the curtain’s fringe.

Since the preceding night he had not seen the girl. She had breakfasted, as she usually did, in her room, and, shortly after the morning meal, matters connected with the bishop’s decease had demanded his presence abroad, detaining him until now.

And as he hesitated, Yarde, who had been speaking in a monotone, pitched his voice in higher keys. Gonfallon’s fingers tightened on the fringe. He hated the man, he hated his looks, the cut of his coat, his intonation, everything, even to his manner and the trick he had of contemplating his fingernails.

“This is the third time I have asked you,” Gonfallon heard him say.

“If it is the last,” Claire answered, “there must be luck in odd numbers, after all.”

“You are decided, then?”

“Fully.”

“Very good. It remains to me—there, listen a moment, won’t you?”

During the pause that followed Gonfallon fancied the young man eying the polished tips of his fingers.

“It is this. Some day you may be in need of assistance. If you are, believe me, there is no one to whom you can turn more readily than to me. You know where I live, and, parenthetically, I can assure you that the walls of my apartment are dumb—”

“Leave the room.”

The command reached Gonfallon with the resonance of a bell.

“Certainly, since you wish it. In fact, I was on the point of doing so. Save at your invitation, I will not venture to enter it again.”

It was evident that Yarde had turned. Gonfallon dropped the fringe, and groped back into the shadows.

“I am sorry to have annoyed you,” the young man added. He had reached the threshold, and Gonfallon moved yet farther away.

“If you do not leave I will ring.”

“And I must assure you,” he continued, “that I would not have made this suggestion had I not—unless, h’m, well—I saw my father this afternoon. He is in Wall Street, you know. Good night, Miss Bucholz.”

There was a rush of light, the curtain fell again, the front door opened and closed.

Gonfallon still stood in the darkness, one arm extended along the wall, the other pendent at his side. His head was bent, his eyes fixed on the stair. From the adjoining room came the sound of Claire’s uneasy tread: she seemed to be pacing the room, restless as a panther is, lashing the furniture with her skirt.

What manner of girl was she, that Yarde should permit himself such a speech? And what manner of man was he, that he should suffer such a speech to pass unpunished? Gonfallon’s hand clinched, and the arm which had extended along the wall he raised in anger. But it was himself he could have struck: he was humiliated at his own attitude. He knew, none better, that it had been his duty to interrupt, to protect, and to force that libertine from the door.

And Claire! He heard her cross the room again, and felt that the indignity was smarting still. If she had repulsed the man at first, might it not be because of him?

He left the shadows; in a moment he was with her. The promenade had ceased: she had thrown herself on a lounge, and sat, her feet crossed, her virginal eyes upturned and pensive.

“I saw that man Yarde go out,” he began, abruptly. “What was he doing here?”

Claire lowered her eyes from the ceiling to the wall. “Really,” she answered; “I took no note of his action. He spoke of the weather, I believe, and—let me see; oh, yes, he quoted a passage from Horace, which if I understood I would repeat, and—and asked after you. Ruth seems better today, doesn’t she?”

Gonfallon’s breath came quicker. The change in Claire, a change which since the preceding night was greater than that of an August displaced by March, the flippancy of her indifference, the enervations of the day, the conflicts with himself, the conversation overheard and uninterpreted, the unexplained presence of a man whom he loathed and whom he could give himself no valid reason for loathing—these things had put him in a state of irritation which is comparable only to that which comes of a sudden depletion of force. But of the inward ferment there was little if any outward show. He eyed her narrowly, his lip austere.

“At your age, Ruth would have felt herself contaminated by such a man,” he said, at last, and paused expectant of some reply.

But Claire answered nothing. Her eyes had gone up again to the ceiling. From beneath her skirt a patent-leather shoe, narrow and pointed, moved in and out.

“Did you not hear me?” he asked.

“Yes,” she answered, with her negligent drawl—“yes, I heard; but you see, Chris, customs have changed since the fall of Troy.”

To this Gonfallon feigned assent, his lip austerer than before.

“Very true,” he said. “Yet, if I may not admonish you, it is at least my duty to inform your father that you receive a ruffian to insult you in my house.”

“Ah!” As though battle were imminent, she straightened herself. Her expression had lost its flippancy; it had become frosty and brilliant. “Do you know, I thought you were listening? In regard to father, do as you like; only don’t tell him you mistook his daughter for—”

The speech unfinished was like a bugle blown through the crimson of an autumn eve. It was harmonious, it was inspiring, but it jarred. It awoke Gonfallon from a trance. Claire’s eyes were no longer pensive; they had the chill and glitter of steel. And now as she laughed her voice was hard and metallic as her eyes.

“There, Chris,” she added, in lighter tone; “I am not one of your congregation yet.”

She had arisen, and was about to pass him by, but something in his face seemed to detain her steps. Through one of those influences occult yet recognized, her lips took on their former sweetness, her eyes glowed, and she smiled.

“Claire—” he murmured, and would have caught and held her, perhaps, but a voice in the hall, unheard by him, must have alarmed her: she eluded him, and disappeared in the dining-room beyond.

“Mr. Bucholz, sir, and can he see you?” It was Jane the housemaid, angular as a hendecagon and prim as a Puritan Sunday.

Gonfallon started. He was as an aeronaut dropped from colorless ether into some dank moraine.

“He says it’s most important,” the woman added, and patted her apron flat.

As yet he was not wholly himself; the variety and multiplicity of emotions had not had the effect of a sedative; but he nodded gravely enough, and presently he caught a whiff of alcohol: Mr. Bucholz was before him.

“Take a seat,” said Gonfallon, mechanically.

“Thanks, I’ve just had one.”

The tone in which he spoke arrested attention. For a second Gonfallon eyed him suspiciously. Could it be that Claire—But no; such a supposition was absurd.

“Gonfallon, I want a moment with you. Are you busy?” Mr. Bucholz spoke with the air of one to whom the possible occupation of his host was a matter of no importance.

To Gonfallon’s hands came a sudden moisture. “No,” he replied.

Mr. Bucholz had a forehead that was wide yet low, the forehead of a murderer. His face was thin, his body obese. Since his disasters his complexion had assumed the hue of a brandied cherry. He looked shabby, and he was unshorn. His manner was a compound of alternate pompousness and jocularity. To Gonfallon he was revolting. To Jane, and possibly to others, it was a matter of wonder that such a man could be the father of a girl like Claire.

“You are well, I hope?” Gonfallon added.

At this Mr. Bucholz laughed aloud; but his laugh was nervous, yet unsonorous as a muffled bell,⸺a laugh that came wholly from within, a laugh which frightened and which chilled.

“See here, parson, I want you to do something for me,⸺something ⸺how shall I put it? Well, let us call it ad majorem Dei gratiam. That is technical, is it not?”

“And concise.”

“And concise, as you say. By the way, I think I will change my mind. Suppose you sit down too.”

Mr. Bucholz found a seat, and Gonfallon, relieved of his sudden panic, followed suit.

“You remember,” Mr. Bucholz continued, “that when Jerolomon got me in that corner everything went. Twenty million; not a penny less. The place at Irvington, the house on Fifth Avenue, the yacht, the stable, stocks, bonds, all the tra-la-la of wealth, evaporated in a night. I lost my grip. The few hundred thousand that remained followed in a fortnight. The last fifty-dollar bill I could call my own I dropped in a bucket-shop. Curious, isn’t it?” And Mr. Bucholz put his hand to his head and for the moment seemed to lose himself in thought.

“Well?”

“Ah, yes.” And Mr. Bucholz looked up again. “Well, after that, as you know, Usselex gave me his gold-business. It was good of Usselex, for I had squeezed him once myself. Jerolomon, I have reason to believe, suggested it to him. However, it was four thousand a year—just the salary I paid the gardener who did picturesque geometry for me at Irvington: why, you get almost three times as much yourself. Or rather,” he added, in an undertone, as though reflecting on the point of the speech, “or rather I got it for you. But that’s as may be. A week ago I learned, accidentally as I then thought, that Jerolomon was engineering another corner in wheat. I went to him and asked a loan. He laughed at me. I told him he had taken everything I had. ‘Bucholz,’ he answered, ‘I took back at compound interest what you once took from me. I am not lending money today: I am paying off old scores. Good morning to you.’ And he turned on his heel. In the course of the afternoon I got ten thousand dollars: I went in and bought. Yesterday the market fell: the ten thousand were wiped out.”

“Dear me!”

“And now,” continued Bucholz, “that ten thousand must be repaid.”

“Of course it must be. Only—”

“Only you haven’t got it, I suppose. Not even ad majorem Dei gratiam. Well, sir, you have got to get it.”

As he spoke, he rose from his seat and fronted his host. His face had changed. Up to this it had conveyed the varying shades of indifference, apathy, and disgust, but now it was resolute, it expressed a determination menacing and inflexible as a bayonet, and of which Gonfallon seemed to feel the point and the chill.

“You have got to get it,” he repeated, “and before Saturday at that.”

And as Gonfallon made no answer, Bucholz bent over him until his face almost touched his listener’s ear. “I put Usselex’ name on the check,” he whispered, and drew himself up.

“You—you say you put Usselex’ name on the check?”

And as Bucholz nodded encouragingly, invitingly even, to the dawn of understanding which he discerned breaking in Gonfallon’s eyes, the latter cowered in his chair. “Why, that is forgery!” he gasped.

“Be still,” hissed Bucholz; “be still.” Then, seeing that the shot had told, he nodded again, and added, with a negligent, musing air, “Yes, that, I believe, is what it is called.” He laughed a little—or was it a laugh?—a sound that had in it the ghoulish mock of the graphophone, a tone that runs cracked and thin, like a man’s laughter, as Swinburne puts it, heard in hell, far down.

Gonfallon still cowered in his chair. Bucholz assumed a graver mien, and, affecting to ignore his son-in-law’s attitude, monologued at the wall. “There was a time,” he said—“but bah! what is the use? Why, I couldn’t turn a block that someone didn’t rush to me with hands outstretched: ‘Oh, my dear Mr. Bucholz, how are you?’ Today the same people—and to every man jack of them I have been of use—the very same ones, people whom I lifted not out of the dust alone, but out of the mud, will not loan me a dollar. After all, they are only human, I suppose. What is that line in the catechism? However, that is not to the point. I am sorry about it all, but it was not for myself I worked, it was for Ruth and for Claire. It was for them I made myself rich, respected, famous even. It was for them I got into that trap of Jerolomon’s. It was for them I did this thing. Ruth you can always look after, but Claire—well, I used to think she would be the richest girl in the land. The hope of a parvenu, you will say. I grant it; but it was for her I cared, for her and for Ruth, not for myself.”

“I can do nothing,” said Gonfallon. In his eyes was the look of one who has sounded an abyss. “No, nothing. The very utmost I could raise would not cover a quarter of the—the—”

“Forgery is the word, but theft will do.”

“Of the amount,” he continued, in a dogged effort to pass the interruption unheeded. “And there is no one to whom I could go,” he added, reflectively, “save perhaps to Nicholas Manhattan. And if I went to him I would have to explain; which of course is impossible.”

“Not impossible in the least,” said Bucholz, very gravely; “not impossible in the least. I don’t see at all why you should say so. Nothing could be more proper. Mr. Manhattan is your parishioner; he is even a warden, isn’t he? I haven’t the pleasure of knowing him personally, and yet I am quite sure that he wouldn’t let a trifle like ten thousand weigh with him if he knew your good repute and that of Gethsemane was concerned.”

“My good repute! My good repute has nothing to do in the matter.”

“You are mistaken, dear boy; it has. When I am promenading a striped suit through the corridors of Sing-Sing, it were facetious indeed did my son-in-law continue to officiate in the Church of the Holy Bilk—I mean Gethsemane. Your parishioners in whom you have instilled so well all the beautiful precepts of Christian charity will show you the difference between theory and practice. Not an atom of charity will you get from them. Why, dear boy, you might just as well begin to pack up at once. If this thing gets out, never will they let you preach again. Really they won’t. I think you can take my word for that—Why, Claire, where did you spring from?”

Unobserved by either, the girl had entered the room. To her father’s query she made no direct answer; she hastened towards him and gave him a fleeting caress.

Then, turning to Gonfallon, “Ruth wants you,” she explained.

“Can she have heard?” he wondered. He scanned her face; it was untroubled, and as she spoke, her voice assured.

“She has not heard,” he decided, and, waving at Bucholz, “I will be back presently,” he said.

“Saturday is the first of the month,” that gentleman announced. “The bank-account will be balanced then.”

But Gonfallon had already left the room. As he ascended the stair, he felt as though it were giving way beneath him. On each side were threatening hands. Yet above no haven was discernible, while below was an abyss.

“Of us two,” he muttered, “the nobler still is he;” and then, mentally, he bolted at the eccentricity of his own thought. “I am daft,” he told himself.

The stair, however, did not give way beneath him, the threatening hands did not detain his steps; he reached his wife in safety and sank in a chair at her side.

“Were you busy, Chris?” she asked. “I could have waited. It is merely a line from Mrs. Manhattan: she wants us all to dine with her on the 12th. I, of course, cannot go. But you will take Claire, will you not?”

“No, no,” he answered, impatiently. The 12th, indeed! He would be in little mood for dining then. “No,” he repeated. “Send a regret.”

“But, Chris, Claire will want to go. Do—”

“Then let her go alone: as for me—” He halted abruptly: an expression in Ruth’s face warned him that he was betraying an obsession of which no sign should be conveyed. “I am tired,” he added, inconsequently.

“Chris, you work so hard—”

To this, with a despondent air, he assented remotely.

“And a little gayety will do you good. Besides—”

“If I could only get away,” he thought. “Is there no place where I can hide?”

“It is one of your duties to go about among your parishioners. I believe it is even a canon in ecclesiastical law.” Ruth laughed as she spoke, and gave her husband a look in which pride and love commingled.

“There,” he said, “do as you will.”

After all, what did it matter? When the time came, Mrs. Manhattan would expect neither him nor Claire. And through his thoughts but one thing fluttered—the longing for a place to hide.

“That is sweet of you, Chris. I will write to Mrs. Manhattan at once.—Come in.”

Someone had rapped on the door, and in a moment Jane entered. “A letter for you, sir,” she said, and extended a note on a salver.

Instinctively he shuddered. It was about that accursed check, he knew. But the superscription reassured him. “It’s from Jones,” he mumbled, and tore the envelope apart.

“Dear Gonfallon,” it ran—“I have just received a telegram from Bronx. My aunt is dying. She begs you to come to her. I go down in the eight-o’clock train. Will you not meet me at the Grand Central? In haste, yours always, A. B. Fenwick Chisolm-Jones.”

“It is there,” thought Gonfallon, “there that I can hide.” He turned to the servant and handed the note to Ruth.

“Is anyone waiting? Very good. Tell him to say to Mr. Jones that I will be there.”

He stood up, and added, in an undertone, “Tell Mr. Bucholz—” But whatever message he had wished to send was lost.

“He’s gone, sir,” the woman interrupted.

And Ruth, intent on the note, murmured, as Jane withdrew, “To think that it was in her house we met! It seems but yesterday to me.”

“I must hurry,” said Gonfallon: “it is seven now.”

VI

It was midnight when the train halted at Bronx. During the journey Jones had been loquacious and Gonfallon dumb. To the one the illness of the countess represented an eternal farewell to the exigencies of syndicates and publishers; to the other, a refuge from the scandal with which New York would presently resound.

Jones, enveloped in an Inverness, wandered out into voluptuous anticipations of wealth to be. “I can go to Constantinople,” he confided to his companion, “or, like Stevenson, I can sail the Southern seas. I can lounge in Quaritch’s, or on the Grand Canal. I can go to Ecuador and foment a revolution. I can turn Buddhist and penetrate Tibet. From an editor’s chair I can bombard my friends and caress my enemies. I will have time to be noble, to be just, and to forgive. I can disappear as though the earth had swallowed me, or I can write a book to please myself. I can live, as Baudelaire wanted to, in a grot of basalt surrounded by slaves whose sole duty it will be to discover the secret of my immense ennui. Like Flaubert, I can call to a chimera to lift me on its wings. Like the Chimera, I can whisper to the Sphinx, ‘O Unknown, I am amorous of thine eyes.’ On the fingers of my sweethearts I can put the crystallized essence of banknotes. I can even pay my debts—some of them, at least. I can—”

And while Jones rambled on, discounting his inheritance in advance, Gonfallon’s thoughts had also taken him afar. In the abruptness of the departure he had no time to make so much as an effort to stay the approaching joust; and now, as he tormented himself with its possibilities, some breath of the philosophies to which the preceding night had been given rose to him, graciously as a balm. “Whatever will be, is,” he mused. “No one can combat the inevitable. If it is written that Bucholz is to founder in the mire and bespatter us all with the mud, no act of mine can prevent it.” But, even as his fancy was comforted, abruptly before him the reef to which he was veering loomed, and in the wreck which it menaced he saw the bishopric gone forever, Gethsemane lost as well. He saw himself a wanderer in unfamiliar parishes, the pulpit loaned on trial, the subsidence in some Western town, and then that most terrible trial of all, the attempt to begin life anew.

In his misery he moaned, dumbly and vaguely afflicted. In an effort to console himself he reflected that Jesus had been a vagabond too—one who had not where to lay his head. Yet Jesus, he instantly remembered, had conquered the world, while he could not conquer himself.

Presently his thoughts deserted father for daughter, and as the train flashed through the night, something in the roll of the car seemed to echo the music of her voice. The irritation which had visited him in the afternoon faded, as irritation ever does. He closed his eyes: he was alone with her again, in his ears was the bubbling ripple of her laugh, his lips were on hers, his were the savors of her skin, his the wonders and caresses of her hair.

Yes, the poets were right: nothing in all the world imitated happiness more perfectly than did love. And if only that nightmare would disappear! If the memory of Bucholz and of his visit would vanish, life, full surely, would be a pleasant gift. But Bucholz declined to be dismissed. He surged like a partition between happiness and Claire. He dominated and appalled. It was all very well to rememorate the precepts of the masters, yet in the rememoration Gonfallon recalled that speech of the warrior Frederick, “Against the ills of the past or of the future philosophy is the best of remedies, but against the ills of the present it is without effect.” And as the train cleft the darkness he blamed himself for his cowardice, for his haste, for the weakness which had made him accept the first excuse for flight, and wished himself back in town, imploring aid there of Usselex, of Manhattan, of Jerolomon even, of anyone who had the power to throttle this thing at its birth. Again he groaned and writhed as Laocoön did.

“It is Wednesday,” he told himself: “by tomorrow noon I can be back in town. Cost what it may, I will get that money, and everything may yet be well. Surely Manhattan will not refuse; and if he does, and Jerolomon declines, then will I mortgage the homestead. H’m, it is odd I should have thought of that last. Meanwhile—”

“Bronx!” The door before him had opened, and a brakeman was bawling in his face.

“We are punctual as a comet,” he heard Jones exclaim.

Gathering their traps, they descended into the night. At the station but one vehicle was discernible, and that, from a loutish driver who stood dandling his whip, they presently discovered was for them. “You ought to have come earlier,” he remarked, with the affectionate familiarity which is peculiar to the New-Englander. “It was sundown when she died.”

“Well,” said Jones, when they had seated themselves in the carriage, “she was a good woman, and a Christian. It’s deuced rough I couldn’t have got here in time. I was her favorite relative,” he added, meditatively. And with that he drew out a large cigar, which he lighted with infinite care.

Through the window Gonfallon gazed at the frostbitten road which he knew so well. Over there, to the right, was the parsonage he had occupied. And here, to the right, was Sever’s house. How small it looked! And as the carriage rattled over the ruts one after another, he recalled the names of retreating structures.

“Yes, indeed,” he answered; “yes, indeed.”

“A woman,” Jones continued, “who may have been misunderstood, as good women often are, but who was never the subject of gossip. I was in knickerbockers when her husband ran off, but I can see him now. He looked like a young emperor of old Rome. And from her never a murmur could be wrung. She did not so much as mention him, or her friend, even, who disappeared at the same time—Mira Wheat her name was, the Admirable Miranda I remember she was called, a famous beauty, and a catch to boot. The count went down at Gravelotte, but what ever became of his travelling companion no one ever heard. It’s odd, those abrupt disappearances. You knew of the Besaluls, didn’t you? There’s a case in point. Besalul married a girl—a Miss Forbush, I think: to all intents and purposes they were dead in love with each other. Two months afterwards, when Besalul, after bringing his wife home from some reception, was sitting in the parlor over the Post, the butler announced dinner. ‘Go upstairs,’ said Besalul, ‘and tell my wife.’ The butler went up and came down: Mrs. Besalul was undiscoverable. They searched the house. In her room were the mantle and bonnet which she had worn at the reception, but of the lady herself not a trace. The night changed to morning, and morning into noon, and still no sign of the absentee. No one had heard her leave the house, and it seemed impossible for her to have done so unobserved. Detectives were summoned, rewards were offered, but all in vain. Three or four years later, when she was practically forgotten, a friend of Besalul’s happened in journeying through France to stop at Toulouse, and while wandering about the town recognized my lady in a rose-garden. She had run off with a man with whom no one knew she was even acquainted.”

And Jones, flicking the ashes from his cigar, added, “I would have worked it up into a novel, but somehow it lacked the dramatic. I never seemed to get a climax. Ah! here we are.”

A servant, a pensioner rather, Rebecca Hays by name, a woman white of face and of hair, whom Gonfallon remembered well, met and led them into the hall. Grief or excitement seemed to have made her vague of speech. The lids of her eyes were watery and pink, her lips twitched spasmodically.

“Elle est devenue idiote,” Jones remarked. “I suppose we had better go up.”

And, motioning to the woman to precede them, the novelist, followed by the clergyman, mounted the creaking stair.

It was a large room which they presently entered, a room that leaned to the south. Across one wall was a stretch of tapestry, not Gobelins, but Gothic, and pictorial of the visit of the Magi. The angle was bare, the other walls cut by windows that gave on the valley below. The floor was of lacquered wood, the centre protected by a rug. Between the rug and the tapestry was a bed draped with curtains that fell from a panoply affixed to the ceiling above. On either side of the bed was a chest of oak. And on these chests candles had been placed.

Very reverently Gonfallon drew one of the curtains aside, and then, as he took one of the candles and held it aloft that he might see the better, Jones peered over his shoulder.

Death had dealt gently with the occupant of that bed. The hue of the skin was little different from what it had been, the folded hands not a whit more transparent than before. Even the expression of the face had not altered: in the elevation of the brow which death had not lowered, in the resignation of the mouth which it had been impotent to distort, the countess looked in the shroud as she had looked in life—as though under her something had been killed, a hope, an illusion, or a dream.

“ ‘I am the resurrection and the life,’ ” Gonfallon through sheer force of habit repeated, and turned to his companion; but Jones had already left him; he stood a little beyond, reading some paper which the white-haired woman who hovered in the doorway presumably had brought.

Ah, yes, the resurrection and the life! He let the curtain fall, and moved to a window. Save for the uncertain rustle of the paper which Jones was reading, the house was so still that one might have thought the countess had already elected it for her tomb. The air, too, was still. Gonfallon looked out into the shadows. To the left some leafless trees crossed their arms, beyond them others, blurred by the night, seemed to crouch in suspense, while beneath in the valley was the shimmer of a lake in which the hillside had turned upside down and the moonbeams danced with the ripples.

“The resurrection and the life, indeed! Where is the faith to which I clung? Gone are its flowers,” he mused, and with a finger beat a muffled tattoo on the windowpane. “Well do I remember the days when death to me was an illusion, a mask of the continuity of life. Now, what is it? At most a chasm into which the stars fall and nations disappear, a depth from which no spar returns, a silence from which no cry ascends. Is there in its darkness a flicker, an intimation even other than that of the ephemeralness of man? There may be. Yes, there may be, but to me no sign is vouchsafed. The countess who died st—have caught the flutter of angels’ wings. The grace which -eh?”

“Read that.” And Jones, who had approached him, thrust a letter in his hand.

Gonfallon crossed the room to the candles and leaned on one of the chests. The paper which Jones had given him was undated, but evidently it was old: the ink had faded a little, the writing was not wholly legible, and from the paper itself came a faint odor of must and of decay. So nearly as Gonfallon could discern, it ran as follows:

“Should you, my dear nephew, survive me, as I trust you may, you will find by my will that your wants are provided for. In return for this, I wish to ask of you a last favor. In my bedroom, where this letter, should you ever receive it, will be given you, are two chests clamped with iron. These chests I beg you to carry, with Rebecca’s aid, to the dining-hall below. They contain nothing of value; merely a few odds and ends, mementos of my late husband, that are of interest to no one but myself. When I die, they can be burned, and no one will be the poorer. Take them, then, unopened, to the dining-hall: they are not too large to go in the fireplace, and by putting in one at a time they can be easily destroyed. I rely on you, Fenwick, to do as I bid.

“Your affectionate aunt,
“Laura of Cinq-Cygne.”

And beneath, by way of postscriptum, though evidently of more recent date, was written—

“Rebecca seems to be failing. If possible, get Dr. Gonfallon to assist.”

“Well?” said Jones.

Gonfallon had read the letter, and stood eying the superscription. “Well,” he answered, “there is a law, whether common or statute I am uncertain, but there is a law which inhibits just such a thing as this. To oblige your aunt is an easy matter. The question is—”

“The law be blowed! The question is whether you will assist me. Whether or not the mementos consist in the frippery of a dead soldier, what does it matter, after all? My aunt speaks of her late husband: who knows what she meant? Women have odd circumlocutions. It is my duty to do as she bids, and do it I will.”

As he spoke he turned to one of the chests, and, removing the candles, drew it to the centre of the room. “See,” he added, “if it were packed with tracts it couldn’t be lighter.” And the gesture which he made was so cynical yet so sincere that Gonfallon, divining the uselessness of argument, nodded his assent.

“Now,” continued Jones, “if you will take one end I will take the other. Yet wait a second.” He left the room, and presently returned. “The way is clear. The sooner we get them down, the better.”

At once then, the chest between them, they moved out into the hall. From the floor above came the faint waver of a light. Beneath, a lamp was burning. As they moved, the flooring creaked; the great house was alive with echoes.

On the landing Jones stopped and lowered his end of the chest. “I will get a candle,” he said, as he did so. But his movement must have been ill calculated or over-abrupt—both, perhaps—for the added and unexpected weight which Gonfallon was then called upon to maintain found his fingers unprepared; the chest slipped from him and with the reverberation of thunder bounded down the giant stair. Barely had it started in its tumultuous descent before it seemed to leap sheer into the air and fall with a final crash on the floor below. Yet even in that infinitesimal space of time, above the reverberations soared the anguish of a woman’s cry; and for one second, leaning on the banister above them, in the uncertain flicker, both caught a glimpse of the white-haired retainer, her eyes dilated and mouth agape. Then, at once, you could have heard a lizard move.

“H’m,” muttered Jones, with an uncomfortable shrug; “let’s ask the other chest to be good enough not to be in such a hurry.”

“Look!” Gonfallon exclaimed; “it has either split in two or the lid has been wrenched open.”

The novelist extracted a monocle from his waistcoat and gazed into the shadows.

“Serves it right,” he answered, and leisurely descended the stair. “ ‘And of the remnants—’ ” he continued, but midway in the quotation he halted. On the floor at his feet was something that sent a thrill down his spine, an object but a trifle larger than a Dutch cheese, one that had ossified and turned from dull red to dingy white, an unpleasant thing that had no business there.

He stooped and eyed it. Near the base was the rictus which the New-England lad cuts in the face of a pumpkin, and above it near the top was a fissure that resembled the signature of an axe. By it a scrap of paper had fluttered, and just beyond, the chest lay yawning and empty.

When Jones stood up again the paper was in his hand—a square bit of parchment stamped with ensigns armorial, under which for legend ran the splendid device, Malgré tout. Beneath, three or four lines had been written.

“ ‘This,’ ” he read aloud, “ ‘This is the head of Jean-Renest-Marie, Count of Cinq-Cygne, Seigneur of Dol, at one time second lieutenant in the 19th Dragoons. May God have mercy on his soul!’ ”

He tossed the paper in the chest, and turned to Gonfallon. The latter was livid. “What do you say to that?” he asked. And then, as his friend steadied himself against the wall, “I will wager,” he continued, “that a companion-piece is in the other chest, another memento like that on the floor, and another document couched perhaps somewhat as follows: ‘This is the head of Mira Almer Wheat, daughter of Arthur Percy Wheat, of New York, esquire;’ and for epitaph, ‘Wheat is not quickened except it die.’ ”

“Hush! for heaven’s sake, hush! Someone may hear you.”

“Bah! The servants sleep in the wing; in this part of the house there is no one but Rebecca—an accomplice I presume, an imbecile I am sure. And to think,” Jones added, after a moment, “to think that for twenty years that aunt of mine should not only have jockeyed the world, but that each night of those twenty years those chests should have been on either side of her, the last things she saw before closing her eyes, the first she saw on awakening! Why, Gonfallon, they were with her sleeping or waking; they were in her dreams, in her nightmares; she had made the dead her life, revenge a sustenance. What a plot! Shade of Balzac, what a plot!”

“Jones,” expostulated Gonfallon, “you are indecent.”

“Ah! I am indecent, am I? Well, perhaps—perhaps. But if you knew what a trade fiction is! Whoso enters there leaves every blush behind.”

He picked up the skull, and, turning it in his hand, half to it half to his shuddering companion, he continued in a lower tone, “I am not a whit worse than another, and yet the desire for exact representation is such that if I hold a girl in my arms I study her abandonment; does she weep, I seek a simile in her tears; in her smile is the possibility of a metaphor; I even count my own pulse. To one in my trade nothing imaginable comes amiss. When a fellow adopts letters he must analyze his own sensations. Has he an emotion, he detains it; a grief, he enjoys it; a pleasure, he torments it into a phrase. He lives not alone in his own individual skin, but in that of every one he encounters. The expression of a face is significant as a panic on the Exchange. A bow in the street will tell him as much as a page of Montaigne. He is in pursuit of the evanescent, a seeker after the key of the little dramas we all of us live and all of us conceal. If need be, he will hold his own linen to the cackle of the public. He is the comedian of the pen: it is his duty to amuse, to entertain—or else to hold his peace. No wonder the critics bark; though, to be sure, they have nothing better to do. No, a viler profession never was. I hate it, I love it. It sends you rummaging where you have no business to be, it burns your fingers, it destroys your eyesight, alienates your friends, bars you from the sunlight, and for reward it offers—what? A back bookshelf and a reproach. Ah, Gonfallon, preach to your congregation, but not to me. No sermon ever delivered is worth one of my aspirations. Yet see, I am indecent no longer.” And, shoving the skull back in the chest, he murmured, with the grimace of an East-Side actor, “Alas! poor Yorick!”

“And now,” he added, “let us get these odds and ends away.”

VII

At the breakfast-table on the morrow Jones was taciturn and Gonfallon white. When a little before in the dim baronial hall the flames had lapped at the climax of three lives, there had come to them unawares one of those emotions that are as potent for good as the conglomerate precepts of sayers of sooth. It was not that sin had appalled, for that it always does: it was that forgiveness had been impossible to one they deemed a saint. And before their vision, as the drama unrolled, each had pictured it according to his nature, but both had dreamed.

To Gonfallon it had displayed another of the uncircuitable labyrinths of the human heart. To Jones it had been a document. Gonfallon had imagined the countess pleading with her husband, pleading with her friend, until forbearance had been warped and the deed was done. Jones had evoked the jealousy of a woman accustomed to reign; he had seen, as in a glass, the first suspicion, the affected cecity, the studied calm, the uncertainty, the vigilance, yet still the smile, the laughing yet observant eyes, then the accumulating trifles, some partial evidence, the lure, the surprise, the axe, and death.

Where Gonfallon had been perplexed at the absence of a tenet which he strove to hold paramount, that tenet which the Christ instilled, which turned the pagan into the knight, founded courtesy and banished the boor, charity to the failings of others and abnegation of self, where he had been perplexed at the absence of this sweetest virtue in one whom he thought little short of perfection itself, Jones had seen the artist in life, one who, having tried every means to retain supremacy and failing, had not hesitated to crush. And as both pondered on the two decenniums in which the countess, with her skulls in her bedchamber and her skeletons in the cellar, had fronted the world without once betraying her secret—that secret which now was theirs—“It is hideous,” thought Gonfallon: “It is great,” thought Jones. And both were wrong, and both were right.

And now, as they sat together, one was taciturn and the other white. Gonfallon broke his bread absently. Into the horrors through which he had strayed, there surged the lancinating dread of the scandal at home, and by way of accompaniment to his thoughts was the memory of Claire. Already he meditated some plan of escape. Truly the office for which he had been summoned was fulfilled, and was he not free to go?

“Jones,” he ventured, at last, “it is the same to you, is it not, if I leave today?”

At this the novelist started with the air of a man awakened abruptly, and Gonfallon felt himself called upon to address the question again.

“Absolutely,” Jones answered, as its meaning reached him, and at once relapsed into dream. Apparently, to him, everything had ceased to be.

Gonfallon left the room and interviewed the coachman. Then, his valise repacked, his preparations completed, he descended the stair and rejoined his host. But during his absence a mourner had come, a little old lady, her face full of wrinkles and benevolence, a friend of the deceased, and a former parishioner of his own. Jones, seemingly, was annoyed at the intrusion, for he sat gnawing his thumb, his face one great scowl.

“Oh, doctor!” the lady exclaimed, as Gonfallon entered, “is it not sad? What shall we ever do without her? And Mr. Jones! Oh, doctor, don’t let him sit there eating his tears; tell him that in the midst of life we are in death, tell him he should not grieve, tell him his dear aunt has gone to a better world, tell him—”

“Gag that woman, can’t you?” Jones muttered in an aside to his friend; and, rising from his seat, he nervously paced the room.

At this the poor lady, anxious only to console, nay, even to distract, waded through the feeble channels of her thought till she encountered her son, a young man who was endeavoring to become one of the ten thousand lawyers with whom New York is blessed.

“And Alfred!—Mr. Jones, the countess always liked him so much: she even promised to give him a case—one of her tenants who kept sending her bills for repairs. Do you ever see him, Mr. Jones? He is very studious; he works I forget how many hours. But the law is slow, is it not?”

“And so is the turtle,” snarled Jones, “but it gets in the soup all the same.”

“Oh, Mr. Jones, you do say such encouraging things! I must write that to Alfred. He will value it coming from you. You know he is a great admirer of yours, Alfred is. I haven’t read any of your works myself, but he says they are great. Tell me, Mr. Jones, do you write, as he does, with a quill?”

And Jones, almost brutally, with a shrug of the shoulders that was tantamount to a slap in the face, answered, “No, madam, I write with my nerves,” and stalked from the room.

Gonfallon lingered a moment with the benevolent lady, and then, with a murmured apology, followed his host. Already the carriage had arrived, and on the porch was Jones.

“You will be back for the funeral, will you not?” he asked. “I would rather you officiated than the ignoramus that is here. Besides,” he added, “it would be more becoming.”

Gonfallon flicked from his sleeve a speck of dust. To the sensitive there are few things as contagious as irritation, and the irritation which Jones exhaled had not left him unruffled. But immediately he recovered himself. Because Jones happened to be vicious there was little reason why he should imitate him.

“I will be back, of course,” he answered, sedately. “But, Jones, if I were you I wouldn’t let this thing—h’m, you know what I mean: it’s bad enough, in all conscience, and I can understand that you are upset, but—”

“Upset? You think I am upset? Is that what you call it? I am in a rage beside which the anger of Achilles was a fleeting annoyance. Upset, indeed! Gonfallon, this morning—no, let me begin aright, last night I was imbecile enough to build the usual castle in Castile: I had a right to, hadn’t I? I was my aunt’s favorite relative. She had forty—fifty thousand a year. With an income like that, and strict economy, a man can go far. I intended to. I saw myself in Tahiti, in Japan, at the same time even. There is not an inviting shore in the world that I did not propose to visit—in my own yacht at that, and with a picked orchestra in the forecastle. And this morning, before I was so much as able to get the taste of last night out of my mouth, Tapling turned up—”

“The attorney, you mean?”

“Yes, the attorney; and, from what I could squeeze out of him, that dear aunt of mine, for whom I am guilty of compounding a felony, has left me this—this cemetery and eighteen hundred a year to keep it up with. Eighteen hundred a year, Gonfallon; fancy the infamy of that!”

“And the rest?”

Jones gave his head the shake which a bull gives at a toreador. “To the devil—to some other Jones—to you, perhaps. As if I cared. It’s gone: that’s the end of it.”

“I am sorry; really I am. I can understand—”

“Yes,” replied Jones, “I am sorry too.” He paused and gazed at the points of his patent-leather shoes. His anger seemed to have spent itself.

“You have no plans, have you?” Gonfallon asked, as a servant appeared with his valise.

“No,” Jones answered, pensively. “No; for the moment, none at all. I may stay in the country and raise hexameters, or return to town and dabble in experimental physiology. But as for Tahiti and Japan, I must give them up. Hereafter I can travel, as I have hitherto, on the map.—Well, I am sorry you have to go. Remember me to your wife.”

“And now,” murmured Gonfallon, as the carriage swept down the hill, “to the rescue.”

VIII

But for that day the rescue was of necessity postponed. Shortly after leaving Bronx the train in which Gonfallon was seated hesitated and halted, barricaded by the derailment of the Boston Express. And there between open fields for four mortal hours Gonfallon sat and twirled his thumbs. Instead of arriving in town at noon, the encroachments of dusk had begun before the station was reached.

As he drove to the rectory he weighed the feasibility of bearding Usselex in his house or of waylaying Manhattan at his club. On Jerolomon no attempt could be made, for that vulture took wing each night to an eyry on the Palisades whither pursuit were futile. The cab moved slowly; a stream of carriages was descending from the Park, and suddenly the rumble of the Avenue was punctuated by a stroke of brass, the trailing cry of a horn, and a coach swept by displaying for a second’s space a panorama of high hats, smart bonnets, and grooms the arms folded, impassible, correct. In its wake came a landau, the panel decorated with a coat of arms that was haughtier than a closed crown, and for occupant a brewer’s mistress. And behind it, interrupted by drays and hansoms, came traps from the stables of Robinson, of Madden, Dunwoodie, Forbush, and Attersol, men whose signatures could ransom popes, to whose daughters princes offered their hands, not the left either, but both, and whose wives could not find houses large enough for the plenitude and atrocities of their taste.

These people Gonfallon passed on his way to the rectory, and as the cab turned into Fifty-Second Street an omnibus lumbered by, and in it he caught a glimpse of Bleecker Bleecker, the richest man out of mythology, who sat caressing his chin, his coat-collar turned up, and in his face that vacuity which only omnipotence can bring.

It was to these people that each Sunday he spoke. At their marriages he officiated; when death came among them, so did he. It was he that baptized their children, it was he that gave them Bread and Wine at the Supper of Our Lord, it was he that counselled and that warned. He was their spiritual guide, their friend as well, one whom they welcomed and feasted and in whose converse they took delight. Yet did he in the direness of his distress go to any one of them now, what metamorphoses might he not encounter, interest changed to apathy, cordiality to rebuff, and, for climax, the door! As he stepped from the cab there came to him the giddiness of a sudden fall. On one side he saw the frayed coat of the mendicant priest, and in it an outcast that was himself; on the other gleamed the rochet, the satin robe, the insignia of the episcopate. It was for him to choose; and as he let himself into the rectory, about the muscles of his jaw there seemed to rise the stamp of that force which is known as Will.

“That money shall be got,” he muttered, “ay, though I dig it from the earth with my teeth.” And as he threw his coat from him, raging at the pusillanimity which had sent him careering over the country, losing him hours of which each moment was a treasure, and determining that, however late it might be, he would not sit himself down until the means of intercepting that forgery were obtained, his eye fell on a telegram that lay awaiting him on the table. “More about the bishop, I suppose.” And thereat he opened it with a stab of the thumb.

“God will reward you,” it ran. “I have only thanks.” And for signature—Bucholz.

Gonfallon read the message twice, gazing at it the while with the air and attitude of a lunatic who thinks himself the proprietor of the asylum in which he dwells. For the moment it even occurred to him that Bucholz through some sympathetic intussusception might have divined the current of his thought and was expressing in advance his gratitude for the effort about to be made in his behalf.

“He is mad,” he muttered. “What can he mean?”

“Chris!”

Rumpling the telegram, he turned.

“Chris!” From the floor above, Ruth’s voice descended, and as he looked he saw the jonquil of her hair.

“Yes,” he answered, “in a moment.” And presently, the telegram in his pocket, his gloves withdrawn and folded, he mounted, still perplexed, to where she stood. “He is mad,” he kept repeating.

“Oh, Chris, I am so glad you are come! I hardly expected you today.” As she spoke, her voice wavered, as though she too were thinking of other things.

“Your father has been here, has he not?” he asked, abruptly.

“No,” she replied; “no one has been here. Is she better?”

Evidently she was referring to the countess, and by way of answer Gonfallon made a vague gesture. But the question seemed to have slipped from her, and to the gesture she gave no heed. She turned and appeared to listen.

“What can he mean?” he repeated to himself. “What new abomination is he at?”

“Come with me,” she continued, and motioned him to her room.

“I must go to him,” he thought, “or I must write.” But he followed her, and when he found a seat he added, aloud, “She died before we got there.”

“Ah!”

“Yes; and I must get back for the funeral—that is, if I can manage it. How is your head?”

“Oh, as for my head!—” And she made a movement as though her head and she were separate, as were it a thing that existed only when other things ceased to be. She went to the door and closed it, and then at once, still standing, she turned to where he sat.

In her attitude, in the expression of her eyes, was a fixidity so unusual that mentally Gonfallon gasped. For the time being Bucholz passed from his thoughts and the telegram was forgot. “She knows all,” he reflected. “Claire has confessed.” But of the inward perturbation his face gave no sign, and for the moment, as the earlier danger sank in sight of this newer one, he told himself, “If she believes it, she will leave me.”

“Yes,” he repeated, “she died before we got there. I suppose I should have remained; but the bishop, you know—” and thereat he nodded, as though the death of that prelate had absolved him from every tie. And as he nodded he eyed her, prepared at the first accusation to affect an appearance of speechless indignation under cover of which he could not only stalk from the room but slam the door as well.

Her lips trembled; she shook her head, almost absently it seemed to him, and one hand which had detained the fold of her gown she now raised, and, drawing it palm foremost across her brow, let it fall again to her side.

“Chris, listen to me. Last evening—you had barely gone—Claire rang for a messenger—she often does, you know—and sent some note. I thought nothing of it, and asked no questions. For a while she sat here talking about a habit she was trying to get, and a little later, it was barely ten o’clock, she said something about being tired, and went to her room. H’m. I think I must have fallen asleep. In any event, I heard a noise such as the front door makes. At first I thought you might have returned. I listened a moment, and then went out in the hall. There was no sound. I went to Claire’s room and tapped: she did not answer. I tried the door: it was locked. ‘She is asleep,’ I told myself, and listened again; but I heard nothing more, and, deciding that I had been mistaken, I came back here and tried to read. But I must have dozed off; for suddenly I awoke again with a start: I was sure I had heard that noise a second time. In a moment I was in the hall, and there, on the stairs, was Claire.”

“Claire!”

“Yes, Claire; it was then after one. She had been out at least two hours—perhaps even three.”

“But where? Where had she been?”

“I asked her, and she said she had been to Miss Pickett’s.”

“But she is often there. She was there only the other night.”

“Yes, I know. She told me that Miss Pickett was having a dance, and that she thought she might as well go. The messenger, she explained, was for the cab.”

“Really, Ruth, it was unconventional, I admit, and you must tell her not to go out in that way again, but, aside from that—no, really, I see no cause for anxiety.”

As his wife had spoken, a great load had been lifted from him—one, however, that was immediately replaced by another. “I must attend to Bucholz at once,” he decided.

“No, perhaps not,” Ruth answered, pensively. “Only she did not seem to be in ball-dress, and—”

But Gonfallon had no time to listen further. “Ruth,” he exclaimed, “I have many things to attend to. If you don’t mind, I will get Jane to give me a bite, and then I must go. Don’t sit up for me; and there,” he added, “I will see that the front door does not creak.”

She had fallen on a lounge, and, bending to her, he brushed her forehead with his lips and left the room.

IX

“Did you ever see a ventriloquist? The ventriloquist speaks, a manikin answers. The questions are so adroit, the answers so natural, that every one, even to the manikin, thinks that the dialogue is real. Such, Miss Raritan, is love—a duo in which one of the vocalists grimaces while the other sings for two.”

“Mr. Jones, I knew your wit was copyrighted, I did not know it was profound.”

For centrepiece that evening the dinner-table had blue lilies afloat in a silver pond. About it were a handful of people, a dozen or fourteen at most, who had assembled at the bidding of Mrs. Manhattan partly to greet Mrs. Jerold Fox, a lady who some years before had deserted New York for the allurements of Paris and the Mediterranean coast, and partly to enjoy the primeur of a bishop en herbe. Mrs. Manhattan, be it said, was just the person to do things by halves.

And there, at the hostess’s right, as Gonfallon, expressing in eye and in mien the indulgence which comes of dishes perfectly served, sat listening to the conversation that fluttered about him, attentive the while to Mrs. Manhattan, affecting even to chide her for a jest which she had invented for the evening and which consisted in bestowing on him the title of Lord which the English give to their bishops, it was apparent that he was at peace with the world.

The episcopate, indeed, was not yet his, but during the fortnight that had elapsed since the terrible journey from Bronx, many things had happened which pointed directly to him as its future possessor. Moreover, the nightmare which Bucholz induced had vanished as abruptly as it had come. An anonymous benefactor, one whom Bucholz fancied to be none other than Gonfallon, had sent him the amount in time. And that anonymous benefactor, whom, in the earliest perplexity which beset them when Gonfallon on the evening of his return from Bronx learned from Bucholz’ own lips that the money had been brought to him and Bucholz learned from Gonfallon that he knew nothing of the sender, that anonymous benefactor, at first unimaginable as Abistek, they ultimately decided must surely be Jerolomon, and, presto! in the eyes of both, the vampire changed to a dove.

Relieved of this burden, Gonfallon had returned to Bronx, departing only when the grave had closed and the last rite had been performed, but not, however, before his old parishioners, radiating in the presence of the now famous cleric who once had been their own, had insisted on his delivering one of his spiritual harangues again. Then, the dust of Bronx barely shaken from him, his mother had been taken ill, and he had been forced to journey to the prim Massachusettsian village in which she dwelt, and to linger there until through an unexpected turn in the malady his mother had been declared out of danger and he was suffered to return to his pastorate in town. Meanwhile, he had caught but infrequent glimpses of Claire; indeed, during his absence such a mass of duties had accumulated, so many parochial matters demanded his attention, that until this evening he had had barely a moment which he could call his own.

But now as he sat at his hostess’s right, interrupting the conversation that fluttered about him now with one of those pleasantries which the popular divine can permit himself, now interjecting some apposite sally—sounding as he did so that resonant accent with which his famous phrase, “Religion, not politics, is the nation’s soul,” had been fired point-blank at the President—he looked once again a maker of songs and of laws and every inch a prelate. With Bucholz inoffensive and the bishopric full in sight, he could well afford to be himself. It was good to smile, and his smile was contagious. There was but one thing that jarred.

On the opposite side of the table, at the farther end, between Mrs. Fox and Miss Raritan, Jones was seated, his recent mourning noticeable only in two microscopic studs of onyx, or of sapphire, the which, parenthetically, give the same effect. On the other side of Miss Raritan was Trement Yarde, and next to him was Claire. To Nicholas Manhattan, the gentlest yet the most easily bored of men—and to whomsoever else would listen—Mrs. . Fox was relating a few of her triumphs. Her conversation, such of it at least as reached Gonfallon’s ear, was a glittering spangle of noble names. During her sojourn abroad, seemingly with no one of lesser degree than a baronet had she ever exchanged a word. Her speech was striated with foreign idioms, and occasionally she lapsed wholly into French.

But it was not Mrs. Fox that jarred on Gonfallon: it was Claire and Yarde. From the first, through one of those illogical processes which often hold the core of logic itself, Gonfallon had detested the young fellow; everything about him, from the part of his hair to the soles of his St. James Street shoes—everything, even to the trick he had of contemplating his fingertips, was antipathetic in the extreme. Later, when Yarde had become a visitor at the rectory, haunting it as it were with his unwelcome presence, the antipathy had changed to detestation; and now that he was talking to Claire, and talking to her moreover in a voice so modulated that no one save the girl herself could hear him, Gonfallon’s detestation addled into rage. For the moment he pitied the girl, and sorrowed for her that she should have for neighbor a man she loathed. But suddenly his pity was shot with wonder, his anger with surprise. During the early part of the meal Claire had chatted amiably enough to the man seated between Mrs. Manhattan and herself, and Yarde had delivered himself up to the fascinations of Miss Raritan. But now the conversation had changed, and Yarde was devoting himself to Claire.

That the former should address the girl whom he had taken in to dinner was a thing which, however objectionable in the abstract, was in the circumstances perfectly proper. Indeed, Gonfallon told himself that although Claire in that conversation which he had overheard had snubbed the fellow right roundly, still the dinner-table of a third person must and should interrupt the continuity of a quarrel subsisting between a man and a woman whom the hostess has placed side by side. And now, in spite of that snubbing, did Yarde not address Claire, and did Claire not respond, it would be unmannerly of the one and unseemly of the other. Platitudes are easy of utterance, and the weather, however beastly, has never caused a shipwreck yet.

But as Gonfallon watched them it was clear to him that no exchange of commonplaces was taking place. When he had last seen the two together, Claire’s attitude had been that of an insulted princess, in her voice had been a threat; now disdain had vanished. where the menace had been was now a smile. On her part the transformation was greater than any regard for the proprieties demanded; while as for Yarde, in place of the sulk of a whipped spaniel there had come an air of confidence which was insolent to a degree. Through some jugglery which Gonfallon felt himself incompetent to fathom, he seemed to be engaged in filching from him a thing which after—nay, with—the episcopate was more precious than all things else. And at this jugglery, at this open pillage of his own chattels, conventionality compelled him to assist, inhibiting him even from so much as warning the marauder off, and demanding that he should laugh, that he should jest, that his flow of small-talk should not tarry.

“Don’t you agree with me, doctor?”

In the little drama Gonfallon played the hero’s role. Of the jealousy which had sprung into being within him, that jealousy which spends itself not in a scene but in a crime, of the revulsion of feeling, of the anger and surprise, he gave no outward sign; not an eyelid had twitched, not a muscle of his face had altered. His observations, however long in the telling, had in reality not outlasted a moment; and Mrs. Manhattan, who had been expressing her views on some subject which was doubtless of importance, never dreamed that the guest who appeared to be giving her his fullest attention had in that moment traversed the world, unconscious of her presence, deaf to her speech.

“Perfectly, my dear Mrs. Manhattan,” he answered. “I agree with you in every respect.”

From the other end of the table came the falsetto laugh which Mrs. Fox used as fanfare to sound the retreat of some noble personage from her speech. She was in great good spirits, and looked around, for admiration perhaps, at Jones. Presumably she had been informed of his calling, one which doubtless was to her incompatible with the usages of the selectest set, for over the oysters she had ignored him entirely, over the roast she had given him a glance which she was prepared on the instant to bestow on someone else. But with the sweets she was surprised into remarking that he looked enough like the secretary of the Austrian Legation to be that gentleman’s brother.

“Who did you say he was?” she asked of her host.

“I call him Alphabet,” Manhattan answered, “but his name is Chisolm-Jones.”

“Not a nephew of Madame de Cinq-Cygne?”

“Her nephew.”

The questions and answers Gonfallon garnered unconsciously. He was in the cerebral condition of a chess-player whom the remark of a bystander addressed during the absorption of the game reaches only when the move is made. Do what he might, his attention was centred on Claire; and through that attention filtered the conversation of the other guests.

Miss Raritan was talking across the table, praising Massenet and the inspiration which that composer displays. Mrs. Manhattan had turned to the man on her left. For the moment both Claire and Yarde were silent. Mrs. Fox was captivating Jones.

“And that dear countess! How is she?”

“Better than she has been for some time,” Jones answered. “She is dead.”

“I am so glad,” Mrs. Fox rejoined: it was evident that only the initial sentence had reached her. “I am so glad. There are few whom I have known—among my own compatriots, of course—who speak French as well as she. Do you know, it is really difficult for me now to accustom myself to my own tongue? You must have experienced the same thing yourself.”

“Often, Mrs. Fox.”

“I was sure of it. Nous autres, n’est-ce pas? Mais tout le monde parle Français maintenant. Figurez-vous qu’à Cannes, l’hiver passé, j’étais vraiment étonnée de trouver ma langue dans la bouche du Prince de Galles!”

“Son Altesse aussi sans doute,” Jones answered, with a sniff.

“What do you think of her?” asked Miss Raritan, in a whisper.

“Fox et praeterea nihil,” he replied; a jest which the young lady did not wholly grasp, but at which, as was her wont, she smiled approvingly.

“And now, do tell me,” Mrs. Fox continued—“you know I have been away so long—what is the last scandal?”

“The last scandal? Let me see.” And the novelist seemed to meditate. “Ah, yes. You remember Mrs. Gwathmeys, don’t you?”

“Cynthia Van Dam that was?”

“Exactly. Well, the other day her husband picked her pocket.”

“Mr. Chisolm-Jones!”

“You don’t understand. It was a pleasantry on his part. He saw a bit of paper peeping out of her bodice, and snatched it from her.”

“You said her pocket.”

“Isn’t a bodice a woman’s pocket? However, Gwathmeys seized the paper, and suddenly he cried, ‘What is this? My love, my chosen, but not mine, I send my whole heart to you in these words I write.—Who is it wrote that?’ ‘Owen Meredith,’ his wife answered.”

“The shameless thing!” interjected Mrs. Fox.

“ ‘I will kill him!’ shouted Gwathmeys.” As Jones spoke he imitated the voice of an ogre in a fairytale.

“And quite right, too.”

“As you say.”

“And did he?”

But Jones’s answer was lost. Mrs. Manhattan had moved, and at that signal her guests rose from the table. When the men, after accompanying the womenfolk into the drawing-room, returned for coffee and liqueurs, the novelist seemed absorbed. He took little part in the conversation, and, until his host suggested that it might be well to join the ladies, he sat now puffing at a huge cigar, now flicking the ashes on the floor.

The drawing-room which they then entered, the smallest of the three which the house contained, was so cunningly furnished with everything that you would have expected most, that it was even comfortable and unsuggestive of a sheriff’s sale. At one end a screen served as a partition between two sofas. Near to one of the sofas was a mantel, near to the other a piano. Throughout the room other nooks had been arranged. It was one of the few places where a tête-à-tête can be enjoyed in a crowd.

When the men entered, Miss Raritan was at the piano. On the sofa nearest the mantel Claire had just seated herself. The other women were in a group. Gonfallon at once took up a position by the mantel, on which he leaned, his back turned to his sister-in-law; Manhattan lounged near the piano; and Trement Yarde sat himself next to Claire.

For a moment the room was resonant with that accent which is peculiar to the after-dinner speech. Then, as Miss Raritan’s fingers strayed over the keys, there was a lull. Presently the girl’s voice sounded, low as yet, for she was heating her throat; then suddenly it rose, and dilating filled the room, and, as she sang, each note was evocative of fancies, each word clear as the token on a coin.

Baise-moy, mignonne, cent fois rebaise-moy.

The refrain of her song drifted from her in a murmur of applause. When she had finished, Jones crossed the room to where Gonfallon stood, and, leaning against the mantel, for a moment he gazed at Claire, still seated with Yarde on the sofa just beyond, and plucked at his yellow beard.

With an effort Gonfallon roused himself from a revery into which he had sunk. “She sings well, does she not?” he remarked. “I wish I could induce her to join the choir.” And, as Jones answered nothing, he added, after a moment, “You are the last person I expected to meet tonight.”

“Because of my aunt? What nonsense! Though, to be sure, after the manner in which I was treated one might easily expect me to be in sackcloth. No, Mrs. Manhattan asked me before the Bronx episode occurred, and, having accepted her invitation, I saw no reason to back out. Yesterday I got together a change of linen and a metaphysical theory, and here I am. It is ghastly in the country. If it were not for my man, I give you my word, I believe I would keep myself full as a harvest-moon.”

“Your man?”

Jones had been speaking in the leisurely growl that was usual to him, in a voice in which a drawl and a snarl seemed to struggle for prominence. But now his face lit up, he straightened himself, and, with a glance at the sofa as though to assure himself of the inattention of its occupants, he plucked again at his beard and continued in a clearer key:

“Yes, the one luxury that my aunt’s munificence has permitted me. I have only had the beggar a week, but I have told him that if he behaves himself I will promote him from valet to secretary. His life has been a magic-lantern: he has visited all sorts of impossible places; he has been to Bokhara, to Quito, to Boston—to Mars, for all I know. If I had had a fraction of his adventures I could busy a room-full of stenographers with the dictation of plots. He keeps me in a fever with his anecdotes; he—”

“Is he an Englishman?”

“No; he is a Swiss, or a Pole—both, perhaps. However, I wouldn’t rely on his veracity. He tells me he has only been in this country a few weeks, two of which he passed as servant to some young man here who sent him adrift because he couldn’t marrowbone his boots.”

“H’m.”

“Yes, so he said. He told me something odd about him, too—rather typical, I thought. The substance of it, I fancy, he must have obtained through the keyhole and his master’s correspondence—a supposition which may account for his dismissal. But to come to the point. It appears that the young man, after the fashion of his kind, was smitten in a certain quarter. The object of his affections, poor, parenthetically, but presumably virtuous, would have none of him. In fact, she detested him as only a girl can who has nothing better to do. It may be—”

Gonfallon had ceased to listen; his thoughts had wandered to the dinner-table, and then, returning, settled on the occupants of the sofa at his back. At the earliest possible moment he determined to take Claire and go.

“It may be,” Jones continued, “that the young fellow, in the vivacity which youth will cause, had played some little trick on her which she resented. Joseph—my man—described her as haughty as a Wittelsbach, and of course, as such, not one to take things lightly. Be that as it may, one afternoon our hero sauntered forth, his boots radiant though unboned, a flower in his coat, and the smell of iris on his linen. It was evident to Joseph that he intended to conquer or to die. An hour or so later our hero—h’m, his name was—er—no, Joseph told me, but I have forgotten—however, our hero returned, looking blacker than Cain, abused Joseph about the first thing that came in his head, and shut himself up in his room. Joseph, as a good servant should, loitered within call. Presently, a ring at the bell, a messenger and a note. No sooner did our hero read it than his face changed from Cain’s to Abel’s. It was then eight o’clock. Ten minutes later he was in evening dress. ‘I will dine at the Club,’ he said: ‘meanwhile, do you go to Klunder’s and get all the flowers he has in his shop cover the room with them, cover the carpet, fill the vestibule if you can.’ Joseph did as he was bid. He secured a hundred dozen roses, a basket of mignonette, and yards of smilax. When his master returned, the apartment had the breath of the Fortunate Isles. I mentioned that he lived in an apartment, didn’t I?”

At the question Gonfallon looked up. Jones seemed to be speaking less to him than to an audience behind his back. Mechanically he turned: apparently Claire and Yarde were talked out, for they sat as though listening to the novelist. Gonfallon felt for his watch and consulted it furtively: five minutes more and his cab would be at the door. “Yes, yes, of course,” he answered, absently. “Well, what then?”

“Then our hero dismissed Joseph for the night; but Joseph must have preferred to await developments. He declares that he had some brushing up to attend to, over which he fell asleep, and on awakening did not wish to make his presence known. But my own opinion is that during his master’s absence he found the note that had been brought, and that that note so piqued his curiosity that he hid in some closet in the hall. However, to make a long story short, just before midnight he heard the bell ring, and presently the sound of a girl’s voice. It was evident that she was excited. She entered the apartment like a tempest, and as she spoke her words came from her by jerks, as though wrenched by the effort of one whose patience or whose breath is gone. ‘See,’ said our hero, attempting to soothe her, ‘these roses are in welcome of you.’ ‘It is not for roses I come, but for money,⸺I am here.’ Then the door of the room which they entered was closed. For a moment there was a murmur, then an exclamation. Immediately the door reopened, and Joseph heard them pass out. This time the girl’s voice was assured. ‘Will you ever forgive me?’ she asked. ‘Will you think better of me than before?’ he answered. Seemingly—”

Gonfallon, weary of Jones and of his tiresome tale, consulted his watch again. Down the room some of the guests had encircled Mrs. Fox. At the piano Miss Raritan was still seated, her exquisite face upturned to some man who was fingering a sheet of music. From behind, Gonfallon heard a rustle, Jones ceased speaking, and abruptly the room was in commotion.

Miss Raritan, rising from her seat, hurried forward, followed by Mrs. Manhattan, and in a moment by the other guests.

Gonfallon started and turned. On the sofa, Claire, her eyes closed, her head on her shoulder, her face but little less white than her frock, seemed to have sunk into a heap. “She’s fainted,” he heard Miss Raritan exclaim, and saw Mrs. Manhattan raise the girl up and beat her small hands with her own. Almost immediately the girl opened her eyes, and Gonfallon rushed to her aid. Yarde, who had stood up, glanced down at her and then over at Jones.

“There, I am right enough,” she lisped.

Again Yarde glanced at her, and then, as though assured of her well-being, he moved to where the novelist stood and looked him in the face. “You brute—”

Jones caught him by the arm. “Listen to me, Trement. There, don’t struggle: she’s over it already. Besides, Gonfallon has his eye on you. Did you ever hear of Balzac? Of course not. Well, Balzac was a machine that blackened paper. One day, or rather one night, someone said to him, ‘There’s a pretty girl.’ He answered, ‘You mean a plot.’ Not a novel did he write that he had not dug from a woman’s heart. For a week I have been hunting for a climax. This evening I tried an experiment; it succeeded. I have my climax now. Call me a brute if you care to, but be good enough to understand that I am perfectly domesticated and thoroughly well trained. I always mask my heroine. There, Miss Bucholz is motioning to you.”

And with that Jones turned on his heel and adjusted his cravat. “I wonder,” he mused, “I wonder what that little imbecile would think of Vernet, who lashed himself to a masthead that he might study a storm?”

X

The drive from Mrs. Manhattan’s to the rectory was always a short one, but on this occasion it was brief indeed. The noise of the wheels brought to Gonfallon the echo of Miss Raritan’s song; and as in a constant resummons of the same refrain it beset and pursued him, forcing him whether he willed it or not into a lunatic duo with the vehicle in which he sat, a disorganized lamppost caught and detained the obsession, and he fell to wondering whether electricity was preferable to gas.

Then at once the query departed of itself. Jones was standing opposite, relating less to him than to an audience behind his back some endless story of nothing at all. And that story, to which five minutes before he had accorded only the show of interest which civility exacts, suddenly became poignant and fraught with interest.

At Mrs. Manhattan’s, in the earliest surprise at the unexpected, he had attributed Claire’s collapse to fatigue, to the heat of the room and the strain of her stays; but now, in fumbling about for the logic of Jones’s anecdote, he recalled the novelist’s significant forgetfulness of his hero’s name, the manner in which he had talked at the occupants of the sofa recurred to him, he remembered the epithet which Yarde had blurted out, and at once a panorama unrolled. He had not been the auditor of a pointless tale; he had assisted at the fabulization of a masquerade; but the clock had struck, the dominos had fallen, the masks were raised.

In a confusion of visions he saw Claire dismissing her suitor like a lackey, the interview between Bucholz and himself, interrupted by her and indubitably overheard; he divined the conflict within her, the rememoration of Yarde’s offer, the knowledge of her father’s guilt. Then one after another he comprehended the first incitement, the inward revolt, the renewed assault, the rebellion in her of all that was best, the martyrdom that ensued, the self-crucifixion, the tension of nerves, the defeat that was a victory, the agony over the wording of the note, the despatch of the message, the comedy played for Ruth, the suffocation hid with a smile, the anguish of the preparation, the dread, perhaps the hope, of detention, the horror of the unlighted stairs, the tragedy of the cab that waited there, the agony of her thoughts as she was driven away, her hysterical entrance into Yarde’s apartment, and then, to the man she loathed, her offer in payment of her father’s shame. No, it was more than noble; it was Greek.

Of her possible contempt of him, Gonfallon gave no thought. And as his fancy veered from Claire to Yarde it was with a little undercurrent of applause. Truly he had misjudged the man, not much perhaps, but still misjudgment there had been. He could have throttled him on that afternoon when he had heard him, in anger at his rejection, make that offer which he had coupled with the insulting assurance that the walls of his rooms were dumb. Yes, he could have throttled him then with delight. And yet, when Claire, in her haste to rescue her father, had in her helplessness knocked at his door, he had been better than his word: assistance had been accorded unexactingly, and so soon as rendered, immediately he had let her go. However the episode might be viewed, in this respect at least Yarde’s conduct had in it a dash of the talon rouge. No wonder Claire’s attitude had changed: it were ungracious of her had it not. But there the matter should rest. Claire should be under no further obligation to smile at this subtler Lovelace. The money he would find means of repaying. As for Jones, he could be hushed with a word.

The cab had stopped, but it needed a movement from his companion to remind him that the journey was done. He got out, aided her to alight, and unlatched the door. As yet, neither had spoken. On entering the house Claire made directly for the stairs.

“Don’t go up yet; I want a word with you,” he muttered, and glanced at the banisters above.

“What is it?” She halted and turned. The cheeks were still pale, and the white fur of her wrap increased the pallor of her face.

He put his hat and coat aside, and, raising the curtain of the sitting-room, motioned her to enter.

For a second she hesitated and looked at him inquisitorially, the brow contracted; then, gathering a fold of her frock, she obeyed the gesture, and, entering the room, she stood, her wrap drawn about her, her head thrown back, one foot beating a measure impatiently on the floor.

Gonfallon glanced again at the banisters and let the curtain fall. “Claire,” he began, “there is but one explanation of what occurred this evening. The fault, perhaps, is partly mine. I had intended on my return from Bronx to take immediate action in regard to your father, but you forestalled me. You forestalled me, moreover, in a manner which—which—well, of which the least said the better. Fortunately, matters are not as bad as they might be. You have been exceedingly imprudent, and I have been remiss. As for that young man, his mere presence is sufficient to tarnish a dawn. From your own demeanor, from things which Ruth has let fall, I understand that he is as objectionable to you as he is to me. The obligation which he has placed us all under must of course be cancelled, and to that I will attend; but hereafter it is impossible for you to see him again. You agree with me, do you not?”

In and about the girl’s mobile lips a sneer hovered like a bee on a rose. Leisurely she undid her cloak. “Not in the least,” she answered.

“But you know I dislike him; you know—”

“And why should you?” Her head, which had been thrown back, she now held a trifle to one side. “And why should you? Has he ever done you a kindness?” She paused a second, and added, “You dislike my father too, don’t you?”

The thrust was keen and venomous as the tooth of a rat. But on her mouth the sneer was so quickly effaced by a smile that one might have thought that in her heart a bird had suddenly burst into song.

At the change in her expression Gonfallon forgot to heed the taunt. “He is unprincipled, Claire—”

“Ah! He is unprincipled, is he? And what of it? You have no principles of your own to boast of. No, Chris, you have none.”

She pointed at him. On the end of her finger were all sorts of pretty gestures, and in her face, to which some trace of color had returned, was the mimic of a child saying, Fi! “You must find a better reason than that.”

At the movement of her hand the wrap fell from her. She was bare of neck and of arm. Her frock was after that English model which gives some freedom to the limbs yet keeps the waist well girt. It was colorless yet scintillant, and in it, with the white of the fur at her feet, it needed little imagination to fancy her a statue of Injustice vacating its niche.

The slender finger still extended seemed to pierce him like a gibe. “You must find a better reason than that,” she repeated; “you must, indeed.” Her smile had bubbled into a ripple, her eyes laughed, and she flushed.

Gonfallon’s breath came faster. He had been staring at her. “It is because I love you, Claire,” he whispered. And in a moment he caught her to him and pressed her lips of silk to his. At their emollient touch his anger evaporated as utterly as had it never been. “Sweetheart,” he murmured, “it is because you are more than all the world to me.”

He gazed into her deep eyes’ depth. Instead of an answering gleam, there was in them an apathy, stagnant and unmoved. “Sweetheart,” he repeated, and as he did so the eyes into which he gazed dilated as at some sudden dread. From behind him came a smothered cry. His arms fell again to his side, and he wheeled about. In the doorway Ruth stood, her face barred by a shadow. Claire stooped for her cloak, and Gonfallon bit his lip.

Ruth advanced to where they stood. Her face now they could see had on it the stamp of unvanquishable pain, seared in, immutable and already cold. She glanced from one to the other.

“Claire,” she said, and as she spoke her words fell from her very swiftly, unseparated by intervals, as though in speech relief might be—“Claire, our mother died when you were born. The first thought I ever had was of your good. The earliest effort I ever made I made for you. I tried to be not a sister alone, I tried to replace the mother you had lost. I have failed.”

Claire made as though to speak, but already Ruth had turned to Gonfallon.

“Christopher, the first dream of my girlhood belonged to you. The only thoughts I did not give to Claire were those I gave to you. You took so many, Christopher! I gave you my whole heart; I thought you gave me yours. I was wrong.”

“Wrong?” cried Claire; “you are stark, staring mad, that is what is the matter with you, Mrs. Gonfallon.”

“I am sure,” Gonfallon hazarded, “I don’t see—”

“I did,” said his wife. The monosyllables fell like a sentence.

“Well, Ruth,” Claire broke in, “if you object to Chris kissing me on an occasion like this—”

“Like this? What occasion can it be?”

“Why, Chris was congratulating me on my engagement. Don’t you think you are absurd?”

A light as from some new dawn seemed to break in Ruth’s eyes. She turned to Claire again.

“I am engaged to Trement Yarde,” the girl added.

Gonfallon felt the blood mount to his temples. “It is a lie,” he told himself. “Or if by chance she is telling the truth, then—”

“He asked me again tonight,” Claire continued. “It was the fourth time; I was afraid he might not ask again—”

“Is this true, Christopher?” Ruth’s voice was almost joyous.

“It is true,” he answered, and ground his nails into his flesh.

“But you don’t love him!” And already Ruth’s arm had wound itself about her sister’s waist.

Claire nodded eagerly. “Oh, but I do, though—lots and lots—corner lots.”

“Claire, dear,” expostulated Ruth, “you said you hated him.”

“H’m, perhaps. It’s the same thing, isn’t it?”

Ruth turned again from her sister to her husband. “Chris, Claire has forgiven me: will not you?”

Gonfallon answered nothing. He tried to give his face some suitable expression, and evidently he succeeded, for Ruth, with the dawn still in her eyes, led her sister away.

When they had gone, Gonfallon dropped on a chair and mopped his forehead. “Hatred, indeed!” he muttered. “It is I that hate.” It was monstrous, he told himself, that she should treat him as she had. From a delight she had changed into a reproach. The desire which she had inspired, and against which he had struggled with all the feebleness of his strength, the hope unformulated yet sentient which she had evoked and against whose luminousness he had hid his eyes, these things had passed, the one into a mockery, the other into a taunt. The innocence which she exhaled, the guilelessness which she displayed, that savor and fragrance of youth which in alluring him despite himself had made him forget his office and his vows, was an acquired, a premeditated trick. Everything about her, even to the serpentine movement of her neck, was the understudy of a lie. And it was such an one as she that had the power to stir his pulse and leave him for hours after to dally with the protocols and uselessness of regret! It was she who had brought him visions of larger life, of new horizons and fresher creeds; it was she with whom he had seen himself straying beyond the conventional, far out of reach of the matter-of-fact to that ultimate meadow where the flowers distil the reason of love! And this was she! Full surely then he had been bereft.

He raised his hand to his head and let his head fall back. He was tired, outwearied by the emotions of the night, and for a little while he toyed absently with a handkerchief, rumpling it into a ball and moulding it with forefinger and with thumb. “I am no longer a lover,” he mused, “I am a judge.” His eyelids drooped, he sank yet farther in the chair, and sighed. “Of heart,” he continued, “she has none. Beneath her stays is some flesh on a stone.”

A little longer he rested, then, slowly, with the hesitant air of one perplexed, he rose from his seat, the handkerchief still rumpled in his hold. “She is an adder!” he exclaimed, and, throwing the bit of cambric from him, he repeated, in yet louder tone, “An adder—that I will fang.”

The next moment, without conscious effort on his part, he found himself at her door. Should he knock? he wondered. But no; the time for ceremony was gone. With a wrench at the knob and a blow at the panel he entered in. Claire was before the mirror. She had removed her frock, but her arms and neck were no longer bare: she had some loose wrapper on, and in it all trace of the mannishness which she affected disappeared. At the sudden noise she started and turned. Gonfallon was livid. As she stared at him he gazed at her, and in that gaze he put something that was like a knee pressed on a breast.

“Wanton!” he hissed.

The girl’s hands fluttered like falling leaves. “Christopher,” she cried, “what are you doing here?”

“Wait; you shall see.”

He made towards her, and as he approached the girl drew back.

“Christopher,” she moaned, “you frighten me.”

“Is it my face that frightens? Could you see my heart!”

And still the girl retreated. Her back now was against the wall, her eyes agonized with fear. With a bound he was upon her, and, catching her wrist in his hand, he threw her on the floor. Vainly she struggled; the grip on her wrist was a vice.

“What are you going to do?” she gasped.

And Gonfallon, still holding her down, turned his head towards the table and across the room as though seeking for something of which he had immediate need.

“I do not know,” he answered; “but say your prayers.”

“Help!” she cried, her voice soaring to its uttermost tension. “Help!”

And as Gonfallon placed his hand over her mouth to hush the cry, the crouching form faded from before him. He felt an undefinable sensation of discomfort. In his ears was the roar of water displaced. With an effort he looked about him. He was still in the chair in which he had dropped asleep, and through rifts of returning consciousness he heard a loving voice: “Chris, are you not coming up? See, it is after one.”

It was Ruth, bending over him, entreating him to rise.

XI

Already a handful of guests had filled the sitting-room. In the study, across the hall, Gonfallon, robed in full canonicals, stood motionless and alone. Once only at the champing of bits and the noise of hoofs he had turned to the window. It was Miss Pickett, garmented in that terra-cotta which affects the eye as a pistol-shot affects the ear. He had heard her rustle past the door and her laugh mingle with Mrs. Manhattan’s. Then a brougham had stopped, and Tandem, in a cutaway coat, a flower in his buttonhole, had alighted and loitered an instant until Yarde had alighted too. For the moment, Gonfallon, at the possibility of their entering the room where he stood, had knit his brow; but Tandem, in his quality of best man, had convoyed the groom to some other refuge. From above came the sound of hurrying feet. The rectory was articulate, its quiet stirred with vocables. In the room overhead he pictured Claire standing before the glass, her head held sidewise, eying the last touches to her gown. Beyond, somewhere, through the walls he saw Yarde contemplating his fingertips, and to the prayerbook which he held Gonfallon gave a tighter clasp.

Since the dinner and its epilogue Gonfallon had barely seen his sister-in-law. The day after she had gone with the Picketts to Washington, and before returning to New York had managed to pass a full month with Yarde’s relatives in the South. Since then her hours had been given to the trousseau. Today she was to be married, and at the ceremony, at her mating to that man, instead of forbidding the banns he was to officiate. It was through him the Church was to sanction a thing against which every fibre of his being rebelled. In an effort to gain some mastery over the expression of his face, he turned again to the street.

There had been a flurry of snow an hour before, but now in the sunlight high noon rang everywhere. On the pavement was an eager glitter like that of broken glass, and at the corner the spires of Gethsemane pointed to a gulf of blue.

“And not a reason for refusing,” he muttered—“not one.” During the preceding weeks he had told himself that this thing should never be. The touch of her lips had sealed her to him. He had felt the willingness, the courage even, to abandon the rochet already in his grasp, his high estate, his reputation, his cloth, Ruth, everything, even to honor, and carry the girl to some one of those lovely lands to which we never go, but which beckon to us, ceaselessly, from afar. In conflicts with himself conscience vanquished had been impotent to coerce. His ordinary duties he had performed with the perfunctoriness of a somnambulist. In his eyes but one light shone, and that light was Claire. And in that light all else slipped by, and he had relied now on the girl herself, now on a whim of chance, and again on some effort of his own, on something, he knew not what, but still on something that should happen in the nick of time and sunder this hateful pact.

In more rational moments he had reflected that, distasteful as the engagement was, it was rendered doubly so by the fact that the other contracting party was one whom of all others in the world he loathed the most; and into that loathing, as though to mock him, there would creep at times the knowledge—banished again and again, but ever returning—that between him and Yarde a girl such as Claire would not hesitate for a second’s space. What chance have forty years, however well carried they may be, against the fragrance and seductions of youth?

And as Gonfallon had thought of this, he would have, had he dared, clapped there and then on that fragrance some one of those masks which disfigure and distort. He would have corroded and blasted. And instead of that he was called upon to stand, the sacerdos, and consecrate his nuptials with Claire. Instead of maiming he was to marry, instead of cursing he was to bless. Could this cup pass from him! But he had no excuse—not one. It was for him to deliver the girl he loved into the arms of the man he loathed. And as he gazed down at the eager glitter of the street there came to his face an expression which Goya would have given to a gibbeted fiend. Was it not a woman that changed into Satan the angel that was Lucifer?

“Doctor, the bride is coming down.”

It was Tandem hailing him from the doorway. Gonfallon drew one long breath and turned; and as he turned he thrust his hate back in him as a soldier sheathes his sword.

“I am ready,” he answered; and to himself he added, “Calvary was easy of ascent.”

Tandem had already gone. Gonfallon drew the portière aside, and, crossing the hall, his head bent, the prayerbook in his hand, he entered the sitting-room beyond. At his entrance the voices subsided and ceased. The guests parted into twin rows, and between them Gonfallon advanced to a mirror, before which two cushions had been placed. There he turned and stood, his head still lowered, waiting the coming of the bride.

Presently, in the lull, Yarde entered, led by Tandem, and, bowing to Gonfallon—a salute which, parenthetically, was not returned—he took up a position on the right. From beneath his lowered eyelids Gonfallon saw him fumble at a pocket. “He is feeling for the ring,” he reflected, and straightened himself just a little. Then came a rustle, a murmur, and Claire entered, leaning on her father’s arm. Gonfallon raised his eyes, Yarde stepped forward to greet, Bucholz in a worthy parental manner dropped his daughter’s arm, and the two young people stood before him who was to make them one.

“ ‘Dearly beloved,’ ” began Gonfallon, in that voice which those present knew so well—“ ‘Dearly beloved, we are gathered together here in the sight of God.’ ”

And as he repeated from memory the subsequent phrases of the opening formula, he looked down at the bride. In her cheeks that hue of the white rose which has the sulphur heart was untouched by the faintest flush. The porcelain blue of her eyes was untroubled, and her mouth still looked inviolate and unaware of love. From the tangles of her curls came the breath of brooks. She was in street-dress, but unbonneted and ungloved.

“ ‘I require and charge you both, as you will answer at the dreadful day of judgment—’ ”

His eyes were still on hers, but as he delivered the warning which is customary he lowered his own beneath the directness of her gaze.

“Trement,” he continued, “wilt thou have this woman to thy wedded wife, to live—”

“I will,” the young man interjected, and flushed at his precipitance.

“Together after God’s ordinance in the holy state of matrimony? Wilt thou love her—” And as the questions fell from him, Gonfallon, outwardly impassible, clutched tighter at the book he held. For a second his voice wavered, and, turning to the bride—

“Claire,” he continued, “wilt thou take this man?”

Again his eyes were on her, and so convulsed were they that to a weaker than she, dismay would have come. He paused, and Claire, as though her thoughts had preceded and interpreted his own, in a voice quasily defiant, her head held like a challenge, her eyes a trifle contracted, and fixed maliciously on his own, made the conventional response.

“Who giveth this woman—”

In speaking he caught an expression in Yarde’s face, a look of smothered mirth as though the mute dialogue had been intercepted and enjoyed. Willingly would he have hurled the prayerbook at his teeth and with his two hands about his throat crushed out his hated life. He bit his lip until it bled, and with an effort dominated himself again.

Bucholz had stepped forward, and, after making a gesture, moved back. He seemed so pompous, so spruce, and yet so unnecessary, that Gonfallon, detecting another quiver in Yarde’s expression, understood his mirth, and in his semi-hysterical condition felt his own lips twitch with a smile.

The troth then plighted, bride and groom kneeled on the cushions at his feet, and, the prayer delivered, rose up again.

“Those whom God hath joined together, let no man put asunder. For inasmuch—” he continued, and, mumbling the archaic phrases that follow, he added, with a gasp, “Amen.”

The next moment Claire was in her sister’s arms and Tandem was shaking Yarde energetically by the hand. The twin ranks of the company fused into a solid square that bore down on bride and groom. Gonfallon watched his opportunity, and escaped to the study beyond.

Thus far he had held himself well. Not one of those present had divined the rebellion that was in him. But now the farce was done, and, tearing the canonicals from him, he rumpled and tossed them in a heap on the floor. The prayerbook which he had held fell from him, and he sank on a chair. Into his mouth had come a sour taste. He raised his handkerchief to his lips, and, looking at it, saw that it was flecked with red. He passed his hand across his eyes; they were dry and hot; and, suddenly, remembering Bucholz, he chuckled and tried to laugh.

The hubbub of sixty people talking at once came to him from across the hall. For a fraction of an hour he listened unhearingly. But presently something stirred him from his mental swoon. He had heard Claire’s voice, he was sure. He started and moved to the door: yes, it was she. He drew the portière ever so little and peered into the hall. Before him the bride stood exchanging a farewell with Miss Pickett. Then the two separated, Miss Pickett turning to the sitting-room and Claire to the stairs. For a moment he waited; then, seeing that he could leave the study unobserved, he hurried out into the hall. Already the girl had reached the floor above, but he called to her, and she stopped.

“What is it?” she asked, and looked down at him from over the rail. Without a word he mounted to where she stood. “Claire,” he whispered, and strove to take her hand, “tell me, you do love me, do you not?”

And the girl, drawing from him, answered almost sadly, with a gesture that was pathetic in the sorrow it conveyed, “Love you, Gonfallon? It is not I that love you; it is Ruth.”

A door closed, and she was gone.

Gonfallon steadied himself and gazed blankly enough at the door which had shut in his face. “And it was for this I toiled,” he mused. For the moment everything seemed to disappear; then, mindful as he always was of Form, and arguing with himself as to what he was doing there, he got into his study again, and roamed about it, likening his restlessness to that of a gyrfalcon in a cage; striving not only to forget, but to cease to think as well.

Beyond, the hubbub still continued. A luncheon was in progress, and he knew that his absence would be remarked. Yet still he could make no effort to leave the room. From time to time he passed his hand across his face and let it fall again to his side. And presently the voices approached: it was evident that the guests were assembling in the hall. From the window he could see a trim brougham, bottle-green, the straw-colored wheels picked out with black, and by it a miniature groom, in his lapel a bunch of white flowers, while at the ear of the horse nearest the rectory Gonfallon noticed that a similar bunch had been placed.

“Chris, where are you?”

It was Ruth calling to him, as Tandem had done, from the uplifted fringe of the curtain.

“Chris! They are coming. Hurry!”

Again he moved out into the hall, bowing this time right and left to the guests that had assembled there. Mrs. Manhattan was prompt at nabbing, and she had him at once.

“How sweet Claire looked!” she murmured.

“Very,” Gonfallon answered, and smilingly caressed his chin.

“Such a good match, too,” she added, “you ought to be tickled to death.”

“Yes, yes, he is a splendid young fellow.”

“Just the man for her. Nicholas was so sorry he couldn’t come. Trement, you know, is a connection of ours. I even had a hand in his bringing up.”

“I was sure of it.”

“And how impressive you did make the service! Ah! here they are.”

About the corner bride and groom had turned. The face of the latter was flushed as were he the sacrifant; the former held her head erect, and her mouth seemed at the slightest provocation prepared to bubble into laugh.

There was a gurgle, a hum, an undulant shout, and they had gone. Through the open doorway Miss Pickett threw a slipper which hit the coachman on the cheek. Tandem had obtained a handful of rice, which he scattered lavishly in the air. And as the brougham drove off, Yarde was seen, his head bent, fumbling at the nape of his neck for a furtive grain that had lodged in his collar.

For a while yet the guests lingered, companioned by Gonfallon and Ruth. Then, little by little, the handful diminished and shrunk, until husband and wife were alone.

“It will be dreary without Claire, will it not?” Ruth remarked as the ultimate loiterer passed from the house. There was no doubt about it—Dr. McMasters was not only a physician, but a sorcerer as well. The neuralgia which had fed upon her had been exorcised long since.

In the adjoining room the maid was busy with the detritus of the wedding-feast.

“Will it not?” she repeated, and, without waiting for an answer, suddenly her arm had wound about him, and for a moment her head rested on his breast. Then, conscious, seemingly, of the presence of the maid, she moved from him, and Gonfallon, turning on his heel, entered the study again.

On the floor before him the prayerbook lay, and he stooped to pick it up. It was not large—hardly bigger than a good resolution—but as prayerbooks go it was a gem. The text was illuminated, and for binding it had tortoiseshell clamped with gold. In the morning Ruth had brought it to him with the request that he would use it at the service which was to be. And now as he raised it from the floor it opened in his hand. On the flyleaf was an inscription in characters thin as hair: “To Ruth, from her loving sister. Christmas, 1879.” And as he read it he understood why the request had been made.

Idly he turned the pages. Between the covenants of the marriage-pact a blue flower had been pressed. During the agitations of the ceremony it had been unnoticed, but now something about it seemed to evoke a memory, and he went back again to the slopes and intervales of Bronx. Idly still he turned the leaves. Before the psalm “With my whole heart thy praise I will proclaim” another flower had been placed, but this one was yellow, as though the hope of the first betokened had mellowed with fulfilment. And as he turned again, facing the collect for Ash-Wednesday he found a clipping from some Poets’ Corner, a bit of schoolgirl verse:

I wait for the story: the birds cannot sing it,
Not one, as he sits on the tree,
The bells cannot ring it, but long years, oh, bring it,
Such as I wish it to be.

He read it twice, and very gently, almost reverently, he put the book aside. Anger seemed to take itself visibly away; he saw it leaving him, and made no effort to detain. Already hatred was departing, and in its train an illusion had unmasked. “It is not I that love you,” someone was saying; “it is Ruth.”

He had fallen in a chair, and sat, his face buried in his hands. Back again from the past one memory after another came to him unreproached first his wooing of her, her shy willingness, the sweet profanation, the earliest reluctant kiss, then the altar-rail, the blush of girlhood abandoned, the wifely solicitude, the unalterable charm with which illness had coped in vain, the tenderness of her nature, the unwavering allegiance, the trust, the belief, the pride in him.

“It is I,” he mused, “with whom she covenanted, it is I whose praise she proclaimed. I am the story she waited.” And, raising his face from his hands, he added, “If that story were only true!”

Already the afternoon had taken itself off. And as the light decomposed and decreased, something that was like to weariness seemed to fill the room. On the ceiling an uncertain dimness gathered. Here and there a gilt nail on the woodwork detained as with a pin a fringe of the mantle of day, but in the background was a somnolence in which objects disappeared mysteriously, one by one. In the corners shadows came and crouched. Under the chairs pits had formed, and out of them crept an obscurity which effaced and devoured the floor. On the ceiling the dimness deepened, the crouching shadows elongated and lapped the walls. A rumble from the street put an accent on the gloom, and presently, by way of vespers, the voice of the housemaid chanting “Jesus loves me” climbed on a treble from the regions below.

For a little space Gonfallon moved uneasily. Then, when night had wholly come, he found his way from the study, and groped through the darkness to Ruth.

THE END.

New York, October-December, 1888.

A Transient Guest

I

Since the Koenig Wilhelm, of the Dutch East India Service, left Batavia, the sky had been torpidly blue, that suffocating indigo which seems so neighborly that the traveller fancies were he a trifle taller he could touch it with the ferule of his stick. When night came, the stars would issue from their ambush and stab it through and through, but the glittering cicatrices which they made left it bluer even, more persistent than before. And now, as the ship entered the harbor, there was a cruelty about it that exulted and defied. The sun, too, seemed to menace; on every bit of brass it placed a threat, and in the lap of the waters there was an understanding and a pact. Beyond, to the right, was one long level stretch of sand on which the breakers fawned with recurrent surge and swoon. Behind it were the green ramparts of a forest; to the left were the bungalows and booths of Siak; while in the distance, among the hills and intervales, where but a few years before natives lurked beneath the monstrous lilies and clutched their kriss in fierce surmise, a locomotive had left a trail of smoke.

“Sumatra, too, has gone the way of the world,” thought one who lounged on deck.

He was a good-looking young fellow, browner far than he had been when he left New York, and he was garbed in a fashion which would have attracted the notice of the most apathetic habitué of Narragansett Pier. Save for a waistband of yellow silk, he was clad wholly in that dead white which is known as fromage à la crême. Had his cork hat been decorated with a canary bird’s feather, you would have said a prince stepped from a fairy tale. At his heels was a fox terrier, which he had christened Zut. When he wished to be emphatic, however, Zut was elongated into Zut Alors.

“The general’s compliments, sir, and are you ready?”

It was the polyglot steward addressing him, with that deference which is born of tips.

Tancred Ennever—the only son of Furman Ennever, who, as every one knows, is head and front of the steadiest house in Wall Street—turned and nodded. “Got my traps up?” he asked, and without waiting for a reply sauntered across the deck. He had met the general—Petrus van Lier, Consul of the Netherlands to Siak—at the Government House at Batavia, and although the trip which he had outlined for himself consisted, for the moment at least, in making direct for that sultry hole which is known as Singapore, yet the general had so represented the charms and pleasures of Sumatra that he had consented to become his guest. In extending the invitation the general may have had an ulterior motive, but in that case he let no inkling of it escape.

And now, as Tancred crossed the deck, the general stretched his hand. He was a man whose fiftieth birthday would never be fêted again. He had the dormant eyes of his race, those eyes in which apathy is a screen to vigilance, and his chin had the tenacity of a rock. His upper lip was furnished with a cavalry moustache of indistinctest gray, the ends upturned and fierce. In stature he was short and slim. It should be added that he was bald.

Though the ship had barely halted, already it was surrounded by prahus and sampans, the indigenous varieties of skiff, and among them one there was so trim it might have come from a man-of-war. In the bow a fluttering pennon proclaimed it a belonging of the Dutch. The coxswain had already saluted, and sat awaiting the orders of his chief.

The general motioned with a finger, the coxswain touched his forehead, and in a moment the boat was at the slanting ladder. Tancred and the general descended, there was a sullen command, and the oarsmen headed for the shore.

“We are so late my people will be worried,” confided the consul, as the landing was reached. “Usually—” and, as he ran on dilating on the unpunctuality of the service, Tancred remembered to have heard that his host was about to be married to an English widow, who, with her brother, was then stopping at the consul’s bungalow.

“Be still, Zut,” ordered Tancred, for the dog was yelping like mad at a fawn-colored butterfly that floated, tantalizingly, just out of reach. It was as big as a bird, and its eyes were ruby. “Be still.”

On the wharf a crowd of Malays and Chinese impeded the way, the Celestials garbed in baggy breeches and black vests, the Malays, nakeder, wickeder, darker, and more compact. Beyond was an open square, a collection of whitewashed booths, roofed with tiles of mottled red, and cottages of thatched palm. In the air was the odor of spices and cachous.

Guided by his host, Tancred entered an open vehicle that waited there. Then, after a brisk drive through the town, a long sweep through a quiet lane that was bordered now by rice-fields, now by giant trees festooned by lianas and rattans, and again by orchards of fruit and betel-nut, at last, in a grove of palms, a house was reached, a one-story dwelling, quaint, roomy, oblong, and still. An hour later the general and his guest were waiting dinner in the balé-balé of the bungalow.

Presently from the panoplied steps came the tinkle of moving feet. The general rose from his chair.

“My future wife,” he announced, in an aside. “Mrs. Lyeth,” he continued, “this is Mr. Ennever.”

She was a woman such as the midland counties alone produce, one whom it would be proper to describe as queenly, were it not that queens are dowds. She just lacked being tall. Her hair was of that hue of citron which is noticeable in very young children, and it was arranged in the fashion we have copied from the Greeks, but her features were wholly English, features that the years would remold with coarser thumb, but which as yet preserved the freshness and the suavity of a pastel. One divined that her limbs were strong and supple. She held herself with a grace of her own, on her cheeks was a flush, her mouth seemed to promise more than any mortal mouth could give; in short, she was beautiful, a northern splendor in a tropic frame.

Tancred, who had risen with the general, stared for a second and bowed.

“Muhammad’s prophecy is realized,” he murmured; and as Mrs. Lyeth eyed him inquiringly, “At sunset,” he added, “I behold a rising sun.”

And moving forward he took her wrist and brushed it with his lips.

“One might fancy one’s self at Versailles,” Mrs. Lyeth replied, and sank into a wicker chair.

“Olympus, rather,” Tancred corrected, and found a seat at her side.

“H’m,” mused the lady; but evidently nothing pertinent could have occurred to her, for she hesitated a moment and then graciously enough remarked, “The general tells me he knows your father.”

“Yes, it may even be that we are connected; there was a Sosinje van Lier who married an Ennever, oh, ages ago. The general, however, thinks she was not a relative of his.”

“I have forgotten,” the general interjected, and glanced at his future bride. “Is Liance never coming?”

From without came the hum of insects, a hum so insistent, so enervating, and yet so Wagnerian in intensity that you would have said a nation of them celebrating a feast of love. Presently the murmurs were punctuated by the beat of a wooden gong, and as the reverberations fainted in the night, a young girl appeared.

The general left his chair again.

“My daughter,” he announced; and as Tancred bowed he remembered that the general had been a widower before he became engaged to the divinity that sat at his side.

“You’re an American, aren’t you?” the girl asked.

There was nothing forward in her manner: on the contrary, it was languid and restrained, as though the equatorial sky had warped her nerves. But her eyes had in them the flicker of smoldering fire; they seemed to project interior flames. Her complexion was without color, unless indeed olive may be accounted one. Her abundant hair was so dark it seemed nearly blue. At the corners of her upper lip was the faintest trace of down. Her frock was like the night, brilliant yet subdued; it was black, but glittering with little sparks; about her bare arms were coils of silver, and from her waist hung cords of plaited steel. She looked as barbaric as Mrs. Lyeth looked divine.

“Yes,” Tancred answered, smilingly; but before he could engage in further speech, the general’s “boy” announced that dinner was served.

“What do you think of it there?” asked Mrs. Lyeth, whose arm he found within his own.

And as they passed from the balé-balé, as an uninclosed pavilion is called, to the dining-room beyond, Tancred answered:

“What does one think of the Arabian Nights?”

But there was nothing Arabesque about the meal of which he was then called upon to partake. It began with oysters, rather brackish but good, and ended with cheese. Save for some green pigeons with their plumage undisturbed, and a particularly fiery karri, it was just such a dinner as the average diner-out enjoys on six nights out of seven. There were three kinds of French wine and a variety of Dutch liqueurs. During its service the general held forth, as generals will, on the subject of nothing at all. And when the meal was done, for several hours the little group, reunited in the balé-balé, exchanged the usual commonplace views. During that interchange Tancred kept himself as near as he could to Mrs. Lyeth, and when at last the party broke up and he found himself alone in his room he drew a breath which might have been almost accounted one of relief.

Through the open windows came a heaviness, subtle as the atmosphere of a seraglio. Beyond, some palms masked a cluster of stars, but from above rained down the light and messages of other worlds. In the distance was the surge of the sea, sounding afar the approach and retreat of the waves. Beneath, in the underbrush, fire-flies glittered, avoiding each other in abrupt ziz-zags and sudden loops of flame. The moon had not yet risen, but the sky still was visibly blue.

And as Tancred dropped on a seat he loosened his neck-cloth with a thrust of the thumb. “That claret was heady,” he told himself, and with a bit of cambric he mopped his brow. But was it the claret? For a little space he sat gazing at the invitations of the equator. In his ears the hum of insects still sounded, and to his unheeding eyes the stars danced their saraband. The sea seemed to beckon and the night to wait.

Thus far his life had been precisely like that of any other well-nurtured lad of twenty-two. He had been educated at Concord, he was a graduate of Harvard; but during his school and college days the refinement of his own home had accompanied him afar. He was one of those young men, more common now than a few years since, who find it awkward to utter one word that could not be said aloud in a ball-room. And in this he was guided less perhaps by good breeding—for breeding, like every varnish, may cloak the coarsest fibre—than by native comeliness of thought. He shrank from the distasteful as other men shrink from the base. His parents had had the forethought to provide him with two sisters, one a year older than himself, one a year his junior; and these girls, who at the present hour suggest in our metropolitan assemblies the charm and allurements of a politer age, had taken their brother in hand. They had taught him what is best left undone, the grace of self-effacement, and they had given him some breath of the aroma which they themselves exhaled. To this his parents had added a smile of singular beauty, and features clear-cut and sure. In short, his people had done their best for him. And now that he was seeing the world in that easiest way, which consists in travelling around it, his letter of credit was not only in his pocket, but in his face and manner as well.

“I must go to-morrow,” he continued. And as he tried to map his departure, the tinkle of a footfall across the hall routed and disturbed his thoughts. Unsummoned there visited him a melody, heard long since, the accompaniment of a song of love. With a gesture he forced it back. Had he not understood—? No; he remembered now there was no boat from Siak for several days. He might engage a prahu, though, and in it effect a crossing to Perang; he could even take the train and journey to another place. Indeed, he reflected, he might readily do that. And as he told himself this, from across the hall a tinkle fainter than before reached his ear. He heard a whispering voice, a door closed, and some one beat upon a gong of wood. It was midnight, he knew.

He threw his coat aside and stared at the stars. They were taciturn still, yet more communicative than ever before. One in particular, that shone sheer above the balé-balé, seemed instinct with lessons and sayings of sooth. And to the precepts it uttered, its companions acquiesced, and smiled. Everything, even to the immaterial, the surge of the sea, the trail of the fire-flies, and the glint of a moonbeam, now aslant at his feet, conspired to coerce his will. The very air was alive with caresses, redolent with the balm and the odors of bamboo.

Slowly he undid the lachets of a shoe.

“It is wrong,” he muttered, and a breeze that loitered answered, “It is right.” “I will go,” he continued, and the great stars chorused, “You will stay.”

Meditatively still he continued to disrobe; but in spite of the stars and the moonbeams the light must have been insufficient, for presently he lit a candle, monologuing to himself the while. And as he monologued he was aware of that fettering, overmastering force which visits youth but once—the abnegation of self before that which is.

In that struggle in which we lay our arguments down and rejoice in defeat he had wrestled with all the weakness of his years. And now, as he flung himself on the bed, he clasped a pillow in his arms and sighed. He hoped for nothing, he expected nothing; but it was bliss to be conquered and enchained. The contest was done. During the coming week his captor would move before him, a luring melody, a clear accord sounded for his own delight, and then he would go, leaving the melody undisturbed, yet bearing a strain of it to feed on, a memory of enduring joy.

From without the hum of insects still persisted, and the waves were noisier than before. His eyes closed, and he smiled. For a moment that may have outlasted an hour he dreamed of the fabulous days in which goatherds dared to fall in love with goddesses. And such is the advantage of a classical education, that he mumbled a line from a Greek pedant, another from a Roman bore. In the dactyls and the spondees he caught the rhythm of tinkling feet; and as the measures sank him into deeper sleep a monstrous beetle shot through the casement and put the candle out.

The whir of wings disturbed him ever so little. For an instant he was bending over sandals, caressing a peplum’s hem. Then all was blank.

“Tuan! Tuan!”

It was a Malay servant, hailing the foreign lord, admonishing him to rise.

The room was filled with sunlight, and on a palm tree opposite Tancred caught a glimpse of a red monkey scratching his knee, chattering and grimacing at a paroquet.

II

At tiffin, that noon, the general was absent. It was usually so, his daughter explained; the duties of the consulate at Siak claimed the clearer hours of the day, and it was only now and then, on high days and festivals, that he permitted himself the surcease of a siesta at home.

“He is indefatigable,” she added, and shook her peerless head.

During the morning Tancred had explored the grounds; he had idled on the red-road and lost himself among the invitations of a green ravine. A grove of tamarinds had called to him, a stretch of aroids had entreated him that way, the sky had imprisoned him beneath a palm, a brook had murmured to him, a lake had coaxed him to its cool embrace. And then, Zut sniffing at his heels, he had returned in time for luncheon at the bungalow.

In pauses of the stroll he had promised himself that during the afternoon he would endeavor to find an opportunity in which to say something of that which was on his mind. This, however, an accident prevented. Miss Van Lier announced that she and her future step-mother were obliged to attend the funeral of a neighbor, a function at which of course it were idle for him to assist. He watched their departure without a protest, and gave a few more hours to the wonders of the woods. When the sun went down his forbearance was rewarded. The general was detained at Siak. Tancred and the ladies dined as they had lunched—alone.

That evening Mrs. Lyeth seemed even more magnificent than the night before. And beside her the sultry insouciance of the maiden heightened the matron’s charm. They were sheerly dissimilar, daughters of antipodal climes and race—the one loquacious and at ease, the other taciturn and absorbed. But it was in eyes they differed most. Those of the general’s bride-elect were moist as some blue flower plucked at dawn; the dew seemed still upon them. Those of the general’s daughter were sidereal, not white nor cobalt, but something that combined the two. To a lapidary they would have suggested gems.

As Tancred’s attention wavered between the charm of the one and the beauty of the other, Mrs. Lyeth had been describing some of the surprises in which Sumatra abounds; but her speech had been lost to him, and it was only the rising inflection with which she terminated a phrase that prompted him to reply.

“In the States, I fancy, you have nothing like it?”

“In the States, no; but in Mexico I believe—”

And Tancred was about to draw on his imagination when a servant offered him some sweets. He would have let them pass, but this Mrs. Lyeth prevented.

“You should try one,” she said. “Liance”—and at this she glanced at the girl—“Liance is the inventor; she will be offended if you—”

And, as she again glanced, Liance arched her brows. At the moment it occurred to Tancred that the relations between Mrs. Lyeth and her future step-child might be a trifle strained.

With the aid of a silver prong Tancred helped himself to a confection. It was yellow of hue, and, he presently discovered, agreeable to the mouth. It had the flavor of honey and of meal, but it was slightly acid, as though the rind of a lemon had been mixed therewith.

“I will give one to Zut, if I may,” he said, and thereat he tossed one, which the dog caught on the fly and swallowed with the discreetest blink. And then, with the appreciation of a gourmet, Tancred added:

“It is excellent; may I have another?”

The dish again was passed to him. Before he rose from the table the majority of the sweets had disappeared. It was evident that both master and dog had a taste for just such comestibles as these. As he devoured one and then another, he noticed that Liance was watching him.

“The general was in Mexico some years ago,” Mrs. Lyeth added, inconsequently. “I have heard him speak of the beauty of the women. But in New York they are more beautiful still, are they not?”

“Yes, they are pretty enough,” Tancred answered.

“I hear they propose to the men,” Liance interjected.

“Ah, that is a libel. In leap-year, perhaps, and in jest, such a thing may occur, but—”

“They are well behaved, then?”

“Yes, indeed. I remember, though, one girl—her name was—there, I have forgotten it. However, a young fellow was evidently taken with her, and she, as evidently, was taken with him. But for some reason or other he never seemed to get to the point. One afternoon, when he was drinking tea with her, the heat of the room—our houses, you know, are fearfully hot—must have affected her. She went off like that! The young fellow was at his wits’ end. It may be that he had never seen anyone faint before. ‘What shall I do? what shall I do?’ he exclaimed, and he was about to scream for assistance, when the girl in her swoon murmured: ‘Kiss me.’ He did so and she recovered at once. H’m—they were married last spring.”

During the telling of this anecdote Tancred noticed that the girl’s eyes were still on his. But as the ultimate phrase dropped from him she rose and left the room.

“She is exquisite,” Tancred confided in a whisper to Mrs. Lyeth. To this that lady assented. “But you—” he added, and then stopped short.

“Let us go to the pavilion, it is cooler there.” Mrs. Lyeth had risen, and Tancred, hesitant still, followed as she led the way.

“But you,” he added at last, “you are perfect.”

She had found a seat and he another. A fan which she held she unfurled and shut again with a sudden click. For a moment she toyed with a fold of her frock, but presently her hand fell to her side. He caught it up and kissed the finger-tips. At once she drew it from him.

“It is the climate that has affected you,” she said, “not I.”

“It is you,” he muttered, “it is you.”

“Even so, there let it rest.”

“I cannot,” he insisted; “I love you.” As he spoke he started, startled at his own temerity. And as her eyelids drooped he tried to catch her hand again.

“Then, if you love me, say nothing.” She had straightened herself and looked him now in the face. “If the general should even imagine—” A gesture completed the sentence.

Tancred nodded. He seemed confident and assured. Evidently the general had aroused no fear in him.

“It was in Mexico,” she continued. “Liance was in the cradle. Her mother”—and Mrs. Lyeth turned her head and looked cautiously around—“her mother was younger than I am now. She was beautiful, I have understood; more so even than her daughter. The general suspected that she was flirting with the Austrian attaché. He had him out and shot him. His wife he drove to suicide. It is only recently I learned this. And yet it is not for that reason that I fear. I have no intention of flirting with you; you know that. It is because—because—”

“Don’t hunt for a reason. I am willing to be shot.”

Mrs. Lyeth hastened to laugh, but her laugh was troubled. It sounded thin, as forced laughter ever does. She unfurled her fan again, and agitated it with sudden vigor.

“It may not be,” she murmured.

Her voice was so low that even the breeze did not catch it. And now, as she turned to her companion, it seemed to him that her eyes were compassionate, sympathetic even, awake to possibilities yet careless of result.

At the moment there came to Tancred that annoyance which visits us in dream. Before him was a flower more radiant than any parterre had ever produced. With a reach of the arm it could be his, but his arm had lost its cunning. Do what he might, it refused to move. And still the flower glowed, and still the arm hung pendent and quasi-paralyzed at his side. It may be—such things have happened—it may be that of the inward effort Mrs. Lyeth marked some sign. She shut her fan again, and made as though to rise. But this movement of hers, like the clock in the fable, must have dissolved the spell. Abruptly Tancred was on his feet.

“One instant,” he said. “There, you can give me that. Nay, see, if you wish to—go.”

And at this he stood aside, as though to let her pass. The magnetism, however, which youth possesses, may have coerced her. In any event she made no further effort to leave; she sat, her eyes a trifle dilated, a whiteness quivering beneath the lace-work at her neck.

“That is good of you,” he added; “I have but a word to say. Listen to it, will you? I was sure you would. Last night—or was it last night?—it seems a year ago. H’m, there are people whom we meet—you must have experienced the same thing—people that disturb us with suggestions of something that has gone before. When I saw you last evening—no, not that; but when I heard your voice, there came with it a reminiscence of earlier and forgotten days. It was not of the present I thought, but of a past I remembered I had dreamed. It was like a tangled skein. One after another the threads unloosed, and as they separated from each parting knot a memory returned. You were not a stranger, you were a friend I had lost. I could have sat with you, and from yesterday I could have led you back from one horizon to another until that posting-house was reached where our destiny changed its horses and our hands were first unclasped.”

This fine speech delivered, he looked down and plucked at his cuff. And presently, as he was about to speak again, Mrs. Lyeth raised her fan.

“After that I have either to thank you or to go!” Her voice was less severe than pained, and she seemed to retreat yet further in her chair. “And I thank you,” she added, after a pause, “but it is you that must go.”

To this Tancred answered nothing. He contented himself with looking insubordinate and cross.

“My poor boy!” she murmured, and sighed—or was it a sigh?—a sound that seemed to come less from the heart than the spirit. “My poor boy! But don’t you know that you are absurd? I have three brothers—one of them, by the way, is here now; he went down the coast on Tuesday with some friends; he will be back, though, to-morrow or the day after. However, each of my brothers has fallen in love with a woman older than himself, and each of them has fallen in love again and again. I am, believe me, grateful for your homage. What you have said is enough to make any woman pleased. And were I younger—well, then, since you will have it so—were I free, I would ask to hear it until I knew the words by heart. It would be pleasant, that. Oh, there might be so very many pleasant things; yet that is one that may not be. To-morrow, the next day, no matter, presently you will go; a week later you will find some beauty in Madras, and, if you think of me then, it will be but with a smile.”

She had risen at last, and stood now smiling too. For the life of him Tancred could not imagine anything fairer, more debonair, nor yet more just than she.

“If I vex you,” he said, “I will hold my tongue. But at least you might stay. I will promise this—”

But whatever the intended promise may have been it remained unformulated. In the entrance of the balé-balé Liance had suddenly appeared.

“It is late, is it not?” Mrs. Lyeth, for countenance sake, inquired.

The girl shrugged her shoulders. A gong in the distance answered in her stead.

“It is late,” Mrs. Lyeth announced. “We had better go in.”

She moved from the pavilion, and presently all three reached the house. The hallway was unlighted, a flicker from the dining-room beyond serving only to make the darkness more opaque.

“Where is Atcheh?” she asked, and called the “boy” by name.

“There,” said Tancred, “let me try to find a match.”

He groped down the corridor to his room and in a moment or two returned. On the way back he passed some one he took to be Liance.

“I could not find one,” he exclaimed.

So well as he was able to make out, Mrs. Lyeth had not moved. To his speech she answered nothing. He advanced a little nearer and tried to take her hand again, but it eluded him. And in an effort to possess himself of it he approached nearer still. Her face seemed to be in the way; for one fleeting second his lips rested on it, then a noise of hoofs must have alarmed him, for he wheeled like a rat surprised. And presently, after he had reached his room again, he heard Mrs. Lyeth welcoming her future husband on the porch.

III

From his window the next morning Tancred caught a glimpse of Mrs. Lyeth entering the pavilion beyond. He left the house at once and hastened to join her; but Liance must have preceded him. When he reached the pavilion she was already there. On her head was a hat unribboned and broad of brim, in her hand a basket. She struck Tancred as being more restless than usual, but the widow was thoroughly at ease. Apparently the episode in the hallway had not disturbed her in the least. For a few moments there was a common indulgence in those amiable platitudes of which the morning hours are prolific, and then Liance stood up.

“If you are going to the coppice, take Mr. Ennever,” Mrs. Lyeth suggested. “He looks bored to death.”

“Certainly I will,” the girl answered.

Her voice was cordial and her eyes and mouth seemed to invite. Tancred, however, did not on that account experience any notable desire to accompany her. On the contrary, he infinitely preferred to remain where he was. But there was no help for him, not even an excuse. He had his choice between going and being downright rude. Accordingly he smiled, but inwardly he swore.

“Show him the rafflesia,” Mrs. Lyeth added.

“The what?”

“You shall see it; come.”

Liance turned and led the way, and as Tancred followed he marvelled at the widow’s attitude. If he had not kissed her at all she could not have appeared more unconcerned.

To the left was a grove of betel-nut palms, to the right a patch of aroids, broad and leathery of leaf. Save for a whir of pheasants in the distance, and the hum of insects, the hour was still. Even the sea was silent; and had it not been for the odors of strange plants Tancred could have closed his eyes and fancied himself in some New England intervale, loitering through a summer noon. It needed but the toll of a bell to make it seem a Sabbath. A mosquito alighted on his hand, and he slaughtered it with a slap. Presently he found himself in a part of the plantation which he had not yet visited, a strip of turf, the background defended by trees. And there, in the centre, was an object such as he had never seen before. He turned inquiringly to Liance; her eyes were on his own.

“The rafflesia,” she lisped, and nodded.

And as he moved to get a nearer view she caught him by the arm.

“Be careful,” she added, and warned him with a glance.

But Tancred was not one to fear the immobile; he moved yet nearer to it, the girl hovering at his side. And as he moved there came to greet him a heavy, sullen odor, a smell like to that of an acid burning and blent with rose.

“The heart is poisonous,” the girl continued; “don’t touch it without gloves.”

The admonition, however, was unnecessary. Tancred was motionless with surprise. Before him was a flower, its petals of such consistency and of such unpleasant hue that they resembled huge slabs of uncooked veal. The chalice was deep enough to hold two gallons of liquid, the pistil was red, and the supporting stem was gnarled and irruptive with excrescences. In appearance it suggested an obese and giant lily, grown in a nightmare and watered with blood. It was hideous yet fascinating, as monstrosity ever is. And as Tancred stared, a page of forgotten botany turned in his mind, and he remembered that he had read of this plant, which Sumatra alone produces, and in whose pistil lurks a poison swifter than the cantarella of the Borgias, deadlier than the essences of Locuste.

The odor, more pungent now, drove him back a step. At the moment it seemed to carry with it a whiff of that atmosphere of creosote and tooth-wash which is peculiar to the dentist’s chair. And slaughtering another mosquito, he moved yet further away.

“What do you think of it?” asked Liance.

“It would hardly do for the button-hole, would it?” he answered.

The girl nodded appreciatively. Evidently she was of the same mind as he.

“There are few of them here,” she continued. “This is the only one in Siak, but back there,” and she pointed to the mountains, “they are plentiful. When a Malay prepares for war he slashes the pistil with his kriss. The wound that that kriss makes is death.”

“H’m,” mused Tancred, with an uncomfortable shrug, “if I happened to fall out with a Malay—”

“Don’t.”

The monosyllable fell from her like a stone.

“I will do my best,” he said.

She turned again and led him back through the coppice. The air was sultrier than ever, heavy with fragrance and enervating with forebodings of a storm. And now, as the girl preceded him, her step seemed more listless than before. She is tired, he reflected. These noons are fierce.

“You are to be with us some time, are you not?” Liance asked.

“No, a day or two at the most. When the next steamer goes, so must I.”

“Could you not stay longer?” She stopped and looked at him, the little basket swaying to and fro.

“I should like to, really I should like to very much,” he replied. The episode with Mrs. Lyeth was still oppressing him, and in answer to the oppression he added aloud, “But perhaps it is better I should not.”

Liance lowered her eyes, and with the point of her shoe tormented a tuft of grass.

“Why?” she asked.

“Because—well, because I feel an intruder.”

The girl raised her eyes at once, her lips quivered.

“You are wrong, so wrong.”

And then, curiously enough, as such things happen, Tancred—who was not a bit stupider than the rest of us—felt an oracle within him. It was more than probable, he told himself, that widow and maid, being nearly of an age, had, in their Sumatran idleness, become the fastest friends; and at once, with that logic which is peculiar to those that love, he decided that, being friends, they must be confidantes as well, and he concluded that two fair heads had come together and determined he should remain. That woman is variable, was a song he knew by heart, and he also knew that woman is apt to do one thing and mean another—to dismiss, for instance, the very man whom she wishes most at her feet.

These ruminations, however long in the telling, did not in reality outlast a moment’s space. It was all very clear to him now, and his blood pulsed quickly.

“If you tell me so, I must indeed be wrong,” he answered. “And let me add,” he continued, impetuously, “it is a boon to know it.”

To his face a flush had come, and his eyes were eager. He had never been accounted anything else than good-looking, but now he was attractive as well.

“You will not be in haste to go, then?”

“In haste to go—” His face completed the sentence. “Tell her from me,” he was about to say, when from the girl’s loosening fingers the basket fell; she drooped like a flower, her eyes half closed, and he had but the time to hold out his arm when she sank unconscious on it.

The grass seemed an inviting couch, and very gently he let her from him. “It is the heat,” he reflected, and kneeling at her side he took her small hand and beat it with his own. “What shall I do?” he wondered. Her cheeks were colorless, though her lips were red, and as, in his perplexity, he gazed at them, he saw them move. “Kiss me,” they seemed to say. Her eyes opened and she smiled.

And still he stared. “Merciful heaven!” he thought; “she thinks I am in love with her;” and feigning that the invitation had passed unheard he sprang to his feet.

“Help me,” she murmured, smiling still; and as he bent again to aid her, before him in the coppice stood Mrs. Lyeth. Already the girl was on her feet. Whether she had been aware of Mrs. Lyeth’s approach, who shall say? She patted out a rumpled fold of her frock, and picking the basket up, glanced over at her father’s choice.

“I almost fell,” she announced. “Mr. Ennever was gallant enough to prevent me.”

In single file all three then returned to tiffin at the bungalow.

IV

The afternoon slipped by like a chapter in a fairy tale. It promised but it did not fulfil, and at dinner the champagne sparkled, but the conversation was flat. When the cloth was removed the general manifested a desire to look over some papers, and Tancred and the ladies retreated to the pavilion beyond. Yet even there the wheels of talk were clogged. Mrs. Lyeth indeed discoursed amiably enough on the subject of nothing at all, and now and then Liance interjected an apposite sally; but Tancred was taciturn. He divided his time between biting his moustache and bidding Zut be still. And when at last through some channel of thought Mrs. Lyeth anchored herself in the shallows of Anglo-Saxon verse, for a moment the young man fancied that the girl was about to go. Liance made a movement, but whether some signal from her future step-mother detained her, or whether of her own accord she reconsidered her purpose, Tancred was unable to decide. The girl resumed her seat, and, one arm extended on the woodwork, the other pendent at her side, her feet crossed, her head thrown back, she sat staring at the stars in that abstracted attitude which powder and shot are alone qualified to disturb.

There is much in an opportunity that might be and is not. In recollection it appears more fecund in possibilities than any other opportunity ever enjoyed. And later on, when Tancred, without having had the opportunity to exchange in private so much as a word with Mrs. Lyeth, found himself in his room, he ravened at fate and at his own ill-luck. Nothing that he could imagine would have been sweeter to him than to have sat the evening through alone with that human flower. There would have been no need of speech; the languors of the night, the caress of the stars, the scent of palms and of orchids, the accent of the waves beyond, these things would have spoken for him more subtly than words could do. Through their silence the breeze would have whispered, and who does not know what a breeze can say? Though they sat apart, the stars that the old gods used as go-betweens were there to join their hands. They might be timid, but is not the surge of the sea a call that stirs the pulse? And the palms had their secrets to tell, and they would have told them, too; nay, the very fire-flies would have conspired together and made the night more dark. And, instead of a communion such as that, there had been an aimless chit-chat, an awkwardness that was sentient, and an embarrassment terminated only by a chill “Good-night.” Truly Zut, who had treed a hedgehog, was to be envied. His evening at least had not been squandered and misspent.

The morrow differed from the day preceding merely in this, that not for one instant during it did Tancred have an opportunity of seeing either Mrs. Lyeth or Liance alone. After tiffin they were inseparate. And Tancred, who had made plans for the afternoon, then made plans for the evening. But the hope which buoyed him was idle. The evening which followed was a counterpart of the one that had gone before, save in this, the general, having no papers to look over, held forth as generals will, and Zut searched for a hedgehog in vain. That night, for the first time, Tancred entered fully into the feelings of Tantalus and those of Sisyphus too. He was dumbly exasperated, the more so perhaps in that he divined that to one cleverer than he no obstacle would exist. If a woman has an ear, and as a rule women have, there is always a way to get at it. Unfortunately for Tancred, the way in this case was by no means clear, and what helped to confuse him was the fact that he was impatient to find it at once, no, but there and then, and without delay. And as in his exasperation he dashed his head against the pillow, he told himself that he had been abrupt, that he had unmasked his batteries too soon, that he had frightened where he had meant to charm. Of Liance he gave no thought whatever, except to decide that she was a nuisance. And such is the selfishness of man, that he wished she would topple over again and sprain a joint; in short, that anything might happen which would keep her to her room and out of the way of Mrs. Lyeth. The idea that the general’s bride-elect might be keeping her purposely at her side was one that never occurred to him. She is a nuisance, he decided, and dismissed her from his thoughts.

Before he fell asleep his mind was clear as to one thing; to wit, that in a small household it is more difficult to be alone with one particular person than in a household where there are many. Whether he was correct or not is a matter of the smallest possible importance. The next morning, when Atcheh appeared with coffee and fruit, he was aware that he had wandered through an assortment of dreams in which the rafflesia and the general were confusedly connected; at one moment the general had changed into that unhallowed flower, at another the rafflesia had bristled with the moustaches of his host. And as he rose from these fancies to his coffee he encountered a scheme which he detained and examined. It was not particularly shrewd, yet at the moment it seemed luminous to him. It was to the effect that if he were inhibited from private speech with Mrs. Lyeth, there was no reason in the world why he should not write. And as he mused, from the porch beyond rose the sound of her voice.

He was too far away to hear what she was saying, and, parenthetically, had he been nearer he would not have listened. But now the intonation, the trailing accent of her speech affected him as a balm. The irritation faded, as irritation ever does; he found some paper, and as, to the accompaniment of her voice, he prepared to write one of those letters in which punctuation is disregarded and sequence of idea forgot, he heard her waving inflection cut by a harsher note. It was the general, he knew. For the moment he wondered why he had not already gone to the consulate, but presently the noise of hoofs, the creak of wheels, a shrill cry, and the hiss of a whip seemed to announce that the conveyance which took the consul each morning to Siak was at the door.

Tancred’s window did not give on the road, but on the coppice and the pavilion, yet when again he caught the creak of wheels it demanded little imagination on his part to picture the general sitting bolt upright in a gharry, driving to the sun-smitten town beyond. And as the clatter of hoofs fainted in the distance, Tancred took up the pen again. The letter which he then succeeded in producing was one similar to what we have all of us written and all of us received—a clear call of love, in which the words are less jotted than shaken from the end of the pen. Its transcription here is needless.

A love-letter which can pleasure anyone save the recipient proceeds not from the heart but the head. Moreover, when Tancred began it he had not the faintest idea what he intended to say, and when it was finished he did not remember what he had written. Oh, sweethearts and swains! mind ye of this: when a love-letter differs from that, it emanates from a poet or a fraud. Tancred was neither. He was simply a young man suddenly enthralled by the charm of a woman older than himself. He intended no wrong, and if you or I or any other implacable moralist had happened that way and told him, as would have been our duty, that he was betraying the sacredest of trusts, the confidence of a host, he would have exhibited the surprise of a child frowned at for innocent prattle. Bear with him then; of wrong he intended none. It is the essence of crime that it be committed with malice aforethought, that the intention to commit it be clear. In the present case the intention was wholly lacking. Tancred was carried along by one of those unreasoning impulses which the psychologist recognizes and cannot explain. And that impulse, after throwing him at Mrs. Lyeth’s feet and dictating a letter to her, left his conscience unruffled and at peace.

His pulse, however, still was stirred. And, the letter completed, he was not in a greater hurry to do anything else than to get it safely in her hand. The manner in which this was to be accomplished was another matter. He might offer it to her in person, or he might leave it in her room. He might even watch his opportunity and slip it into her hand; but, for that, he immediately reflected he would have to wait the opportunity—a tedious operation at best; and, moreover, was he not in haste? And as he mused he remembered that Dugald Maule, a New Yorker like himself, finding himself in similar strait, had, under the very nose of a duenna, deliberately abstracted a handkerchief from his inamorata’s pocket, and, wrapping a letter up in it, handed it back with the civilest inquiry as to whether she had not just let the handkerchief fall? That was a remarkably neat trick, Tancred told himself, but somehow it seemed to demand a degree of assurance of which he felt unpossessed. Besides, it was a trick, and as such distasteful to him. And as he twirled his moustache, vaguely perplexed, undecided in what way to act, determining that it were better perhaps to leave it all to chance, he caught a glimpse of Mrs. Lyeth entering the pavilion alone. She was in white from head to foot, alluring as spring, and doubtless every whit as fragrant; she moved easily, her body erect and unswayed, and as Tancred caught sight of her he would have taken his chances then and there, but almost simultaneously he saw Liance following behind. In the annoyance he filliped forefinger and thumb together, and tried to possess his soul with patience. It was not impossible that in a moment the girl might go, and then his time would come. Meanwhile it behooved him to be careful and to remain unseen. But no, Liance must have seated herself at the other side of the pavilion, for he could hear Mrs. Lyeth address her, and the murmurs of the girl’s replies. Presumably they would remain together until tiffin, and if before tiffin the note was not delivered, another afternoon, the evening too, perhaps, would be wasted and lost.

And as he thought of this, behind him he divined rather than heard Atcheh’s noiseless tread. He turned at once. Another idea had come to him, one on which he determined to act at once. The “boy” was already retreating, a tray in his hand.

“Dja keno,” Tancred called.

On shipboard he had not been altogether idle. The Malay tongue is as easy to speak badly as Italian, and Tancred had found slight difficulty in acquiring enough mouthfuls for ordinary needs. “Dja keno—come here.” The sultry savage wheeled and obeyed.

“Ba gnio inong—take this to the lady.” And as Tancred spoke he pointed through the lattice to Mrs. Lyeth.

The Malay took the note and bowed.

“Baë, Tuan,” he answered. “Your lordship, it is well.”

In a moment the man had gone, and in another moment Tancred saw him approach Mrs. Lyeth and place the letter in her hand. He could see that she was eying it, wonderingly no doubt, for now she turned her head, but already the Malay had disappeared. And as she still looked about her, holding the letter unopened before her, Tancred felt as though something were clutching at his throat. From out the coppice, not a dozen yards distant, the general had suddenly emerged.

In a state similar to that mental paralysis which visits us in dream, Tancred marked his advance. It seemed perfectly natural that he should be there; without an effort he recalled the fact, forgotten albeit until now, yet still the unaccountable fact that it was Sunday; and presently, as the general halted, his thin figure erect, a bamboo switch in his hand, his cavalry moustache more bristling than ever, and proprietor-fashion surveyed the grounds, it was to Tancred as though he had been there for all of time. Then at once the cerebral swoon departed, in a confusion of visions, with that thing still clutching at his throat and his heart beating like mad, he saw on one side Mrs. Lyeth open the letter, and on the other the general decapitate a poppy with his switch.

Already Mrs. Lyeth had turned the initial page; she had read the second and was beginning at the last, when the general, to whose presence behind her she was obviously oblivious, advanced on tiptoe to where she sat. Tancred saw him raise a warning finger to his lips, beneath the moustache he divined a smile, invisible to him, yet apparent, doubtless, to Liance, at whom the warning gesture must have been made, and then, bending over his fiancée’s shoulder, he peered at the letter which she held. Yet before he could have deciphered so much as a line of it, Mrs. Lyeth started, as we all do when taken unaware. In an instant, however, she recovered her self-possession. She turned to the general, her mouth compressed into a pout.

“Do you know,” she said, from the tips of her lips, “you are as bad as Atcheh. A cat would make more noise.”

At this reproof the general laughed aloud, and, as though in sheer excess of glee, beat his leg with the switch. Tancred could see it was, indeed, a merry jest to him.

“My bonny Kate!” he gurgled. “I frightened her, did I not?” And again he beat his leg and laughed. “And whom is the missive from?” he asked. “I heard the gharry’s wheels an hour ago. Will you pay me if I wager and I win? Will you pay me? I wager it is from—h’m—let me see. I wager it is from that coffee planter’s wife you met at Singapore.”

And Mrs. Lyeth, with her bravest smile, answered:

“You have lost.”

“From whom is it then? There is no European mail to-day.” He eyed her, laughing still. “From whom is it?” he repeated. And as he spoke he bent again and looked down at the letter, which still lay open in her hand. “Tancred Ennever!” he exclaimed. “Why, what has he to write to you about?”

“Don’t ask me,” she answered, airily; and then, presumably, she must have understood the uselessness of further parry, for she added, carelessly enough, “It is to Liance, not to me.”

From the window Tancred could see the general turn to where his daughter sat. And as he watched he saw the girl issue from the shadow, take the letter from Mrs. Lyeth, and escape with it to the house. During the entire scene she had not uttered a word. She had been a witness, not an actor, and now as she crossed the lawn, the letter rumpled in her hold, there was an alertness in her step and such expectance in her face that you would have thought her hastening to a rendez-vous. It was evident that she, too, had taken the fib for truth.

Tancred moved back. When he again peered out, the general and his bride-elect had disappeared.

V

Over the luncheon to which Tancred was presently summoned a foreboding hovered, ambient in the air. Mrs. Lyeth was not present, confined by a headache, Liance explained, to her room. The girl herself preserved her every-day attitude, and Tancred did his best to engage her in speech; but she did not second his endeavors. When he addressed her she answered, if at all, with her eyes, and in them she put something that resembled a monition. Save for the reference to her future step-mother, she broke bread in silence. As for the general, Cruikshank would have taken him to his heart; he was both jocose and irritable; he feigned a glutton interest in his plate; he loaded the soft Malay tongue with curious oaths, which he exploded at the servant; he alternately praised and reviled the food, and from beneath his bushy eyebrows he glanced in the kindliest fashion now at his daughter and now at his guest. And so well did he succeed in heightening the enervation of the latter that it was not until the acrid caramels were passed that Tancred even pretended to eat. Then, remembering that it was Liance that made them, he ventured to compliment the girl, and, as she answered nothing, acknowledging the tribute only by an inclination of the head, he saw in the expression of her face that she was even more emotionalized than he. Presently a burning coal and some cigars were brought. Liance rose from the table, and Tancred, rising too, accompanied her to the door. There, it may be, she had some message to impart; her lips moved, yet before Tancred could grasp its import the general called him, and he was obliged to turn. The girl wandered out on the veranda, and Tancred resumed his seat.

“Will you smoke?” the general asked. His tone was so friendly that Tancred felt more miserable than before. “Take one,” he continued. “Sumatran tobacco ranks nearly with the Havanese.”

For a fraction of time which seemed immeasurable the two men smoked in silence. But in a moment the general gave a poke at the coal, and looked up at his guest.

“Mrs. Lyeth tells me that you have done us the honor to ask for my daughter’s hand.”

Tancred glanced at the point of his cigar, and discovered that it was out.

“May I trouble you?” he murmured.

The general shoved the brasier toward him, and watched the relighting with evident solicitude.

“It’s the dampness,” he announced. “H’m. Am I correctly informed?”

Tancred gave a puff or two, and then, withdrawing the weed, he held it contemplatively between forefinger and thumb; but he answered not a word.

The general knocked the ashes from his own cigar and eyed the burning coal.

“H’m, let me ask you, did you write to my daughter this morning?”

And Tancred, with that long-drawn breath we take when we prepare for the worst, answered shortly:

“I did.”

To this avowal the general nodded encouragingly. Tancred, however, seemed averse to further confidences; he kept looking at his cigar as though it were some strange and uncanny thing.

“H’m, well—er—did you, did you begin the letter with a term of endearment?”

“Yes, general.”

Tancred had tossed his cigar—a cigar that ranked nearly with a Havanese—into the finger-bowl. He straightened himself and looked his host in the face.

“Yes, general, and I am sorry for it. I have no excuse, not one. It was a piece of unpardonable ill-breeding. I had no right to send the note; I had no encouragement to write it. The only amend in my power is an apology. I make one now to you; let me beg that you will convey another to your daughter.”

The general half rose from his seat and hit the table with his fist. His face was convulsed. He was hideous.

“But, bandit that you are,” he cried, “she loves you.”

“No, general, you are wrong.”

“Ah, I am wrong, am I? Not an hour ago she told me so of her own accord.”

“General, it was a jest.”

“A jest! You call it a jest to surprise a girl in the dark”—

“To what?” gasped Tancred. “To what?”

“There, you know well enough what I mean. I refer to the other evening.”

“Merciful heaven!” groaned Tancred, “it was she then that I kissed.”

“It is a jest to do a thing like that, to write impassioned letters, and to win a heart. Is it a jest you call it, sir, or did I misunderstand your words?”

“No general, not that. What I meant was that it was impossible for Miss Van Lier to have confessed to any love for me—”

The lattice at the window was thrust aside. For a second the girl’s sidereal eyes blazed into the room.

“He is right, father: I do not love; I hate.”

The lattice fell again. She had gone.

During the moment that followed you could have heard a lizard move. Tancred fumbled at his collar, and General Van Lier sank bank in his chair.

“Mr. Ennever,” he said, at last, “you are my guest.”

The tone in which he spoke was low and self-restrained, but in it there was an accent that was tantamount to a slap in the face.

Tancred was on his feet at once.

“If you permit me, I will leave to-day.”

General Van Lier moved to the door.

“There is a boat from Siak at five,” he answered.

“General,” Tancred hesitated; he was humiliated as he had never been, and rightly humiliated, he knew. He was trying to say something that would express his sense of abasement, and a fitting speech was on the end of his tongue.

“General—”

“After you, sir.” The general was pointing to the door.

“General—”

“Nay, sir, after you. I insist.”

Tancred bowed and passed out. A moment later he was in his room.

In a corner was a trunk. In another a shirt-box. Tancred gathered his traps together, and tossed some into the one, some into the other, a proceeding at which Zut yelped and fawned with delight. Evidently on him at least the attractions of the bungalow had begun to pall.

“Yes, Zut, we are going.”

And at this the dog yelped again and curveted sheer across the room.

“But you must be quiet,” Tancred added. “There, be still.”

He was thinking of Mrs. Lyeth, and wondering whether he should see her before he went. If he could exchange but one word with her, surely, he told himself, she would understand. He lounged to the window and leaned on the sill.

It was one of those afternoons, brutal and terrible in beauty, which only the equator provides. The sky was like the curtain of an alcove, the sun a vomiter of living glare. Beyond was a riot of color such as Delacroix never dreamed, a combination more insolent than the Quetzal possesses, all the primaries interstriated, a rainbow of insolent hues. And there, in white, a parasol over her head, a basket dangling from her wrist, Liance appeared, emerging, as her father had, from the coppice beyond.

Instinctively he drew back: he had no wish to see her eyes charged with hate again. She was not one to forgive, he knew; the beauty of the equator was in her, and its pitilessness as well. And yet, he reflected, if I could but tell her not alone how she and I have erred, but how sorry I am for it all. But no; manifestly an explanation was impossible. Did he attempt one it might inculpate another. He was not alone solely to blame, he was blockaded in his own disgrace. He told himself this; he repeated it even in varying keys; but beneath it all he felt that some redress should be. The idea that the house he had entered as an honored guest would see him depart in shame had already brought the blood to his cheeks. And that blood now was leaving a stain that years would not efface. “I must write,” he decided; “I must write some word.” And he was about to seat himself at the table, when Atcheh appeared.

“Tuan,” he murmured, in the soft vocables of his tongue. “The gharry waits your lordship.”

At this Zut, who was surprisingly polyglot of ear, yelped with renewed delight. Tancred pointed to his effects, and waited until they had been removed. It was possible, he reflected, that he might meet Liance or Mrs. Lyeth in the hall. Yet should he not do so, then, he told himself, he would write from Singapore.

But when he reached the veranda, only the general was there. Beyond, the gharry stood in readiness, and by it was Atcheh, the trunk and shirt-box already strapped in place. Tancred stretched his hand.

“General—”

“I wish you a pleasant journey, sir,” that gentleman answered, and lifted his hat.

Mechanically Tancred raised his own.

“I thank you,” he said. And with a backward glance he called to Zut and entered the conveyance.

A whip cracked, the gharry started; in a moment it was on the road. Tancred turned to take another and a parting look. Already the general had disappeared, but from a window he caught a glimpse of some one robed in white. A curve was rounded and the bungalow disappeared.

For an hour over a road beside which the Corniche is commonplace indeed, the gharry rolled on. To Tancred, however, its beauties were remote and undiscerned. If he noticed them at all it was only as accessories. He was wholly absorbed in his own discomfiture, and the gharry drew up and halted at the wharf before he was aware that Siak had been reached and the journey was done.

About him was the same assortment of fat-faced Celestials and gaunt Malays that he had noticed before. Apparently nothing had happened to them; they had contented themselves with continuing to be. Before him was a glistening sea, a limitless horizon. To the left the shore extended, fairer and more brilliant than the courtyard of a royal domain. Just beyond, one of the ships of the Dutch East India service was moored, her funnels lengthening and fading in spirals of smoke. And when Tancred had attended to the transfer of his luggage, and was about to step into the sampan that was to convey him to the steamer, there came a clatter of horse’s hoofs, and on a black and panting pony Atcheh suddenly appeared.

“Tuan,” he cried, and waved something in the air. “Tuan, a moment more.”

In that moment he had sprung from the pony and run to where Tancred stood.

“From the little lady, Lord,” he said, and, handing a basket to his master’s guest, bowed to the ground.

Tancred found a bit of gold.

“For you,” he said, and the Malay bowed again. “To the lady, give my thanks.”

And at once his heart gave an exultant throb; his departure was regretted. As he lowered himself into the boat his excess of joy was so acute he nearly fell. Truly, if it be pleasant to appreciate, it is also pleasant to be appreciated. He still clutched at the basket, his hands moist with excitement, his face aglow, and it was not until the ship was reached that he noticed that Zut was sniffing at it.

“Behave,” he ordered. But his voice was so kindly that the little fellow only sniffed the more. It was easy to see that he was jubilating too.

On deck Tancred experienced some difficulty in securing a cabin. But for what were rupees coined and tips invented? The steward consulted the purser, the purser consulted the first officer, and in five minutes the cabin of the latter functionary was at Tancred’s disposal. It was roomy and cool; or perhaps it would be more exact to say that it was fully as large as a closet and that the thermometer did not mark one degree above ninety. In short, Tancred had every reason to consider himself in luck. He shut the door and throwing himself on a wicker settee he opened the basket, which until now he had kept tight clasped in his hand.

It was, he saw, filled with sweetmeats such as he had eaten at the bungalow. On top, pinned to the interior of the basket, was a slip of paper that contained a single line—Souvenir et bon voyage—and for signature, Liance. He read the message twice, and, it may be, he would have repeated the message aloud, but Zut kept bothering him with little hungry yelps. To quiet the dog be tossed him a sweet and put the basket down.

In some mysterious manner his joy had taken itself away. It was not from Liance he had expected a remembrance. When Atcheh placed the basket in his hand, he had told himself that, whatever it might contain, it was at least a gift from Mrs. Lyeth, a token expressive of her regret at his departure. And instead of that there was a handful of bonbons that might have been sent to a child, and a meaningless message from one to whose solicitude he was indifferent. The disappointment, indeed, was great. For a while he let it intensify within him. But presently he stood up: it was getting dark; long since the sob of water displaced had told him that the ship had started; a turn on deck might do him good, he thought; and as he moved to the door he called to his dog.

“Zut!”

And as the dog did not immediately appear, Tancred wondered could he have got out. But no, the door was closed.

“What the dickens can have become of him?” he muttered, and turning again he caught sight of Zut stretched on the floor. “Hello!” he exclaimed, “there you are. Why don’t you come when you’re called?”

Even at this, however, the dog did not move. Tancred bent over and touched him, and then suddenly kneeled down. “Why, what is the matter with him? A moment ago he was right enough; it is impossible that—Zut! Zut Alors!”

And raising the dog’s head up he stared at it. The eyes were convulsed, the tongue was swollen and distorted. “He is dead,” he murmured. “He is dead. But how?”

To this question no answer was vouchsafed. In his bewilderment he stood up again and leaned at the port-hole. Already Siak had faded. Above was a splatter of callous stars, beneath was the sea, black now and almost chill.

“But how?” he repeated. Then at once he clutched at the woodwork; his eyes had fallen on the basket; he remembered the sweet he had tossed to the dog. The cabin seemed to be turning round.

At his side the door opened, and the steward looked in. “Supper is ready, sir; will you come?”

“The rafflesia!” Tancred gasped at him. But what he meant by that absurd reply the steward did not think it necessary to ask.

“Very good, sir,” he answered, and shut the door.

An Old-fashioned Man

Again Claire looked at the anonymous letter. On florid paper, in a hand that was cramped and perhaps disguised, but in words entirely free from restraint, it informed her that her husband was amusing himself elsewhere.

She turned. A Verelst——that is to say one whose ancestry extended to the days when New York was a sleepy Dutch seaport—there were few here better born than she and, as she never mentioned the fact, there were few also that were better bred.

Now before her was a mirror that showed back the portrait of a woman beautiful, ardent, alert, alive.

It mocked her. Again she looked at the letter. It had come by post, just before luncheon, but it was not until afterward that she had read it. Meanwhile she had heard Fred telephoning to some one named Malvolio—no, Marvalho. But what about she did not know. She had heard but the name. Then at once, without a word to her, Fred had gone.

Fred was her husband. Usually he was less cavalier. Two years before he had lifted her quite off her feet. Delightedly then she had become the wife of this man whose charm, surviving the perils of matrimony, delighted her still.

But Fred Hemingway was always gracious, invariably serene. Never had she seen him angry——save once, a few evenings previous, when her brother and his wife were dining with them and the butler had been drunk. That might have annoyed anyone. It had annoyed her. But it had enraged Fred. Violently he had dismissed the man who had gone exuding abuse. Otherwise and to her, always he had been perfect, entirely unselfish and, for a husband, preeminently gallant.

Again she turned. The venom which the letter distilled was dulling her faith in him. As yet it had but smeared it. As yet she was but doubting, hesitating, uncertain how to act.

But uncertainty was rare with her. Ordinarily she knew what she wanted to do and did it. Now, mentally, she reviewed her list. It was long as her arm. On it was everybody who was anybody. But for the moment she saw but two to whom she could rightly turn—Harry, her brother, and Lilian, her brother's wife. Lilian was so dear that she might have been really her sister except that they never quarreled.

Presently, in that region just beyond the Plaza which is Manhattan’s Mayfair, Claire was at her brother's door.

The footman who then appeared was properly sorry but Mrs. Verelst was out.

“And my brother?” Claire asked.

“There he is now, mem.”

Behind her, at the curb, a motor had stopped and from it a man in clothes that were obviously Savile Row, was alighting. He waved at Claire. A moment and he was in the hall.

“A letter for you, sir,” the footman announced.

But Claire was also speaking. “Harry, where is Lilian?”

Harry, pocketing the letter with one hand, removed his hat with the other. “God knows! Shopping, I suppose. Calling. Great heavens, the way you women amuse yourselves!”

About him was an odour of champagne and Turkish tobacco. He was not squiffy exactly, but he had perhaps been doing himself rather well. Claire did not notice and animatedly he ran on:

“I never make calls. I loathe shops. Though, to be sure, shops now have their uses. To-morrow is my birthday. What are you to give me? But come in here.”

Lifting a portière, he moved aside. Then, following his sister, he entered a room, long, wide, bright, fitted in Empire fashion. Near a table was a sofa on which he dropped. Opposite stood a chair which Claire approached.

Harry patted his tie. “I have been lunching down town. You'll never believe it, but even there they are turkey-trotting. New York has gone crazy. Crazy!”

For a little yet he rambled. Claire had seated herself. Absently she was considering her gown. Astonishingly simple, it must have been equally dear.

Her inattention arrested him. “What’s wrong?”

Claire raised her great eyes. “I have had an anonymous letter. It’s about Fred. You can imagine the contents.”

Harry sat up. “And you came to tell Lilian about it?”

“Yes, Lilian or you. I don’t know how to act.”

Harry nodded. “Then I'll tell you. Forget it. People of our sort never see or hear anything that was not intended for them.”

Claire nodded also, not at him but at the remark. It was an old friend—an old enemy rather. Since childhood it had been dinned into her.

“Possibly,” she replied. “But unfortunately this was intended for me.”

He caught her up. “Not by Fred, though. Does the letter say who the lady is?”

Claire shook her head.

“Have you told Fred?”

“No.”

“Then don’t. Above all, no sobs. No little scenes.”

“Harry! I am not the sobbing kind.”

“Then don’t be the jealous kind, either. Jealousy—well, jealousy always denotes a sense of inferiority. That's it. A sense of inferiority. Don't show any.”

“And act toward Fred as though—— Oh!”

“Yes, why not? There is nothing a man appreciates more. A woman who suspects and screams is to be avoided. The woman who smiles and says nothing is adored. Fred probably thinks you an angel. Act as I say and he will find you are a saint.”

“But I am nothing of the kind,” Claire angrily protested. “I don’t want to be either. I am flesh and blood and I won’t permit—”

“There, there!” Harry grandly threw in. “Assume a virtue though you have it not. In the Gospel of Matrimony it is written—or should be—Blessed are they that ignore, for theirs is the Kingdom of Love.”

“Don’t!” Claire cried. It was protection she wanted, not platitude. “Can’t you see that if there is a word of truth in this I shall leave him?”

“Nonsense,” Harry, much as though she were a child, replied. “You have to consider—”

But Claire’s great eyes had narrowed. “What I have to consider is my self-respect.”

“Self-respect!” he repeated. The expression seemed to amuse him. “But what in the world is that but egotism? It is rank selfishness to make a scandal. Why, at the mere thought of such a thing your grandmother would turn out of her grave.”

“Don’t,” Claire again protested. “If Lilian were to get such a letter about you, you would not talk grandmother to her.”

“Wouldn't I?” Harry exclaimed. But the statement sobered him. With anonymous letters in the air no one could tell where they might strike. His conscience was none too clear, his skirts either. Abruptly he tacked. “But that is neither here nor there. What you have to consider is that if Fred should be amusing himself—and mind the if—it does not in the least follow but that he cares for you as much as ever.”

“A queer way to show it, then.”

“Yes, but men are queer and that’s the point—a point, too—that women such as you never understand. A man may like terrapin and canvas-back. He can’t eat them every day. A man requires variety in the menu. It is not his fault. Nature made him that kind of a brute.”

“But you are ridiculous with your terrapin and your menu,” Claire got in. “I don’t know at all what you mean. What I do know is that no man can care for two women at the same time.”

“Certainly he can—unless one of them catches him at it.”

“Well, apparently I am that one.”

“But you are not sure.” And as Harry said that ardently he hoped that Fred had covered his tracks. “Yet supposing you were,” he continued and in so doing promised himself to tip Fred off. “Supposing you were. Then, in that case, for heaven's sake, don’t get hysterical and shriek for divorce.” By George! he thought, between us, Fred and I will gag her first. “No,” he resumed, “all that is such wretched form. Decent people never make a fuss about anything.”

He paused and for clincher threw out: “I am sure Fred doesn’t.”

Impatiently Claire looked him up and down. “What has that to do with it?”

“Why, everything! Everything in the world! If Fred made a nuisance of himself, if as some eminently virtuous people do, he nagged, argued, contradicted, found fault and sulked, that would be a different kettle of fish. But he does not, and in married life it is the cardinal virtues such as his that count—the big things like smiling and forbearing and minding your own business. It is these things that count, never the trifles that occur behind your back and of which you are supposed to know nothing.”

“But I can’t take it out in supposing. I do know.”

Harry made a gesture. “No, you do not. But if you should—” He hesitated. An idea had come to him. He blurted it. “I say! You have not by any chance got a man up your sleeve, have you?”

At that, indignation marks shot from her eyes.

Harry waved at them. “You see nowadays sensible people don’t take jumps in the dark unless there is somebody with an electric light in waiting. But since that is not your case, then don’t be stupid enough to kick the apple cart over and all for what? I ask you for what? An illusion!”

But Claire was rising. “Is it constancy that you call an illusion? Harry!”

“Well, any way, it went out with crinolines—before then even, it went out with girls in turrets and knights in armour. If you like, though, we will call it lack of imagination.”

“Then I am very unimaginative and, fortunately for you, so is Lilian.”

Sagaciously Harry nodded. “It is not imagination that Lilian lacks. It is temperament. It is the same way with you. Good women never have any. It is their salvation, their husbands’ as well.”

With a smile—the self-satisfied smile of a man whose salvation is assured—he fumbled for his cigarette case. But the thing eluded him. In its place his fingers closed on the letter which he had received in the hall. He drew it out and indifferently, with a gesture of apology, opened it.

At once a curious phenomenon occurred. If, from under the table, a dog had run and bit him he could not have started more quickly. He looked as though he were in some dreadful dream. His mouth went dry and chokingly he stared at the letter.

Claire, who was standing, approached. “What is it?”

With an intake of the breath, he gave her the letter.

On florid paper, in a cramped hand, Henry Verelst, Esquire, was informed that his wife and brother-in-law were no better than they should be.

At sight of it, Claire's lips parted. She had not known whom to suspect. Now that she was told, she gasped. Realizing instantly that this letter and the one which she had received emanated from the same sewer, she realized as rapidly that the writer, however mephitic, was only a fool.

To her great eyes a mist came. She had known Lilian too long, too well, too wholly, to credit anything of the sort. The charge had overshot the mark. From Lilian it fell away ridiculously and, in falling from her, fell, too, from Fred.

“I'll divorce her. As for him—”

In any one’s anger there is humour, if you can only see it, and Claire, though her eves were brimming, could. Drying her eves, she laughed and returned the letter.

“Here, take the stupid thing and don't be an imbecile. Lilian is as innocent as a babe unborn. Besides, a moment ago you said that decent people never see anything that was not intended for them, that they never make a fuss, that a matter of this kind is quite negligible, that constancy went out with crinolines, that the things that count are not the trifles that occur behind your back but the cardinal virtue of minding your own business.”

Without, at the street door, a bell sounded. Neither heard.

“That is what you said, did you not?” Claire maliciously ran on. “Or is it that you have a woman up your sleeve?”

Ragingly Harry backed. "What I meant—"

But what he meant was never explained, or at least not then. The portières had parted. Through them, with none of that wearily satisfied look which culprits display, but debonair and exuberant, sauntered the suspects.

Menacingly Harry glared. “Where have you been?”

Fred, who was removing a glove, looked him over. “Never ask people where they have been. It’s not civil. If you are curious, ask where they are going.”

Lilian laughed. Dressed not in the mode of the moment, but of the morrow, she was radiant. She turned to Claire. “Belovedest, I am so glad you are here.” She turned to Harry. “Yes, and I'll tell you. I am going to give you a birthday present. Fred and I have been selecting it. Fred came here after luncheon to see you and—But wait a moment, I'll order tea.” Turning again, she vanished.

Fred nodded. “So I did and in the hall here I saw a letter for you. I could not help seeing it. It was the twin of one that I got. Before coming here, I took mine, together with a receipt for wages, to Marvalho, the handwriting expert. He said my ex-butler wrote them both. I propose to have him up for it. Give me yours and I will turn it in with mine.”

Harry blinked. He had been about to have a kick at the apple cart, but Fred’s directness, Lilian’s manner, these things superposing on Claire's mockery and abruptly he saw that there was no cart to kick. But he could not get in a rage and out of it in a moment.

“What was in this letter of yours?” he suddenly and severely inquired.

Fred patted a smile. “Well, though addressed to me, it must have been intended for Lilian. It said that you were a model husband, yes, the model of what a husband ought not to be.”

“Oh!” said Harry. He found but that.

Claire looked up at her husband. “Then it was like one I got about you. As for Harry's, dear me! It made him foam at the mouth.”

Harry flushed. “Nonsense! I saw at once that it was rubbish.”

But now Lilian reappeared. Behind her two men in livery were bringing a great silver salver that was heaped with things.

“Well then, Harry,” Fred resumed. “You give me your letter and Claire, you give me yours. Marvalho says it’s five years.”

“But—” Harry laboriously protested. The plan did not at all suit his book. However clear other skirts might be, his own were not for exhibition.

“But what?” Fred threw at him.

“You see,” Claire cut in, “Harry probably thinks that if you have the butler up, our names will be in all the papers.”

Bravely Harry helped himself to a hot and buttered scone. “That is just what I do think.”

“The dear boy!” Lilian admiringly exclaimed. “He is so delightfully old-fashioned.”

Daughters of the Rich

I

WHITE PEACOCKS

“Nearly a crumpler,” said a fat-faced man to Welden, whose horse, stumbling in the main street of Santa Barbara, had almost sat down.

Welden, pulling him together, dismounted. Supple and vigorous, he had an attractive face, laughing eyes and the air of being some one. Moreover, if this street in Southern California had been Rotten Row, he could not have been more studiously attired. His breeches were perfect. His boots had been marrowboned into blonde mirrors. From one of them he flicked a speck with his crop.

“What shall I do with the brute, Wicks?” he asked. “And, by the way, if you expect me to buy him also, I will chuck the whole thing.”

Wicks, standing fat-faced and bare-headed in the sunshine, reddened with emotion. The fish was landed, he told himself, and none too soon.

Wicks was in real estate, with signs—signs which described him as the Alert and Indefatigable Wicks—strewn through Santa Barbara, strewn, too, through the adjacent suburbs of Montecito and Miramar. It had been a bad year, however. Of nibbles there had been few, of bites none at all. Instead of the usual regiment of opulent Easterners, so eager for a residence in the perfumery and sunshine of the Slope, that they took anything at any price, there had been but a handful of paupers, considering penurious bungalows.

Wicks, himself, had a bungalow, one unfortunately mortgaged. Also, he had his office before which, fat-faced and bare-headed, he stood. The rent was due and back, toward the Sierra Madre, in that bungalow, was Mrs. Wicks, two little Wickses, and a hired girl.

These luxuries mean money, and to Wicks money had become a haunting and elusive thing. Then, suddenly, by special grace, in the nick of time, just as the grocer was turning ugly, Welden, with all the aroma of wealth about him, had dropped from the cars, demanding something fit and on the sea.

“Something,” a woman who accompanied this providence melodiously interluded, “in which one, if one liked, could have a little frisk.”

As she spoke she had smiled, very infectiously, for Welden smiled too, and Wicks, who had not an idea what a little frisk might be, unless their visit could be so catalogued, smiled also. But the woman’s smile was not merely infectious, there was in it and about her a charm that was absolutely relaxing. She exhaled ease and an atmosphere indefinably foreign.

“Is she pretty?” the wife of Wicks’ bosom inquired that evening when, on the porch of the mortgaged bungalow, he told her the incidents of the day.

“Yes, and better. I should say she was—she was—” Here the Alert and Indefatigable groped mentally after a term which suddenly he nailed. “I should say she was princessly.”

“Princessly!” Mrs. Wicks dubiously repeated. “How was she dressed?”

But the question was beyond Wicks, as it is also beside the issue, which was in effect that these luminous people had concluded to consider White Peacocks, a house at Miramar, which an Englishman had leisurely built and then, on acceding to a title, had actively vacated, leaving it to Wicks to sell for a hundred thousand dollars. “Not a ha’-penny less,” the Englishman had enjoined, “and more if possible.” “Certainly, my lord,” Wicks had replied, “I will try for a hundred and fifty.”

Then, simultaneously with the Englishman’s departure, there had occurred in Wall street a panic from which germinated a nightmare that sullenly overspread the entire land, and, until Welden appeared, no one had come that would consider at any price the purchase of the property.

But, on the first day, when in a motor, hired by the hour, Wicks had taken the Weldens there, he had felt that it was probably a go. At the start, that is, once the main street of Santa Barbara was behind them, and they were rolling along the ocean boulevard which leads to Miramar, he had mentioned, casually, as though it were an unimportant detail, the top price, adding immediately and mechanically, after a habit of his: “And such a bargain!” Then, mechanically also, he had played the flute to its charms.

White Peacocks needed no aria from him It breathed for itself. The grounds, full of palms, of lilies, of masses and draperies of purple and scarlet blooms, were like an unglassed conservatory open to the air. They had the sea before them, the mountains behind, and the house with its thirty rooms, every one of which was scented the year around with geranium, with heliotrope and with brine, was agreeably furnished, comfortably arranged. Beyond, for servants, was another house; a stable, a garage; and in front of the main dwelling, on a lawn of vivid green, a dove-coloured peacock moved gingerly, almost moodily, but, at sight of them, expanded slowly yet demeasurably the fan of its extravagant tail.

It was the finishing touch.

Wicks, conscious of the impression produced, had been about to play the flute again, when Welden, who had been talking in French with his wife, turned to him.

“I will try it for a month; then, if it still pleases Mrs. Welden, I will make an offer.”

Wicks, the Alert, the Indefatigable, sighed and looked down. Actually at the moment he was in agony. The unexpected and magnificent fish that had so providentially come into his net was wriggling unarrestably away. The commission on a month’s rental was all on which he could surely count.

Conscious, however, that he must make some reply, with an effort he rallied.

“I don’t know,” he said, “that the owner would care to rent the property. But if price seems—”

Welden, standing there supple and smiling, cut him short.

“I never argue.”

After all, Wicks had immediately reflected, the property was worth certainly a thousand a month—to any one who could be induced to pay it. At ten per cent. that meant a hundred for him, with the chance still of the bigger commission.

“Very good, sir,” he had replied. “I will assume the responsibility.”

In this manner the business had been temporarily concluded. On the premises was a lame ostler, who was Irish; a minute gardener, who was Japanese; a half-breed man of all work and an obese negro cook. These the Weldens retained, reinforcing them with servants of their own and with others recruited from Los Angeles—preparations which seemed to postulate permanency if signs and portents might. But Wicks could be sure of nothing, nor was he, until this radiant forenoon, when the crumpler nearly occurred, and Welden, damning the brute, dismounted.

It was then, reddening with emotion, that these anterior events were recalled, for now, at last, the fish, the magnificent fish, was landed.

“No, certainly not, we won’t burden you with him,” he replied in answer to Welden’s protest. “If you will take a seat in my office for a moment, I will leave him at the livery across the way.”

Pleasurably, a hand on the bridle, he led the horse off. The netting of the fish meant—at seven and a half per cent., which was the commission agreed—in the event of the top figure being reached—eleven hundred and twenty-five dollars. It was certainly a very radiant forenoon.

Welden, meanwhile, flicking still at his boots, strolled into the office and sat down on one of the three chairs which the place contained. On the wall was a map. Beneath was a pulpit desk, high and narrow. On it were documents, a china cat, other things as well, but most noticeably, a telephone, which, as Welden seated himself, began ringing.

Welden, still flicking at his boots, stared aimlessly about. On one of the other chairs was the local sheet; he reached for it and was looking over the news of the day when Wicks reappeared.

“Excuse me,” said the agent, who went to the telephone, which had continued to ring.

Welden but glanced at him. He had just read that the New York Central had decreased its dividend. The item was of interest; he happened to be a stockholder and mentally he began on a calculation which Wicks, his hand on the receiver, interrupted.

“It’s for you. Your man, I think. He wants to speak to you.”

Absently Welden looked up. “Nonsense,” he presently remarked. “Harris knows better than that. If there is any message, though, tell them to give it to you.”

Then, after fumbling in a pocket, he got out a gold pencil with which he jotted figures on the margin of the paper that he held. But the operation did not prevent him from hearing.

“Yes,” Wicks was saying. “Mr. Welden is here. Mr. Welden says you are to tell me for him. He—What!”

At the “What,” which was not a query, but an exclamation, Welden replaced the gold top on the pencil and putting it back in his pocket, turned again to the news.

Before him Wicks stood, the receiver at his ear, a hand pendent at his side. It was shaking a little.

The motion, odd in itself, attracted Welden. His eyes roamed slowly upward from it to the agent’s face. Wicks was standing now, his mouth half open, looking limply at him.

Welden tossed the paper aside.

“Are you ill?”

Wicks closed his mouth, shook his head, then partly opened his mouth again. But still he did not speak.

Welden stood up. “Are you?” he repeated.

Then finally Wicks did speak. “Your wife!” he said slowly, and hanging the receiver up, flopped into a chair.

The nightmare that had overspread the land was battening individually on him. Through it the face of the grocer peered. With the grocer was the mortgagee. Both were throwing him and his out on the country road. That indeed might yet occur. At the moment, however, he was but being shaken, not roughly, but authoritatively, from a form of mental swoon.

“What is this about Mrs. Welden? Why the devil don’t you tell me? Is she ill?”

Wicks, the Alert and Indefatigable, could but nod in reply.

“Very?” Welden persisted. “Come, damnation, don’t keep me questioning you like this. What did they say?”

The winded Wicks now had got his breath. He straightened himself, and rising from the chair, put a hand on Welden’s arm.

“She is—” And Wicks raised his eyes.

“Not dead!” cried Welden, starting back.

Wicks moved nearer and with that sympathy which, in certain crises, one human being will always show to another, said lowly:

“Mr. Welden, they tell me that this lady has been killed.”

“Killed!” Welden, again starting back, repeated; “but how?”

Then the detail, passably gruesome, was produced.

“They found her in bed, her throat cut from ear to ear.”

II

THE INQUEST

Astride the brute on which ten minutes before the crumpler had nearly occurred, Welden tore down the street, galloped along the ocean boulevard, and on, into a scarlet lane, at the end of which stood White Peacocks.

The entrance was a bit beyond. Rather than make the brief circuit, he cleared a hedge, raced through the grounds and flung himself off at the steps of the verandah.

In the hall, through the open door, he had a glimpse of servants huddled together, and of a woman, her face to the wall, whimpering like a frightened cur.

On the floor above, at the head of the stairs, a man of the unmistakable domestic type stood uncertainly.

Welden pointed below. “Send those people where they belong.”

Hurrying by, he wrenched open a door which he closed behind him. When presently that door reopened, he looked older; not white, but worn.

As before, at the head of the stair, the man was standing. Welden motioned him into another room, one wainscotted with bookless bookcases, from which two windows gave on the sea.

Through one of them Welden looked, though certainly it was not the sea that he saw. After a moment he turned. The man was standing by a table, his hands hanging at his sides. In and out of the palms the fingers moved, regularly, mechanically, perhaps unconsciously.

“Harris, close the door.”

The man obeyed.

Welden added: “Tell me everything.”

“It was my wife, sir, Perkins. She was taking in the tray with the breakfast things, and when she saw, she let it fall and ran out and called to me, and I telephoned to Mr. Wickses.”

“Have any of you any idea who did it?”

“No, sir, but—”

“But what?”

“Thinking as how you would wish it, I telephoned to the police.”

Welden nodded. “I told Wicks to. They will be here shortly. Fetch some brandy and soda.”

Harris turned. He was reopening the door when, through the windows, came the whirr of a motor, the sound of voices, the shuffle of feet.

“If that is the police,” said Welden, “send them here.”

From an oblong silver box that lay on the table he took a cigarette. While he was lighting it Harris reappeared. Accompanying him was a large man with small eyes, a deformed stomach and a red moustache. As he entered he looked Welden over.

“I’m Chief of Police,” he announced. “Right off I want—”

But Welden, accustomed to give orders and not at all to receive them, cut him short.

“Harris, show the way. Do whatever is required. The brandy and soda can wait.”

In a little, however, the liquor was forthcoming.

“There are two of them, sir, besides the chief,” Harris volunteered, placing, as he spoke, the bottles on the table. “And the coroner is here.”

Welden, who had seated himself, took another cigarette. Through the windows came the savour of salt, the scent of flowers; there came, too, the bark of a dog, caught up and repeated. The forenoon was departing in perfect clarity and, save for an occasional footfall, save, too, for an indistinct murmur of voices, in a peace that was perfect as well.

Shortly the silence was stirred. There came a rap at the door. Before Welden could answer, it opened. The chief entered. With him was a little man, with smoke-coloured glasses and a suit of leprous brown.

Closing the door, the officer indicated his companion. “This here is Dr. Quizenberry, the coroner. We’re goin’ to ask some questions.”

“Sit down,” said Welden. “Will you drink anything?”

The chief accepted, but the coroner refused. Welden filled a tumbler which he gave to the former.

He drank it noisily. “Nasty business,” he muttered. “Damn nasty.” Wiping his mouth and drawing a chair, he seated himself in front of Welden. “When did you last see yer wife?”

“A moment before you got here. You probably mean, though, when did I last see her alive. That was at midnight.”

“Nothin’ unusual been goin’ on?”

“Nothing.”

The chief gnawed moodily at a finger nail. His thoughts were few and slow. He was assisting at their laborious accouchement. Presently, delivered of one, he looked suspiciously at it and from it to Welden.

“You and yer wife had separate rooms?”

Welden nodded.

“The man out there showed me yours, it’s on the other side of the house.”

Again Welden nodded.

“Durin’ the night you heard nothin’?”

“Nothing whatever. But in regard to my domestic arrangements you may have noticed that in this house there are but two sleeping porches, one abutting from my room, the other from Mrs. Welden’s. I have been in California before and when here I prefer to sleep in the open air. Mrs. Welden had not accustomed herself to it, though naturally she slept with the windows open.”

“That’s right,” said Dr. Quizenberry, “and with the screen door to the porch unfastened. Anybody could have climbed in.”

“Anythin’ missin’?” the chief inquired.

“I do not know,” Welden answered. “Usually Mrs. Welden did not appear much before noon. This morning, long before she would ordinarily have been up, I was in Santa Barbara. Since I got back I have had no time to look.”

Under the steady gaze of Welden’s eyes, and the prompt and rapid fire of his speech, the chief’s laboriously accouched suspicion died. Burying it decently, he asked: “Had yer wife any enemies?”

“Probably,” Welden, with an uplift of the chin, replied. “But hardly among such people.”

At that the chief leaned forward. The coroner cocked an eye. The possibility that the statement had not been understood, occurred to Welden.

“I mean,” he resumed, “that such enemies as Mrs. Welden may have had were of her own class, and assuming the impossible, assuming, that is, that their enmity could have been murderous, they would hardly have gone about it in this way.”

“Hey?” the chief, groping still in dark ness, threw out.

But the coroner had got it. “That’s right,” he threw in. “It’s not the crime of an educated person; more like some Jack the Ripper business.”

“Or the Roo Morgue,” the now enlightened chief insinuated, indicating by the insinuation that he, at any rate, was educated. “You’ve a greaser here,” he continued. “I don’t care for him, or for the Jap either.”

“They were here before I came,” Welden answered. “There is also an Irishman, a negro and some servants we got from Los Angeles. I know nothing about any of them. But Harris, the man who showed you about, and Perkins, his wife, came with us from Europe. I have every confidence in them. Perkins always took care of Mrs. Welden’s jewelry.”

“Had she much?”

For a moment Welden’s long thin fingers beat a tattoo on the arm of his chair. “Quite a lot,” he finally replied. “But the majority of it is at our bankers’ in Paris. Here Mrs. Welden had with her a string of pearls, a few pins and some rather valuable rings which she got recently in India.”

“There are no rings on her hands. Did she sleep with ’em?”

“Really,” said Welden, “I am not sure. My impression is that she did not.”

“What were they, dimons?”

Welden drummed for a moment again. “There were two table-cut diamonds, two tallow drop emeralds, an inch-long sapphire and a double ruby, a ruby set on a ruby, one on top of the other.”

The chief sat up. “What would yer say they were worth?”

Welden, running his fingers through his thick, bright hair, looked at the ceiling and then back at the officer. “At Delhi, in our money, the rubies cost forty-five thousand, altogether the others cost as much more. Here, of course, they would come higher.”

The chief whistled. It was his welcome to the light, clear, direct, unequivocal, which then broke fully upon him. He jumped to his feet.

“If they’re gone,” he exclaimed, “there’s the motive. Let’s see if they’ve been pinched.”

“That’s right,” said Dr. Quizenberry, rising too.

“Chief,” said Welden, rising also, “I was in that room before you came. It may give you a poor opinion of me, but it will be a little before I care to return.”

“Poor opinion! Lord! If my wife had been done up as yours has, I’ll be jiggered if I could show your nerve. It’s grit yer got, real grit.”

“That’s right,” the coroner repeated. “That’s right.”

But Welden had rung for Harris. As the authorities passed from the room he went again to the window.

Before him the Pacific stretched, a syrupy blue. Over it he looked and far beyond, to another ocean, one that beat against the coast of France. Above it a vision mounted, the picture of a pillowed head. That picture, photographed on the mind’s encephalic films, became a negative on which developed others. At Deauville, in the hall of a villa, he saw—

“Mr. Welden,” some one was saying.

He turned. The authorities were before him, the chief nodding significantly while the other grimly smiled.

“Won’t you have another drink?” Welden asked.

“Yes, I will,” said the chief.

“That’s right,” said the coroner, “I will too.”

Then, as they helped themselves and stood there, the one large, the other small, both ludicrous and equally imbecile, they reminded Welden of some scene, in some play, that he had seen somewhere long before.

“The pearls and pins are safe,” the big man began. “They were locked in a bag, and they’re there now. But the rings are gone. The maid says they were on the dressin’ table last night, when she was gettin’ yer wife ready for bed. Since which they’ve been cribbed. Whoever pinched ’em did it, and I’ll bet yer now I know who that is, for though they’re gone, somethin’ has turned up. Can yer guess what?”

But Welden could not.

“The instrument! When there’s any funny business, that’s what we look for; that and the motive. When we’ve both, we’ve only to show the opportunity to nail the man. Well, we have. It’s the Irishman. The knife was in the barn. The motive—and motive enough—was the rings; the opportunity—”

“But,” Welden protested, “the poor devil is lame. He could not have climbed to the porch.”

“Oho! You don’t know how spry a lame man can be. Besides, how do we know that he did climb? In a house like this, unless the boss sees to it himself, yer never sure about the doors and windows. Anyhow, what did he have a carving knife stuck in his hay for? That’s no place for a bleeder. Lord! And an alibi rollin’ right out of him. That’s the way with these vermin. Whenever they do anythin’ crooked, they always have an alibi and more vermin to back ’em up. It’s my sworn duty to protect the bastard, but, if it wasn’t, Lord! I’d say lynch him. I wasn’t raised here, I came from the South.”

“That’s right,” the coroner remarked, and meditatively finished his glass.

“Well, anyhow, he’s on his way to the lock-up,” the chief continued, putting down his own.

“When’s the inquest?” he asked, turning to Dr. Quizenberry.

“To-morrow noon.”

Turning to Welden he added: “I can count on yer to be there?”

“Naturally,” Welden answered, and the authorities withdrew.

When they had gone, Welden took from his pocket a letter, one already opened, which he re-read, tore slowly to bits, and then poured out a glass of brandy. Before he had finished it, Harris reappeared.

“Will you have luncheon, sir?”

Welden nodded. “You and Perkins must get everything in order. You must also find an undertaker. Say that he is to arrange about a plot and that he is also to arrange with an Episcopal clergyman to hold services here and at the grave. Afterward, I shall not require Perkins, and as I cannot expect you to leave her, I will give you each six months’ wages, and your expenses home.”

“Thank you, sir, I am sure we are both very grateful. Will you have luncheon here, sir, or in the breakfast room?”

“I will have it here. By the way, Mrs. Welden is to be in ball gown. The canary one, Perkins will know, with a lace scarf about the neck, high up. If the scarf is insufficient, use an opera cloak, the violet and gold one. Perkins will know about that also.”

“Yes, sir. It will be attended to. Shall I fetch the luncheon now, sir?”

Welden nodded.

In a little while the man returned with a tray. When he had arranged it, he said:

“Begging your pardon, sir, I was to ask would you wish the hair marcelled?”

“Whatever is necessary. And, Harris—”

“Yes, sir.”

“Tell the undertaker that before the coffin is closed, he is to notify me. I wish to go there.”

“Yes, sir; thank you, sir. Luncheon is served.”

For hours Welden sat, looking at the sea, looking, too, at the pictures that developed on the mind’s encephalic films.

Toward sunset, other pictures developed. On the horizon clouds, sinister and malignant, shaped themselves into the resemblance of enormous centaurs, combating with each other for mountains of gold and of flame. The sky was dyed with their wounds, flooded with the hemorrhages of the monstrous massacre. Sometimes masses of flesh were torn and hurled into craters. Sometimes others were tossed like shawls across the bleeding sky.

Eastward, from over the Sierra Madre, titans trooped to the fight. It was as though they had sprung suddenly across the ages from their fabulous dream, and just as they menaced the world, abruptly they vanished. Before them an immense arc had been flung. Within the rainbow, throughout its entire semi-circumference, a vapour floated, thick, glistening and mauve.

Presently, as if a curtain had risen, that passed, banished by the sudden sun. From the west the centaurs had fled, and now, throughout the heavens, stretched archipelagoes, deliciously pink, that seemed like lands of love.

Coerced by the splendour of the spectacle, Welden had gone out on the lawn. The fair beauty of the sky detained him. It seemed inaugural of larger life.

III

THE CLUE

To the vulgar any indecency is amusing, the greater the shamelessness of it the more thorough the mirth; and, on the morrow, there was thrown into this tenebrous drama, a quick note hilarious and obscene, one that, with the usual attentuations, went reverberating through the press. For the case, already famous, entered at once into that high spectacular class which invites people, previously unacquainted, to discuss and surmise.

In the trains, on the boats, in smoking compartments, wherever men are penned together, individuals who had never seen each other before, and who, ordinarily, would not much wish to again, found in it a subject of common concern.

Perhaps nothing excites the imagination quite so thoroughly as mystery does, and here was one graduated to every taste, a story equally absorbing to high and low, and not locally merely, for, as it was immediately recognised, the Weldens were people of position, both at home and abroad.

According to statements telegraphed to the California press, from New York, Welden’s family had been identified with that city since its incorporation, and even before, at a time when it was Nieuw Orange, and not yet New York. While, as for the murdered woman, born a Kandy, and affiliated with quite Manhattan’s best, she had married Welden after divorcing her first husband, a foreigner, the Duc de Malakoff.

To these outlines, details were added. Prior to the marriage, Welden, who was a man of inherited wealth, had been engaged to Miss Barhyte, a New York girl of the ultra-fashionable set. But, coincidentally with the divorce, the engagement had been broken, and Welden and Malakoff had gone out together, though, after the French fashion, without appreciable damage.

But why had they gone out? Why had the engagement been broken, and why the divorce?

Here were pleasurable mysteries superposing themselves on the denser darkness of the crime, and suggesting to the detectives of the breakfast table that it was assassins of the duke who had done it; if not, then emissaries of the girl.

For by the time the foregoing and very incorrect details, together with bogus presentments of all concerned, had been journalistically set forth, by that time, the lame ostler had been released.

Amid great hilarity and to the satisfaction of everybody—save of one policeman only—he had demonstrated that if at the hour, two A. M., at which time it had been shown the crime was committed, he were illegally occupied, the illegality had been effected at Santa Barbara with the privity, connivance and in the society of that policeman’s wife. The woman, immediately summoned, had at first hotly denied, but prodded with questions at once circumstantial and deplorably intimate, finally yielded, and admitted the fact.

Thereupon, no one else being under suspicion, and no further evidence having been adduced, verdict was rendered that the deceased had come to her death at the hands of some person or persons unknown.

Then, for the bono publicanism of it—which, being interpreted, meant little more than the coin of affluent Easterners, who, already scarce, might become scarcer—it was felt that town and county ought to make the apprehension of the person or persons definitely worth while. But before the matter could be put into an inviting shape, provided, that is, there was any real intention of so putting it, Welden offered a reward of $25,000 for such information as would lead to their arrest and conviction; $5,000 additional for the recovery of the rings.

The gross amount, a small fortune to some, a large one to many, fevered a number of people and, among them, Wicks particularly.

In those days, Wicks was an unhappy man. Only a fortnight had intervened between the renting of White Peacocks and the morning on which Welden had intimated his intention of buying the property. Then this thing had occurred, and from his hand, from his lips even, the cup had been torn. The cup, or more exactly its contents, the compensation, would have sufficed until January, when the Eastern influx of affluence was usually due. But this was April. January was many moons away, and things looked very bleak in the mortgaged bungalow, on the porch of which, endlessly he went over them all. It was, though, a distressed and weary Wicks who did it, and weary and distressed was the woman whom he forced to hear and rehear the tale.

Then, into the bleakness of things, there tumbled the announcement of the rewards. They inflamed Wicks, who, though he lacked the gift of divination, was at least alert and indefatigable, or at least, so claimed to be, and these were attributes which, chance facilitating, might aid him to secure the portentous sum. In his favour moreover was his superior quality of agent of the estate. Strangers might hover about there, detectives, whether amateur or professional, might prowl there as well, and against these the guilty would be on their guard, whereas his presence would be taken as a matter of course. In the mere exercise of his functions he was free to roam at will.

These considerations, natural in themselves, had for basis an assumption, which Wicks by no means reached alone, that the murder was the work of someone directly associated with the estate. Possibly it might have been done by a passing bandit. Possibly, also, the criminal might be a pirate come in from the sea. But in that case it were necessary to assume on the part of an outsider, an entire familiarity with the locale, and a knowledge not only of the jewels, but of the intimate fact that the dead woman slept alone. Acquaintance with these matters was of course possible, for the reason that anything and everything is. But, at least, it was not probable.

Eliminating, therefore, the outsider, the murder was necessarily the work of some of those within. From the latter the adulterous ostler was already excluded. The others, the half-breed, the negro, the Japanese, together with the laundress, a scullion and a housemaid, recruited from Los Angeles, were all quartered in a separate building. The fact had been brought out at the inquest, where it had been also shown that during the Weldens’ tenancy, none of them, except the housemaid, the scullion and the cook, had ever entered the house; and into the main part of it, as distinct from the kitchen and its offices, the cook and the scullion had not once, except on the morning when the murder was discovered, been known or permitted to come.

The housemaid had necessarily the run of it, but by day only, and while information concerning the rings might have been conveyed by her to other parties, she would not have been aware that they were unprotected at night, unless she had been so informed by Perkins, or by Harris, who as Perkins’ husband, probably knew as much as she did.

On the other hand, information of this character would hardly be supplied by upper servants, who lived apart from the others, particularly as one might say, on an acquaintance so brief. You never can tell, however, yet accepting the facts as they appeared, the matter narrowed down to those who slept in the house, that is to say, to Harris and Perkins.

For clearly Welden was out of it, if for no other reason than because, had he wished to be rid of the lady, a brief sojourn in neighbourly Nevada would suffice to set him legally free. Or, if divorce seemed circuitous, a slight shove from the bluff, a tarantula put nesting in her bed, and, without inconvenience, the thing was done. But anything of the kind was beyond peradventure, in addition to being absurd. Men of the world do not kill an obnoxious wife. They find it simpler to detest her. Moreover, such men as do murder their wives, do not first steal the lady’s jewels and then offer a reward for their own apprehension, another for the recovery of the gems. They do not, that is, unless they are lunatics, and anyone saner than Welden it were difficult to meet.

These deductions Wicks did not reach unaided or even as they are here set forth. On the contrary, they were prompted in part by the press, partly by the wife of his bosom. As a consequence, they were superficial and, therefore, unsound. But they satisfied, so fully even that he kept an alert eye on Harris, an indefatigable one on Perkins.

In spite of which he saw nothing suspicious. At the time being he was not, however, as close to them as he could have wished, and that defect he artfully remedied. After the funeral, Welden, leaving for address the Plaza, New York, boarded a train and was taken away. But these two remained in situations luringly procured at wages—California wages!—such as they had never known, never heard of or even dreamed.

Then for a while mention of the murder, dropped by the press, faded from Miramar. But not from Santa Barbara. There the Alert and Indefatigable, after rehearsing it endlessly to his weary wife, happened suddenly on a clue.

I

SALLY’S DUKE

To go back a little.

Sally Malakoff was twenty. She was rich, good looking, and a duchess, yet she described herself as a miserable woman and the world believed her. But though the world believed it did not sympathise. It was felt that she had not acted as she should have. For that there were excuses.

A little while before she had married a brute. Though a New York girl, she was at the time very ignorant. In the way we live now that is exceptional. Married women discuss matters before the young person with a clarity which leaves her nothing to guess about. Through some miracle, Sally had been left in the dark. A contributory cause may have heen her mentality which was shallow, but, as she was naturally sly, the miracle was none the less marvellous. Otherwise, in appearance and manner that is, she was a typically sweet young thing. She talked nicely about nothing. Her features were dainty and delicate. Her hair was dark and she had mauve eyes, which, oblique and half closed, gave her an aspect faintly Chinese. Born a Kandy, and known generally as Sugar Candy, she quite lived up to the name.

Heat sugar and abruptly it boils. Sally did boil, not long, and not effervescently. but with a sort of contained rage. Marriage she had seen somewhere defined as an association for the pursuit of things human and divine, and it was with angry amazement that she discovered what, in her case, was the derisive falsity of the definition.

During the honeymoon, or more exactly during Malakoff’s, for the girl was but an indignant participator in it, the man approached her after the fashion of a pasha who has acquired a slave. The girl loathed him for it, and it was that loathing perhaps which directly precipitated this drama. On the other hand, if, as it has been affirmed, one’s destiny is preordered, it may be that even otherwise the result would have been the same. Admitting fatality, one’s moods cannot alter it. But the fault of it, in so far at least as is humanly discernible, rested, primarily, not with Sally’s husband, but with her mother, never more than a relative to this girl, whose father had been but an acquaintance.

The latter, Sam Kandy, could have had but three objects in life; to marry, have a child and make a fortune; for these things accomplished, he concluded to die, and did so, after the fine New York fashion, with no fuss whatever, and in a manner which Mrs. Kandy, who had no affection for him, or for anyone save herself, described as most gentlemanly.

That, though, was only an amiable commonplace. In New York it is a man’s mere duty to leave a lot of money. Sam Kandy bequeathed to his daughter one million for life, with reversion to her issue, failing which, the principal passed to his nephews. To his widow he left six million absolutely.

The provisions of the will enabled Mrs. Kandy to bear the testator’s loss with a fortitude eminently Christian. She was a large, fair woman, with a large, fair wig, and the purplish complexion which internal disturbances when combined with poudre de riz will impart, and when through a jewelled lorgnette, she surveyed the trappings of her woe, she declared in the shrill voice which was habitual to her, that black is not becoming.

Nor is it. But the lady must have preferred colours. Shortly she resumed them, and, with Sally, betook herself to Paris.

It was in Paris that Malakoff was encountered, and the marriage ensued.

Jean-René-Marie, Duc de Malakoff, Prince de l’Alma, had, from adolescence, been trained like a colt for the Grand Prix in the international steeplechase of marriage. “Duchesse de Malakoff,” his mother, ceaselessly, had dinged in his ears. “That, at the lowest, is worth ten million francs.” The poor woman knew. Five million francs was what her people had paid—five million thrown in the gutter—and since then prices had doubled. But her son, thus far, when not outclassed, had been outpaced. There was Miss Murray, the American heiress, welshed from him by Solférino. There was Miss Beux, laden down with brewery guineas, whom d’Ostende had won by a nose. There was Mlle. Moses, the pearl of the Ghetto, whom d’Eylau had jockeyed away. There was Señorita Lopez y Montez, sole child of the Chilean Crœsus, whom Cambacères had filched from his hand.

These misadventures diminished the lustre of a title that, while obviously Second Empire, was yet a trifle heavy for one who has nothing, which, barring debts—the floating debt of the duchy—and an assortment of vices—the traditional vices of the French nobility—constituted the sole possessions of this man, who was not bad looking.

Malakoff had blue-black hair, blue-black eyes, a thin, straight nose, and a retreating chin, which a pointed beard concealed. Without being tall, he was not short, but, since the misadventures, perhaps out of training, for he had ceased to give in at the waist. He dressed less abominably than the majority of Frenchmen, got his clothes from London, and with them displayed an air of being surrounded by lackeys ready at a gesture from him to shut the door in anyone’s face, that air of indisputable superiority which, at an earlier epoch, when the nobility had been divested of other insignia, persisted, and so exasperated that the one remedy for its arrogance was the austere guillotine.

Though seigneurial—in appearance—he could—when it suited him—unbend. On such occasions he was affable or merely canaille.

Mrs. Kandy, who met him on the stalking ground which the American embassy is, thought him simply fascinating. To Sally, he was part of the landscape, and that not from any democratic disdain—she had none, the New York girl never does have any—but for the more intimate reason that in the neighbourhood of Fifth Avenue there was a man with laughing eyes, with whom she fancied herself in love.

Sally, quoted currently at ten million francs, flattered Malakoff’s eye. He had trained for more, but latterly he felt that he had trained in vain.

Mrs. Kandy, who had trained also, but only in social values, for which she had a naïve and inexact appreciation, encouraged him to make up to the girl, when she saw that he had no intention of making up to the girl’s mamma, which he certainly would have, had he known the terms of Sam Kandy’s will.

He did not know, however, nor, at the moment, was there any one that could acquaint him with them, except Mrs. Kandy, who, in telling the truth, which she sometimes did, sometimes found it advantageous not to tell all of it.

“And so you wish to have my little girl for your wife,” she shrilly resumed, when, in the elaborate suite which she occupied at the Elysée Hôtel, the formal and unleisurely demand had been made.

“Partly that,” he replied in the passable English which he had acquired in preparation for the Prix. “Partly that, but partly also, that I may have you for mother-in-law.”

No duke had ever talked in such a fashion to Mrs. Kandy. Barring the Duke of Kincardine, who, the previous winter, had lounged about New York, no duke had ever talked to her at all, and, as for Kincardine, he had, on meeting her, only said; “Hello,” after which he had lounged away. Malakoff’s treatment was at least more gracious, and graciousness to herself was Mrs. Kandy’s forte.

“If you are good to her, I shall feel that I can die in peace,” remarked the lady, who, whatever happened, had no intention of doing anything of the kind.

Malakoff, with equal sincerity, replied: “The dear angel, I will refuse her nothing.”

“Sally has a million dollars,” Mrs. Kandy threw in, omitting, however, to fill it up with the fact that the million was for life.

“Devilish thin,” thought Malakoff, who thought, too, of backing out. But a million dollars spells five million francs, and that amount he doubted his ability to duplicate.

“At my death,” Mrs. Kandy added, with a candour which she afterward tearfully regretted, “Sally will have six million more.”

But the contingency, remote to him, lugubrious to her, neither chose to consider further, and presently, after Sally had been summoned, and the non-existent duchy had been placed at her feet, Malakoff took himself off.

Not far, however, around the corner merely to the rue Galilée, where dwelled a Mme. Oppensheim who was his mistress, and who had supported him for years.

Giselle Oppensheim, born de Beaupré, had been married into the high finance by her people, who were very noble, prodigiously proud, and equally poor. Giselle de Beaupré accepted Oppensheim for money in the same measure that he sought her for place. That was ten years before. Since then, Oppensheim had paid for his aspirations, and, from an Anglo-Saxon standpoint, perhaps most notably in Malakoff, with whom, none the less, he was on the best terms in the world and to whom not infrequently he complained when the third party of this unholy trinity became, as she often did become, particularly waspish. For the lady, imperious to Oppensheim, was wax in the hands of Malakoff, whom she loved with a love that was at once violent, sensual and tender.

On this evening, after leaving the Kandys’, he told her of his venture.

“It is not the Peru,” she swiftly summarised, when he had cited the dower. “Enfin!” she consoling continued, “you might have done worse. Besides, in marrying an American, there can be no question of mésalliance.”

That sentiment her race dictated. Oddly, it had never reproached her with the left-handed mésalliance that she had contracted with this man, whose grandfather had been a cheesemonger. But love has its own extenuations. Moreover, while, from the standpoint of the old nobility, Malakoff was nobody, he yet managed to appear as though the spirit of that nobility were incarnated in him.

“Tell me,” Mme. Oppensheim continued. “In appearance is she better than I?”

Is the lily fairer than the rose? Sally had the ephemeral charm of the former. She was a book bound in muslin, with all the pages blank. What time and fate would scrawl there, fate and time would tell. As yet they were white. As yet the girl was a lily. Mme. Oppensheim was the rose, large, colourful, majestic.

At the question, Malakoff looked at her. Her eyes, like his own, were dark. There the resemblance ended. For while he was almost typically Latin, the fainter umber of her skin, and the rich orange of her hair, suggested an alien race. It had been said that she was the souvenir of a caprice which her mother had entertained for an Austrian prince, and as, at the question, Malakoff looked at her, he recalled the story.

“Bah!” he replied.

The exclamation sufficed. Besides, Mme. Oppensheim was otherwise assured. Between Malakoff and herself subsisted what is called the collage, that glueing of two natures together which is the result of a long liaison and which, when effected, is the strongest of life’s fragile ties. The lady was, therefore, unvisited by any vulgar sense of jealousy. In addition, in spite of the collage, or more precisely, because of it, it was necessary that Malakoff should establish himself in a manner befitting his rank. The anterior misadventures of the steeplechase had disappointed her almost as thoroughly as they had him.

“Very good,” she resumed. “I will call on her to-morrow.”

Around the corner, meanwhile, the poetry of the engagement was also being discussed.

“Of course, my dear,” Mrs. Kandy remarked, “some mothers prefer Englishmen for their daughters, but where can they get a duke?”

Meditatively Sally helped herself from a sac of bon-bons. “I don’t see,” she replied, “why they should want one at all.”

Mrs. Kandy waved her lorgnette. “That only shows how foolish you are. A duke makes a duchess, and wherever a duchess goes she is It.”

“And I don’t love him.”

“On such a short acquaintance it would be most improper if you did. For that matter, when I married your father, I did not love him, either, but I admired him, and any girl can admire a duke.”

Sally shook her head. She was thinking of the man with laughing eyes. Thinking, too, of his attentions to Maud Barhyte, a New York girl whom she also knew, and whom she envied greatly.

“I don’t know,” she answered at last.

“But I do,” retorted Mrs. Kandy. “Now ring for Perkins and go to bed.”

Sally did ring. A wooden-faced maid appeared. Later, when the woman was brushing the girl’s hair, Sally said to her:

“I am engaged to a duke.”

“Yes, mem.”

Had Sally said she was engaged to a baboon, the reply would have been the same. Perkins knew her business. It was not for her to manifest any interest in anything concerning her employers. It was for her to attend to her duties. She did attend to them, and attended to them well.

“But I will keep you, Perkins.”

“Thank you, mem.”

The brushing continued. Presently Perkins said: “If you please, mem, I’m to be married too.”

In the mirror before her Sally looked at the woman in whose face there was not a vestige of expression.

“His name is ’Arris, mem. He’s butler and valet, mem, and been only in the best ’ouses.”

“Harris!” Sally repeated. “Well, perhaps, I may take him when I have a house of my own, but you will be Perkins just the same.”

“Thank you, mem.”

Such was Sally’s wooing. The marriage was equally enchanting.

Before it occurred, Malakoff, apprised by his avoué of the terms of Sam Kandy’s will, laughed. It was not a pleasant laugh. Had Mrs. Kandy seen him at that moment, she would have been alarmed. Could she have read his thoughts, she would have known that her alarm was justified.

There was the Duc de Chose, who had bagged the booty of despoiled Venezuela; de la Dèche, who had got the loot of the wreckage of the railways of the United States; Prince Eugène, the most obscure of the obscurest Napoléonides, who had gobbled the heiress of Monte Carlo’s perfumed hell; Solférino, who had pocketed the prize American dot; d’Ostende, who had received with his bride a ton of brewery guineas; and he, Malakoff, who was as good as any of them, was done, done again, and out a beggarly million at that!

He could still desist, and would have, but an idea occurred to him. It was then that he laughed.

In accordance with local usage, the civil ceremony, which precedes the religious rites, took place at the Mairie of the precinct in which Malakoff resided. The formalities, brief in themselves, became exasperating by reason of a long delay which intervened.

Afterward, at the Elysée Hôtel, Malakoff requested a word with Mrs. Kandy.

“Madam,” he began, when Sally had gone, “in asking the hand of your daughter, I said it was not merely that I might have her for wife, but in order, also, that I might have you for mother-in-law. Do you recall it?”

Mrs. Kandy, laced to the point of suffocation, wished that he would hurry and go. But, manfully, from a red and gilt armchair in which she squirmed, she smiled.

“I do, indeed. I thought it very gracious.”

Malakoff smiled also—that smile in which the eyes have no part, and which consists in showing the teeth.

“You are most amiable. But at the time I hardly supposed you would leave me in the cold.”

“In the cold!” Mrs. Kandy, shifting uneasily, repeated.

“In the street, if you prefer. For that is what it amounts to. You told me that your daughter has a million. It is true. But the income only. That is insufficient.”

Mrs. Kandy raised her lorgnette. “But you knew this before. Mr. Ridgeway—”

Malakoff bowed. “That is also true. This Ridgeway, your lawyer, acquainted my man of business with the facts. But enamoured as I was, and am of your daughter, I did not sufficiently consider them. This morning, during the delay which I regret you should have experienced at the Mairie, I had the fullest opportunity to do so, and I have concluded to proceed no further.”

“What!”

Malakoff plucked at his beard. “I have concluded not to marry your daughter.”

At the outrageousness of that, Mrs. Kandy forgot her stays. She realised only that she was the mother of a duchess, the potential grandmother of a prince, and dismissing grammar, she cried: “But you are; you have.”

Malakoff looked at her much as though she were a wriggling worm, and it was with utter indifference to her anguish that he answered: “Not by the Church, and in my world it is only the religious ceremony that counts.”

“And you mean to say!” Mrs. Kandy screamed. Then, English failing, she soared into French. “Mais, c’est indigne! You leave my child neither fish, flesh nor fowl.”

Malakoff caught the statement and with a shrug of his shoulders tossed it back.

“It is only what you leave me. In the Americas, I am aware, matters arrange themselves otherwise. There a man may work. I believe a man is even expected to. Here it is different. A man, such as I am at least, not only is not expected to work, but would not be tolerated if he tried. Imagine to yourself the Duc de Malakoff, grocer, stockbroker even! Alors, quoi?”

From purple, Mrs. Kandy turned livid.

“I shall appeal to the embassy. I will send for my lawyer!”

Malakoff took up his hat. “I earnestly recommend you to do both. Meanwhile favour me by conveying my homage to your daughter. I have had the honour to bid you good-day.”

But when he had gone, and Mrs. Kandy had loosened her stays, she felt better and thought better, at least of one of her threats. The embassy could do nothing. To appeal there would be but to bill the whole ridiculous story to all the cynical world. She telephoned instead to Ridgeway, who shortly was announced.

Mr. Ridgeway’s mouth was full of gold teeth. While listening to her tale, he exhibited them very freely. He was thinking what an amazing fool she was.

“Of course,” he said at last, placing as he spoke a forefinger in the middle of his forehead, “the marriage has not been consummated, and an action to nullify the contract can be brought. Even otherwise, the attitude of this gentleman has been foreseen. It constitutes what the Code terms a sévice grave, and a divorce can be had. But any proceedings in the matter will cause a scandal, one that unfortunately will reflect on your daughter. Now it is evident that this gentleman wants money. They all do, the majority of the aristos that is, and they rarely marry unless they get it. My advice is, give it to him. Probably a hundred thousand francs will suffice. I will see his avoué and let you know.”

“It is outrageous,” said Mrs. Kandy, sniffling and snuffing at a vinaigrette. “No lady was ever so treated.”

Mrs. Kandy was then in a loose flowing robe, tenderly pink, which lace befluttered. In spite of her plaint, she felt better.

The relief was transient. Mr. Bidgeway on visiting Malakoff’s attorney found that a hundred thousand was a mere fraction of the amount required. Malakoff demanded five million francs.

When these figures were recited to Mrs. Kandy, instantly the woman in that tender gown was ousted by a female. She grimaced queerly. Epilepsy of the epiglottis attacked her. Instead of employing the language of the ornate, she dropped into that of the fish wife.

“Pay a man a million dollars to sleep with my daughter! Never!”

Never is a long word. Before the interview was concluded, she decided to do so.

“I am ruining myself,” she sobbed.

“It is very noble of you,” said Mr. Ridgeway, who, for that remark of his, and for that other of hers, charged extra.

II

A LITTLE TOKEN

When the five million francs had been paid and Sally Kandy became definitely Sally Malakoff, an act interrelated with the drama of her life was occurring in New York.

There in the library of a large house, situated in that part of Madison avenue, which, with Gramercy Park, still represents what residential New York used to be, a man was talking to a girl.

The man was Welden, the girl was Maud Barhyte. She was standing. He was seated.

Beside him was a table on which was an Oxford edition, in Greek, of the old Sicilian poets. At the moment, it was the only book that the library contained. Opposite was a mantel, above it, a mirror. To the right was a piano, at the left a sofa. On the walls were pictures of former Barhytes, women with pointed bodices and powdered hair; men in vermilion with swords and lace jabots. In addition to the book, the table had on it a buvard, an elaborate service for writing, and a jewelled bag of gold mesh, which the girl had put down.

A little before, letting herself in with a latch-key, as was her custom, she had come from a drive. She wore a costume of light cloth, faintly blue, exquisitely embroidered. Beneath was silk and mousseline de soie, less durable, and more costly than the garment. On her head was a hat for which she had been charged eighty dollars. She had worn it once before, and might wear it once again.

The girl was not on that account a fool. She read Plato in the original, and what is less lovely and more difficult, she read Kant. What is unusual, she thought; what is exceptional, she meditated; what is remarkable, she prayed.

She prayed that she might do nothing that should not charm, say nothing that should not please.

Generally the prayer was granted, and sometimes more fully than she wished. Men on first meeting her forgot that they were conventional beings, and remembered that they were men.

“That ought not to be allowed,” the wit of a ball-room had remarked, when in shimmering white, this girl had passed. For in her eyes that were violet, in the rich orange of her hair, in the contour of her lips, that seemed meeting for love, in the oval of her perfect face, and in her figure that pulsated with health and with life, there was a charm too alluring, almost aphrodisiac.

Of the emotions that it aroused, the girl was aware. It mortified her extremely, and through her demeanour she tried to attenuate it. But from her voice, which was naturally low, she could not always banish caresses. She could not always eliminate the incandescence from her eyes. The more demure she tried to appear, the more desirable she became. Her prayer was, perhaps, only too fully granted.

Now, on this late mid-April afternoon, there came through the open windows the surrenders of spring, and the metallic roar of the city.

“If you won’t marry me, tell me why?” Welden was saying.

With that air of being somebody which certain New Yorkers occasionally attain, he sat, supple and vigorous, looking hungrily at her. The hunger, a hunger for her, for a year and a day he had tried to appease, but hitherto quite vainly.

In and about the girl’s lips a smile hovered deliciously.

“Supposing you wearied of me, what then?”

Welden laughed. “I never could.”

The hovering smile fluttered and fled. “Supposing, then, I wearied of you!”

Welden laughed again. “I would not let you.”

To that, the girl, with a movement of her head, assented.

“Perhaps. But does it not rather seem that affection is a thing which cannot be commanded? It seems so to me. It seems to me that it commands us. It seems to me too, that, the quantity being limited, some day it must give out. When it does, love ends. No effort can prevent it.”

Welden nodded. “Some day, yes. But a hundred years with you would be insufficient for me. I could love you all through this life, and all through another.”

The smile which momentarily had gone from the girl, rejoined her.

“ ‘In æeternum te adorabo,’ ” she quoted. “I know. I have heard it before. I have heard it said by people who, when I next heard of them, were applying for a divorce. I heard Rivers swear it to Beatrix Leroy. Where are they now?”

“In the hands of their lawyers, I believe.”

“Yet, almost the day before yesterday, they were apparently mad about each other, quite as much as we are, and probably more. Now, as you put it, they are in the hands of their lawyers. Then there are, or were, the Cottings, the Colvilles, the Methuens, the Lennox Joneses. Where are they?”

“In the same box, I suppose. But what of it? What have their various deviltries to do with us?”

“Everything. We might get in the same box ourselves.”

“Ce n’est pas la mer à boire,” Welden lapsing into French, as certain New Yorkers sometimes will, replied.

Again the girl assented. “For a man, certainly not. But for a woman, it rather proclaims the fact that she has put her love and life into the hands of an individual who has destroyed the one and ruined the other. Women endure much, and I could endure that on condition, however, that I alone were aware of it. But, to have it known, printed, discussed; to have my private misfortunes public property, no, I would rather—”

The girl hesitated as though at loss for a simile. Before she could find one, provided, that is, she wanted to, Welden cut in.

“But, Maud, are you not putting the tilbury before the tandem? That people do get divorces is obvious and in the majority of cases the reason is obvious also. Men here, as a rule, marry too young. They marry because they cannot decently get the girl otherwise, and as they afterward discover, it is not the girl, but a girl that they have got. To me, you are not a girl; you are the girl, the one girl in the whole wide world.”

Maud looked the matter over as it reached her, and indicated the flaw in it with a smile.

“We are taught that experience teaches, and I may suppose that you have had yours, many experiences, I dare say. In that case, you have had a liberal education, which I have lacked. Your experiences have qualified you as an expert, and it is as such that you are able to decide that I am the one girl in the world for you. That is very gratifying. But what is there to enable me to determine that you are the one man? You may be. Probably you are. But how can I tell? How can I?”

Sagaciously Welden answered: “Try me.”

Maud turned away, and with her two hands made a pass in the air. It was as though in some rite known but to herself, she were interrogating the invisible lap of the indifferent gods.

Then, looking suddenly at him, she exclaimed: “I have a great mind to.”

In spite of a gesture meant to stay him, Welden sprang at the girl, caught her in his arms, and pressing his lips to hers, so bent her with the embrace, that she fell backward on the sofa.

At once, freeing herself, she pushed him away.

“Oblige me by sitting where you were.”

As she spoke, she went to the mirror, readjusted her hat, patted her frock. These operations concluded, she turned again.

“We may as well say that we are engaged. In that manner we can be together whenever we like. Come to dinner to-morrow. I will speak to my father to-night, you can speak to him then.”

She moved back. “Don’t kiss me here. Don’t. Now you must go. I have to dress.”

Welden passed from the library into a reception room which adjoined it, and from there to the marble flagging of the hall.

Near the entrance stood a man, an old family servant who had known Welden throughout the year and the day of the siege and who now handed him his hat and stick.

Welden, considering him with laughing eyes, fumbled in his waistcoat and said:

“William, put that in your pocket and don’t be surprised if you hear any news.”

“Thank you, sir. Thank you, Mr. Welden,” the man answered knowingly. “I shan’t be surprised; no, sir.”

Opening the door, he held it open until Welden reached the street.

That night, when some guests had gone, Maud spoke, as she said she would speak, to her father. They were in the drawing-room which, after a New York fashion of long ago, was frescoed, furnished in yellow and black, fitted with enormous mirrors and with chandeliers almost as big, equally ancient.

“I am engaged to Gerard Welden.”

General Barhyte, who had taken up an evening paper, put it down and removed his glasses. He had bushy white hair, a white cavalry moustache, and a fierce red face which suddenly could become indulgent.

It became so then. The Weldens had been identified with New York as long as the Barhytes, possibly longer. Welden himself represented all that was locally desirable in addition to the fact that he was personally agreeable, pleasant to the eye, liked by men, admired by women, a man of means, an M. F. H., President of the Swordsmen Club.

These items considered, the general replaced his glasses and looked up at his daughter.

“He is not in business, is he?”

Maud, who had been standing, seated herself on an S in upholstery.

“Well? And you? You are not either.”

For a moment the general considered the point. “That’s another story. I think nowadays a man should have some occupation.”

Maud smiled, displaying the nacre of her teeth. “So do I. He will have me. It will be enough for him.”

“Or for anybody,” laughed the general. “When is it to be?”

“When is what to be?”

“Why, God bless my soul, the wedding, of course.”

From under the girl’s skirt a white slipper, butterflied with gold, moved in and out.

“Oh, not for a long time yet.”

“Why?”

“Because.”

The general laughed again. “That is the best reason in the world. Well, puss, you have my consent and your mother’s money. You have been a good girl and I hope to God that you will be happy. He means to say a word to me, doesn’t he?”

Maud stood up. “To-morrow. I have asked him to dinner.”

General Barhyte, gathering again the evening paper, nodded. The match was everything he could wish. The more he considered it, the more he was pleased.

The following evening, when Maud had left the table and Welden had said the promised word, that pleasure he expressed.

“I hope,” he added, “that after you are married you will be willing to live here. Why, God bless my soul, the house is big enough for a dozen of you. I always breakfast in my rooms, usually I have luncheon at the Athenæum, and I have always wanted to dine there.”

“You are very kind, General,” Welden, sitting, smiling and supple, before him, replied. “Personally I shall like nothing better, particularly as my own house has gone the way the rest of New York will go—engulfed by office buildings and department stores.”

“Yes, yes. They are making the town impossible. God bless my soul, if I did not know better, I should think I was in Chicago. But there is Maud looking in. Don’t let me detain you.”

Welden stood up, shook hands with the old gentleman, thanked him again, and followed the girl into the faded splendours of the drawing-room.

“I have something for you,” she announced.

From a little box she took a sapphire, flat and oblong. About it was a thin gold band and at one end a clasp. On the band was engraved: Aultre n’auray.

“ ‘None but you,’ ” she translated as he examined the device which, long ago, a girl wove for a king.

“Now,” she resumed, “if you will put that on the stem of your watch, it will not be offensive, will it?”

“On the contrary. But how odd!”

“I meant it to be. It is a token between us. If you ever change your mind, do not let me see that you have and do not tell me. Send this to me.”

“It will go with me to my grave,” Welden answered.

Drawing her to him, he kissed her, longly at first, then so penetratingly that the least pulses of her being shook.

Slowly, in her low, caressing voice, the girl said to him: “Dearest, I adore you.”

III

A LITTLE LOVE

In the way we live now, the income derived from two million dollars is better than nothing, but, for a duke and a duchess, it is little more. Yet in Paris, provided one know, money may be made to do double the duty that it can effect elsewhere.

Malakoff did know. The last price of anything, the real value of no matter what, he thoroughly understood. It was a boast of his that no one could do him, and apart from the welshings in the steeplechase, it is probable that he had never been jockeyed in his life. On the perhaps meagre income he succeeded, consequently, in setting up an establishment which, if not princely, was not bourgeois. He succeeded even in setting up two of them, one at Deauville for the villégiatura, another for town life in the Avenue Malakoff—“my avenue,” as he, with what perhaps was pardonable pride, described it.

The house there or, to speak French, the hôtel, had been obtained at a rental relatively low. Situated between court and garden, it had a vanilla frontage, variegated at the windows by a touch of green, at the balcony by another of pink, which gave it vaguely the appearance of a Neapolitan ice.

Sally did not take to it nor did she take to her existence there. In the unholy rites of the marriage, each one of which had set a separate mark upon her, she felt cheated of her girlhood and, in this house, she felt cheated, too, of happiness and love. Many are without suspecting it, many others cheat themselves. But Sally had been thrown blindfolded into the arms of a man who did not care for her, who did not want to care for her, and she had been so thrown for no other earthly reason than that a stupid woman might be related to a duke. Sally hated her mother for it with a hatred which equalled, when it did not exceed, the loathing which she felt for her husband.

Ordinarily the results of a husband’s inconsiderateness are but temporary. Given but time and the bride forgets and forgives, and Sally, who was not only shallow, but, like all shallow people, impulsive, might have ended by loving the man whom she loathed, had not his inconsiderateness been succeeded by defection. Barely a wife, she ceased to be one, and that, while distinctly a blessing, aborted the possibility of anything further between them, anything, that is, except indifference on his part and antipathy on hers.

Her thoughts at this time were not, therefore, very gay, and their lack of gaiety was complicated by the fact that she had not many of them. But she found compensations, among these a curious one in Mme. Oppensheim, who, for obvious reasons, had determined that Sally should like her, and who succeeded in that which, other things being equal, would have been an impossible task. Sally did like her, or perhaps it will be more exact to say that she relished the attentions shown her by this woman of the world, who, not content with being merely gracious to an inexperienced American, took the trouble to form her, to teach her the tone, the ways and manners of the Parisian, in particular that désir de plaire which gives to the speech and bearing of the mondaine her untranslatable charm.

Sally at first was necessarily unaware of the relations that existed between this woman and Malakoff. When she was better informed, as she promptly became, she felt grateful to her for standing between them.

The gratitude was very feline. Though Sally purred, she could scratch. But meanwhile discovering, moreover, as she also did, that in the special world in which she moved, the situation, far from being exceptional, was the reverse, she felt not merely grateful but Parisian, and in that state of advancement, dispensed both with the sense of dignity which should be natural to the married woman, and with the sense of morality which usually is instinctive in the young.

Incidentally it amused her to be duchess. She was glad to be rid of her mother. She liked to drive without her, and view landscapes of modes. Moreover, in the Avenue Malakoff, she received detachments from what is called All-Paris—the glittering and rakish ship of fashion, in which the distaff-side of the Faubourg Saint-Germain does not always deign to sail. But though the feminine portion of the old nobility has its reserves, the men are less punctilious and even otherwise there are always others quite as agreeable and frequently more so, the cosmopolitan leaders of life and sport, who nowhere else are as enterprising. Of these, many made up to her, a circumstance of which, quaintly enough, she complained to Mme. Oppensheim.

“But, ma toute belle,” the latter remonstrated. “When a man delays more than fifteen minutes in making up to me, I regard him as insulting.”

“You are so beautiful,” Sally replied. But she thought her simply fantastic, and that not through any straight-lacedness, but because she did not yet understand how a woman can permit any man, save the man of all men, to attempt an approach however circuitous, to the heart’s tender places. In that respect, Malakoff’s treatment of her had been beneficial, and while in the antipathy incited, it had necessarily failed to reveal what love may be, none the less it had suggested possibilities which were then accentuated by Welden’s presence in Paris.

Prior to her marriage, she had fancied herself in love with him. Now, in looking back, she realised that she had not known the meaning of the word. It still held its secrets, mysteries unrevealed, the esoteric love of a doctrine which only life can impart, only life and a lover. But the latter term had also its shadings, between which Sally wavered, not through any loyalty to Malakoff, she owed him none; nor through any loyalty to herself, she was unaware that she owed any, but because Welden was an inaccessible person.

At a five-o’clock in that amiable region which is known as the American colony, Sally made him such little tentative advances as a woman may. Agilely he extracted himself from her ambuscades. Ordinarily, he might have stormed them. That would have been only civil. But what ordinarily would have been civil, in this instance, would have been base. He was bound by bonds that to certain natures are the strongest of all. Apart from which he had no desire to encourage Sally. Maud left him none.

A fortnight after the episode of the little token, the girl and her father sailed for Paris. Welden accompanied them and it was in Paris that the consummation of the agreement occurred.

Previously the matter was somewhat debated. Maud Barhyte knew many things, among others, that once upon a time it had been heretical to think, heretical, also, to love. She knew, furthermore, that since then progress had liberated thought without, however, completely emancipating the heart. But, she had argued, the right to think and the right to love being both fundamental in human nature, one is as clear as the other, and while, to the bigot, any freedom in love may be heretical still, none the less, such liberty is permissible, provided the appearances are preserved, and no one else is injured.

These views she put before Welden. Their fallacy was patent to him. For while the whole moral value of marriage may subsist in a union which is contracted solely in the consciences of those who enter into it, and while such a union may not only present but preserve the entire and eternal law of Right, yet, when such a union is contracted in conditions such as theirs, there is an injury to others. There is an injury, though it be but potential, to the unborn. There is a further injury, and a grave one, to the woman, often, also, to the man. A woman is never completely woman except in the family, and there can be no family once certain conventions are contravened. These conventions, which jurists did not invent, or codes originate, are exterior to woman, superior to man, and, when disregarded, inimical to both of them.

But, though the fallacy of the girl’s views was patent to Welden, the fallacy of refuting them was patent as well. The rare gifts of the gods should be piously accepted, never refused. Apart from which, in the way we live now, men of the world do not recite moral maxims after the manner of Confucius. Welden was too modern for that, and incidentally too hungry. But he saved his conscience.

“Your views,” he declared, “are as adorable as they are advanced; but they would be still more adorable were they antiquated enough to induce you to marry me.”

“Dearest,” she replied, “have we not been all over that?”

They had indeed. At the time they were in New York. In the after joy which love and life in Paris brought, neither, between them, could have discovered a regret, the vain desire merely that it should never end, never! and in a world where all things must and do.

Meanwhile felicity was theirs, one so full, so absorbing, so intense and eager that sometimes from their commingled breath, rose the deceiving image of felicities larger and more fair. Sometimes, from the fountain of delight, a clear jet falling in drizzling sheaves, shook stars in their eyes and ears. Sometimes the pulsations of love swept over them like tides. Sometimes the waters lifted them, sank them, lowered them deeper, caught, carried and drifted them, hour long, unappeasably, from night to dawn. Once, from the mysterious affinities that similarise the flesh and spirit, a fear seemed to mount and warn of a catastrophe unknown, yet near.

The latter impression, wholly momentary and immediately forgot, came later. At the time being, their clear sky was cloudless. Intermediately, for general convenience, they were but another engaged couple, and it was by the simple expedient of announcing the engagement that Welden, at a five-o’clock in the Avenue Marceau, extricated himself from Sally’s ambuscades.

“To Maud Barhyte!” exclaimed Sally, who certainly took her defeat very well, “how perfectly dear! I was thinking of her only the other day.”

Sally, like her mother, sometimes spoke truly. In this instance, what she said was exact. She had been thinking of a resemblance that existed between Mme. Oppensheim and Maud.

“Where is she?” she continued. “And where are you? I want you both to dinner.”

“Thank you,” Welden replied. “Maud is at the Mirifique, in the rue de la Paix, and I am across the street.”

“How nice and convenient that is. Well, tell her with my love, that I am coming to see her at once.”

Sally smiled and nodded and turned. “Bonjour, Madame de Chose!” she said to a woman. “Bonjour, Prince!” she repeated to a man. “How sweet you look, Pinkey!” she added to a girl. “Bonjour! Bonjour!”

Sally certainly took her defeat very well. In the crowded salons of Mrs. Cawtree, her hostess, a New Yorker who had lived so long in Paris, that she was unaware how Parisian New York has become; in the spacious and peopled rooms she looked far more victorious than vanquished, and incidentally very sweet. “But too animated,” Mrs. Cawtree, to whom such attenuations were pleasing, afterward declared.

Welden fell back and away. Presently in a motor-cab he was sailing down the Champs Elysées, and on to the Cercle de l’Escrime, a fencing club, of which he was a member, where, when in Paris, he usually went for a bout each day.

The bout served a double purpose. It combined practice and pleasure. It did more. It helped to keep him in that condition of supple vigour which it is the mere duty of an idler and particularly of a lover to maintain. To this condition other causes were contributory. He had a hack for the Bois and near Longchamp he kept a hunter, one that he had bought, not indeed for any immediate sport, but for future runs on Long Island. This horse, Irish by birth, and Blazes by name, was strong enough to carry a house. He had short legs, a short back, prodigious quarters, shoulders like the top of a haystack, and an impudent eye. He had cost a pretty figure, but Welden, who knew as much about horses as any one can, except a vet., felt that he had got him cheap, and to his Longchamp groom, a middle-aged, weasel-faced man, he gave these simple and sound instructions: “Mind you, now, plenty of oats and plenty of work.”

On this afternoon, in the salle d’armes, he found, among other members, Louis Le Hillel, a Franco-American, to whom, through his grandmother, he was vaguely related, and with whom he had long been on terms of agreeable, though not oppressive, intimacy. Le Hillel had the face of a prelate, the manners of a débutante, and a wildcat’s fearless agility.

After a bout with him, after a shower bath, and after dressing for the evening in the club, as is customary there, Welden sailed away in another cab to dine with Maud and her father.

The Mirifique, where they lodged, had been considered smart in the days of Balzac’s beaux, and that distinction it had contrived to maintain. But then it had not succumbed to the general teutonising of such places. The management was not German, the servants were not Swiss, the chef was a chef. Though situated on that most cosmopolitan of streets, which the rue de la Paix is, it remained really Parisian. Guests there were not considered fit merely to be robbed, but patrons to be pleased. Mainly these patrons were Russians, than which, in the managerial eye, there is nothing superior, save only those appertaining to some grrande famille Américaine, for that is the ideal, and that is what the Barhytes were.

The suite which they occupied was on what Italians call the noble floor, and which the French, less translatably, describe as the first above. It gave on the street, and consisted of a vestibule, a frescoed salon, a tapestried dining-hall, and the usual sleeping rooms. The general’s quarters, and those of his daughter, were separated by the dining room and salon. But Maud’s had that which the general’s lacked, a private entrance. It gave on a stairway at the rear, and though it was supposed to be used only by Maud’s maid, Maud herself made use of it when returning unduly from Welden.

When he entered that evening, there was mounting from the street its odour of verbena and absinthe. Following that, were the cries of the hawkers who are never still. Then at once there was a waiter announcing dinner.

Already Welden had been greeted by the general. For a moment he had held Maud’s hand in his. Slender, white and very cool, it burned him. The contour of her figure and her too alluring looks, burned him still more. At the pressure of his hand on hers, she, too, must have burned. A faint flame leaped to her face, coloured it charmingly, and sank slowly away.

“And where, may one inquire, have you been?” she asked, with that clinging intonation of hers, which was a caress in itself, and which lent to her simplest words the effect of a kiss. “We rather fancied that we should see you.”

“So we did,” said the general. “But dinner appears to be ready. Welden, will you take Maud out?”

“I have been talking to a friend of yours,” Welden presently remarked, unfolding, as he spoke, a beautifully folded napkin. “Sugar Candy, she wants us to dine.”

“That is Sam Kandy’s daughter, isn’t it?” the general interjected. “Let me see, she married—”

“A very good looking man, I hear,” Maud answered. “Have you met him?” she asked, turning to Welden.

“That reminds me, Maud,” the general ran on. “At the Visitors’ Club to-day, a Frenchman, a painter, was introduced to me. It appears that he has seen you somewhere. God bless my soul! What an extravagant mood you put him in! He wants to paint your portrait and he says that if he may, it will be the clou—what do you call it in English—the success? Yes, the success of the Salon. A most extravagant chap. It was Colonel Floyd who introduced him. By the way, Floyd wants us to go to Frascati’s. He is to be there for July and he says—”

“Frascati’s at Hâvre?” said Maud.

“Yes, where else should it be? Now how devilish good that fish is, isn’t it? They do do you well here, don’t they? Floyd says—”

The general rambled on. Dishes perfectly cooked, perfectly served, succeeded each other. Coffee came. Finally the general stood up.

“Welden,” he said, “don’t let me disturb you. Stop and keep Maud company.”

He turned to the girl. “I have an engagement with Floyd. Shall you be up when I return?”

“Ah! that depends.”

“God bless my soul! Of course it does. I hardly believe I shall be late, though. Good night, Welden.”

The old gentleman passed on and out, wondering a little, as he occasionally did, why, as yet, no date had been set for the wedding. Had he known, apoplexy would have seized him. But he did not know, and fortunately never learned. Fortunately for us all there are mysteries that we never elucidate. In its inscrutable ways the Inscrutable is beneficent.

IV

A LITTLE FRISK

The multiple brilliancies of the table were punctuated by goblets which lackeys in silk stockings, knee breeches and the saffron liveries of the Malakoffs replenished with gloved hands. A maître d’hôtel, after presenting a sturgeon from the Volga, was supervising its service. Through the hum of talk, the tinkle of silver on Sevres, above the glittering table, rose the rich voice of the duke.

At his right was Mme. de Solférino, gorgeous and golden. At his left was Mme. de Cérisy, a massive brunette, outwardly attentive, but inwardly blaspheming. Next to her was de Dol, a sportsman with racing stables at Chantilly. Farther down was Welden. Opposite de Dol was Aquaviva, an Italian, master of the Roman hunt. At his right sat Maud. Beyond, at the other end of the table, was Sally, a Turkish legate on one side, a Russian prince on the other.

Between Sally and Malakoff, were eight other guests, or sixteen in all, a number relatively restricted, but, afterward, there was to be a sauterie, a little frisk, to which a hundred more were coming.

Mme. de Cérisy, outwardly smiling, but inwardly cursing her couturière, wore a confection that matched her name. It did not do and the consciousness that it did not was increased doubly, first by the glitter of Mme. de Solférino, again by the picture presented by Maud, who, with the ivory of her neck and arms, the rich orange of her hair, her incandescent eyes and too alluring looks, seemed a dream and a despair.

Malakoff, turning from Mme. de Cérisy to her, moistened his lips.

To annoy him, Mme. de Cérisy remarked: “Giselle Oppensheim is not with us to-night.”

“Unfortunately no,” he answered. “She was awaited elsewhere.”

It was a fortnight after the episode at Mrs. Cawtree’s. On the afternoon that followed the little skirmish, Sally called at the Mirifique, and finding Maud at home, embraced her, congratulated her, and asked her and Welden to dinner, an invitation which she later reinforced by another, begging both to come to her at Deauville, from the third to the tenth of July. The two bids had been jointly accepted, and it was in response to the first, that Maud and Welden were then dining at her house.

At the moment, Malakoff was addressing himself to Maud. Welden could not hear what he said, but in spite of intervening candelabra, he could see the girl’s face. She was smiling, apparently amused.

Welden felt no jealousy, nothing but the calm of invincible possession, and, as he ate of farcied truffles, which had just been served, and drank the blonde wine with which his glass was constantly replenished, he told himself that in a few hours the girl would be in his arms.

Some vibration of the thought must have reached Sally. Leaning forward, she called at him.

“Isn’t she radiant? In New York she was exquisite, here she is exquisite and radiant besides. What has done it? Is it love? Is it? Ah, alors! Qui done m’apprendra ce que c’est que l’amour?”

With that, a nod and a ripple of laughter, Sally turned to Cantire, an under secretary of the British Embassy, a boy with pink cheeks and fair hair.

The dinner proceeded. Courses succeeded each other. Sweets came and went. Solemnly the butler approached Sally and muttered at her.

But Sally, her attention diverted, had not heard. Presently she looked up.

“Well, Harris, what is it?”

The man muttered again.

“On arrive!” cried Sally, rising. “The others are coming! They are here!”

From beyond floated a kiss of harps that were marrying violins to the strain of a waltz; Malakoff, rising also, bent to Mme. de Solférino, and, her hand on his arm, led the way from the brilliant room, to rooms more brilliant.

In a little, though, marshalled by him, Welden, Cantire, Aquaviva and de Dol returned to the table, where cigars and liqueurs were being served, and where other men joined them.

“Monsieur Welden,” Malakoff called from where he stood. “You know the Marquis Aquaviva de Santamarta, the Comte de Dol and M. Cantire.”

Then as the men nodded, collectively he added:

“Messieurs, this gentleman, a compatriot of the duchess, is a renowned sportsman. Should he consent to enter, in all conscience, I may say, have a care.”

“Thank you,” said Welden, biting the end from a cigar. “But enter what?”

“A little run over the sticks at de Dol’s,” Cantire, in English, replied.

“Permit me,” said the count, approaching. He had honest eyes, a slight moustache, and a careful manner. “Monsieur,” he continued to Welden, “at Chantilly, I have some stables, oh, nothing to speak of, but a little stretch which is, perhaps, sufficient, and these gentlemen, with Kara Saraguine, whom I do not see at this moment, have been arranging a hurdle-race for the sixth. If now you, monsieur, will be amiable enough to enter, it will become truly an international run. Prince Kara is Russian, the Marquis Aquaviva is—”

“I should like nothing better,” Welden cut in. “But on the sixth, I have arranged to be at M. de Malakoff’s.”

“And most amiable it is of you,” Malakoff exclaimed. “I thank you infinitely, but—”

“I have also,” Cantire, in English, interrupted. “We can send our horses to Chantilly before we go, and run up from Deauville together.”

“Voyons!” said Malakoff. “Shall we not talk French? De Dol does not understand, or Aquaviva either.”

“Pardon, yes, a very little,” the count softly interposed. Then lapsing serenely into French he added: “As a baby, I studied it with my nurse.”

“It is arranged then?” said Aquaviva to Welden. He had a full beard, pursed lips, and an air of being very much pleased with everything. “You will join us, is it not so?”

Welden, turning to him, with his laughing eyes, nodded. “Yes, thanks, it ought to be very good fun.”

“Well, then, what would a little cut at baccarat say to you, messieurs?” Malakoff in his rich voice inquired. “Ah! behold Cantire, who abandons us now.”

For Cantire, rightly preferring the nobler possibilities of captivating women, to the more sordid chance of winning gold, was then making for the frisk.

“A hundred louis,” Malakoff resumed. “It is I who am banker. If you please, this way.”

He motioned at a footman and a door was opened to a fumoir where an oval table was set, and where presently Welden, to whom he dealt practically nothing but eights and nines, relieved him of a major portion of the money.

Malakoff laughed and got up. “Bah! Another time it will be my turn.”

But now Aquaviva took the bank. Other men, drifting in, staked against him. Welden continued to play and continued to win. Meanwhile Malakoff had gone. De Dol, too, had disappeared. Of the original party only Aquaviva and Welden remained. Finally Welden himself stood up, and, guided by the harps, entered the room that served for the frisk.

It was large and luminous. The polished floor was swept by trains undulant and glistening. There were black coats from the lapels of which hung clusters of minute decorations; white shirts which the broad ribbons of higher orders enhanced. Bare shoulders and jewelled necks emerged from pearl embroidered corsages. Coils of hair, bitten by combs, gleamed with hereditary gems. There was the sheen of silk, of diamonds and of flesh. There was, too, an aroma of orris and flowers which, while a trifle voluptuous, was also a little heavy. But over it, above everything, there mounted that atmosphere which is the marked characteristic of such assemblies, the vaporisation of a sentiment shared by all, that of being among oneselves, and of being thereby generally and solidly united by nothing whatever.

In the centre of the room, couples were turning. Beyond, in a doorway that led to other salons, Sally stood talking to Cantire. Opposite, on the other side of the room, high windows that descended to the floor, opened on a balcony.

Welden moved on. He did not see Maud, and in search of her, he went to the nearest of these windows. In front of it, her back to the balustrade, the girl stood talking to Malakoff. She was looking down and did not see him, and Malakoff, who was facing her, did not either.

Tranquilly and courteously he approached. “Without indiscretion, if I am not interrupting—”

Maud looked up, and Malakoff looked around.

“I beg of you,” said the latter.

“Would you care for a turn?” asked Welden, who, as he spoke, nodded and smiled at both of them.

“Voilà!” Malakoff exclaimed. “You remind me. I also have my duties. Mademoiselle!” Moving aside, he bowed.

“Sans adieu,” Maud called to him over her shoulder, and accompanied by Welden passed on and in.

There Welden put an arm about her and together they began gliding and reversing with that ease, which, in all the cosmopolitan world of fashion, Americans best display. As they floated over the floor, others, who were also waltzing, stopped to observe them, noticing which they stopped themselves.

“Let us go in there,” said Welden, indicating the door at which, a moment before, Sally had stood.

It led to a smaller room, delicately fitted, where, however, they were not alone. Other people, Parisians with whom they were unacquainted, were seated or standing about. But, near the entrance, was an unoccupied sofa, on which Maud sank and Welden dropped.

The girl unfurled a fan. “Dearest, do you know, Malakoff talks really rather well.”

Welden nodded. “He isn’t such a bad sort. I won a pot of money of him to-night. By the way, I am in for a race. It is to be on the sixth—”

Further confidences were interrupted. In the doorway Cantire appeared, looking eagerly about.

“Oh, Miss Barhyte,” he cried, as he spotted the girl. “Won’t you give me this dance, or at least, what’s left of it?”

Maud, rising, took the boy’s arm, and Welden, who had also risen, dropped back.

The pot of money which he had won, while inconsequential, was an assistance. There had been a very inconveniencing crash in Wall street. That morning he had meditated wiring there and having the proceeds of July coupons and dividends cabled to his Paris account. But now, meanwhile, the pot, however relatively small, was a help. Mechanically he felt of the pocket in which he had placed it.

As he did so, Maud reappeared. Other confidences ensued, which, as before, were interrupted. A new aspirant for a turn came to the girl. After the second, there was a third, then there were more. For in the minds of men, however obtuse, her beauty put a restlessness, a trouble, sometimes a hope. Those who were free coveted the possibilities it evoked; those who were not ruminated the savourousness of those possibilities.

“Dearest,” she said at last. “Shall we go?”

“Yes, à l’Anglaise,” Welden answered, expressing in the language of the land its neat equivalent for the English “French leave.”

“Dearest,” she remonstrated, “I at least must say a word.”

In search of Sally, on through the ball room she passed, surrounded by homages, enveloped by the glances of men.

Presently, after the word had been said, and her cloak had been put about her, she went down through a double hedge of lackeys to the perron below, where her lover waited and a footman bawled:

“The people of Madame la princesse de Solférino!”

Very gorgeous, very smiling, the princess, formerly Fanny Murray of New York, interrupted her luminous exit to remark to them: “Hasn’t it been jolly?”

When she, her glitter and her platitudes had gone, the footman bawled again, this time for Welden’s carriage.

About the entrance was a group of grooms, idlers, birds of the night. Down the avenue glowed the lamps of waiting cars and broughams. Before these a sergent-de-ville, his head bent, his hands behind his back, promenaded Napoleonically. Above, the moon hung, a round of butter in the sky. In the air was a sweetness, and from the open windows sank the swooning measures of a waltz.

Welden, after putting Maud into the carriage, drew from a pocket of his white waistcoat a chainless watch, from the stem of which her token, the sapphire, dangled.

“You have had no supper. Suppose we go somewhere and take a private room?”

With a quick intake of the breath, the girl answered: “Dearest, yes, and let us hurry.”

“The Café de la Paix,” Welden threw at the coachman’s back. “Et vivement!”

Then, in a moment, when he was beside her, the girl withdrew a glove, put her hand in his and whispered:

“Dearest, I am so happy that it frightens me.”

“Yes,” Welden replied. “I know. I, too, am afraid.”

“You!”

“In any love affair there are always three. The third is the unknown. It is that which frightens.”

What he meant he could not have told. The remark, passably oracular, had but sprung into the sudden utterance, which, occasionally, prophecies take. Dismissed at the time in immediate embraces, afterward it was shudderingly recalled.

V

THE VILLA PORTUGAISE

To the cosmopolite, Deauville is delightful. The days fall by in an atmosphere dripping with ammonia and desire, scented with caprices and brine, shuttled too by that general deviltry, which those consorts of society, wealth and idleness, inevitably produce.

The house there which the Malakoffs had taken was known as the Villa Portugaise. The reason of that was inscrutable. Instead of the patio, loggia, fountains and blooms which the name implied, there was a trim lawn fronting a thoroughly English dwelling that looked obliquely at the sea.

In spite of the Britannic reserve of its appearance, there was in it an ease, an entire liberty, a complete sans-gêne that harmonised very perfectly with the Deauvillian air.

On the ground floor were the living rooms, spacious, cool, perhaps a trifle severe. These gave on the ocean. On the lawn side was a wide hall that extended from one end of the house to the other. In the centre was the entrance. At the right of the doorway was a table on which were reviews, papers, periodicals. Above it was a rack in which letters were put. To the left of the entrance, at the extreme end, a flight of steps started, continued for a few steps, then halting, turned abruptly and directly up to a galleried floor above where the bedrooms were, which for general convenience had been numbered.

When, on the evening of the third of July, Maud and Welden arrived, they were met in the hall by Sally, by Malakoff, the Cérisys, the Solférinos and a dozen others, among whom was Cantire.

The boy, attired in beautifully cut evening clothes, looked hot, or rather red. Mme. de Cérisy, taking advantage of his youth, had put to him questions which even at Deauville were perhaps indiscreet. Mrs. Cawtree, who had come over from her own very neighbourly villa, had overheard and was laughing.

“Hasten, my children,” Sally, after the first greetings, called in French. “We dine and at once.”

Maud was then taken to No. 10, a room at the head of the stairs. Opposite was No. 12. It was there Welden was shown. The arrangement was so convenient that he congratulated himself on its idyllic simplicity.

A little later when he and Maud had dressed and both were about to descend the stair, they could hear Sally exclaiming.

In her hand was a blue rag of a telegram on which a string of typewritten words had been gummed.

“What is it?” Malakoff asked.

“Giselle Oppensheim who wires that she comes to-morrow. But where shall I put her? Where?”

“Bah!” answered Malakoff. “It will arrange itself. On s’avisera.”

Mrs. Cawtree, who knew everything, everything fashionably knowable that is, looked admiringly at Sally. It was not every bride and particularly it was not every American bride, who was capable of being so indulgently sans-façon. Mrs. Cawtree’s esteem for Sally mounted. But at once an attenuation followed. Probably she does not know, the lady reflected.

“Do you fancy that the duchess knows about Mme. Oppensheim?” she asked of Cantire when presently she found him next to her at dinner.

“Knows what?” the boy inquired, choking down as he spoke, the velvet of a bisque.

“I remind myself,” Mrs. Cawtree inconsequentially resumed, “of the woman who asked Dumas whether there was anything between him and the Princess Belgioso. ‘Madam,’ he replied, “sometimes nothing whatever.’ ”

It was a moment before Cantire got it. When he did he laughed in a fashion so disorderly that to steady him, Mrs. Cawtree asked him to a frisk at her house the next night.

The effort succeeding, she turned with a similar invitation to Aquaviva who was opposite, after which she asked Prince Saraguine who sat between her and Sally.

Kara Saraguine had an air of having lived extensively and of fully intending to continue such living. At the moment he was eating mussels from the sauce of a sole Normande and while listening to Sally’s chatter, had an eye on Maud, who sat a little beyond, on the other side of the table.

“That youthfulness is ravishing,” he remarked and wiped his mouth. “A compatriot, Duchess? One could devour her.”

Cantire’s eyes were now on the girl, so were Malakoff’s and Solférino’s, and Maud, knowing of old the ideality of men’s thoughts, blushed suddenly and divinely.

But at once, for countenance’ sake, leaning forward, she called, in English, to Sally.

“What sort of a place is Etretat? While I was dressing they brought me a telegram from my father. He is to motor there from Frascati’s to-morrow. Is it nice?”

“Charming!” Saraguine volunteered in French. “The downs, the cliffs, the view, whatever you will, is charming, except the world there. No, frankly, Mademoiselle, that is everything there is of most grocer.”

“Etretat!” Solférino, also in French, exclaimed. “I promenaded myself once that way. Once, that is permissible, twice would be a sin. And I, I am not exacting. I—”

Solférino ran on. Presently everybody seemed to be talking at once. Momentarily Maud’s too alluring looks were forgotten. But when the dinner was over, several men gathered in the hall about her and there remained until drawn into the fumoir, where Welden was the last to follow and where, afterward, with the hopelessness of a regret that is to be eternal, he wished he had never gone.

There, a footman was trundling a chest on wheels. In it were cigars of different shades and sizes, cigarettes of various brands. As Welden entered, the man steered it up to him. He took a londrès and surveyed the room.

Near by was a buffet, hospitably inviting. On it were decanters of chartreuse and maraschino; flagons of brandy and gin; bottles of Vichy and Eau de Vals. These latter had obviously been attacked. But with that abstemiousness which is a characteristic of the way we live now, the liquors and liqueurs were untouched.

Contiguously was a billiard table on which Cantire, a cigar between his teeth, was knocking balls about. Opposite on a sofa, raised by a dais, Solférino sprawled. He looked precisely like a fat old woman.

Idly Welden wondered why his wife had accepted him. She was a Murray. The Murrays were not brilliant. But in point of birth and, for that matter, of breeding, her family, like Maud’s and like his own, were superior, in every way, to any imperial spawn.

He passed on. Beyond was the green baize of a baccarat table, about which now other men were grouped. Saraguine was dealing. The cards which he gave to the right, Aquaviva received; those to the left went to Malakoff. Behind these the others stood and punted.

Presently, Malakoff, to whom Saraguine had furnished an almost uninterrupted series of picture cards, got up, and Welden, after a circular look of inquiry, took the vacated chair.

The ill luck that had visited that side of the table continued. Across the way Aquaviva and his backers were winning. Meanwhile Welden and those behind him lost. Then, as is usual in such circumstances, the losers abandoning their positions, deserted to the favoured side and shortly, from the chair which Malakoff had relinquished, Welden was betting alone.

He had begun with hundred franc wagers. As these vanished, his stake increased. From a silk card case he drew blue and white notes, one after another, until all which it held were gone. Barring some loose gold in his waistcoat he had nothing.

“Je suis ratiboisé,” he remarked. “I am cleaned out.”

He was getting up, as Malakoff had done, when Saraguine, seeing his predicament and perhaps conscious that if he desisted, the game might cease, said to him:

“If you will, I beg of you, stake on parole.”

“Thanks,” Welden answered and resumed his seat. “A hundred louis.”

The game proceeded. Cantire had left the billiard table. Solférino approached. Aquaviva, relinquishing his chair to de Cérisy, went to the buffet, drank largely of Vichy and walked away.

“Nine!” said Welden, exposing his cards,

“Eight!” said Saraguine, exposing his own.

“Nothing,” said de Cérisy, pushing his cards aside.

Saraguine, after gathering in the money from that quarter, paid Welden and redealt.

For a while thereafter, fortune changed. The players that had deserted Welden returned. He recovered what he had lost and ten thousand francs in addition. Then luck veered. He staked the ten thousand, lost them and, a quarter of an hour later, had lost fifty thousand more.

Tranquilly, but this time definitely, he got from his seat, drank of the Vichy and went out in search of Maud.

In the hall women were grouped, talking modes and morals, the cosmopolitan gossip of London, Paris and Rome. Maud, a little removed from the others, was in a rocking chair, a slipper just visible beneath the hem of her skirt, her bare arms upraised behind her head.

Before her, Malakoff balanced himself on the arm of another chair. As Welden approached, he stood up.

“You won, I hope,” he threw out, and sauntered away.

“As it happened I lost,” Welden exclaimed, not to him, but to the girl. “I shall have to go to Paris to-morrow.”

“Dearest, I have money, eight or nine hundred francs I think,” Maud slowly, in her low, caressing voice, replied.

Welden laughed. “I could not take it and even if I could, it would not be anywhere near enough. As it is I shall have to cable.”

“Dearest, to-morrow is the Fourth, it is particularly for to-morrow we are here and in the evening Mrs. Cawtree wants us to come to her. Could you not put it off?”

“Not very comfortably. The money has to be paid at once, within the legal delays that is, and they amount to twenty-four hours. But I will be back in time for Mrs. Cawtree’s. At the latest I can take a train which gets here at nine and to-night—”

“Dearest, be careful,” the girl interrupted. Slowly she looked around. But they were quite alone. “Be sure first, won’t you,” she added, “that no one is about.”

Welden ran his long thin fingers through his bright thick hair. Not for this world certainly and probably not either for the next, would he by so much as a gesture have compromised the girl.

Much later, after he had waited longly and listened vainly and made two abortive attempts, when at last the villa seemed entirely hushed, he crossed the little space that lay between his room and hers.

The door was unlocked. As he opened it the disposition of the room was such that he could see of the girl only the rich orange of her hair, the outline of her pillowed head.

At the noise, ever so slight, which he made on entering, she turned. Immediately he heard, or thought he heard, a footfall in the corridor without. Quickly he closed the door and bolted it. It was, he noticed, massively made, of solid oak.

In the momentary uneasiness which, in circumstances such as these, even a problematic footfall may and does properly excite, he reflected that no one could get in and then immediately he told himself that no one would try.

VI

THE HEAD

The next evening Welden left Paris for Deauville. Ordinarily, as he had told Maud, he would have arrived at nine. But the derailment of another train interfered. It was eleven when he reached the villa.

A gale was blowing. From within, through the windows and the open door, lights fell on the driveway, chequering the pebbles with yellow spots. From beyond, in a lull of the wind, came the sound of violins and voices. The villa itself was silent.

As Welden entered, a footman came running. No one else was about. Turning, he passed on to the stairs and up them.

During the delay that had supervened he told himself that because of it, Maud, ceasing to expect him, would have gone on to Mrs. Cawtree’s, and it was with the idea of dressing and of joining her that he made for his room. But, while on the stair, it occurred to him to look in hers.

On reaching it, he turned the knob. The door was unlocked, it opened at his touch, and, precisely as on the night before, he saw the rich orange of her pillowed head, but saw too, beside her, Malakoff.

For a second only. Enveloped momentarily, yet, for the moment, enveloped absolutely by the catastrophic emotions of a whirlwind of nightmares, before he could move, the door, slammed in his face, was bolted.

In the instant concussion, the anchylosis of the anterior shock fell by, replaced immediately by blood madness.

Behind that door a man and a woman were occupied in continuing to be. Of that alone he was conscious. Over all the cells of his brain a somnolence had fallen, over all, save one, and that one cell, vehemently active, was inciting him to tear with bare hands life from the man, that done, to tear it again from the woman.

But for the door he could and would have.

Violently he flung himself against it. Violently yet vainly, and before perhaps it were possible for him to have realised the futility of the effort, he did realise that some one was near him, somebody who had a hand on his arm and who was offensively interfering.

Savagely he turned. Before him, in ball dress, a fichu of lace about her head, was Sally.

“Don’t,” she was saying. “Don’t.”

Welden, maniacal still, could have struck her. She saw it. But she did not flinch. Though naturally agitated, she did not seem frightened, surprised merely and also uncertain.

Welden raised his hand with a movement that threatened her, threatened the occupants of that room, menaced the house, Deauville itself, a gesture wide, insane, elemental and human.

“Don’t,” she repeated.

In the constant reiteration of that one word there must have been something of the effect of a spray. The irritability of the one active cell subsided, that of other cells was aroused.

Welden’s arm fell at his side. He stared at Sally. Then, for the first time, one of his two selves recognised her.

Sally, discovering not that, but the altered attitude, faced him.

“He would not be there unless she wished.”

The words fell over him plentifully like water thrown from a bucket. In the full douche and splatter of them, their meaning insinuated itself into the arteries of thought. The man’s two selves, the objective and the subconscious, rejoined each other; mania subsided, somnambulism ceased. Abruptly his entire brain awoke. The potential troglodyte that was in him, as potentially he is in us all, dematerialised. At once a man of the world in flannels and a straw hat found himself in the presence of a lady. That hat he removed.

In the eyes and about the mouth of the lady was an expression which some ladies have when they are occupied less with what they say than with other things which they do not propose to mention.

It was quite the same to Welden. That which occupied him was the ineluctable truth of her statement. Malakoff would not be there if Maud had not consented.

It was in a shrill whisper that Sally had produced it. Now, in the same tone, looking him still in the face, she said:

“Come below with me.”

As she spoke she stooped, gathered the train of her dress and together they descended the stair.

In the hall a footman stood. Sally left Welden and went to the table. Above it in a rack was a letter which she avidly took and put in her corsage. Then, turning, she spoke to the servant.

Welden, meanwhile, was still absorbed by her statement. But happiness was yet so recent that the ineluctable truth had not fully permeated all the cerebral convolutions, and the fact that it had not, manifested itself in the melodramatic phrase which all have uttered, all at least whom the unforeseen has felled.

“It is impossible; I am dreaming!”

At that, instantly, there surged before him the vision of the pillowed head, but now, through some miracle of hell, he could see the body, the fair ivory of it blotched with postules.

Again hæematomania would have claimed him. For a moment it was not only the vision that he saw but zigzags of black and scarlet. Determinedly he reacted. Almost immediately the natural poise of the man returned, with it as quickly came the realisation that since already he had done nothing, there was nothing that he or any other civilised being could do, except indeed to leave the house.

At the sure cognition of that he looked about for Sally. She was speaking to a maid.

“I am going,” he told her.

Sally, from over her shoulder, nodded at him.

“So am I,” she answered and went on with her orders.

“Perkins,” she was saying, “M. de Malakoff is in number ten. Tell Harris to have two of the men remain near by until they see him leave it.”

Welden wondered absently at her reply. It was odd, he thought, that she also should be going. Then, as absently, he remembered that she was Malakoff’s wife and he contemplated the fact gravely, without pity. It seemed to him just that besides himself someone else should suffer.

“And Perkins,” Sally called at the now retreating woman. “Bring my jewel case and some things, enough for to-night.”

“Come,” she added to Welden, moving as she spoke to the door. “I am going to Mrs. Cawtree’s. You had better go to the hotel, to the Roches Grises.”

The weather, like themselves, had become dramatic. The high wind that swept the frivolity of the land, came from the sea, perhaps from the Pole. It was strong and rude and, as they issued from the house, it pounced on them, howling and gay as a pack of foxhounds.

Sally’s clothes were lifted and tossed, the fichu was nearly torn from her head. She dominated her dress however, maintained the bit of lace, and, as they went down the path, she called at Welden: “What shall you do to-morrow?”

The “to-morrow” was all he caught. The rest of the question the gale scattered before it reached him. But it was enough. It prompted. As yet he had not thought. Then at once he knew, and he determined to wire to Le Hillel and dispatch him, with some local acquaintance, to Malakoff.

Sally, fancying that he had not heard at all, cried at him again, repeating the question.

Welden, holding his hat on with one hand and pointing back at the house with the other, shouted: “I shall have friends of mine call there.”

That was very satisfactory. Sally, her head bent, considered it gleefully. It was what she had hoped, an additional arrow for her quiver, in which already was divorce. Presently she spoke again, but what she said Welden did not hear, did not care.

The sea, pounding on the shore, was creating a thunder deafening and confused. It was as though a gigantic machine were hastening terribly to some enormous task.

Sally, in despair of making Welden hear otherwise, caught at his arm and motioned him to lower his head.

When he had she shrieked in his ear: “I want you to do me a great favour, a very great favour, will you?”

“Will I what?”

He had heard but half of what she said, not because of the roar but because of his thoughts which she, with her questions, entangled.

Now, however, again she was shrieking: “I want you to kill him.”

But though she shrieked, she smiled and, in spite of the tossing gale, in spite too of her ballooning dress, she looked sweet and simple.

Welden nodded. For the first time since they had known each other, what she wanted he wanted also.

Sally nodded too. Clutching at her dress she shouted: “Don’t let anyone know why; promise that you will not.”

They had reached the gate of a little park in which the Cawtree villa stood. In the shelter of the wall there was a respite from the gale. The sea too sounded less thunderous.

“Promise you won’t,” she repeated more normally.

Welden cried at her: “That reminds me, will you do something for me?”

“Anything,” Sally cried back. “I will do anything in the world for you.”

The fervour of the protestation Welden let pass unnoticed.

“Is Prince Saraguine in there?”

“He is leading the cotillon.”

Welden got at his card case and from it took a cheque already made out.

“Give him this with my thanks.” He turned. “Good night,” he added.

“Good night,” she replied and, as he moved into the gale, she made a trumpet of her hands and screamed through them: “Good luck.”

Welden, holding his hat to his head, passed on to the village. The wind that blew through his flannels, bent the trees, swept the narrow streets, dispersed their germs, refreshing whatever it touched, leaving the quivering air pure and delicious.

The hall of the Roches Grises, saturated with tobacco and electricity, full of people, of hurrying waiters, of parties returning from the Casino at Trouville and of tourists eyeing one another hostilely or with indifference, resounded with calls of the telephone, with slamming doors and the noise of lifts that ceaselessly rose and descended.

At the bureau, Welden secured a room, sent a chasseur for his things to the villa and, these recovered, at last was alone.

The room, though quiet, was as peopled as the hall. There were visions in it, very many, that gradually, without effort, fused into a picture of a girl’s pillowed head.

The girl herself was a stranger. It was not she he had loved, it was another, totally different, one whom his imagination had created, a girl who had never lived and who now was dead. The past alone was real. It surged phantasmagorically, like a great deceit, a lie enormous and cruel, inexplicable from sheer monstrosity. The crime he had witnessed permeated that past, smearing it with the odiousness of a coarse vulgarity.

In the chair in which he sat, he moved. From the wall at which he stared, he turned. Wherever he looked the picture appeared. To escape it he hid his face in his hands. He saw it there the clearer. At that, an agony made of a thousand wounds, each distinct, each more lancinant than the other, caught and enveloped him. The torture of it thrust into being memories long ablated. Fragments of recollections multiplied in his mind. There came to him the day he had first seen her, the hour he had first loved her, the moment he had first thought she might care for him, and, traversing these memories were tempests of others; shaded interiors, chairs under the trees, the ball-rooms of Newport, Long Island lawns; sudden tableaux of wherever a new delight had been experienced, of wherever a fresh sensation had been born, of wherever she had exhaled her invincible charm.

Within him the sea of these things mounted, adding their bitterness to the sear of his wounds. There was no myrrh for them. There is none for a death rattle, and as the obsessing vision returned, it brought with it a lassitude so large, so empty and desolate, that it resembled extinction itself.

VII

THE DOOR

On the morrow the gale had gone, flown afar, to die perhaps on some shore of the Mediterranean. In Welden too a tempest had subsided. In the eager sunshine that filled the room he stood, contemplating a note, a hurried scrawl from Sally informing him she had learned from Perkins that Malakoff was leaving for Paris.

The letter fell from him. A telegram different from the one he had meditated must, he saw, be sent, and he wrote one asking Le Hillel to meet him at the Escrime. But there were other things to be done and done quickly. He gave orders; tubbed, dressed, drank some coffee, for even in the great crises of life one must do these things, and in the same spirit perhaps that, at the reveille for battle, men shave and see to it that their gloves are spotless, Welden adjusted his neckcloth and considered the sheen of his shoes.

But Malakoff’s move perplexed. He could not understand why the man should be leaving. Toward the man himself he was now indifferent. It was not the man he hated, it was the male. The man had outraged every canon of decency. He had broken hospitality’s first and highest law. Yet, he could have done none of these things if Maud had not consented and, the consent granted, any other male would have done the same. Toward the consenter he felt no hatred either, a distaste merely, very immedicable, one that poisoned her and him and life.

A rap had come. It was time to be going and shortly, the bill paid, the service fee’d, he was off to the station.

There, already, an employee was calling loudly for the voyageurs, and Welden, after purchasing his fare and getting his luggage ticketed, went from the bare white room to the platform and mounted into the grey upholstery of an empty compartment of the train.

He was but seated when he saw Malakoff swinging in. Rising abruptly, brusquely he forced himself by and out.

Malakoff turned angrily.

“Monsieur,” he called, “you have a manner of disregarding the bagatelles of the door which I do not applaud. If you care to apologise—”

“I never apologise,” Welden threw at him.

Malakoff, pulling a glove from one hand, raised it with the other.

Instantly that hand was pinioned. In another instant it was flung aside and Welden, whose jaw had become ominously square, confronted him.

“That is sufficient. Where can my friends find yours?”

“At my house if it suits them.”

“En voiture, messieurs, en voiture!” a guard yelped, for now there were more laggards; Aquaviva, Saraguine and a man whom Welden did not know.

These, ignorant as yet of the little scene, had just issued from the station.

“Monsieur Welden,” said the Russian, “my thanks for the envoi of last night.”

“Monsieur Welden,” said the Italian, “do not forget Chantilly to-morrow.”

To an accompaniment of the employees’ yelps both were speaking at once.

“You go with us, do you not?” asked the prince, climbing as he spoke into the section into which already Malakoff had mounted and where Aquaviva followed.

“This way, this way,” a guard barked.

Welden had but time to clamber into an adjoining compartment. At once the bolt was shot, a whistle tooted, the train was off.

In a corner sat a woman, very well dressed, tall, fair, presumably English, who looked invitingly at him. Except to remove his hat, Welden ignored her completely.

The clarity of the morning sky, the poplars that bowed and fainted, the lovely Norman land, these things he ignored as well. Over the white leagues his thoughts had run on ahead. He was standing somewhere, in tennis shoes, his neck bare, his sleeves rolled up, a yard of steel in his hand, and Malakoff was before him. Mechanically his wrist moved. The point of the steel advanced and retreated in a line absolutely straight, effecting in the parries only the minimum circle. There were men that stood about and watched and suddenly they saw Malakoff fall, spitted, that yard of steel gone through him.

What was the fair English woman, the clarity of the sky, the bowing poplars, the lovely Norman land beside these pleasantly murderous sensations? They entertained him fully until the rush of the train decreased into a soapy slide and the porters of Saint-Lazare were calling at him.

Leaving his things in the rue de la Paix, Welden drove on to the Escrime, the fencers’ club of which he was a member.

There, in the main hall, on a black divan, a cigar between his teeth, Le Hillel was seated.

Adjacently other members were seated and two men, their hands behind their backs, paced slowly up and down. From a lateral entrance, a colossal lackey in the club livery, with knee breeches and silk stockings, called loudly the sempiternal announcement of French clubs, the amount of money in the baccarat bank.

Le Hillel, withdrawing his cigar, waved it.

“I got your wire. Nothing serious, eh?”

“Do you know Malakoff?” Welden asked, seating himself on the divan.

“Enough to say Good-day. Anything wrong between you?”

Welden nodded. “We had some words this morning.”

Le Hillel stretched himself luxuriously. “About a woman?”

“No. On the contrary.”

Le Hillel assumed an attitude of still greater luxuriousness. “You mean that the lady is not to be mentioned. That’s of course. Whom have you got?”

“You for one, I suppose?”

“My dear fellow, with the greatest pleasure.”

“And I will ask Cantire.”

“Cantire, no. He is under-secretary. A little matter of this kind always makes talk and that is displeasing in an embassy. Do you know Louradour?”

Welden shook his head.

Le Hillel stood up, balanced himself on his heels, then, with that tread which athletes share with panthers, he joined the two men who were pacing up and down and spoke to one of them.

With a motion of apology to the other, the former turned with Le Hillel to where Welden was seated.

As they approached, Welden arose.

“Baron Louradour,” said Le Hillel, “this is my friend and brother-in-arms M. Welden of New York. M. Welden has had an argument over—By the way,” he interrupted himself to ask. “What did you say it was about?”

Welden, raising his hat in response to the baron’s salutation, answered. “A door.”

“A door!” Le Hillel repeated. “That is a very dangerous topic.”

“Monsieur,” said the baron, employing as he spoke an inflection which musically rose and fell, “we have here in France an adage with which doubtless you are familiar. It is that a door should be open or closed. Perhaps this one was neither—”

With that, in a gesture of complete appreciation, the baron extended both hands. Though presumably fifty, he had the pink skin of a child, a smile of infinite indulgence, and a large, loose tie.

“But permit me,” he resumed. “With whom did this argument occur?”

“With Malakoff.”

“And permit me, is he to send his seconds?”

“No, I am to send mine.”

“That is to say,” interrupted Le Hillel, “You and me, Baron, if you will do my friend that honour.”

“But how, then! It is your friend who honours me. Permit me once more. Your adversary has the choice of arms; and you, monsieur, have you any preference?”

“Thanks,” Welden answered, “anything but swords.”

Louradour smiled, displaying as he did so teeth small, even, white as white paper. It was obvious to him that that door had opened or closed on something extremely definite.

“I see,” he replied. “No child’s play.” Turning to Le Hillel he added: “M. de Malakoff resides I suppose in his avenue? Good. It would be discourteous to keep his friends waiting.” Turning back to Welden he continued: “You will remain here? Good. In an hour at the latest. Meanwhile allow me to express all my pleasure at meeting an American who views matters as we do.”

Laughing and nodding, the two men passed on.

Presently Welden got the club chasseur and sent him with a five franc piece to buy a little cardboard box which cost two sous.

“Keep the change,” he said when the servant reappeared.

Welden was lunching then. The meal concluded, he took out his watch from which hung the sapphire with its old French device: Aultre n’auray—None but you.

The moderate irony of it mocked him. He detached it, put it in the box and going to the reading-room, wrapped, sealed and directed it to Miss Barhyte, in the care of her bankers, rue Scribe. Then, again requisitioning the chasseur, he sent him with another white piece to deliver it.

“Finis!” he muttered with set teeth and for a while contemplated the epitaph.

“Pardon. There are gentlemen who demand monsieur.”

Welden looked up. He had been far away, on the longest journey that a mortal can take, into the depths of the irreparable. It was the colossal lackey that had addressed him. Rising, he followed the man into the hall where Le Hillel and Louradour waited.

“To-morrow at eight,” the former announced. “Baron Louradour has obligingly arranged to have the meeting take place at the residence of M. de Ponthieu, his father-in-law.”

“You are really too good,” said Welden,

The baron bowed. “It is nothing, nothing at all. M. de Ponthieu is with my family at the waters. And let us see. Yes. It is foils.”

He smiled, patted his tie and added: “You will excuse me, my dear sir, will you not? Till to-morrow.”

“Deuced nice of him too,” said Le Hillel when he had gone. “We might have had to go to Neuilly. His father-in-law’s place is five minutes from your hotel. I will stop by for you in the morning. And now, what is the programme?”

Welden lit a cigarette. “Later, if you like, I will have a bout with you. Then we might dine somewhere and I will go to bed early.”

Approvingly Le Hillel nodded. Welden was a man after his own heart, a man sure of himself, one who had no intention of writing letters, of making a will or even a night of it, a virtuoso who knew that the wrist of a swordsman is as sensitive as that of a violinist.

VIII

THE DUEL

The morning broke darkly. When Welden reached the street the sky was heaped with clouds sulphurous and evil. To the thin thunder of metal shutters a lout, across the way, was opening a shop. Beyond, two Percherons, harnessed to a high white cart, snorted their ennui. At the curb, in a motor, was Le Hillel. With him was a little man in a tall hat, who held a bag on his knees.

“Hello!” Le Hillel threw out. “Hop in. Be careful.” As he spoke he indicated a long green bundle that lay at his feet. “Avenue Gabriel,” he called at the chauffeur.

“Do you remember Sarcey?”—he presently resumed as the motor flew up the street. “On a morning a bit worse than this he had an affair which he insisted on conducting under an umbrella. ‘I may be winged,’ the old idiot declared, ‘but I refuse to catch cold.’ How did you sleep? This is Dr. Meyer.”

The machine now had turned into the rue de Rivoli. Scudding on, it crossed the fountained Place and shortly stopped in the briefest and most seigneurial of Parisian avenues.

Before them, a great double doorway opened slowly, with respect. Above it was a stone arch in which a blazon had been cut. On either side was a vast, white wall. Within was a vista of trees, large urns, marble benches. Beyond was a tennis court, farther away a house. In the damp, fresh air, a scent of roses and acacias clung. Over all was a brooding quiet, the splendid disdain of nature for the imbecile activity of man.

Simultaneously with the motor, a crimson touring car flew up. From it descended Malakoff, Aquaviva, Saraguine and a man also in a high hat, also with a bag who, as the others saluted, exchanged with Dr. Meyer a professional smile.

Without speaking all passed in and slowly, respectfully, the great doors closed. On each side a servant in brown was stationed. A step beyond stood Louradour.

He raised his hat. “Gentlemen, I salute you.” As the others raised their hats, he added: “It may rain. If preferred, we can get under cover.”

Saraguine, withdrawing a glove, stretched his hand horizontally and looked at the sky.

“A little mist,” he announced. “It is nothing.”

“Good,” Louradour rejoined. “There is then nothing to detain us and no better place than the court over there. You have the foils, Le Hillel?”

For answer the green bundle was displayed.

At once, with the French observance of what is correct or, more exactly, of what is so considered, gravely, dumbly, in two detachments, the eight men proceeded to the tennis court where four of them, gathering together, consulted.

Welden took off his coat and waistcoat and tossed them on a bench. He undid his collar, opened his shirt, rolled up a sleeve and was rolling the other when he paused, arrested by a remark overheard.

“I say, Le Hillel,” he called. “What is all that about Aquaviva’s holding a stick within reach of our foils? To prevent an accident, is it? Well then, be good enough to say that I will submit to nothing of the kind. I am not here to learn how to fence. It was for a thing of this sort that I did learn.”

Welden spoke in English which Aquaviva did not understand and which Saraguine who was talking to Louradour did not hear.

Malakoff heard.

The remark, perfectly audible to him, equally intelligible, carried a significance of its own. He knew that Welden could ride, he took it for granted that he could shoot, that he could handle a sword was, he had thought, within the range of possibilities, but that he could fence had never occurred to him. It was for that reason he had chosen foils. A poke in the ribs and easily, in no time, he had fancied he would be done with him. These ideas aiding and fortified moreover by two good seconds, he had come to this meeting, as he had gone to others, without the shadow of a preoccupation, with the view merely to the transaction of an entirely formal and tiresome affair.

Now, however, at the remark and at the sight of the man bare-necked, bare-armed, supple and vigorous, looking very much alive and equally deadly, the ideas he had had evaporated, his rank fell from him like a cloak, his titles like bits of armour, and in that nakedness, he shivered. Before him surged the abrupt apparition of death.

For one moment, that apparition, the instruments, bands, compresses, antiseptics—enough for an ambulance—which Dr. Meyer and his colleague were taking from their bags, grotesquely but poignantly maintained.

Then at once, the cultivated sentiment of form came, asserted itself, rescued him. With that air which he could assume, that appearance of being surrounded by lackeys ready, at a gesture, to shut the door in anyone’s face, he took off his coat, undid his collar, rolled up his sleeves. That done, he looked again at Welden who was looking at him.

“I will see what he knows,” Welden was thinking. “Then, in two minutes, Bonjour!”

Concerning himself he had that entire absence of apprehension which comes to some men from confidence, to others from indifference. Both left him as much at ease as though he were about to play polo.

Aquaviva, meanwhile, who had unwillingly yielded to the objection which Le Hillel transmitted, but who had tossed with him for the choice of arms and place, approached now with the foils which he offered, first to Malakoff, whom he stationed fronting the arch of the entrance, and then to Welden who, in facing Malakoff, faced also the house. Yet, as there was no sun, the advantage to either was negligible.

“Are you ready?” Saraguine asked.

Welden felt the point of his steel. It was sharp as a needle. He advanced toward Malakoff and both fell into position.

“On guard!” the prince called. “Go!”

The foils, united for an instant at the ends by Le Hillel, now were seeking each other, crossing, clashing, functioning with light movements of the wrist.

Welden, taller than Malakoff, perfectly trained, perfectly tranquil, maintained the athlete’s easy poise and, while his wrist moved, looked pitilessly at his adversary. As yet however he attempted nothing decisive. His parries, effected always in the smallest possible circle, were as clean, rapid and precise as though, with a buttoned foil before him, he were on the boards, in an ordinary bout. But in parrying merely, he forced Malakoff to show his hand, to tell what he knew, to expose the varieties of his play.

These were of the school, classic but not brilliant, and Malakoff, at the sight of those circles, at the sight of that steel which, when not describing them, advanced and returned in a line almost geometrically straight, saw that he had to deal not only with a swordsman but with a swordsman of the very first class. On the part of an American he had counted on nothing of the kind. At the evidence of it his sense of nudity increased. He felt not only wholly naked but horribly insecure. The episode which he had regarded as an entirely formal and tiresome affair had rapidly assumed the proportions of an assassination.

“Halt!” cried Saraguine.

Malakoff was livid. Visibly he perspired, audibly he panted and on his forearm was a thin red line.

“You are touched,” the prince added.

The wound was examined. It was but a scratch and so slight that it did not require even to be staunched.

Welden, in an undertone, said with a smile to Le Hillel: “I know him now. In a moment I will pin a carnation in his shirt.”

Thoughtlessly while speaking, he had rested the point of the foil on the ground. Dr. Meyer approached and tenderly with a little sponge disinfected it.

“On guard!” Saraguine called and, as the two men fell into position again, again he called: “Go.”

The foils met as before. Malakoff, to hide the nakedness of his debility, masked himself behind the hilt, and parried only until after a counter-disengage from quatre to tierce, not finding Welden’s blade, he lunged. But the foil, manœuvred by another and surer hand than his, deflected. An unawaited riposte touched him on the breast and, as he backed from the prick, a return sudden and violent ran him through the throat.

Before him, the double doors, the blazoned arch, the high white wall, soared in the air. They came to him, fell on him, bore him down. From under him the earth slid gently. The savour of something acrid filled his mouth. Above him were peering faces and fluttering hands. These blankly fainted. In that early morning it was night.

Welden looked at the prostrate form and nodded at it. From the street beyond there floated a cry, trailing and musical, the call of an itinerant offering to repair broken porcelain. Otherwise in the silence of the fragrant garden there was all of nature’s unconcern for the idiot agitations of man.

Save Welden, every one, Dr. Meyer included, had got about Malakoff. Welden, who could see of him now but the veneered sole of a shoe, stuck his foil under his arm and went, buttoning his shirt on the way, to the bench where he had tossed his coat. The tableau behind him differed not at all from one that he had seen on the train. It was an old acquaintance and he nodded once more.

At the bench he put the foil down and, getting a cigarette from his coat, lighted it.

Springingly Le Hillel approached. He had with him the long green bag in which now was the other foil.

“You are wounded!” he exclaimed.

Welden, expelling a puff of smoke into the damp, sweet air, stared at him.

“I never was better in my life.”

“But look at yourself.”

Welden did look. Beneath his left arm his shirt was red. He laughed.

“That comes from the foil, from my foil. Here, take it and put it with the other one.”

In a moment he had his coat on, his collar and neckcloth readjusted.

“Where is my stick?” he asked.

“Your stick? In the motor probably. Shall we go?”

But now Louradour, detaching himself from the others, advanced. He looked at Welden.

“Monsieur, I may compliment you and reassure you also. M. de Mal—”

“Is he alive?” Welden, strangling an oath, threw out.

Louradour, pressing together a thumb and forefinger, exhibited them.

“By that much! The carotid artery just escaped. Allons! So much the better. In no time, in three weeks, he will be on his feet.”

Silently Welden cursed. But Louradour’s thumb and forefinger had separated, a hand was extended which Welden shook, and then, with Le Hillel, he passed on through the slowly opening doors to the purring car without.

“There’s your stick,” said Le Hillel as they reached it.

Welden looked at the sky. “It’s raining,” he announced.

“What do you care?” said Le Hillel as both got into the machine and he called: “Rue de la Paix.”

“Personally, not a rap,” Welden answered. “But I race to-day at Chantilly. If it keeps on it may interfere with the others.”

Le Hillel considered him admiringly. “Gourmand!” he cried. “This morning you nearly killed a man, this afternoon you will nearly kill a horse. That’s fine, very fine.”

Welden shrugged his shoulders. To change the subject he asked: “What became of the little chap?”

“Meyer! Good Lord! I forgot the poor devil. After I drop you, I’ll go back for him. By the way, his fee is fifty francs. Malakoff’s man will come higher. Did you notice that he was decorated? That means a hundred.”

“Yes, confound it; and he’ll earn it. I thought I had spared him that. If I had known in time I believe I would have finished his client as he lay there.”

Le Hillel laughed. “No, you wouldn’t, and, anyway, we would not have let you. Besides, why be so bloodthirsty? You fought like a god, now you will ride like a demon. I would give a red pippin to see you. By George! I would give two of them, only—”

“Only what?”

With a little modest air Le Hillel pulled at his cuff.

“A lady is to lunch with me.”

“Here’s the fifty,” said Welden, who meanwhile had got the money out.

Le Hillel pocketed it. “Shall I see you to-morrow?”

There are morrows that never dawn. What is more notable, there are men who know they will not. But Welden nodded and shortly, when the car stopped again at his hotel, he thanked Le Hillel, who whirled away.

IX

THE RACE

After one blue brief moment, the forenoon died, suffocated with clouds. The agony of the day melted into rain. The drops, thin and hurried, fell in sheets, draping the trees with humid fringes, pouring their melancholy on Chantilly’s sandy soil and, as Welden, in breeches and boots, drove up from the station, they added a dreariness of their own to the dreariness that was his.

To greet him came the pungent odour of stables, the clean smell of wet turf. He had too a glimpse of dripping ostlers, the vista of a vacant lawn, of a miniature tribune and of a course, punctuated by fences that circled the grounds. But, in lieu of the careless women, the careful men, the line of drags, carriages and cars that ordinarily would have been there, there was but gloom. Instead of clattering hoofs, ripples of laughter and mounting cries, there was silence and the falling rain.

At the perron of a gaunt, grey house, ugly and comfortable, the cab stopped. As Welden got out, there flew up a covered motor from which Cantire and another man alighted.

Cantire, like Welden, was in riding dress.

“Hello!” he cried. “Rather rotten, isn’t it?” Indicating his companion he added: “You know Lord Ferrers?”

“Met you at Melton,” said the latter, advancing toward Welden, his hand outstretched.

He was tall, slim, very fair. He wore a monocle and spoke with a slight stutter.

Welden, recalling some incident, mentioned it and both laughed. Meanwhile the door opened. All three passed into a hall where immediately de Dol appeared.

“But!” the Frenchman, in French, exclaimed. “What good wind brings you! You received my dispatch?” he continued, looking as he spoke from Welden’s boots to Cantire’s breeches. “The race is postponed. Kara Saraguine and Aquaviva telegraphed yesterday asking me to put it off. Thinking you would agree I wired you both at Deauville.”

“To the Villa Portugaise?” said Cantire. “It’s closed. The duchess chucked the whole thing. Why, I haven’t an idea. Have you?” he asked, turning to Welden.

“Not the faintest.”

“Of course not. How should you? I remember now, you went up to Paris the day before. There must have been the deuce of a row. Malakoff took the first train yesterday. Aquaviva and Saraguine went with him, I believe, but the rest of us straggled on at noon.”

“You were saying?” intervened de Dol, whom the conversation, carried on in English, had left in the dark. “But, I pray you, come this way.”

Moving aside he motioned them into a room hung with etchings and photographs of sporting scenes and horses. There was a table there, a divan, several straight-backed chairs and the frame of a horse, wooden and articulated.

“You were saying?” he repeated.

Cantire, in French, summarised the matter for him.

De Dol raised his hands. “But! It is unbelievable! There, one would say, was a household veritably united. I did not grasp why these gentlemen wired, yet it could not have been because of what you tell me, nor could they have foreseen the rain. Have you seen them since?”

Cantire shook his head. He had straddled the wooden horse. Lord Ferrers was on the divan, Welden on a chair.

De Dol turned. “Have you, Monsieur Welden?”

Welden nodded.

“And they said nothing about the race?”

“Nothing.”

“It is unbelievable!”

“They could not very well,” Welden resumed. “I was having a word with Malakoff and they were acting for him.”

“The deuce!” cried Cantire, sliding from the horse. “A duel! And you not even pinked!”

He laughed. The idea of it pleased him. His grandfather was a duke, a real one, a stately old man with a head empty but noble. Whether on that account or for other reasons is immaterial, but he had always thought Malakoff a mucker. It was not on his account he had gone to Deauville. It was for Sally.

“But!” exclaimed de Dol, his mouth agape. A little panorama was unfolding before him—Welden and Sally surprised in amorous conversation by Sally’s husband. “And Malakoff?”

“He will be all right shortly.”

As Welden spoke, de Dol bowed slowly to an advancing understanding of it all. Malakoff’s seconds, aware of the conversation and foreseeing that for at least one of the principals the duel would be damaging had, for that reason, asked that the race be postponed.

“All the same,” he affably rejoined, “It was most amiable of you to come. When it rains one’s friends are doubly welcome.”

Welden turned to Cantire. “Are you afraid of a wetting?”

“Good Lord, no, why?”

“Our horses are here, if we don’t race now we won’t race at all. I will back myself against you. I will back myself against Ferrers too, if he will. M. de Dol can give him a mount.”

“Done,” said Cantire. “Let’s make it a fiver.”

Lord Ferrers dropped his monocle. “Not for me, thanks, but I’ll hold the stakes.”

“You were saying?” asked de Dol, who had caught his name but who otherwise was again in the dark and that too despite the fact that a flash of intense vividness lit the room, one which a great crash followed instantly.

“It will be clearing shortly,” said Ferrers, rising from the divan and peering through a window. “I say,” he called, “I believe it is.”

De Dol meanwhile, to whom Welden had translated the gist of it and who thought him and Cantire crazy, was giving the necessary orders.

Welden got from his chair and joined the others at the window. The rain had ceased. In the west was the glow of renaissant day. From a tree near by water was falling in little drops, soft and multiple. Overhead in the still neutral sky, long ribbons of ravens formed themselves into black wreaths and sombre garlands. Welden, to whom the visible existed, considered the signs which it is perhaps their mysterious duty to convey.

But now a footman appeared with raincoats and a lad from the stables, touching his forehead, just showed his nose.

“The horses are here,” said de Dol. “Will you have a coat, monsieur?” he asked of Ferrers.

The latter displayed an umbrella that was thin as a walking-stick.

“Thanks, no. This will do me.”

De Dol however had himself helped into a great-coat, took a fat umbrella besides, swung a field glass about him and, accompanied by the others, went out to the perron before which stablemen swarmed and the hunters stood.

The course began the throw of a stone beyond. While Welden and Cantire examined the girths, verified the stirrups, looked to the bits and bridles, Ferrers and de Dol passed on. Before they reached the stand, Cantire and Welden were in the saddle.

“I say, Ferrers,” Cantire called. “You give the signal, will you?”

“Very good,” the Englishman answered. “Now, then, steady.”

He pulled a rope. Before the flag could fall, Welden’s horse, over zealously, had bolted.

Welden got him in hand, turned him, brought him back, flattering him with pats on the shoulder.

“Vive l’Angleterre!” shouted de Dol. “Vive l’Amerique!”

“And vive la France!” Welden and Cantire, almost in unison, responded.

De Dol laughed with satisfaction. He still thought them mad and said as much to Ferrers.

The latter inserted his monocle. “The going does not seem so bad and the obstacles are not tremendous.”

He spoke in French, very correctly, but with so marked a British accent, that he might as well have replied in English. De Dol thought he was agreeing with him and laughed again.

“Steady!” Ferrers called and for the sec ond time pulled the flag-rope.

This time they were off, taking the sticks as though there were nothing there, clearing them, in spite of the rain, easily, without effort.

De Dol followed them through his glass, Ferrers through his monocle.

Beyond, the country stretched, inert and dolent. In the west the glow had heightened. Overhead, the darker sky was veined with flashes thin and sudden. The ravens, assembled now in screaming flight, shot southward.

Quickly but quietly Ferrers swore. Cantire was down.

“I awaited it!” cried de Dol. But at once he could see that the boy was up and in a moment that he was on and off again.

Welden now was leading. Blazes tore on. The splendid brute, with his impudent eye and shoulders like the top of a haystack, had covered the course; he was nearing the stand when, just as he was about to take the final fence, there came a flash vivider than any, a bolt so neighbourly and dazzling that it looked raspberry, and whether it unnerved the horse or the man or both, in any event Welden bent heavily forward and together, turning a somersault, they tumbled.

For a second, without sense of injury or sensation of pain, Welden lingered. Then his two selves, the conscious and the subconscious, scattered, evaporated, ceased to know. Again on that day it was night.

“God of gods!” cried de Dol. “I said they were mad!”

Ferrers, extracting his monocle, vaulted to the ground, where, as from the ground itself, stablemen came swarming, while, over all, indifferently, from disrupted clouds, the sun looked out.

X

THE DEVIL

A surgeon obtained, it was found that Welden had a fracture of the ankle, a fracture of the collarbone and a fracture of the skull.

The surgeon, Dr. Binet-Valmer, thought the first fracture trite; the second, stupid. Had there been but these he would have abandoned Welden to other hands. But the third fracture had the high merit of interesting this man whose country-seat was near by and who was one of the lights of French science.

“He won’t die to-day,” he absently announced.

As for the rest, a phrase which, for the benefit of the ignoramuses about him, he employed to designate the cerebral cortex—that marvellous pulp behind the forehead through which the objective changes of the external world are, by some undiscovered witchery, converted into the subjective changes of consciousness—concerning that magical mystery and the fate of it, he had an opinion which he kept to himself.

The examination concluded, he addressed the Comte de Dol precisely as though the poor man were a lackey. He did not regard him as such, he considered him an insect. The Earl of Ferrers and the Honourable Mull Cantire were to him two insects more. Welden was not an insect or even an entity, he was a Case.

“An ambulance,” he ordered.

But de Dol shook his head. The fractures had occurred on his grounds, to a guest of his bidding, and, with that decent sentiment of what decency is which the Arabs discovered, he had Welden tended in his house.

Through the enigmatic laws of life any kindness is repaid in pain. De Dol never actively regretted the charity, though certainly had he wished he might have, for when the report of it all had gone abroad, a woman, very modishly attired, emerged from a cab at the perron and demanded to be taken instantly to where Welden was.

Obviously the lady appertained to that class which the French describe as the top of the basket. But de Dol’s footman knew his business.

“Perfectly, madame,” he replied. “Will madame give herself the trouble to pass this way?”

Whereupon he showed her into the room hung with pictures of sporting scenes and horses.

From the threshold he added: “Will madame say whom I am to announce?”

“The Duchess of Malakoff.”

The man bowed and vanished. Presently he returned, ushering de Dol.

“But! But!” exclaimed the latter, shuffling in, affecting to seem pleased yet succeeding so meagrely that, to cover his embarrassment, he raised and bent over the gloved hand which Sally put out, wondering all the time what the devil he could do with her.

Sally told him. In her sweetest voice she said: “Take me to him, please.”

De Dol, sparring for wind, protested, “Duchess, he is unconscious.”

Sally motioned at the door. “I know. I have brought a trained nurse. We will take care of him together.”

De Dol, sparring still, again protested. “Duchess, I pray you, consider your position.”

Sally lifted her little chin. “He considered that. He fought for me. What I consider is his condition.”

But now de Dol had got his wind. For a moment, thoughtfully, with kind, honest eyes he looked in hers. Then he went at her.

“Duchess, believe me, never intentionally have I refused a lady anything. It is regrettable to be obliged to refuse you. But your husband is my friend. He has been gravely injured by this gentleman. If you will not consider your position, I pray you consider mine. Can you not see that it would be intolerable were I to do as you ask?”

Sally, floored but not defeated, leaned from the chair in which she sat, flung her arms on the table beside her, sank her head there, and audibly began to cry.

Men who face death unflinchingly, quail at a woman’s tears. What is worse women know it. Sally used hers much as though they constituted a stick and de Dol, bruised and belaboured, cursed himself that he had not, at the start, invented some ukase of the surgeon to which she must unquestionably bow. Yet, after all, he reflected, the surgeon certainly would pronunciamento, and that edict he could hold in reserve should other tactics which then occurred to him, fail.

Timorously he approached and gingerly, with one finger, touched her.

At the attention, Sally’s slight frame shook.

“Duchess, calm yourself. Calm yourself, I pray you. If you will but calm yourself, there is a little idea that has come to me which may result in what you wish. Will you let me tell you? Will you?”

But Sally felt now too securely intrenched to yield to what, perhaps, were mere treacherous cajolements. She continued to weep or appeared to, yet, apparently also in a fashion more broken, leaving invitingly between the sobs increasing intervals during which he could speak and which, if what he said were not agreeable, she, with renewed activity, could curtail.

Warily but boldly he utilised one such pause.

“Duchess, let us see. Be reasonable enough to listen. From the moment when this gentleman was carried from that divan to where he now is, I have not seen him, no one has, save the surgeon, the aids and imfirmieres, nor, until he is conscious do I believe that the surgeon will permit anyone to see him, no one, not even the man’s own mother were she here. If, therefore, I can not do as you would wish me, it is not merely for your sake and my sake, it is for his. But when he is better, when such danger as there is has been passed, enfin! in a little while, I, I who speak to you, will not be here. Then who comes and who goes, I do not know. I do not inquire. It is my intendant who has charge of such things. Do you appreciate, Duchess? My intendant has not the honour of your acquaintance; he is not a friend of the duke. Let us suppose then that of a morning a lady arrives and says: ‘I have come to sit with this gentleman. I am his sister, his promised, his chère amie, his whatever you like.’ My intendant says: ‘But what then? But certainly! And patatis, patatas.’ And behold the lady who then creates the rain and the fine weather. Does that say nothing to you, Duchess? Does it not seem well machined? Later, I return. My intendant says: ‘The sister, the promised, the chère amie, the whatever you like of the sick gentleman has been here.’ And I say: ‘That does not regard me. I wash my hands.’ ”

Long since the intervals between the sobs had so elongated that the sobs themselves had ceased. Sally’s bowed head was lifted. For a lady who had wept so profusely her eyes were phenomenally bright.

“Yes,” de Dol resumed. “That is what I say to him. I say: ‘I wash my hands.’ ”

“You promise I may come?”

“But no, Duchess. But no. I do not promise. It is not for me to promise anything. I have nothing to promise about. I play that I am dead. It is when I am gone for the lady of whom I speak to do as she may wish. Of my departure she can inform herself. It is easy as Good-day.”

Sally stood up. She held out her hand and looking at him through her oblique, half-closed and entirely tearless eyes said sweetly: “You’re a dear.”

De Dol took the hand. Bending over it he sighed, deeply, with relief.

“A cup of tea, Duchess? A glass of wine?”

Sally, shaking her head at the offer, sighed too.

“Forgive me, if I have seemed to insist.”

“Duchess, I pray of you, it is for me to ask your pardon.”

Sally moved on. A moment or two later when de Dol after accompanying her to the cab, saw to it that she really got in, really drove off, he sighed afresh and muttered:

“Let the devil catch me again—if he can!”

XI

AT THE SIGN OF THE SWAN

To those about Welden it was as though he were dead, drowned rather, sunk into depths where nothing can follow, into those deepest depths where life is without form, without colour, without sensation of any kind. But presently either because of their efforts, or because of influences not higher; but the reverse, because he had not suffered enough, death, loosening its hold, retreated; life beckoned, calling him from where he swooned, and imperceptibly, little by little, after infinite hesitations, relapses, retrievals, drifting upward from those depths, he awoke.

Where he was he did not know. What had happened, he could not tell. He did not try. He did not care. He had but one wish, to sink back again and sleep. But again life caught and called him, wrapped him, rocked him, accustoming him gradually to its subtleties, reconciling him to it and to himself.

It was at this juncture that Sally declared herself a miserable woman. In the opinion of the world she deserved to be. The opinion of the world is very valuable. The fried mixture of falsities on which it daily breakfasts would induce apoplexy in any entity less robust. In its distinguished opinion Sally’s husband had fought because of her with a man who was engaged to one of her intimate friends and whom she had inveigled from her.

Even in the way we live now such behaviour is not regarded as nice. Yet any woman might have done as much, and more and worse, and been smiled at, provided only she and her husband continued, outwardly at least, on good terms. But on the open scandal of scandalous ruptures the world, which if credulous is also discreet, turns always its ponderous back.

It turned it on Sally. Though young, rich, good-looking and a duchess, the attitude of the world justified her declaration and the knowledge that it did gave Sally’s mother an attack of indignation morbus of which the nausea lasted through twelve pages of pen and ink.

For final hiccough there was this: “You have disgraced me. No decent person will ever receive you unless you return to your husband at once.”

Mrs. Kandy was then at Aix. The paroxysm dispatched, she felt better. Sally was then at Chantilly. The eructation received, she felt no worse. Lodged at the time at the Sign of the Swan, she had with her Harris and Perkins. She had also her thoughts. These, if not many, were pleasant.

Among them was the fact that Mr. Ridgeway, who had conducted the delicate arrangements of her marriage, was occupied with the still more delicate details of her divorce. Before going to Deauville she had consulted him. On her return she had consulted him again. She had done better. She had retained him. He had assured her that she could be free.

He was as good as his word. Evidence of the conversation that had occurred on the night of July the Fourth sufficed. But with that regard for the honour of families and the repute of women which Anglo-Saxon tribunals lack, during the punctilious and brief debates, the court, in withholding any mention of the co-respondent’s name, obscured the lady from the public.

That is but gentlemanly. None the less the obscurity was one in which the world saw many things, the obviousness of the fact, for instance, that Sally had but stolen a march on Malakoff who, gallantly, had desisted from counter charges.

Sally did not attempt to undeceive the world which would not have believed her had she tried. She did not try, however. It would not have suited her book to do so. She had another and a more agreeable task.

De Dol meanwhile had gone, summer was going and Welden, issuing from the great iced bath of death, remounted to life’s surface. Among other lesions, there had been an injury to the occipital cortex which resulted in impairment of vision. For a time he could not distinguish objects. When he succeeded, the first thing he saw was Sally.

He resented her presence. He regarded it as an intrusion. Moreover, the reason of it was beyond him. Then from being a phenomenon objectionable and occult, it became a phase of his condition, one that primarily he accepted from sheer inability to avoid and finally from the familiarising effects of habit. It is related that men who entered the Bastille as though it were their grave, had to be afterward ejected by force. They had got used to it and what human beings get used to they get to like. That was the case with Welden. In accounting for Sally’s visits he forgot her former ambuscades and attributed present attentions to the effort he had made to rid the world of Malakoff. Anyway, what did it matter? Sally made his prison endurable. She was blithe as a humming bird. On the end of her fingers was every kind of pretty gesture. They were alert too, very divinatory. They knew what he wanted as soon as he did. They omitted to be in the way. They grew discreet. Recognising their usefulness, they ceased to flutter. They took themselves away, and away remained, until their return was solicited.

When that occurred Sally, even to the world, could no longer affect to be a miserable woman. She radiated smiles, she exhaled good humour. Dr. Binet-Valmer, who thoroughly approved of the presence of young gentlewomen in the bedrooms of convalescents, encouraged her visits. He knew she was only an insect but he realised that she was a pretty one. Without any faith in drugs whatever, with hardly any faith in anything, he yet had confidence in the tonic of prettiness, smiles and good humour. The infirmieres had too. The intendant had also. To them, to the trainers and stablemen, Sally was the right sort. There was no end to her presents and pourboires.

Such were her occupations. In addition she had another. She, too, was having a run.

The post was a good bit off. Between her and it were wide ditches and tall fences. At any moment a tremendous crumpler might occur. But behind her were other obstacles, bigger and wider still, timber which she thought she could not take and which she had cleared without effort. Moreover, now she was nearing the home stretch. Provided she kept her seat, kept, too, a hand light, yet steady, luck might land her a winner, and at it she went, full tilt, straight ahead, at a pace so clinking that it accounted perhaps for her smiles and good humour.

It was not because of these radiations, but because of others, because it was his destiny to do so, that Welden no longer resented her presence. He accepted it, but with that curious lassitude which Death, in revenge it may be, puts on those for whom it has come and not got.

Apathetic and indifferent, he rejected the news of the day, ignored the cataclysms in Wall street, refused to see Cantire, Le Hillel, Lord Ferrers and the string of visitors that called. But apart from the apathy, apart, too, from the debility incident to his condition, health had returned. Long since his collar-bone had been mended and his ankle, treated after the setting to massage instead of plaster, was now but a little stiff.

Presently, Sally prompting, these things he recognised and recognising also that further delay would constitute a breach of hospitality, he wrote de Dol his thanks, asked him as an additional obligation to accept his hunter and, after distributing princely presents to the service, had himself transported to the Sign of the Swan.

“What you need,” Sally said to him that evening, “is a good, long sea trip. Dr. Binet-Valmer told me so. Don’t you agree with him?”

They were at table in her sitting room at the Hôtel du Cygne where, served by Harris, they had dined. The cloth had not yet been removed but Harris had gone. Sally wore a gown in the corsage of which ochre and lilac were blended. Welden’s evening coat fell about him loosely. He was smoking.

“Don’t you?” Sally repeated.

“Yes,” he answered. “But hardly alone and for the moment I know no one whom I could ask to go with me.”

Sally smiled, displaying her teeth, bits of mother of pearl, glistening and pointed.

“You could ask me.”

At this prelude to the Invitation à la valse, Welden shrugged his shoulders. Men generally thought Sally very fetching. Her mauve eyes, oblique and half-closed, might have tempted saints, demons even, with whom she was perhaps akin. But she failed to represent to Welden that which makes some men constant not necessarily to one particular woman but to one particular feminine type.

“Nonsense,” he told her.

“It is not nonsense at all,” Sally, shaking her head and cocking an eye at him, retorted. “Why do you say so?”

Welden considered the prelude closer. After all there was a certain worldly justice in it. Maud having taken up with Malakoff, it was perhaps nonsense for him to balk at taking up with Malakoff’s wife. Jointly and severally they could combine for the payment of old scores. At the same time, between public and private payment, there was a margin.

“Why do you?” Sally repeated.

Welden lighted a fresh cigar. “I should be compromising you irretrievably.”

Sally sighed. “You have already,” she promptly answered.

From over the cigar Welden looked at her. About her throat was a string of pearls. One hand that lay invitingly on the table was covered with gems. But from it the pretty gestures had gone, from her face the smiles had passed. She looked virginal and sad, a sort of melancholy angel, only much better dressed than angels usually are. Through her half-closed eyes she watched him. There had been her visits to de Dol’s, he was thinking, but that was her affair.

“In what way?” he asked.

“Well, you see, don’t you know, everybody says the duel was on my account.”

That also Welden considered. It seemed logical enough. On a certain night Sally had abandoned her husband. Within thirty-six hours he and that husband had fought. Their reasons for fighting no one, save themselves, Sally and Maud could possibly know. Clearly it was logical enough and yet insufficient to warrant the full measure of the Invitation.

“Mrs. Cawtree wrote to me,” Sally resumed, “and Fanny Solférino and my mother. My mother was very violent. My mother said that I had disgraced her. She declared that no decent person would ever receive me, unless—”

Sally paused. Like the lady whom she was quoting, she sometimes embroidered the truth.

“Unless—” she presently continued, and paused again.

But, as Welden manifested no interest in the proviso, she prodded him.

“I don’t like to tell you.”

Then, seeing that Welden had no intention of urging her, she took her courage in her jewelled hand.

“Unless you marry me.”

Welden had been occupied with the logic of her previous statement, but the unobtrusive modesty of this announcement surprised him from it.

He removed his cigar. “I had an idea that you were married already.”

Into the melancholy of Sally’s face there crept a smile. “I was,” she answered. “I am no longer.”

“Ah,” said Welden. “Is Malakoff dead?”

But now the smile in Sally’s face deepened. It burrowed under the melancholy and tossed it aside. She laughed.

“No, divorced. It was so amusing too. Shall I tell you about it? Shall I? Well, after I put in the petition, the judge had us both see him in private. Ridgeway told me he would. It appears that in divorce cases here the judge takes a sort of fatherly attitude and tries to get the parties to make up and, if you will believe me, he did try. He was so nice about it, too, that you would have thought he was my aunt and Malakoff was so rude you would have thought he was my mother. But the judge was really very nice. And so civil! Dear me, his mouth was just full of madame la duchesse and monsieur de duc. Later on, in the decree, he fined his monsieur le duc a hundred francs. Don’t you think it was amusing?”

Welden shrugged his shoulders. After the duel it had been grievous to him that he had not killed the man. Now he did not care. During the race he had tried to kill himself. There too he had failed. But that also was a matter of indifference. Before either race or duel he had been obsessed by the vision of a pillowed head. It had gone. Though he had failed with Malakoff and failed with himself, he had thoroughly assassinated that.

“Don’t you think it was amusing?” Sally repeated.

“You certainly have not been idle,” Welden replied. “What were the grounds?”

Sally made a gesture. Though there are things that men do, there are women who do not mention them.

Welden nodded. “Who was the co?”

“Who?” cried Sally. “Have you forgotten already? Don’t you remember the night of the Fourth of July?”

Welden nodded again and knocked the ashes from his cigar. “You are no longer, then, madame la duchesse.”

Smilingly Sally stood up. She moved from the table, dropped him a curtsy and sweetly, yet simply, replied:

“I am Sally Kandy again, and yours if you will have me.”

“Thank you,” said Welden, quite as though he had been offered another cup of coffee. “Thank you. But did not this Ridgeway tell you about the Court of Cassation? Malakoff has six months in which to appeal. Of course he will do nothing of the kind. None the less, in the interim, any marriage of yours would be bigamous.”

At that last word Sally flushed and sat down. It is possible that she had misconstrued its meaning.

“What a dreadful expression,” she exclaimed. “I am sure I never should think of anything so horrid. But, in the interim, as you call it, what is there to prevent us from going to South Africa or, better still, to the East?”

At the door came a rap. Harris entered, busying himself with the cloth. Welden got up and limped to the window.

In the park without, leaves were falling, falling from branch to branch; falling slowly, as with regret; falling undecidedly with precaution. In their faint rustle was a sound such as the steps of fate may make when approaching furtively, a-tiptoe.

The hesitancy of it filtered into Welden’s thoughts. Usually, he knew what he had to do and did it. But illness plays strange tricks and destiny plays others. After all, he told himself, eventually there would be someone else. Perhaps as well then Sally as another. At least she would serve to show to Maud how indifferent he was to her. Even otherwise, how should it matter? How should anything matter any more?

He turned. Harris had gone. Sally through her half-closed eyes, was watching him.

“Very good,” he said. “We will go to the Orient since you wish it.”

With a feline twist of the tongue Sally moistened her lips. She had the sensation of being lifted lightly in the air. It was the last fence. She had reached the post a winner.

Alone in his room that night Welden still heard the leaves. They fell slowly, solemnly, burying the past beneath their slender weight, raising between him and it a veil, tenuous and aerial. Higher it rose, higher still, ever higher until, sinking again, it enveloped memory in it.

A fortnight later Welden and Sally, attended by their servants, embarked from Southampton on a voyage that took them first to India, where they loitered, then to Hong Kong, where they were married and finally to White Peacocks.

There the journey ended. There, for one of them, eternity began.

I

PERSPECTIVES

“Well, William, how are you? Is Miss Barhyte at home?”

“Yes, sir, Miss Barhyte has just come in. I hope I see you very well, sir. It’s a long time, sir—”

Taking Welden’s hat and stick, the servant showed him into the library, which apparently, was unaltered. The cushions on the sofa were as colourful as before. Opposite, the piano stood, and from the walls powdered heads looked down. But, from the table, the Sicilians had gone. In place of Greek poetry there was now a book of French verse. Otherwise the room was quite as it had been the year previous and, apart from a black band on the sleeve of his grey coat, Welden himself was unchanged. There was the same smile in his eyes, the same glint in his hair, the same appearance of suppleness and strength.

He had opened the book and was loitering in its languors when William reappeared.

“I am sorry, sir. I made a mistake. Miss Barhyte is not at home.”

The mistake must have been anticipated. Welden manifested no surprise.

“Is the general in?” he asked, his eyes still on the book.

“No, sir. The general is not at home either.”

But now Welden put the book aside and nodded.

“Give him my compliments and say that I will wait on him at nine to-night. How is he?”

“Pretty well, sir.” The man moved out through the reception room to the marble of the hall, where he handed Welden his hat and stick. “That was a nasty accident he had last summer. He limps a little still. Yes, sir.”

Opening the door, he held it open until Welden reached the street.

Welden sauntered on. Five days previous he had left Santa Barbara. It was but an hour or two before that he had reached New York. In his head he could still feel the motion of the cars. That would pass, he told himself, as all things do. It would pass, as would also pass a girl’s disinclination to be at home.

He sauntered on, turned into Fifth avenue, and sauntered up. At once, a man whom he knew stopped him, buttonholed, questioned, platitudinised. From passing traps and motors, women bowed, two other men joined him and, at the curb, a withered creature tossed from a barrel-organ a strain of Italian love.

The men annoyed him. It wearied him to talk about what had happened. It wearied him as much to be told about stocks. Pretexting a pretext he hailed a hansom and sailed away.

Presently, at the Plaza, where he had put up, it was comforting to find that his luggage had arrived. After the philistinism of the West, it was agreeable to be lodged in an artistic inn. After the horrors of a trans-continental trip, it was a pleasure to dress at ease. After the convict fare of the Limited, food properly served was a relief. After a tragedy, a change of air is good for the nerves.

Welden, as he sat at table that evening, his recent mourning indicated in his shirt by two small black studs, considered momentarily these minor gifts of the minor gods. But he had work ahead of him and, at five minutes to nine, hailing a hansom, he sailed back to Madison avenue.

At a door there, as he rang, a melody of Beethoven’s which was being played within, ceased abruptly. The door opened and William, after taking his hat and coat, showed him into the dining-room where, before a wide table, the general sat, looking, as perhaps a general should, very fierce.

“William,” he ordered, “close the door behind you.”

Then, rising, he turned at Welden.

“Had you left your address this afternoon, I would have warned you not to call here. Your conduct has been dastardly. Dastardly! God bless my soul, there is no other word for it.”

He paused, removed his glasses and shook them.

“After an accident which I experienced and Maud had joined me at Frascati’s, you picked a quarrel with Malakoff, induced the duchess to obtain a divorce and married the lady, married her, God bless my soul, when you were engaged to my daughter and to-day, your wife barely cold in her grave, you have the impudence to come here. Damn me, sir, if I had acted as you have I would have come expecting the cowhide.”

As the tirade proceeded the general’s voice mounted to the diapason of a roar. At its conclusion he stamped a foot.

“Yes, damn me, the cowhide.”

Immediately, but without heat, Welden took it up.

“From no other man living would I endure for an instant that expression, nor yet the one which preceded it. But you are right, right, that is, from your point of view. It would be dastardly, and it would be the cowhide I should expect, if I had acted as you say I have, intentionally.”

“Intentionally,” the general shouted. “Intentionally—”

He would have run on but Welden cut in.

“When your daughter left Deauville I was on my way to Paris. She wrote me of your accident, telling me she was going to you at once, and asking me to join you both at Frascati’s—”

“Damn me, sir, this is ancient history.”

Welden nodded. “Yes, to you and to your daughter. But not to me. The letter which your daughter wrote at Deauville on the morning of the Fourth of July, I received less than a fortnight since at Santa Barbara.”

“Even so what of it? They were not dumb at the Malakoff’s, I suppose. They all knew of it. Anyone could have told you.”

“General, not only no one told me that your daughter had gone, but I was led to believe that she was still there and did not wish to see me.”

“Stuff and nonsense! Do you mean to say that you are a born fool? How could anyone gammon you with such rubbish?”

There are explanations which explain nothing. Unhesitatingly Welden advanced one.

“For the very reason you have given. Because I was a fool. But however much of a fool I may have been I am not a knave. Your daughter will appreciate that.”

General Barhyte reached forward and touched a bell.

“Never,” he answered. “I shall not allow you to see her and even if I did, she would refuse to do so.”

The servant entered.

“William, the door for this gentleman.”

He turned his back, took up an evening paper and sat down. To him Welden had apparently ceased to exist.

But Welden was thoroughly alive. Preceded by William, he passed into the drawing room and on to the hall. There, after getting his hat and coat, instead of going out, he turned into the reception room and went through it to the library beyond.

At the piano, a sheet of music before her, was a girl who, as he entered, turned slowly and slowly arose.

Welden, his hat in his hand, his coat on his arm, looked at her. Unlike the room, she had altered. The allurement of her face, the caress which she had exhaled, the charm of manner which always she had conveyed, these emanations were absent. In place of allurement was blankness; in lieu of the caress was rigidity; instead of the charm, a chill. In her eyes and about her mouth was an expression of distant inquiry, an air of saying: Who are you and what do you want?

Welden, prepared for the situation, began methodically at its demolition.

“Maud, there has been that between us which I know you will come to believe justifies me in disregarding any instructions you may have given, your father’s orders as well. When I returned the sapphire—”

Insecure in her intrenchments the girl let fire. “It was your right to do so. It was a right which I had given you and expressly stipulated that you should use. In returning it you said everything there was to be said. There can be nothing to add to it.”

“When I returned the sapphire,” Welden continued, “it was because I thought you wished it.”

“You may or may not have been mistaken, but you cannot possibly have been as mistaken in me as I have been in you.”

“When I returned the sapphire,” Welden persisted, “it was because I believed I had seen you in Malakoff’s arms.”

For a second, with diligent disdain, the girl considered him. Then at once, after the fashion which royalty has devised to signify that a conversation is at an end, she moved back.

Welden had been prepared for that also.

“Do you recall our last night together?”

At the memory evoked, the girl coloured and the disdain mounting with the flush, increased, accentuated by the wantonness of the question.

“Forgive me for referring to it,” Welden added. “But that night when I entered your room, the disposition of it was such that I saw at first but your head. The next night I saw you as before, with this difference however, Malakoff was with you—with you I say, for it was but recently I learned that that night you were at Frascati’s and that your room was occupied by a Mme. Oppensheim, a person whom I did not know existed.”

On the music stool behind her the girl sank down. The flush had gone from her face but the disdain remained.

“Do you know of her?” Welden asked.

Maud, without unbending, bent a little; “She reached the villa as I was leaving it.”

“Then you are aware of the resemblance between you. Her hair is precisely the colour of yours. Now do me this favour; put yourself in my place. Had you seen me as I thought I saw you, would you not have acted as I did?”

The girl straightened herself. “No,” she answered shortly.

“Do you mean that it would not have affected your relations with me?”

“I mean nothing of the kind.”

“Without indiscretion, may I ask then what you do mean?”

“Because I happened to fancy that you were volage, I myself would not have become so.”

“Forgive me, Maud, I do not quite follow you.”

“Nor can I allow you, nor do I wish to. Admitting your delusion, one by the way which must have been almost self-evident, the slightest effort on your part would have corrected it.”

“Maud, believe me, I had no opportunity.”

“I do believe you, your opportunity lay elsewhere.”

“No,” Welden protested, “it did not. Moreover, the opportunity to which you refer came months later, and though utilised then, it was only for the wretchedest and therefore the most human of reasons, in order that I might at least be revenged.”

“On Malakoff?” the girl tauntingly threw at him.

“Damn me, sir,” some one was angrily calling, “when I instructed my servant to show you the door—”

Welden turned. Before him the general stood. Immediately Maud interposed herself between them.

“Father,” she said, pushing him as she spoke, toward the adjoining room, “go in there, I must speak to you.”

“You told me,” the old man remonstrated, trying vainly to resist. “You told me—”

“I have not a doubt of it,” Maud, pushing still, replied. “But I told you also never to believe a word a woman said.”

The door closed suddenly. Welden could at last put down his hat and coat. He had not, he knew, demolished all the intrenchments, but in view of the girl’s defence of him, he felt that he had sapped their base.

He was quite in error. None the less, in a few moments, when Maud issued unaccompanied from the conflict in the outer room, her parliamentaries there may have suggested a temporary truce. She stopped at the table, took up the book of verse, looked at it, replaced it and with tolerable irrelevance remarked:

“That was very terrible about Sally. Have you any suspicion who did it?”

“No,” Welden answered. “None whatever.”

“I ought, I suppose, to condole with you, but I cannot. Neither of you I think behaved very well. She knew about Mme. Oppensheim even if, as you say, you did not. It was because of her that she got the decree. Everybody knew that. It was not in the papers, but it was common talk. Were you deaf at the time?”

“Partially,” Welden replied. “At Chantilly I made rather a mess of it.”

Of that mess the girl had been informed. At the time and since she had thought it not unmerited. What she did not know and what she never learned was the fact that the mess was intentional. For there are some things that some men do not talk about. Even otherwise, there are times and seasons when any compliment, however unique, falls flat.

“Afterward,” Welden resumed, “it was quite a bit before I was about.”

“But when you were, did you not hear?”

“When I was, Sally told me that it was you who were the co.”

Maud lifted her hands. “She told you that! She told you that I was the co-respondent!”

“In so many words.”

“When did you learn that I was not?”

“The other day at Santa Barbara. It came about rather oddly. We were on the lawn, the wind was blowing, it disarranged her hair. Her hair, if you will notice. She wanted a barrette. There was no one within call. She asked me to get it. It was in some case, in some bag. She told me where and where the keys were. She was very explicit about it all. But I misunderstood. I opened the wrong bag or the wrong box. In it I found a letter addressed to me. I know it by heart. ‘July the Fourth, Villa Portugaise. Dearest: They have just wired me from Frascati’s that my father has been injured. I am going over on the noon boat. Join me there to-morrow. Mille baisers, M.’ ”

“She had concealed it!”

“Evidently.”

“What did you do?”

Welden made a gesture. At the time when he found the letter his mind had shot backward. Facts and incidents trivial in themselves and long since forgotten, mounted from those cellars of memory where whatever we do or say or see is noted, registered, catalogued and preserved. In a sort of retrograde vision the madness of a night returned. He beheld the silent villa and Sally, her hand on his arm, saying: “Don’t.” He recalled the singularity of her attitude; the avid movement with which, when in the hall below, she had taken and concealed the note; her subsequent eagerness to have him fight; her stupid insistence that he should tell no one why; her speeches and answers at Chantilly: and suddenly a curtain rose. He saw, if not the truth, at least the lie.

“What did you do?” Maud repeated.

“I went to her and asked whom Malakoff had been entertaining that evening. It was a little before I could get her to admit that it was not you. Finally she acknowledged that it was Mme. Oppensheim.”

Again Maud lifted her hands. “It is incredible!”

“Yes, particularly as from the start she quite played on my mistake, at first, I suppose, in order to have me kill Malakoff and later on, perhaps, because she felt compromised by the duel.”

Maud considered these premises and then supplied the deduction.

“That is why she asked you to marry her.”

“I did not say that.”

“No, men never do say such things but sometimes women infer them. How long afterward did she die?”

“The same night, or rather the next morning.”

Maud considered that also, but more longly.

“Don’t you see,” she said at last, “were these things known, you would be suspected, arrested perhaps?”

“Naturally. If ever a man had a motive I had one. On the night when I went to the room which you had occupied and saw what I took to be you, Sally was at my elbow. She had come to surprise Malakoff, and finding me there and divining my error, took advantage of us both. I am sorry now for Malakoff. I intended to kill him. He knew it, knew the reason, knew that it was all a mistake. But, bounder that he is, he could not like an ordinary cad come to me with an explanation.”

“No,” said Maud. “Men never explain and women always do. None the less—”

“None the less,” Welden ran on, “though I can be sorry for him, I cannot be for Sally. What happened to her was the judgment of God.”

That verdict Maud examined and at once indorsed.

“Yes, for with a word she could have set you straight.”

Welden nodded. “It has been a tragedy of errors. Yet, of course, if the police at Santa Barbara had so much as an inkling of it, I would be in jail there now. They suspect me as it is, I think.”

“But I read that you offered a reward.”

“Yes, and it was then I felt that I was suspected.”

Maud looked that over also, but without seeming to get the point of it.

“Surely they could not fancy that you would offer a reward for your own conviction?”

“No, but they could readily fancy that I offered it to divert suspicion, for that is precisely what a bungler would have done.”

Welden paused. Presently he added:

“I did not realise that until afterward.”

At this, Maud, who had remained at the table, crossed the room and seated herself on the sofa. Welden took a seat beside her.

“What do you propose to do now?” She asked.

“Beg you to marry me.”

The girl shook her head. “You need not. I have no intention of it.”

“For the same reason as before?”

“Partly. But for others also.”

It was now Welden’s turn to consider things. While he was at it, she helped him.

“It is not that I cannot forgive you,” she explained. “But I have so long regarded you as unforgivable that I cannot immediately forget. Besides, that you should have suspected me is one thing, but that you should have consoled yourself is quite another.”

“Consoled!” retorted Welden. “The word does not fit. I had no relations with Sally.”

Maud turned and looked at him. She had never known him to lie, but she was not credulous and Sally, whatever her demonism, had been a very pretty woman.

“That’s as may be,” she answered. “The point is you hurt me and meant to. I think I could not have done that to you.”

For a second she hesitated, her hands lying interclasped in her lap. She opened them and slowly added:

“But I am quite sure I could have done a little harm to her.”

“The little harm has been done,” Welden remarked.

But that Maud could not have found herself quite able to concede.

“By another,” she answered, “and incompletely.”

In what manner the harm could have been completer she did not say, nor did Welden ask, but he marvelled at the girl, who, in spite of the character of their previous intimacy, now, for the first time, revealed to him her naked soul.

She stood up, went to the piano and with one hand struck the keys into notes violent and discordant.

Then, as she turned, displaying the oval of her perfect face, and stood there, elaborately gowned, her head erect, she might perhaps, to any other, have presented but a genre picture of a society girl, ultra smart. To Welden she was something else, something higher or it may be, lower; a being intensely human, vibrant with elemental passion.

“She was made for me,” he told himself, and crossing the room, he looked her in the eyes.

But however vibrant the girl may have been, however primitive also, she was not in a mood for caresses. Dumbly against him she felt the revolt which women have for the man who comes to them from the arms of another. Those arms were lifeless now and such enfoldings as they had given perhaps were scant, but some at least there had been, and at the thought of them she recoiled instinctively.

“No,” she said in answer to that look. “Not now, perhaps never. I cannot tell. Do not try to ask me.”

“Good night,” she added after a moment, when Welden, who knew better than to urge against her will, had taken up his hat and coat.

II

THE BENEDICTION

The fatigues compressed in a journey across the continent are of a completeness that satiates the sturdiest. On leaving Madison avenue, Welden slept thirteen hours, awoke, tubbed, dressed, drank some coffee, read a telegram, also a newspaper and, other details terminated, drove to the Grand Central where he arranged to repeat the trip.

The telegram, a night message from Santa Barbara, marked Collect and signed Wicks, was as follows:

Perkins indicted on evidence personally obtained. Rings recovered, trial to-morrow. I claim rewards.

“The imbecile,” Welden muttered as the message fell from him.

But the purport of it he found repeated in a morning paper, strung out there with sensational details, stories of full confession, others of priceless jewels—the property of the murdered woman with whom Welden had eloped and then been shot by the outraged husband—the usual farrago of fiction, garnished in this instance with a picture of White Peacocks which resembled the scene of the crime about as closely as it did the Plaza.

Beneath the ribbon of rubbish there was none the less a fact. There was also a possibility. There had been an indictment, conviction might follow.

The rooms which Welden occupied gave on Central Park. For a moment, from a window, he stood looking at the rain of sunshine, the leisurely motors, the gingerly stepping horses, the parade of nurses out with their charges for the midday air. Yet, though he looked, he did not see, or rather it was not the Park that he saw, but Santa Barbara and the obligation to return there.

The prospect was not agreeable. He had, however, contemplated it before. Now, with no thought of shirking, he contemplated it again. Then, the letter written, other details terminated, he went down Madison avenue for a word with Maud.

But the girl was not at home. William assured him of that, assured him that this time there was no mistake, that she was really out, gone but a little before in her brougham.

Welden took from a pocket the letter which he had written.

“Here is a note for Miss Barhyte. Give it to her yourself and say that it is not to be opened until she hears from me. I leave town to-day and I will wire shortly, but the letter is not to be opened until then. Do you understand? You do? You are sure you do? The letter is not to be opened until I wire. Very good. Here is something for you.”

“Thank you, Mr. Welden. Thank you.”

The man bowed Welden out, after which he put the letter on the hall table where, later that afternoon, Maud letting herself in with a latch-key as was her custom, found and read it.

Welden then was on his way to Chicago. The press there supplied him with fresh news from Santa Barbara, at Omaha there was more. But thereon, over the plains and through the hamlets which in a sort of horrible coquetry vie in hideousness with each other, there was a silence that continued until Ogden was reached.

Ogden too has its coquetries. But the news of the day may be had there. There is also a stop.

The stop is brief, yet it sufficed for Welden. He wired to Maud, got his trunks from the baggage car, his bags from the Pullman and boarded a returning train.

In a Salt Lake sheet he had read that, the prosecution collapsing, Perkins had been released. It was then that he wired. The wire was a request that his letter should not be opened. Four days later he was in New York.

On the evening of that fourth day, a bit fatigued, the motion of the train actively continuing in his head, but in a white tie, a white waistcoat—between which two small black studs served to indicate his recent mourning—he was again in Madison avenue, this time in the parlour, as the local drawing-room is sometimes called and on this occasion very properly, for a parlour or parloir is a talking place and Welden found himself called upon to say more than he had expected, and on a subject at that concerning which he had not intended to talk at all.

Maud was not present when he entered and he looked at the faded frescoes with a yawn. In a moment however, from the dining-room beyond, the girl appeared.

Her neck and arms were bare. Her gown was white, striated with violet. As she entered she stooped to arrange or to release a fold. The attitude, but momentarily maintained, was so graceful that Welden forgot his fatigue. Then, as she straightened and approached, one hand just upholding a hem, the picture she presented indemnified him for the little horrors of the trip.

The week previous he saw that she had altered. Now he realised that she had changed again. It was as though when bending at the door, her whole manner had unbent.

She took his hand. “Dearest, another would say that what you went from here to do was noble. I do not. It was You.”

Passably perplexed, Welden stared. In the stare the perplexity was reflected.

The girl smiled. Her hand still in his, she led him to the S in upholstery, in one of the curves of which she seated herself while he, guided by her, seated himself in the other.

“Dearest, will you promise me something?”

Welden nodded.

“Will you promise not to be annoyed?”

Welden nodded again.

“I must tell you, then, that I have read your letter.”

Vexation lifted Welden visibly like a lash. He dropped the hand he held, sprang from the seat and went to the window. On reaching it he turned. Maud was looking at him.

“Your promise!”

Welden ran his long, thin fingers through his bright thick hair.

“Your promise!”

“But, Maud, I am not annoyed. Annoyance is not the term. If anything, I am alarmed.”

At that the girl also left her seat. Advancing to where he stood she said in his face: “It is the first time then in all your life.”

Welden, moving uneasily, turned away.

“Dearest, can you not trust me? Even if I had not read the letter, sooner or later I would have known.”

With the goaded action of a bull before the matador, Welden tossed his head.

“No, never, unless—” He stopped, looked at her, weighed her. “Unless matters had gone the other way. It was only in provision of the contingency that I wrote you and when I did, I expressly instructed William that you were not to read the letter until you heard from me again.”

“Yes, so he told me—after I had read it. I am not sorry, nor should you be. No earthly thing could have brought us nearer. Dearest, do you not see that between us now it is for always?”

“You mean that?”

“Mean it! If you wish, I will go with you to-night. The world will say that I am your mistress, but I would rather be that than empress to an emperor.”

“Doña Sol!” Welden, with assumed lightness, threw out.

“Doña Sol, yes, if you like, and Héloïse also, for both said it. With them, though, it was heroics; with me it is the truth.”

Welden took her hands in his. “Supposing I put you to the test?”

“Give me only time to get a cloak, and for William to call a cab.”

“I don’t mean that. I mean a greater test.”

“Is there any?”

Welden nodded. “Will you marry me?”

Maud laughed in his face. “Do you call that a test? Do you?”

Welden, a bit relieved, laughed also.

“Well, you see,” he said, “heretofore it has rather seemed one. I give you my word I had no idea but that you would refuse me.”

Maud turned, surveying the room. Then, assured that they were quite alone, she disengaged her hands, put them on his shoulders and raising herself, whispered:

“What girl would refuse a man who loved her enough to kill another woman for her? Dearest, I adore you.”

Welden drew her to him. Presently, as he held her in his arms, he said: “I hope you destroyed that agreeable information?”

With a smile the girl freed herself.

“Completely,” she answered.

Then taking him again by the hand she led him back to where they had been seated.

There, after a moment, she added: “Dearest, tell me about it. Did Sally know beforehand?”

“Now, Maud,” he protested, “don’t be morbid.”

But naïvely this girl in whom there was so little naïveté persisted.

“Dearest, tell me this; was it because of the letter you killed her?”

“I killed her for what she killed in me, for her assassination of my belief in you. That was more to me than life, and for it I took hers.”

Maud thought it over. But still the episode of the letter rankled.

“What did she do when she found you had my note?”

“What did she do?” Welden repeated, “Personally she did nothing. But the most curious of all physical phenomena manifested itself in her. The red phantom of the human conscience appeared in her face. She flushed with a flame that came to her from hell.”

Maud contemplated the picture. It seemed to her over coloured. With a question she toned it.

“Don’t you suppose that she was merely angry at herself for having kept the note? I cannot conceive what folly prompted her to do so.”

“A folly that is common enough,” Welden answered. “Almost all criminals leave or preserve some evidence of their guilt. There is an uncontrollable impulse which compels them.”

Maud smiled. “Thank fortune, that impulse did not actuate my criminal. Did it, dearest?”

“Oh, but it did though. You read about the jewels, the famous jewels, the rings that cost ninety thousand and which an imbecile out there discovered, or thought he discovered, in Perkins’ possession?”

“Yes, but it appeared that they were imitation and her own. The papers said she had a receipt from a Paris manufacturer, made out to her in her name.”

“Precisely. Sally’s stones cost more, but nothing like what I represented. I know it was not very nice of me to have exaggerated their value as I did, but I had to supply the police with a motive. Ça n’a pas fait un pli. They swallowed it whole.”

Maud laughed. “That was very clever of you. Where were they at the time?”

“The rings? In my pocket.”

Maud laughed again. “Where are they now?”

“Where I put them, neatly done up, in the coffin.”

“You put them there! But why?”

“Partly from that uncontrollable impulse, but chiefly in provision of just such a thing as nearly happened, in order that if another were convicted, I could prove that I was the man.”

“And if Perkins had been convicted you would have done so?”

“Naturally. It would have been the merest duty.”

“Dearest, do you wonder that I love you? No. I was right from the first. There is none but you. Tell me—”

But whatever the girl’s question may have been, it was not asked or at least not then. In the door through which she had come, the general stood.

“Father!” she called in her clinging voice. “We are engaged again and we are to be married shortly.”

Furiously the old gentleman turned on her.

“In all my life I have never heard of such indecency. Yes, damn me, indecency. You were engaged to that man before and he threw you over to marry another woman. The day you leave this house for him, you leave it forever. You are of age, you can do as you like, but so can I, and, damn me, I’ll disown you.”

Cursing and fuming, the general strode on.

It was their benediction. They knew it, knew, too, that it was deserved. But the ball was over, the nightmare as well. Life larger, though more lawful, was about to begin. Slowly the girl’s arms went about her lover. At their touch, in sudden retrospect, he saw again White Peacocks and the inaugural sky: the massacre on the horizon, the trooping titans, the luminous arc, the flight of the centaurs and the mirage of the archipelagoes of love.

FAUSTA.

There are many beautiful things in the world, and among them, near the head of the list, stands dawn in the tropics. It is sudden as love, and just as fair. Throughout the night the ship had been sailing beneath larger stars than ours, in waters that were seamed and sentient with phosphorus; but now the ship was in the harbor, day had chased the stars, the water was iridescent as a syrup of opals, at the horizon was the tenderest pink, overhead was a compound of salmon and of blue; and beyond, within rifle range, was an amphitheatre of houses particolored as rainbows, surmounted by green hills, tiared with the pearl points of cathedral steeples, and for defensive girdle, the yellow walls of a crumbling fort.

“On this side,” thought one who lounged on deck, “it seems bounded by beauty,” and he might have added, “by ignorance on the other.” He was a good-looking young fellow, dressed Piccadilly-fashion, and yet, despite the cut of his coat, the faint umber of his skin and the sultry un-Saxon eyes marked him as being of Latin blood. His name was Ruis Ixar. He was the son of a certain Don Jayme, who was then Governor of Puerto Principe, and in Castile, Count, Grandee of Spain, and Marquis, to boot. Don Jayme had emptied his coffers in discreet rivalry of his king, and his king, who admired prodigal fathers, had given him leave to replenish them in the New World. This permission Don Jayme had for some time past made the most of, now by exactions, now by fresh taxes, by peculations and speculations, and also by means of a sugar plantation a few leagues beyond Santiago de Cuba, in the harbor of which his son, that morning, was preparing to disembark.

Don Jayme had been domiciled in the neighborhood for five years, and the five years had been to him five Kalpas of time.

He felt desolate as a lighthouse. He had come expecting to make a rapid fortune, and in that expectation he had been wearisomely deceived. The province which he had intended to wring dry as an orange had been well squeezed by earlier comers, and as for his hacienda, he found it more profitable to let the cane rot uncut than to attempt to extract the sugar. He hated Cuba, as every true Spaniard does, and the portion of Cuba which he administered hated him. He longed for Madrid, for the pomp and ceremonial of court; and particularly did he desire that his son should enjoy an income suited to his rank. Though he had not as yet succeeded in replenishing more than one or two of the many emptied coffers, there was no valid reason why his sole descendant should be poor. And if his son were rich, the former splendor of the Ixars would blaze anew. Don Jayme was a selfish man, as men brought up in court circles are apt to be; he was not a good man, he was not even a good-looking man, but the bit of lignum vitæ which served him for heart was all in all for that son. It was for him he had come to Cuba, and if the coming had been a partial failure, that partial failure would be wholly retrieved did he succeed in supplying the heir to his title with a well dowered wife.

So argued Don Jayme. But he was careful to argue with no one save his most intimate friend, to-wit, himself. To his son he said nothing; he merely wrote him to take ship, and sail.

It so happened that when this communication was received, Ruis Ixar was as anxious for a trip to the New World as Don Jayme was for a return to the Old. He was tired of the Puerto del Sol; he was tired too of the usual young woman that lives over the way. He wanted a taste of adventure; and moreover obedience to his father’s behests had been the groundwork of his education. He had therefore taken ship with alacrity, and on this melting morning of December, as he gazed for the first time at the multicolored vista before him, he was in great and expectant spirits. Concerning the town itself, had he been put on the rack he could have confessed to but two items of information: one was that his father was chief official; and the other that there was not a book-shop within its walls. To the latter fact he was utterly indifferent; he had learned it haphazard on the way over: but the former was not without its charm. The influence of that charm presently exerted itself. He was conveyed from the ship in a government boat, and two hours later, while his fellow-passengers were still engaged in feeing the supervisors of the custom-house, he had reached the hacienda behind the hills.

The hacienda, or ingenio as it is more properly called, was several miles of yellow striated with red, punctuated with palms and cut by paths that were shaded with the great glistening leaves of the banana, while here and there, Dantesque and unnatural in its grandeur, rose the ceiba, its giant arms outstretched as though to shield the toiler from the suffocation of the purple skies. And beneath, for contrast, the brilliance of convolvuli and granadillas opposed the tender green. At the southernmost end was Don Jayme’s habitation, a one-story edifice, built quadrangularwise, tiled and steep of roof, and semi-circled by a veranda so veiled with vines that at a distance the house seemed a massive mound of pistache.

“Even in Andalusia,” thought Ruis, as the volante brought him to the door, “there is nothing equal to this.” Like all his race, he had a quick eye to the beautiful, and for the moment he was bewildered by the riot of color. And while the bewilderment still lingered, a gentleman, slim and tall, entirely in white, with face and hands of the shade of Turkish tobacco, kissed him on either cheek.

“God be praised, my son,” he murmured, “you are here.”

And with that he led him into the cool of the veranda. It had been years since they had met, there was much to be said, and in that grave unvociferous fashion which is peculiar to the Spaniard of Castile, in a language which nightingales might envy, father and son discussed topics of common and personal interest.

Thereafter for some little time, a fortnight to be exact, things went very well indeed. Ruis expressed himself enchanted with his new home. The plantation was a wonder to him, the half-naked negroes and their wholly nude progeny a surprise, and the brutality with which they were treated caused him a transient emotion. In turtle fishing he found an agreeable novelty, and in the shooting of doves and the blue-headed partridge he became an immediate adept. But when a fortnight had come and gone he felt vaguely bored; he grew tired of strange and sticky fruits, the call of chromatic birds jarred, discordant, on his nerves, the turtles lost their allurement, the weight of purple days oppressed him. In brief, he thought he had quite enough of rural life in the tropics. Aside from his father, there was not, on the estate, a soul of his own race with whom he could exchange a word. And though he had nothing whatever to say, yet such is the nature of youth that he heartily wished himself back in Spain. The young girl that lived there over the way he would have hailed as life’s full delight, and two or three of her scrappy letters, which through some oversight he had neglected to turn into cigarette-lighters, he set to work to decipher anew. The writer of them was an ethereal young person with a pretty taste for fine sentiments, and as Ruis possessed himself of the candors of her thought, he very much wished that he could kneel immediately at her feet.

From the early forenoon until the sun has begun to set it is not at all agreeable, or prudent either, for the unacclimated to be astir in that part of the planet in which Don Jayme’s hacienda was situated. But the mornings are mellow indeed, the dusk is languorous in its beauty, and as for the nights, none others in all the world can compare with them. The stars are as lilies set in parterres of indigo. In the air is a perfume and a caress.

And Ruis, out of sheer laziness, made the most of the dusk and the early hours. At sunrise he was on horseback scouring the country, now over the red road in the direction of the town, and again across the savannas, past cool thin streams and ravines that were full of shadow, mystery, and green. And when the sun had lost its ardor he would be off again, and return in company with the moon. As a rule he met but few people, sometimes a man or two conveying garden produce to the sea-port, sometimes women with eggs and poultry, now and then a negro, and once a priest. But practically the roads were unfrequented, and without incident or surprise.

One morning, however, as his horse was bearing him homeward, he caught sight of an object moving in the distance. At first he fancied that it might be one of the men he was wont to meet, but soon he saw that it was a woman, and as he drew nearer he noticed that she was young, and, in a moment, that she was fair to see. By her side stood a horse. The saddle was on the ground, and she was busying herself with the girth. At his approach she turned her head. Her mouth was like a pomegranate filled with pearls; her face was without color, innocent of the powdered egg-shells with which Cuban damsels and dames whiten their cheeks; and in her eyes was an Orient of dreams. She was lithe and graceful, not tall; perhaps sixteen. About her waist a crimson sash was wound many times, her gown was of gray Catalonian calico, and her sandalled feet were stockingless.

“A Creole,” thought Ruis; and raising his right hand to the left side of his broad-brimmed hat, he made it describe a magnificent parabola through the air, and as he replaced it, bowed.

“Your servant, Señorita,” he said.

“And yours, Don Ruis,” she replied.

“You know my name, Señorita! May I ask how you are called?”

“I am called Fausta,” she answered; and as she spoke Ruis caught in her voice an accent unknown to the Madridlenes of his acquaintance, the accent of the New World, abrupt, disdainful of sibilants, and resolute. He dismounted at once.

“You have had an accident, Doña Fausta; let me aid you.”

But the girth was beyond aid; it was old and had worn itself in twain. And as he examined it he noticed that the saddle was not of the kind that women prefer.

“It is needless, Don Ruis. See, it is an easy matter.” And with that she unwound her crimson girdle, and in a moment, with dexterous skill, she removed the broken girth, replaced the saddle on the horse, and bound it to him with the sash. “But I thank you,” she added, gravely.

Ruis was a little sceptical about the security of this arrangement, and that scepticism he ventured to express. But the girl was on the horse, unassisted, before he had finished the sentence.

“Have no fears, Don Ruis. Besides, our house is but a little bird’s flight from here. I could have walked, if need were.”

Ruis remounted. “May I not accompany you?” he asked.

“To-morrow,” she answered; and for the first time she smiled. For to-morrow in a Cuban mouth means anything except what it expresses. And as she said it, Ruis smiled too.

“How do you know my name?” he inquired.

“We—my mother and I—we are your neighbors.”

“Ah, Doña Fausta, in that case, I pray you make my duty to the lady your mother, and beg of her a permission that I may do so myself.”

Again she smiled. “To-morrow,” she lisped, and whipped her horse.

Ruis raised his hat as before, and bowed.

“God be with you, Doña Fausta.”

“And with you, Don Ruis.”

The next morning he was on the red road again, but no maiden in distress was discoverable that day. The sun chased him home, and as he lounged through high noon in the cool of the veranda, he marvelled at his earlier boredom. Later on he sent for one of the overseers and questioned him minutely. Whatever information he may have gleaned, it was presumably satisfactory. He watched the sun expire in throes of crimson and gamboge, and night unloose her leash of stars. Then he took horse again, and, aided by information received, in ten minutes he was at Doña Fausta’s door. It was a shabby door, he noticed, the portal of a still shabbier abode, and even in the starlight he divined that if ever wealth had passed that way, it had long since taken flight. The noise of hoofs brought the girl to the porch.

“At your feet, Doña Fausta,” he said, and raised his hat. “I am come to offer my homage to the lady your mother, and to you, if I may.”

“Who is it?” called a voice from within; and then, for ampler satisfaction of the inquiry, a lean old woman, gray of hair, unkempt, wrinkled, and bent, appeared in the doorway and fastened on Ruis two glittering, inquisitorial eyes.

“The son of Don Jayme,” the girl answered; “he wishes you well.” With a perfectly perceptible shrug the woman turned and disappeared.

“She has suffered much,” the girl explained. “Don Ruis, you are welcome.”

Ruis dismounted and gave the horse a lash with his whip. “It will be pleasant to walk back,” he said, as the horse started. “Mariquita can find her way home unguided.” He smiled; he was pleased with himself: and the girl smiled too. “Tell me,” he added, “do you live here always?”

“Always, Don Ruis.”

“Ah, you should come to Spain. You would love Madrid, and more than Madrid would you love Grenada and Seville. Santiago is a little, a very little, like Seville. You go there often, do you not?”

“But seldom, Don Ruis.”

“To the fiestas, surely.”

“To go to the fiestas one needs a brave gown, and I have none.”

“I,” said Ruis, “I am tired of fiestas, and truly at Santiago they cannot be very grand. After all, you miss little. Ah, Doña Fausta, you should see them in Spain. And,” he continued, in a tone that was almost a whisper, “you should let Spain see you.”

In this wise the two young people talked together. And when the fractions of an hour had passed them by unmarked, the old woman appeared again on the porch, and Ruis withdrew. On reaching the hacienda he went to the room which he occupied, and tore into bits the scrappy letters of his Madridlene. “To the deuce,” he muttered, as he stretched himself out beneath the mosquito netting, “to the deuce with thin women and the communion of souls.”

The day following Ruis did not venture to make a second visit, but he loitered on the red road both in the clear forenoon and in the slumbering dusk; but he loitered in vain. On the morrow his success was not greater: yet on the succeeding day his heart gave an exultant throb; she was there. It was not necessary for him to be verbose. His manner was caressing as the air, and her eyes were eloquent, almost as eloquent as his own. Before they parted they had agreed upon a tryst, a spot wholly sheltered by cedars and tamarinds, through which a brook ran, and where tendrils with a thousand coils embraced the willing trees as would they smother them with flowers. And there each day they met. Love with them was like the sumptuous vegetation in which they moved—swift of growth. To Ruis, Fausta was the most perfect of playmates, a comrade that each day brought him some fresh surprise. She was at once naïve and imperious, docile and self-willed. He noticed that she was friends with the mimosa, for once, when she touched the sensitive leaves, they did not shrink, the timidity was gone. And once, when she spoke of her father, who had been shot as a conspirator, her anger was like a storm on the coast, glorious and terrible to behold. She was sweet indeed, yet heat sugar and abruptly it boils. To Fausta, Ruis was present and future besides. As for the past she had none save in so far as it had been a preparation for him. He had told her that she should be countess, though for that she cared nothing, except that in being countess she would be his wife as well. And so over constant meetings two months went by. In their Eden, Ruis at first was usually the earliest to arrive, and when he heard her footfall he would hasten to meet her and hold her in his arms.

“Speak to me, Fausta,” he would say; “I love your voice: look at me; I love your eyes. How fair love is when we are together and alone! Is it not exquisite to speak of love when all else is still?”

And Fausta, waist-encircled, would answer, “Ruis, I love you; I need to see you, to see you again, and always. When you leave me it is as though I fell asleep, to reawake only at your return.”

It was with this duo and its infinite variations that they charmed two months away. To Ruis, at first, no other months of all his life had been so fertile in delight. To Fausta they were not months, but dreams fulfilled.

Meanwhile, Don Jayme had not been idle. He had been much in Puerto Principe, and he had made two journeys to Havana. Now from Santiago to Havana the distance is 600 miles, and Don Jayme was not a man to undertake such a journey without due and sufficient cause. Be this as it may, it so happened that after his second visit to the capital he enjoyed a memorable interview with his son. To him he had as yet said nothing of his plans, but on this occasion he made no secret of them.

“Ruis,” he said, leisurely, with the air of one engaging in conversation solely for conversation’s sake, “you know the House of Sandoval?”

“Surely: we are more or less related. A hundred years ago an Ixar married a Sandoval—”

“Of the younger branch, however. We do not bear their arms.”

“There was no bluer blood in all Castile.”

“No, nor yet in Aragon. Don Jorge is in Havana.”

“Don Jorge of Sandoval! I thought him dead.”

“His credit was, but that has since revived. He came to Cuba the year before I came myself. I am little richer now than then, but he has garnered millions.”

“Ah!”

“Yes, millions—three at least. In the Convent of Our Lady del Pilar is his daughter, Doña Clarisa. We have agreed that you and she should wed.”

Ruis laughed. “To-morrow,” he answered; “I am not in haste for matrimony;” and laughed again.

“Ruis, Don Jorge and I, we have agreed.” There was something in the father’s face that banished the merriment of the son. “This night we leave for Havana. See to it that you are in readiness.”

In his perplexity Ruis twisted a cigarette.

“Have you understood me?” Don Jayme asked. “In a month we shall be in Spain. You will like to be back there, will you not?” he continued, in suaver tones. “You will like to be back there, rich, and—and the husband of a beautiful girl. Eh, my son? You will like that, will you not? Ruis, see, it is for you. You are all I have. It was for you I came here; it was for you I made this match. For myself, nothing matters. I have had my day. It is in you I live, in you only; and in our name to which this marriage will give a new and needed lustre.”

“And you say we leave to-night?”

Don Jayme nodded.

“That will be difficult. H’m.” He hesitated, and as he hesitated his father looked inquiringly at him. “It is this: there is one here who thinks that name is to be hers.”

“Then does she flatter herself. Who is she?”

“A neighbor.”

“Bah! the Fausta? The Fausta is it?” Had Fausta been a negress Don Jayme could not have displayed greater contempt. “Why, the Fausta is a Creole, the daughter of a highwayman.”

“Father, she is a flower.”

“Of which you have enjoyed the perfume. Doña Clarisa is a bouquet. The change should be pleasant. Come, Ruis, prepare yourself; in an hour we must start.”

“I have given my word.”

Don Jayme coughed and examined his tapering, yellow fingers. “Then get it back,” he said at last.

“Ah yes, but how.”

Don Jayme coughed again and shrugged his shoulders. Then suddenly he filliped his forefinger and thumb together as were he counting coin. “Send for your horse, Ruis. I will attend to that.” When Ruis returned Don Jayme placed two small yet heavy bags before him. “Offer one,” he said; “it is ample. But should she play the difficult, then give the other too. And Ruis, the road is not always safe; are you armed? At least take this dagger. There, I had forgotten; that there may be no complications, get a receipt.”

Ruis stuck the dirk in his belt and placed the bags in the holster. His father stood watching him on the veranda. “I will wait for you here,” he said, as Ruis mounted; “do not be long.” And as the young man touched the horse with his heel, he called out, “I count on you, Ruis.” He waved his hand to him lovingly. He was in great good spirits; the goal to which for five years he had striven was full in sight.

And Ruis from the saddle answered, “Count on your gold, Don Jayme.”

In a moment he was out of sight, galloping down the road, with only stars and fire-flys to light the way. But of the road the horse knew every inch. And as Ruis galloped he thought of Madrid and its allurements, of the corrida and its emotions, of the Doña Clarisa that was to be his, and of other doñas that he would meet. The future certainly was very bright. As for the present, it was not entirely to his liking. There was an awkward five minutes to pass, but once passed he would shake the red dust from him and never set foot on that road again. Fausta, truly, had been very sweet, and she had beguiled for him many and many an otherwise wearisome hour. But she was like the fruit, which on arriving he had relished. She had lost her savor. I will give her the gold, he thought, the gold and a kiss. The gold will serve for dower and the kiss for farewell.

So mused Don Ruis. He had reached her door, and, as before, at the noise of hoofs she came out with a welcome.

“Ah, Ruis,” she murmured, “I have watched for you the entire day. This morning I went to our Eden, and again this afternoon. Where were you? Ruis, I caught a butterfly, it was like a winged acacia, and I gathered the jasmines you like, and waited, but you did not come. My Ruis, I thought you ill perhaps, yet everything was so fair and still I knew you could not be but well. And, Ruis, as I was leaving, a yellow-breast began to sing. He seemed to bring a message from you. I know it now, it was that you would come to-night. Ruis, forgive my foolish words, it is because my heart is full of love for you. But why do you not dismount? Come, we will stroll there beneath the stars. Do you know, Ruis, with you I am so happy there are moments when I could die of joy. But why do you not speak to me? Is it the night? My Ruis, your face seems changed.”

“Fausta, I have come to say good-bye.”

“Good-bye? Ruis, you jest.”

“No, Fausta, it is not jest. Don Jayme and I return to Spain.”

“To Spain! It cannot be! You said that when you went, we both should go; that I should be your wife.”

“Don Jayme has found another for me.”

“And what of your word, Don Ruis?”

“There, Fausta, it is painful enough. Were it not for Don Jayme, you know—naturally, you know—you know very well what I would do. But see, what would you? It is painful, indeed.”

“Painful? Painful to whom? Not to Don Jayme, nor seemingly to you.”

“Ah, but it is; and see, I have brought you this, and this too.” He took the bags from the holster and held them to her. Yet she made no motion to take them. She stepped back a little, and to the midnight of her eyes came a sudden flash. “How much is in them,” he continued, “I do not know, but it must be like St. Peter’s pence; you can see”—and he affected a little laugh—“they are not light to hold. Truly they must represent a pretty dower, for Don Jayme said—for pleasantry, no doubt—‘Ruis, you will do well to get an acknowledgment.’ ”

“Ruis! He called you Ruis! Your name is Judas.” The girl’s face was always white, but now it was whiter than the moon. The red had left her lips, and her voice, which had been melodious as the consonance of citherns and guitars, grew abruptly harsh and strident. She was trembling from head to foot.

“But will you not take them?” he asked, referring to the bags of money which, awkwardly enough, he still held out to her.

“Get back, Spaniard, into the night from which you came. I gave you love, you bring me gold. I gave my trust, you ask a receipt. You shall have it.” She had moved forward near to him again, and glared in his face.

“But if you refuse the gold, what,” he asked, almost piteously, “what can I give?”

“Nothing save this dirk.”

And before the intention could have been divined, she tore the dagger from his belt and sheathed it in his heart.

“There is my receipt,” she cried.

The bags fell heavily to the ground, and of one of them the canvas burst open and scattered the contents on the ground. Ruis would have fallen too, but with one steadying hand she held him on the saddle, and with the other unwound her scarlet sash. In a moment’s time she had tied him fast; then she gave the affrighted horse a blow and stepped aside. And as she did so the horse veered and rushed up the road, bearing the lifeless Ruis, bound as Mazeppa was, with the dagger still in his heart, to the father who waited his return.

For a little space she listened to the sound of retreating hoofs. She was trembling still.

On the porch the old woman had tottered out. “What was it?” she asked.

“Death.”

“Ave Maria purissima!” croned the hag.

And the girl, turning her back to the darkness in which the horse had vanished, answered, as is the custom, “Who conceived without sin.”

Fausta re-entered the house, but her mother loitered on the porch. The next morning the gold had disappeared.

Madam Sapphira

I

“I told my father that you expected to make a hundred thousand this year. He said he didn’t believe in miracles.”

It was Mrs. Carol Nevius who, from the head of the dinner-table, addressed her husband.

“Did he though! That’s odd, seeing that it has taken a succession of them to keep him out of Sing-Sing.”

Mrs. Nevius laughed. She was a pretty little woman, very well dressed, with a noticeably good manner. And as she laughed it was evident that her father was not one who inspired respect.

“But if you do,” she insisted, “if you make a lot, you will let me entertain, won’t you?”

Nevius shook his head. No, not though it were millions. In the now remote bachelor days he had his fill of society, and while it is colloquial to maintain that those who do not care for society are those for whom society does not care, in his case the argument was invalid. He was too busy to fatigue himself further with futilities and late hours.

His wife was not. She was essentially social, schemingly so, with a dream unfulfilled, yet, perhaps still fulfillable of leadership in the upper four, and so exasperating did her husband’s disinclination for any form of entertainment seem to her, that had you confessed her privately and apart she would have declared illicit commerce as nothing in comparison.

But this was natural. Not until her engagement was announced did society become aware of her existence. Born a Snaith, her people were believed to be rich and known to be common. Her father was an old person of both sexes—possessed of all the vices of woman and none of the virtues of man—a Wall street rat who told untenable stories and insisted on morning prayers. His wife, it was rumored, was of better stock, and in reviewing the documents, it seems difficult for her not to have been. But she had little to boast of. She was a bloodless creature, with a deprecatory manner and a total inability to look you in the face.

To these people two children had been born, both girls. The elder, Frances, became in time the wife of young Montrion who promptly landed her in a set which, while not censorious, has a curious habit of closing its doors on women who leave their own wide open. In what manner and through what circumstances Mrs. Montrion became negligent in regard to her vestibule is not a matter with which the telling of the accompanying episode need be delayed. Suffice it to say that after being urged from one end of the avenue to the other the sufficiency of that urging ceased.

This occurred at the hour when her sister, Hilda, was about to make some form of début. That the latter was thereby materially handicapped goes without phrases. Apart from a handful of school friends, their brothers and lovers, the girl knew no one. It was Mrs. Montrion on whose offices she relied to join the since defunct F. C. D. C., and to tread Assembly floors. It was through her she was to be smiled upon by the Bleeckers, Rewicks and Wainwarings. It was through her she was to grasp those two potential fingers with which Mrs. Amsterdam sealed the advent of the debutante, and just when the frocks were ordered, presto! up and down Fifth avenue one door after another was closing on Mrs. Montrion’s back.

It was hard on the girl, very. But she held her tongue, and the frocks which were to have been worn at routs she wore quite graciously at home. Now and again when her father could be induced to secrete himself, the handful of friends, their brothers and lovers, were asked to break bread at the house; and in return now and again her friends asked her to their own abodes. It was on one of these occasions that she met Carol Nevius.

Nevius was then in his twenty-fourth year. As men go his appearance was not distressing, he was neither effeminate nor beefy, his chin may not have been one which Lavater would have praised, but his features were good, he held himself well, and he dressed as those do who put themselves in West-End hands, and then dismiss the subject. A little before he had taken honors at the Law School, and had been welcomed to the bar by judges to whom his name was evocative of old New York and the early history of Manhattan. Of immediate relatives he had none. His income, derived from a small bundle of bonds and the rental of the Nevius house in Tenth street, was sufficient to enable him to live without toil though not without debts. An existence of that kind not being to his liking he had fought for spurs and won them, so notably even that the cigars he smoked while digesting the Code were paid for from the emoluments of his profession.

His initial encounter with Miss Snaith occurred at a dinner. As the conversation expanded he found himself taking pleasure in the sound of her voice, and presently he discovered that her eyes were so blue they dazzled; that her mouth was perfect the poise of her head delightful; that though slight of figure, she was adorably constructed; that her wit was nimble and her manner subdued. She seemed to exhale all that is good in woman—simplicity, sympathy, sweetness ard strength; manifestly she was pure of mind, of eye and tongue, and before the dinner was done he told himself that her beauty was the least of her charms.

These impressions he kept to himself, but on learning that at her house a cup of tea was to be had any afternoon for the asking, he thanked her with much gratitude and took her at her word the next day.

But was it tea she gave him? Surely there was a philter in that samovar. It was February then, but by the time Lent had come and gone and the spring’s bold emissaries were in the air, such was the potency of that brew that only her people and his poverty prevented him from praying her to become his wife. Try as he might, he could not reconcile himself to her family, and try too as he was able, he could discern none of the cohorts of advancing wealth. And yet the girl was so radiantly fair, so graceful in speech, so gracious in bearing and apparently so unexpectant either of love or betrothal, that he saw no reason why he should cease to quaff that cup. Nor did he cease till spring had gone and summer jumped upon the town.

At the first monition of impending heat the Snaiths were accustomed to desert Fifth avenue for a red chalet at Bronx, a roomy structure standing on grounds that leaned to the water’s edge. Sometimes a poor connection could be lured that way, and sometimes a friend of the girl’s would come unwarned and then take flight, abashed by the speech of that coarse old man, unnerved by the stealthy air and cattish smile of the mother. But as a rule guests were infrequent.

By what means Mr. Snaith was induced that year to try the waters of Sharon is not a part of history, but try them he did, and during his absence Nevius was asked to Bronx. Over that invitation he hesitated and continued to hesitate until after a minute review of recent events he was able to affirm that not once had the girl even alluded to engagement rings. Then he went, and as Mrs. Snaith kept herself aloof, very pleasant he found it.

Of a morning there would be a skurry on horseback through bye-lanes and hedges; when the sun was oppressive there were the poets—Meredith, Bailey, Rosetti, Blunt and Swinburne too; in the late afternoons there were decorous drives over dusty roads, but in the evening there was the moon, the gurgle of waters, the caresses of a midsummer night. There were strains too from that duo in which we have all taken part, and there were monologues, spaced with silence. The moon, the waters, the hush of locusts, the sorceries of the poets, these things are sworn accomplices to adventurous desires, and one morning Nevius awoke, wondering at fate, appalled by it, overcome by a remorse into which a sweetness filtered and declined to go.

When he sought the girl she was not immediately discoverable. It was not until he set out through the grounds that he discerned the white and buttercup of muslin beyond. As he approached she rose from a bed of flowers, and, as he took her hand, her lips parted and she smiled. Never had she looked more fair. Beneath the blue splendors of her eyes were the faintest of circles, but in the gay sunlight she was as fragrant as the flowers she held.

“Wish me good morning,” she admonished. And that office performed she led him to another parterre, where she gathered more flowers and joined them with the first.

“They will do for the table, don’t you think?”

“Hilda, will you marry me?”

She turned to him, a quick, glad look on her face.

“You know that I love you,” he added. “You must know that, or—or—”

Lamely he hesitated. But the girl must have divined his meaning; she made a gesture that dispensed with needless explanations; a little color came to her cheeks, yet her eyes rested bravely in his own.

“Yes, I know, and you too must know how I love you. Carol, I have always loved you; that line in Festus was made for me: ‘My love was perfect from the first, it did not grow as meaner things mature.’ ”

There was no riding that day. Later the girl made avowals sweeter still. To all intents and purposes her life had been but a waiting for him, the preparation and prelude of his coming. There were many things over which she had wondered, but now they were all made clear. She understood music and its meaning. She understood the witcheries of spring, the ripple of the rain, the breath of brooks. She understood at last why the stars had filled her with unrest. She understood when they first met why a bird in her heart had burst into song. It was love, always love; her love appealing to his.

This was very pretty, and of such avowals Nevius became thoroughly avaricious. He, too, was in the festival of youth, and apart from the three or four episodes which inevitably occur to one who moves in certain circles and whose appearance is not distressing, he might have repeated to her everything she said to him. His heart at least was as virginal as her own. If he had taught her the meaning of love, she had shown him the meaning of life. Heretofore he had been ambitious to make a name for himself. Now at once he was ambitious to make a name for her. And with a little perplexity, a little embarrassment, he told her of himself. There was the house, the meager income and his professional hopes.

In view of the fact that the Snaith household was kept on a footing of perhaps fifty thousand a year, and by no means lavishly at that, the girl might readily have dismissed so indigent a suitor. Then, too, in spite of the sweetness and simplicity which she exhaled, she was not one to contemplate with enjoyment such pleasures as are said to reside in surburban flats. But she had faith, less in her lover’s success perhaps than in the possibilities of her father’s money. At the moment, however, she seemed quite content, and a day or two later informed him that her father had arrived and had been approached.

“You are to speak to him after dinner,” she said. “If you were a broker he would love you.” At that period brokers made money. “But you are a lawyer, and he says lawyers are tricky. Come.”

Nevius looked down and away. In regard to trickiness Mr. Snaith’s reputation was indeed above reproach, but in this respect, it surpassed it. Yet, after all, it was not the father he was to marry, nor yet the mother, it was the girl he loved. The entire catalogue of distasteful things which her family represented, faded at thought of her. He looked up and followed her from the verandah to where her people were.

At the entrance of the lovers Mr. Snaith grunted and made for the dining-room beyond. His wife stroked a bloodless hand and asked did it look like rain.

“When I am with Hilda,” Nevius answered, “the sky is always fair.”

“Ah!” exclaimed the lady, by whom that phenomenon had evidently passed unobserved. “Ah! indeed!”

Nevius turned to the girl, she was smiling, the red tip of her tongue just visible, and so adorable was her expression that it was only a proper appreciation of form which prevented him from catching her and smothering her with kisses in his arms.

But in the dining-room the enthusiasm of the moment was forgot. Mr. Snaith broke a raw egg into his soup and refreshed himself with whisky and lithia, a beverage that he declared was tip-top for gout, which statement passing unchallenged he entered into a long tirade against physicians in general and professional men in particular. They were either idiots or scoundrels. “Yes, sir, every damn one of them.” To all of which Mrs. Snaith assented. Then he relapsed into a domineering silence, and some attempt was made at more amiable forms of talk but without sufficient success to cause any needless prolongation of the repast.

When the bowls were brought and the women had gone, Nevius turned to his host. All over him was written the fact that he had seen worse days and never intended to see them again. He was short and obese, with a face like a brandied cherry, and as terrible as vulgarity and ready-made clothes could make him. He looked exactly what he was and nothing worse could be said of him.

“I believe you are aware that I have asked your daughter to be my wife.”

“She has made her bed and she can lie in it,” Mr. Snaith replied.

“Am I to infer that I have your consent?”

“Infer? I don’t know what you infer. She’s got a good home, I don’t see what she wants to leave it for.”

“Doubtless,” answered Nevius, “for the same reason that Mrs. Snaith left her own.”

“That’s nothing to do with it. She’s not fit to be married, I’ve told her mother so. But let’s cut it short. What’s your income?”

“Forty-six hundred.”

“I’lI give her the same as long as I can afford it and not a damn cent more.”

“Perhaps in a year or two it won’t be necessary for you to give anything.”

“So much the better for me then.”

And with that Mr. Snaith left the table and hobbled from the room.

Had Nevius been other than himself, he too would have left the room, Bronx as well. Even the law had not brought him into contact with a boor such as that. For a second it seemed to him that in spite of Hilda and the irreparable he must wash his hands of the whole affair, but in that second Hilda was at his side and led him out to where the red moon was, the gurgling waters, the locust’s hush.

Before the red moon waned white he was reconciled. A girl such as she possesses enchantments which dull regret. And during the prenuptial honeymoon which ensued the only regret he could maintain was that which concerned his position toward her. But for what was the marriage service invented? In the autumn their loves were consecrated by a diligent bishop, and for a while they loitered among the quick of Paris and the ghosts of Rome. When they returned, the house in Tenth street was made habitable, and Nevius threw himself into work as another plunges into dissipation.

A year passed, another, a third, six in all, yet on this particular evening, as Mrs. Nevius from the head of the table questioned him in regard to the possibilities of future income, she was, if not a bounder, as the word is used, still as far from the inner sanctuaries of upper fourdom as when the doors were closing on her sister’s back.

At the time being she had no opportunity of expatiating on this wrong. A servant appeared and announced that Mr. Ablaut was in the drawing-room.

Mrs. Nevius rose from her seat, and her husband, punishing a yawn with a tap of the finger, made for the library.

“If it were Jenny now,” his wife called after him, her eyes half-closed, her chin upraised, “you wouldn’t be in such a hurry, would you?”

II

“I would rather have written Salammbô than have built the Brooklyn Bridge. It was more difficult, and besides it will last longer.”

Mr. “Alphabet” Jones, the novelist, a thimbleful of champagne in his throat, was discoursing to the guests whom Mrs. Nevius had assembled.

“Yes, of course,” interjected Mrs. Anderson, a young woman with the face and manner of a cocotte. “Ah, yes,” and she smiled with an air entendu; “but does literature pay?”

With elaborate manifestations of bewilderment, Jones threw himself back in his chair.

“Pay, Mrs. Anderson? Pay, did I understand you to say? Why, look at Bradshaw. Year in, year out, he clears ten thousand pounds sterling.”

“Bradshaw? Bradshaw?” Mrs. Anderson shook her head vaguely. “Oh, yes, the author of Ben Hur.”

“Ce qu’elle est idiote,” muttered Nevius to Miss Jenny Adulam, who sat at his side.

“Ce qu’elle m’ennuie,” responded that young woman. But her eyes said more than the words conveyed: they complimented Mrs. Anderson with a look of absolute abhorrence.

“What is it?” Nevius asked, who had seen but not understood. “What has she done?”

“I can’t tell you.”

“But you must, Jenny.”

“I can’t; I told Hilda and that’s enough.”

“No, dear Mrs. Anderson,” Jones was saying. “Not Ben Hur; you are thinking of Mr. Gunter. Bradshaw is the author of Rabelais, Tristram Shandy and the Bride of Lammermoor.”

“Yes, yes of course, but then you see I thought he was dead.”

“Not dead, dear Mrs. Anderson, and that is just the point I was seeking to convey. Dead he is not, but departed, for the artist never dies. But how well Scalchi sang last night. Don’t you think her voice must have been changed in the cradle?”

From across the dinner-table Clayton Anderson, a fat man with a beard that concealed the total absence of chin, labored to the rescue of his wife.

“By the way, Jones, that was a nasty criticism the Saturday Review had of your book. Stupid sheet, isn’t it?”

“Stupid? not a bit. Only the year before last it had a most excellent article on manure. It is admirably edited, I assure you.”

“By gad,” snorted Anderson, an appreciative smile on his sodden, good-natured, face. “If I had the editor’s address I’d drop him a line and tell him what you say.”

“Drop it in the sewer, it will get to him in time,” Jones answered, and began anew at Anderson’s wife.

Ablaut, who sat at Mrs. Nevius’ left—James Ablaut, Jr., a large redheaded man, who dripped platitude and exhaled stupidity from every pore, yet the son of a Patriarch and as such supposed to be possessed of social power—grinned contentedly at his truffles.

Mrs. Nevius turned to the novelist: “Tell me,” she said, in reference to an episode which was then occupying not only society but the newspapers of two worlds as well—a husband who, surprising his wife with her lover, had killed the latter almost in the woman’s arms. “Tell me, what do you think of the Ex affair. Is it not terrible?”

“Terrible in its selfishness, yes,” Jones answered. “And still more terrible in its bad taste.”

“We men of the world—” Ablaut, anxious to get an oar in, began, but Jones was too quick for him.

“There’s a plural that is singular. Now, Mrs. Carol, since you do me the honor to ask my opinion, I think it was Ex’s duty to have made himself more attractive to his wife than anyone else could, but having failed, having seen that he failed, the dog-in-the-manger act which he committed was abominable. If any shooting was necessary it was himself he should have shot. But all that sort of thing is out of date and bad form too. A man of the world never sees or hears anything that was not intended for him.

“You think he ought not to have made a fuss then? Well, perhaps; but when a man surprises his wife in that way—”

“He should apologize for the intrusion.”

“And do nothing?”

“Oh, if he really feels the need of satisfaction, he might express some astonishment and say to the lover, ‘Is it possible, sir, that you are embracing that lady without being obliged to?’ A little remark of that kind can be as effective as a bullet and has the advantage of not raising the roof.”

“Stuff and nonsense,” objected Anderson pompously. “This man was a snake in the grass. He was Ex’s friend and under cover of that friendship he led his wife astray. In Ex’s place I should have done the same thing.”

From where Mrs. Anderson sat came a ripple of laughter which silenced her husband strangely. Jones turned to him with serious mien:

“No, dear boy, permit me. A woman is never led astray. She trots, or gallops or bolts astray, but never is she led. Lovelace, Faust, Don Juan, rolled into one, are helpless where virtue is. Besides, in these days a man never makes the first advances, he hasn’t time. It is the woman, always the woman, who—”

“Dear me!” Mrs. Nevius was making a fine show of indignation. “Dear me, are all women as bad as those in your books? Haven’t you ever met any with a conscience?”

“Plenty, Mrs. Carol. Plenty. Some even with two.”

And as the novelist through his shrewd, tortoise-rimmed glasses gazed at his hostess, that lady lowered her eyes.

At the other end of the table Nevius was chatting inaudibly with Miss Adulam, a girl less pretty than fetching, small of feature, with the flush of youth still in her face and about her that intangible something discernible only in the end-of-the-century virgin of higher New York life, that air which, while indicating total incapacity for wrongdoing, indicates also a perfect comprehension that wrongdoing exists; in short, a girl to whom a man may talk without the disheartening dread of seeming to say more than he means. Nevius had known her when she was in short frocks, and a few years previous, encountering her haphazard in Paris, had made her acquainted with his wife. Since then the two had been much together, Mrs. Nevius, who understood perfectly the advantages which a married woman possesses in the companionship of a decorative young woman that can be relied upon to hold her tongue, having grappled her to her heart with hooks of steel.

“So you are not going to Tuxedo,” the girl was saying, though less for information perhaps than for conversation’s sake.

“No, why should I?”

“Hilda goes tomorrow with the Andersons and Ablaut.”

“Ah! I knew nothing of it. I did not even know they were to be here tonight. You either, for that matter. Hilda only told me when I got uptown. But what is this about Tuxedo?”

The girl shrugged a shoulder. “Some party they have made up. You don’t mind?”

“It wouldn’t matter much if I did, I fancy. Though if I seem to, it is only because of Mrs. Anderson, who is common as—as, well, let us say Narragansett Pier.”

“She is your guest,” Miss Adulam murmured.

“Very true.” And for the moment Nevius subsided.

Presently there was a general move to the adjoining room. There Nevius sat with the girl, Jones occupying himself for literary purposes in drawing Mrs. Anderson out, the other men dividing their hostess’ attention. But by eleven, husband and wife were alone.

As the front door closed for the last time, Nevius went over to where his wife was seated.

“I have been having a chat with Jenny.”

“So I saw.”

“What is it that Mrs. Anderson has been doing to her?”

Mrs. Nevius opened her great blue eyes in wonder.

“Doing to her? I am sure I don’t know. What do you mean?”

“Jenny said she had told you.”

“Oh, what nonsense. Dulcibella happened to be a little friendly with her and she went to work and imagined all sorts of things.”

Nevius stared at his wife very blankly.

“I don’t understand. What did she imagine?”

“How do I know? She’s probably got her head farcie with the Deux Amies or some similar twaddle and is capable of imagining anything. Give me a cigarette will you? It’s not worth talking about.”

Nevius went back to the dining-room, but when he returned his face was grave.

“Do you know, Hilda, I wish you would drop that woman. What you tell me is not reassuring, but, independent of that, she has neither manners, breeding nor brains. And how should she! Her grandfather was a Tweedringer, her father the receiver of stolen goods, and yet in the List she has got her maiden name down as Wainwaring; why she is no more a Wainwaring than you are.”

“That is one of her middle names, I think,” Mrs. Nevius answered remotely. “But even otherwise, what does it matter? How can you be so old-fashioned? Nowadays people don’t expect a patent of nobility in everyone they meet; what they do expect is money. Bella has a hundred thousand a year and no one would object if she called herself a Knickerbocker. Besides, is it her fault about her grandfather? I dare say if we got down to bottom facts the original Nevius was no better.”

“The original Nevius was a Latin poet, but that’s neither here nor there. I won’t have her at dinner. She’s a woman with preferences for everybody and attractions for none.”

“She is nothing of the sort, she is very pretty, and anyway there is no use in your picking up Alphabet Jones’ cigarette stumps. He never means a word he says; he talks and talks just for effect. I am tired and sick of him. Did you notice the way he spoke to Ablaut tonight? He doesn’t seem to be aware of the difference in their positions.”

Nevius smiled helplessly and tugged at his moustache. “I think he is, but I am quite sure he would not try to wound Ablaut by referring to it. Here, Michette!”

A black monster, amber of eye, the neck furred like a ruff, the tail fluttering like a banner, gazed through the portière. Leisurely it promenaded a haughty stare, interrogating the escritoire, the pedestalled lamps, the yellow shaded candles, the grave hangings, capacious chairs, cushioned lounges, plants, flowers and knicknacks with which the high-ceiled room was provided. Then, assured that all intruders had gone, it stepped gingerly and circuitously to where Nevius sat and with a sudden purr bounded to his side.

“There Michette, I know all about it. You don’t like strangers any more than I do. Do you, you lobster?”

Michette opened and closed his eyes and purred profusely.

“And you have not the remotest desire to go to Tuxedo, have you?”

A thin smile came and vanished in the corners of Mrs. Nevius’ mouth.

“Did Jenny tell you that, too?”

“That Michette—”

“Don’t be absurd.”

“Yes, she said you were all off tomorrow. I do hope you won’t be gone long.”

“But, Carol, when I am here you see nothing of me. You come in just in time for dinner, and after that you are either talking business or writing letters. Oh, I know what you are going to say—that you are trying to make a fortune—but what good does that do me? I want to go out. I want to entertain and be entertained. I want to lead the life that my friends do; and, instead of that, I might just as well be at Bronx. You won’t go to the opera, you won’t go to the assemblies; last winter you would not even take me to Mrs. Bleecker’s. If once in a century I ask people to dinner, unless you have Jenny on one side of you and Jones within call, you don’t speak. And if it were my friends alone that you snubbed! But you won’t even speak to my own family. There was a time when my mother used to beg me to bring you there. Now she never mentions your name. My father says you cut him in the street. But don’t you know that you are making yourself very well hated? The lecture you have read me about Bella Anderson is all very well, but it would be the same thing in regard to any one else; it always has been. You objected to Viola Raritan, to the Yardes, to the Jerolomons, to this woman, that man and the other. Do you know what I think?”

And Mrs. Nevius, in spite of her manifest indignation, smiled frostily.

“Do you know what I think? You want a wife simply for domestic purposes; to pay the bills, talk to tradesmen, see that the machinery runs smooth; to be your housekeeper by day and your mistress at night.”

“At least I want no other wife than you. It may be selfish, of me to act as I do; no doubt it is, but since I have got into these companies I haven’t a moment.”

Mrs. Nevius, whose cigarette had gone out, relighted it, and for a while puffed meditatively. Presently the cigarette was put aside, her features relaxed, and she looked up at her husband with great amiability.

“There, Carol, forgive me. I am out of sorts. I know you work hard; say the word, and I won’t go to Tuxedo.”

“But Hilda, I am delighted to have you go if it amuses you. The only thing is—”

“Well, what?”

“Your companions.”

“What a goose you are. The Andersons are received. Whatever you may say. Belle is perfectly presentable.”

“Oh I don’t mean to imply that she eats sweets with a spoon; nor was it so much of her I was thinking. Ablaut is all very well in his way, but don’t you think he is too much in yours? Don’t you think if he is tagging after you down there that people will gossip?”

Mrs. Nevius gave a twist to her skirt and laughed for sheer joy.

“You dear thing, are you jealous? Tell me, Carol, are you?”

Nevius tormented the tip of his nose reflectively and glanced at his wife. She looked the embodiment of merriment, of coquetry too, of grace as well, and prettier even, more tantalizing and tentative than in the old prenuptial days. No, he was not jealous and said so.

“Now see,” she continued, straightening herself and distributing wide breezes from an enormous fan. “See how little jealous I am. Every evening while I am away, Jenny is to dine with you.”

“You don’t mean that you asked her!”

“I did then, and she said she would like nothing better.”

“But won’t the servants think it odd?”

Mrs. Nevius gave him a curious, investigating look.

“What are the servants’ thoughts to you?”

“Nothing. It was Jenny I was considering.”

“She cares as little as you do. If I ask her, who is to object?”

“Not I, certainly. Jenny is very sweet, I am very fond of her, and if she comes I shall take it as very kind of her, but she is not you. It is you I want.”

He leaned forward; there was a light in his eyes which she saw and recognized, but before he could reach her she was on her feet.

“There, Carol, behave. I am tired, and besides, anyone would think we were on our honeymoon still.”

III

“This is really delightful of you. I had hardly ventured to hope—”

“If you are going to be formal, Carol, I won’t stay.”

Miss Adulam, preceded by Michette, was entering the drawing-room. Such outer wraps as she may have worn had been laid aside, but her frock, cut sufficiently low in the neck to be suitable for evening wear, had none of the insignia of festival.

And now, as she stood holding a hand to him, there was about her a little simple air of dignity which a princess might seek and got not.

“I won’t be called formal. I am not formal.” And Nevius, raising the hand, touched the wrist with his lips.

From between the curtains at the end of the room a servant appeared, annunciant of dinner.

“But it is good of you,” he continued. “It is worth while to be a bachelor to have such compensation as this.”

Miss Adulam withdrew the hand.

“If Hilda had not insisted I should not be here,” she said; “but she has been so good to me that it seemed stupid to refuse, particularly as it appeared, sir, that if I had, you would not have let her go.”

“Aha! I’m a tyrant now, am I? All the same, Miss, I wish you would try to imply that you are here just a little for me.”

“But I am,” the girl exclaimed. “Really I am. If I were not very fond of you do you suppose I should be here at all?”

“There, that’s something like, that’s my dear old Jenny. Now let’s go in and see what we are to have to eat. But afterward you must play. When I was younger, oh! ever so much younger, I swore a great oath that I would never marry a girl that did not. And Hilda, who did play at the time, has not touched a piano since. Her hand is no longer big enough for the octaves, if you please. That’s the way we men get cheated. There!”

Nevius had seated his guest and taken the seat at her side.

“Put my things here,” he called to the servant, for his place had been arranged at the other end. “And what is there to drink? Champagne and claret? No, I want moselle and seltzer. Serve the champagne to Miss Adulam. You won’t have claret, will you? By George, I believe these are Mumford coves. I take that as being very thoughtful of Hilda. Maintenant,” he added with just a glance to where the servant stood. “Causons. Et nos amours?”

“That’s hardly the expression, is it?” The girl answered in French. “But after all he is so nice that call it what you like.”

“He’s a deuced lucky fellow, that’s all I have got to say about him.”

“Not so lucky, Carol. Not a penny, not one.”

“And what of it? When I married I hadn’t a penny either. But it’s idiocy of him to stick in Texas. He won’t make anything in cattle. That day has gone. This is the era of syndicates and New York is their home. Make him come back, Jenny. I can put him up to any number of things. Nevius and Tredegar! How does that sound?”

“Beautifully. Carol. But Jack won’t do it. You know how obstinate he is; once an idea in his head and only a surgical operation could get it out.”

“And his heart?”

Miss Adulam smiled demurely.

“Anyway,” Nevius persisted, “you have something of your own.”

“Eventually I shall have something; a hundred thousand, perhaps, but not more.”

“But that’s very neat. You could live comfortably on it in Paris and luxuriously in Florence. Of course it’s not much here, and nothing at all in London. And you wouldn’t care to live anywhere else, would you? After all, New York would be a mighty nice place, if it were not for the New Yorkers. Don’t you think so?”

“Here,” he called in English to the servant. “Give Miss Adulam some more champagne, and I want some more seltzer. What is there after this? Quails? I hate quails. Never have them again.”

He turned to the girl.

“Does he write often?”

“Who? Jack? Every day.”

“And what does he say?”

“Mais, Monsieur, vous me demandez des choses!”

“I didn’t mean that.” And Nevius shook with laughter. “Though I can fancy, of course,” he added after a pause, which he purposely made significant.

“You are very impertinent, sir, and I am going home.”

“Yes, of course. And that is just the odd thing; it is always an impertinence to divine a woman’s thoughts. Her wishes passe encore.”

“Why, aren’t you ashamed of yourself?” and the girl turned on him a look which was meant to be quite severe yet was not. “I am afraid Alphabet Jones is corrupting your good manners.”

“Do you know, Hilda said something of the sort last night. By the way, she intimated the other evening that Ablaut was in love with you.”

“Carol!”

“She said something to the effect that he came here more to see you than anyone else. I shall tell Jack, Miss Jenny, mind that.”

With an inappositeness which afterward was to occur to Nevius as curious in the extreme, the girl became abruptly barometric.

“Wasn’t it nice this afternoon, so cold and brisk!”

“Cold? yes, it was certainly that, but I don’t know what your idea of niceness is. It rained pitchforks down town, didn’t it rain here? Why, Jenny, you are crying!”

But not a bit. The phantoms of twin tears had come and gone. Miss Adulam was mistress of herself at once.

“Poor Jack,” she murmured.

“Why, you foolish thing,” expostulated Nevius with much noise and indignation. “Damn Jack. No, forgive me, I didn’t mean that. I don’t know what I meant. I was only jesting anyway.”

“What’s all this,” he cried furiously at the servant. “Carry it all away and serve the coffee in the other room.”

“Come, Jenny,” he added in another tongue and milder tone. “Let’s have a cigarette in English.”

Michette, who lay, a ball of fur, before the fire, stared indolently at their approach, then, his back arched, his tail full as a bludgeon, made crab-like zigzags across a rug.

“I know what you want, you lobster, you want some music to dance to.”

And presently, the coffee disposed of, Nevius and Miss Adulam took seats at the piano and played a succession of resounding duets.

Whether Michette accompanied them with pirouettes and entrechats is not a part of history. The duets continued until, during a wonderful series of resounding accords, there came a ring, and Miss Adulam stood up.

“Thank you, Jenny. That went off very well, didn’t it? And you will come tomorrow? You are sure it doesn’t bore you?”

In a brotherly fashion he drew the girl to him and kissed her pure brow.

“Miss Adulam’s maid.”

A portière had been drawn. The servant entered and disappeared.

“Yes, certainly, I will come.”

Nevius followed her to the hall, aided her with her cloak, accompanied her to the cab, and, as he reentered the house, told himself that it would not be a bad idea at all to see what effect a letter from him might have on the obstinacy of Miss Adulam’s lover.

IV

A week passed. Once Nevius read of his wife’s presence at the country club to which she had gone, and once she wrote. But the letter was brief, relating mainly to household affairs and conveying but meager details as to the writer’s occupation and environments.

Meanwhile Miss Adulam had been almost as good as her word. She had dined at Tenth street twice and on the intervening Sunday had lunched there as well.

On that evening Nevius dined with Michette. The cat was loquacious, but its loquacity was not of the interruptive order, and as it monologued interminably on what seemed to be the same subject, Nevius felt bored. As a relief, the cloth removed, he wrote to his wife.

That pleasure at an end, the boredom returned, loneliness as well, and for companionship’s sake he looked in at the Athenaeum club where he ran into Alphabet Jones and managed to kill an hour.

“I hear you are making money,” the novelist between two whiffs remarked. “I hear you have enough to burn.”

“I wish I had. No, I may have to go to Chicago in a day or two, I am afraid even that I may have to go abroad.”

“It wouldn’t frighten me a bit if I had to. Will your princess go too?”

“Oh, of course.” And Nevius nodded with an air of assured conviction. “But how is the Muse? What are you writing now?”

“Cheques, dear boy,” Jones answered negligently. “Cheques, that’s all.”

“I thought you had something on the stocks.”

“Stocks is the word. The pillory comes later.”

“Your books are too confounded cynical. Alphabet. The public don’t like it.”

“But did I invent human nature?” And the novelist looked at his friend with an air ruminant and bovine in its innocence.

“I don’t believe,” retorted Nevius, “I don’t believe at all that it is human nature for women to act as they do in your books. Anyone might think that New York was peopled with demireps.”

“Perhaps. But then you see every one isn’t blessed as you are.”

“No, that’s a fact, I admit. But even so, what is the use in choosing such subjects?”

“I choose a subject! Why, dear boy, a writer, if he happens to be worth his syndicate, never chooses a subject. The subject chooses him. He writes what he must, not what he might. That’s a thing that the public can’t understand. The secret of any work of value lies in the harmony existing between the subject and the author. And even then his one chance of success consists not only in yielding to the subject but in caressing it. Every artist knows that. Flaubert has rung his changes on it a thousand times.

“Oh, well, if you bring up your heavy artillery I surrender. After all I don’t mean to abuse you.”

“But I love to have you. The next time you have a moment skim over a history, and then come and tell me the name of one man of ability who has not been abused. And the greater the ability, the greater the abuse. It is the tribute that failure pays to success. Mediocrity is never discussed, and, being unforgiving, resents it. As for my books, if they please no one, doubtless they are poor, but if they pleased everybody I should consider them rot. Vox populi, vox stulti. The majority is always wrong. What would a Scotch and soda say to you?”

“That I am vile and vicious I suppose. No thanks. I think I will be getting home.”

“By the way, if you and Madame go abroad, will Ablaut and Miss Adulam join you?”

“No, why should they?”

Jones lit a match and fumbled for a cigarette. “Are you sure you won’t have anything? Where is that devilish case gone now! Ah, yes, here it is.”

“Why did you ask?” Nevius repeated.

Jones glanced about the room. “For no reason, dear boy,” he murmured apologetically. “For no reason. I had got to look upon you all as a family party, don’t you see, and it occurred to me that—that—it occurred to me—”

Irritated by this mummery and hesitation. Nevius got from his seat. “I don’t know what can have occurred to you, but if you fancy for one instant that anything, even platonism, exists between Ablaut and Jenny Adulam, I may just as well tell you that you are off, ‘way off.’ ”

“I should think so;” and Jones smiled in his beard. “No, indeed. Wait a second, dear boy. No, indeed, I never gave the matter a thought. But that subject of platonism now is really very interesting. Speaking in the abstract of course, I believe in it, but not as you do. I think that the affection a nice girl may have for a man who is neither her brother nor her lover, a man I mean with whom she is constantly thrown in contact, is often of that order. But it is different with the man. It seems to me that however pure at heart he may be, however honest in intention, nature is apt to resent that negation of sex. And it is for that reason that platonic affection, or, more exactly, reciprocal platonism, is discoverable only among married people. Nature having had her way, has no slights to resent, and occupies herself, if at all, in directing the attention of the parties to the possibility of other enterprises. In such circumstances there are women who, noting in their husbands a decreasing desire for the pleasures of the tête-à-tête, appeal to the courts. There are others astute enough to understand that it is not in the nature of man to subsist on a single dish, and sufficiently refined not to give that bit of information to the newspapers. But there are also women whose fastidiousness is such that they are the first to desire a change in the menu. When this occurs there are husbands that return to the animal state and shriek for blood; there are others of finer breed who collaborate with their wives in an effort to observe the courtesies and amenities of civilized life while agreeing that individual tastes shall suffer no interference. Now there you have true platonism, the ideal state in which the ancients instructed us, the—”

“Ideal state of pigsty,” Nevius gruffly interrupted. “What’s all this rubbish you are rehearsing on me?”

Amused and vatic, Jones set about polishing an eyeglass.

“Rubbish, is it, dear boy? Well, perhaps; but then we have been merely exchanging ideas. Do have a liquor.”

“No. I’m off. Good night.”

Jones watched him go and nodded confidentially to himself. “Le ménage a trois, c’est encore joli. Mais à quatre! Non, c’est d’un pur!”

V

Mrs. Carol’s return was unheralded. One evening after a dinner at the Downtown Club. Nevius found her entrancing as an angel, but far better garbed, outstretched in the drawing-room. From beneath the hem of the skirt the gold clockwork of a stocking glistened, the blue eyes that met his own were languid and sultry, and as he bent over to kiss her there rose to greet him the fresh odors of iris and of health.

“There, don’t muss me up.”

Unabashed Nevius drew a chair to where she lay, and taking her hand held it in his own.

“I can never tell you how glad I am. And I have wanted you so. You enjoyed yourself, I hope. Tell me all about it. Are you glad to be back?”

Mrs. Nevius withdrew the hand he held, and with two fingers patted a yawn.

“Of course I am glad to be back. Carol, do be careful,” she admonished, for he had bent toward her again. “There’s some one there. Of course I am glad to be back. I hate living in a trunk. What is it, Rebecca?”

The servant had entered; a note on a tray.

“A letter for you, mem. And there’s an answer, mem.”

Nevius moved his chair. His wife stood up and went forward to a lamp. There she turned.

“You are not going out, are you?”

And as Nevius shook his head, she made a motion to the servant.

“I will ring.”

The woman left the room, and Mrs. Nevius, seating herself at the escritoire, busied herself with pen and paper.

“Whom is it from, Hilda?”

The question must have entangled her thoughts. She took the sheet on which she was writing, tore it up and tossed it aside.

“How can I write if you keep talking to me?” she asked almost piteously. “It’s from Frances.”

Frances was her sister, Mrs. Montrion, and as Nevius gathered up the Post and tried to lose himself in the advertisements, the name evoked a series of incidents that were not at all to his taste. There was the liaison with a dyspeptic boor, which, however, had interested him remotely, if at all, until Mrs. Montrion took it into her head to have herself and the cavaliere servente chaperoned by Hilda during a trip abroad. At that he had rebelled, and his rebellion had not been lessened on learning the object, which was to enable the Snaiths, during Mrs. Montrion’s absence, to secure evidence against that lady’s husband, whereby she might obtain a divorce and marry her lover. But the plot had fallen through. Montrion was not a man to be trifled with, and his wife grew timorous of results. Then, too, the cavaliere servente after the fashion of his kind, had bestowed his services elsewhere. The subject was not agreeable, and to dismiss it Nevius tried to lose himself in the columns of the Post. Before he succeeded, the answer was written, dispatched as well, and Hilda returned to the sofa.

Nevius threw the paper aside. “If you are glad to be back,” he began with a bad attempt at banter, “at least you are not enthusiastic.”

“But what do you expect? Here I am tired out, and besides after what you wrote I thought you would be on your way to Chicago.”

“Yes, I remember. But I found it was not necessary and I am glad now it was not. I only wish you had wired. If I dined down town it was only because it is less appalling than the house when you are gone.”

Mrs. Nevius smiled with bright frostiness.

“But you have had Jenny all the time. Dear me, Carol, what do you want? A seraglio?”

And as though in challenge, she raised a fan and unfurled it with a sudden click.

Nevius shook his head.

“It is not nice of you to speak that way. It’s not like you either. You know that I want no one but yourself.” As he spoke he bent toward her, but before he could touch her, Mrs. Nevius moved, and shoving him gently enough aside, sat upright, smiling still.

“Listen to me, Carol, how long have we been married? Nearly seven years. Now, tell me, don’t you think that in seven years a woman may get just a little tired of that sort of thing.” In her great blue eyes interrogations floated, and in the corners of her mouth was a candor which would have delighted Greuze. “For I am. And if you are not,” she added with a gesture so wide that it took in all New York, “there are so many other women who would like nothing better.”

Nevius was on his feet. Into his face had come a look which his wife had seen before, and at which, mentally, she retreated. But before he could speak, she was at his side, her arms about his neck, her lips on his.

“Dear,” she murmured. “Couldn’t you see that I was jesting. Don’t you know it, Carol? Don’t you know that if I thought you could look at another woman it would break my heart?”

With both hands on his shoulders she held him a little from her, and with a pathos that seemed charged with love and grief eternal, gazed into his face.

“Tell me?”

“I suppose so,” he answered, though with a thoroughly masculine sigh. “But then, whatever I may do or leave undone, you come always first.”

Mrs. Nevius’ eyes lighted visibly. She led him back to where they had sat and for a while very sweetly discussed with him matters of common interest. At last she stood up again, declaring that it was late.

“I am going,” she announced. “Are you coming presently?”

Nevius led her to the door and drew the portière that she might pass.

“And Carol, when you come don’t forget the gas.”

The portière fell again. Nevius returned to the Post. There was an editorial which he read unheedingly. From a cablegram he learned of an epidemic in the Orient. From another that an English duke had died without an heir. A paragraph in the financial column interested him. There was a statement which concerned his own interests. He got out a notebook and studied some figures; an idea in connection with them occurred to him, and at the desk he jotted down some memoranda which he recopied and tearing up the draft put the copy in his pocket. He looked at the clock, the half hour which he had given himself had gone and he went upstairs, the gas forgot.

The following afternoon, on returning to the house, he went directly to his own room. At the office he had found that the memoranda were not in his pocket. In ordinary circumstances he would have recalled the substance of any such paper unaided, but in this instance subsequent episodes had driven the purport from his mind. Not in his bedroom, however, nor in his dressing-room, was the paper to be found. He questioned the housemaid; she had no information to impart. Where is the housemaid that ever had? After all, he reflected, it was not a matter of life or death, and if it were lost, was it not as Hilda had often said, because he was fiendish in his carelessness? And he was about to give the matter up when he remembered that he had first made a draft which he had torn and thrown aside. There was a chance that the housemaid had left the scrapbasket undisturbed and, presently, after getting into evening dress, he went to the drawing-room below.

The lights were lit, on the table was the Post; there, against the wall, was the escritoire of lacquer work and brass on which he had written, and beside it a basket of beribboned velvet. One glance was sufficient, the contents had not been touched, and, emptying them, he began to arrange them on the desk. Yes, they were all there. In a moment he had them not only in proper position, but with three pieces of paper to spare. These he would have brushed away, but something on one of them caught his eye—Dearest J—, written in his wife’s hand. But what preceded the adjective, or what had followed the J, there was nothing to tell. The second scrap was larger, and on it was written he has not go—; on the third were two words and a fraction that must have come from the middle of a sentence—can’t see y—.

Nevius stared at these little papers and, as he stared, all interest in his own memoranda evaporated.

He looked again in the basket. It was quite empty. Whether the other bits of that letter had fallen, not in the basket, but on the floor, and had then been swept away, he did not try to determine. Enough remained. The J, of course, was Ablaut—Jimmy, as he was familiarly called. As for the rest, a child could have supplied the missing words—He has not gone to Chicago; I can’t see you tonight.

And this was Hilda! For a while he sat, staring at the scraps, conscious only that he was suffering, endeavoring even to delude himself into a belief that some explanation might set this horrible thing aright. But little by little, as the impossible merged into the actual, the understanding came to him that the worst that could be done had been done, and he ceased to suffer. It was time to act.

From the stair came a rustle of silk, the sound of a footfall that he knew. As yet he had no plan. But as he became aware that Mrs. Montrion’s sister was entering the room he stood up. His lips may have been a trifle compressed, but otherwise he had his everyday air; he looked well groomed, sedate, anxious, if at all, merely that dinner should not be too long delayed.

Mrs. Nevius passed through the curtains, the light shuttling her hair, illuminating the rose of her mouth. In her blue eyes were evocations of summer, and beneath them, on her cheeks, on the lobes of her ears, health had placed its token in pink. She was adorably dressed, adorably constructed, and dressed and constructed to be adored. In one hand was a fan, in the other a fold of her gown. At sight of her husband she smiled.

Nevius stayed her with a question.

“What was it that Frances had to say that was so important last night?”

With that motion which a swan has, Mrs. Nevius turned her head and for a moment seemed lost in the query. But at once she must have recollected.

“Nothing. The address of a milliner. How are tilings in the Street?”

“And you gave her the address, did you?”

“Of course, I did. Why? But what do you mean by asking all these questions?”

“And you found it necessary to add that I had not gone to Chicago, and that you couldn’t see her, didn’t you?”

Mrs. Nevius’ big blue eyes seemed to grow bigger and bluer, but to her face came a flush with which health had nothing to do.

“You found it necessary to add that, didn’t you?”

The fan she held, she opened and closed.

“I am sure,” she said at last, “I don’t understand—”

“Look.”

At the invitation, at the gesture which accompanied it, she crossed the room, peered down at the scraps, at the basket from which they had come, at the rug and floor. When she raised her head she turned on her husband a look of absolute scorn and, straightening herself, confronted him.

“You, you, Carol Nevius, condescend to rumble through waste papers! A scullery-maid might do such a thing, a gentleman—never.”

“Ah? Perhaps. But it was not for sociological information that I asked you to look at these things. It is because they are addressed to Ablaut, who, I see, is your lover.”

Mrs. Nevius stepped back. In her face had come an expression which a princess might assume to a lackey who had dared to question her. Then at once, as in a storm, a sky of buttercups and forget-me-nots will suddenly appear, the indignation vanished and she laughed outright.

“Why, you great goose, that was written to your Jenny.”

And as Nevius contented himself with staring at her. “But how,” she cried, “how is it possible for any one to be such an idiot as you are!”

“I don’t see—”

“Then you shall. On our way to town Mrs. Manhattan offered me a box for next Friday. I thought I could get you to take both Jenny and myself. Last night before you came in I sat down to write to her. I told her of the offer, and referring to you I said, ‘If he has not got anything on hand I can’t see yet but that we may persuade him.’ Then I heard you at the door, and determined I would ask you first. But did you give me time? Did you? Was ever a woman mauled as I was? Aren’t you ashamed of yourself? No, but aren’t you?”

“Will you forgive me?”

He was very penitent, very meek, very happy, and as his wife pretended to look as though she were not quite sure whether forgiveness could be granted to such a sinner, he caught her in his arms.

“Oh Carol!” muttered that aggrieved little woman, freeing herself as best she might. “How can you be so dreadful! Some one’s there.”

Between the curtains Rebecca stood in silent announcement of dinner.

VI

For several days Nevius saw little of his wife. At no time had she been visible when he left the house, and now when he returned there seemed to be always some one at dinner. The cloth removed, he sought the library, a room on the second floor which separated his apartment from hers. By day it was gloomy, for light reached it from above but at night it was pleasant and very still. Lined on three sides with books, it was furnished with a wide table, easy chairs, a hanging lamp, and a sofa large as a bed. Here Nevius passed his evenings. Time was valuable to him just then; he had more documents to examine than he could handle at his office, and many a letter to read and write. Later, the work at an end, he would go in search of his wife, but in those days she must have been overfatigued; her door was locked.

This regimen made him morose. That the effect was noticed is presumable. One evening he was gratified with the intelligence that he was to dine alone with Hilda, and incidentally that there was a surprise in store. What was it? Ah, voila! If she told, where would the surprise be?

In his delight at recovered companionship Nevius promptly forgot all about that surprise; during the service of the courses he talked of his plans and projects as he had not had the chance to talk for ages before, and when the meal was done and they had gone to the other room there was a caress in his manner which Mrs. Nevius understood.

“Now, Carol,” she admonished, as he took a seat at her side. “Do behave, it’s immoral, there’s no other word for it.”

“Immoral!”

“If it is not immoral then, it’s worse. It is bourgeois.”

From the past there floated to him memories of the old prenuptial days, when there had been no question of ethics, no question of customs, nothing in fact save a frank abandonment to love and life. But to those days he was incapable even of an allusion.

“It is not nice of you to talk like that,” he answered. “You accused me some time ago of picking up Jones’ cigarette stumps; a speech such as yours smacks of Mrs. Anderson a mile away. I have begged you so to drop her.”

“Oho! I’m not nice, eh?” And Mrs. Carol nodded and smiled seductively. “Wait till you see. Now tell me, how have you been passing your evenings?”

“Very badly.”

“But how, I mean. What have you been doing?”

“Writing letters.”

“And how long has it taken you?”

“Two or three hours.”

“Precisely. Now if by any combination of circumstances I were able to shorten those two or three hours into one, and mind I only say If, but if I were, would I be nice or would I not?”

To these propositions Nevius assented. “Very good, will you come with me for a moment.”

Mrs. Nevius led him to the floor above and threw open the library door. Seated at the table was a young woman of that type of blonde beauty which only a sight of creates in the average man a desire to jump straight down the possessor’s throat. As the door opened she rose from her seat, and with a gesture, perhaps of embarrassment, her hand went to the side of her head and busied itself with a curl.

Mrs. Nevius looked at the girl, and in a little voice, which was used only on particular occasions, affably, from the tips or the lips, she murmured:

“This is Mr. Nevius, Miss Vührer.” Then with a glance that stripped Miss Vührer from neck to heel, she turned to her husband.

“Miss Vührer is a stenographer. Oh, quite an expert, I believe. Miss Vührer thinks she can be of great assistance to you. If you have any letters tonight, why not let Miss Vührer show you her abilities?”

Whether or not this projection of peaches and cream into the privacy of the library caused Nevius pleasure or displeasure, not even a lady who was eying him could decide.

“Certainly,” he answered, but he spoke in the matter-of-fact way which he brought into all business transactions. “Certainly, I make no doubt that Miss Vührer is competent, and I shall be glad of her assistance. Let me see. Yes, I have several letters. Perhaps—”

“I will leave you then.”

With a sweet little bow to the young woman, Mrs. Nevius backed from the room and closed the door.

“Perhaps you will sit down, Miss Vührer. Yes, you might sit there, please. You have everything you require?”

Miss Vührer, a pad in her hand, a row of sharpened pencils before her, resumed her seat. Nevius dropped on the sofa, and after a glance at some papers, which he had taken from his pocket, began:

“Waters and Rivers, Wabash Avenue, Chicago, Illinois, Dear Sirs:—In reply to yours of the 18th I have to inform you that—”

And so on and so forth. For an hour the dictation continued uninterrupted, save by pauses of thought, and the tick of the clock on the mantel. Once Nevius heard the door bell ring, and once he found himself scrutinizing this blonde young creature, who rarely turned her eyes to him. The letters done, he stood up.

“Thank you, Miss Vührer, that will do. If you will copy out what you have, I can sign later on.”

He left the room and went down the stairs. On the way he caught the sound of a voice, which, musical as the squawk of a bicycle he recognized at once, and on reaching the hall, picked up his hat and coat. But his step had been heard, his movements perhaps divined, there was a jostle of portière rings, and before he had got his arms well into the coat, Mrs. Carol was at his side.

“You are not going out, are you? Do come in. It’s only Ablaut, you don’t mind him.”

“Not in the least, but I do mind his carrying off my best umbrella every time it rains, and I wish you would tell him so too.”

“Oh, pooh! Who’s afraid of you? Tell me,” and Mrs. Carol came closer to her husband. “What do you think of her?”

“Miss Vührer? She is very pretty.”

“Is she really!”

The air of surprise which Mrs. Nevius assumed could not have been dissimilar to that which the Duchess of Burgundy exhibited, when she learned that other women had five fingers like herself.

“Is she really! I didn’t notice. How queer men are! But do come in.”

“No, not just now. I have an odd feeling in my head, a walk will do me good.”

And bending toward his wife he received from that lady a rapid and noiseless peck.

When Nevius returned Miss Vührer was about to leave. The drawing-room was dark and untenanted. He opened the door for the girl, wished her good night, and went in search of his wife. But Mrs. Nevius must have already retired. There was no answer to his knock.

VII

Meanwhile nothing further had been said about Mrs. Manhattan’s box. Mrs. Carol may have abandoned the project, and as for Nevius, the matter had passed from his mind. He had other things to think of. One evening he returned to the house later than usual; he was tired and looked cross. On entering the drawing room he found his wife already there. At the moment he said nothing, contenting himself with staring at her. Her gown was an artful combination of silk and tulle, colorless yet silvery, and in it, with a large fan and a low bodice, very delightful she was to behold. About her were the incendiary and not altogether definable emanations which the well sent-out of her sex not infrequently exhale, but of which she had made a study. There are women, few indeed, but there are women who merely in raising their arms define the reason of love, and Mrs. Nevius was one of them. The costume, however, and its attendant charms were not, Nevius understood, intended solely for his own delectation. A festival of some kind was imminent.

“Aren’t you going to dress?”

As Mrs. Nevius spoke, the tips of her lips just moving, her chin a trifle advanced, her eyebrows arched, the blue splendors of her eyes dilating, she might have sat for Spring pouting at Winter.

With the sans-gêne of a married man, Nevius dropped in a chair.

“Anyone would think I had shot you,” she added, after a pause which she made populous with interrogations.

Nevius straightened himself.

“How long will it take you to pack?”

“Two months.”

“Hilda! do be serious.”

“Two months I tell you. Not a minute less. But what has happened? I give you my word you look as though you had been studying the extradition treaty. What’s gone wrong?”

“I go to Paris tomorrow and I want you to go too.”

To this Mrs. Nevius made no reply unless the click of a fan may be so accounted.

“The Board of the Interocean Canal met today and they want me to go. In fact I have to. The stockholders, in spite of De Lesseps, are all there, and the Board needs more money. How much God only knows, and when I say God only I exaggerate—”

“Don’t be coarse,” Mrs. Carol interjected, but she spoke mechanically, her thoughts afar.

“I have the ticket, a cabine de luxe; it is big enough for three. Rebecca could get such things as you need in shape in no time. And it would be so sweet,” he added.

This conclusion was allowed to pass unnoticed. With a gesture which was habitual to Mrs. Carol when called upon to think quickly, she raised a hand to her forehead. On one finger a great jewel glistened, but not more so than the fingertip. When she lowered it her face was almost apathetic.

“It would be so sweet of you, Hilda.”

Mrs. Nevius dropped her fan, patted a fold of the skirt, and, as though reflecting still, crossed to where he sat.

He was on his feet at once.

“I knew you would!” he cried, and caught her to him.

“How long are you to be gone?”

“Oh,” he answered eagerly, “the time to get there and turn around.”

Mrs. Carol freed herself.

“Dinner has been announced. Let us go in.”

“Yes, and let’s have some champagne. Do you remember the St. Marceau we used to get? Do you remember the little restaurant we went to one night on the other side of the Seine? Do you remember—”

The memories of other days returned, too abundant, too fragrant, too sacred even, for enumeration while the servant was there. But during the progress of the meal there was plenty of animation in that room, many a jest and many a laugh. The jests, however, came from him. Mrs. Carol smiled and nodded, and nodded and smiled, but otherwise her contributions to the gaiety were slight. At last they moved again to the adjoining room. There, when they had got seated, she took his hand in hers.

“Carol, I can’t go.”

Surprise, annoyance too, lifted him from the seat.

“Now wait.” With but a gesture she had him back again. “If you insist I will obey you, but—”

“Obey me, why—”

“But it will be very selfish of you. I am not a bagman’s wife, Carol. I can’t leave New York at a moment’s notice. In spite of your attitude I have some small position in society. I have engagements to keep, duties to which I must attend. I have my friends, my family. What would they all say? But supposing I were to go. Who would look after the house? When I got back it would be in rack and ruin. You’re to be gone but a few weeks. Surely after nearly seven years you can do without me for that space of time. And I would only be in your way. But look at it from a different point. Supposing, as many a woman has, I not only refused to go, but refused to let you. Whereas I am going to do everything to get you off comfortably, and not only that, but I shall be on the dock to welcome you home. Only on one condition though—”

And as he manifested no earthly interest in the condition, as he looked sulky and very cross, she twisted about in such a manner that he was obliged to notice her, and repeated tentatively and seductively:

“Only on one condition though—”

“Well, what condition then?” he finally snarled.

But Mrs. Carol was very patient that evening; very tender. She stroked him much as she might a big baby.

“That you promise, no, but faithfully and honestly promise to be back in six weeks.”

By way of answer Nevius bit his lip.

“And see,” she continued, “I was going to Mrs. Usselex’ tonight. I was going to make you take me too. Yes, whether you liked it or not. But Mrs. Usselex have to do without me. Why, Carol, I wouldn’t leave you tonight, no not to sup with the queen.” She touched a bell.

“Rebecca,” she ordered when the servant appeared. “There was a cab to be here at eleven. Countermand it, and tell Miss Vührer not to wait.”

These commands distributed she turned again to her husband.

A glance was enough to tell her that his annoyance had gone, that presently he would accept the situation, its logic as well, and with some inward approbation of her own prowess she stood manfully to the guns.

“You can do so many little things for me, too, Carol. I want corsets of that woman in the Rue de la Paix. I want gloves from the Louvre and lingerie from Doucet. If you tell the corset woman I want six more like the last she will understand. And you must order them as soon as you get there. Corsets take forever. And the gloves—but I had best make a list. You won’t lose it, will you? Oh, if it were April now how I would jump at the chance. In the winter Paris gives me the horrors. You must be good, though; no flirtations, rien des horizontales. Do you hear?”

Yes, he had heard; he gave the required promise, but absently, his eyes on the rug.

“And you must take good care of yourself, too. You mustn’t tire yourself out, and catch one of those horrid Paris fevers. If you did, though,” she added after a moment, “how I would fly to you!”

The words were nothing. But in the intonation, in the expression of anxiety her face took on, there was a tenderness, a solicitude, an affection so sincere and abiding that Nevius felt ashamed.

It was selfishness, he reflected, to wish her to accompany him on a disagreeable trip, and it was surly of him now that he saw the selfishness of the wish to sit staring at the intricacies of the rug. But still, though he said nothing, his face spoke for him and presently when he put his arm about her Mrs. Nevius felt that the battle was won.

VIII

Save in New York, and in the antipodes, the early winter is rarely pleasant. But when Nevius reached Paris the sky was white as tin and in the air that sparkle which Fifth avenue knows in March.

He descended, to use an idiom of the land, at a small hotel in the Rue Castiglione, where he was greeted as only those are who are magnificent with small coin.

“Seigneur! I who dreamed of Monsieur the night of the day before yesterday. No, it does good to the eyes to again see Monsieur. And Madame? She carries herself always well? Ah, how I am content! God of gods, to say that I of it have dreamed!”

It was the janitress, obese and fulsome, welcoming him in the excesses of her tongue.

“And Baptiste? It is there he is. The trunks of Monsieur to the number 12, and let it not loiter. And hey!” she cried with much haughtiness to an interloper who had opened the cab-door and was now officious in the transfer of the luggage, “And hey, species of calf’s head marined in mud, go, I pray you, a little that way and see if I there am.”

Number 12, in which Nevius presently found himself, was a yellow suite, where he had brought his wife on each of their visits to Paris. Though two years had passed since the last trip, apparently nothing had happened to it, it was as ornate and trivial as before. He had but to close his eyes and fancy her calling to him, as she was wont to do from the room beyond, and, for a while, in an absurd, canary-covered armchair he sat reminiscent.

The journey over had been uneventful, as such journeys ever are. There was the usual number of merry commercial gentlemen in the smoking-room, and on deck, blanketed in sedan-chairs, the usual quota of unalluring dames. Apart from a man whom he remembered but whose name he could not recall, he had barely exchanged a word with anyone. But then, he had not been well. On the second day out the curious sensation of a lancinating burn had come and gone, leaving him perplexed as to the cause, yet mindful of an anterior, though less acute attack. On the morrow there was nothing, a heavy feeling merely, which he attributed to the effects of the sea, and which remained with him until the voyage was done.

And now, as he sat in the little sitting-room, he felt he was ill, yet after the fashion of men to whom illness exists only through hearsay, he refused to admit it. He would dine, he told himself, and look in at the Comedie. For though be objected to theatres in New York, there was no weariness to him in that home of perfect acting and perfect French.

Contrary to precedent, the prescription did him good. On the morrow he awoke, if not alert, at least refreshed, and after a breakfast of coffee and the Figaro—in which he learned that Mr. Cleveland had the Constitution of the United States tatooed on his back—he went to the corset woman, across the way to Doucet, afterward in search of gloves to the Louvre, and it was only these matters attended to, that he bethought him of the duties which had brought him to France.

Business in that country is not transacted with the same dash which has made the success of our own. The agents whom Nevius visited were not to be hurried. There was a preliminary plenitude of form to be observed, punctuated, it is true, with abundant promises. But the Canal Company, albeit in its quality of corporation, without a soul, had, nevertheless, a stomach, and Nevius was fully aware that that stomach was not to be fed and be filled on the faith of tomorrow’s baked meats. Yet beautifully clear was it made to him that it was precisely on food of that kind that the company would have to subsist until a general meeting could be called and terms arranged. Meanwhile, the agents would be only too glad to have him breakfast with them, dine with them and sup, as well.

Under the diligent supervision of friends encountered and recovered, a week was helped away without any abuse of these offers. The corset woman, he found, was not as dilatory as she had been represented; already a package of her wares had come, another from Doucet, too. As for the gloves, long since they had been in his keeping. The machinery in the agent’s office was at last at work, and in a fortnight, so far as he was then capable of determining, there would be nothing to prevent his return.

On the morning of the ninth day after his arrival there came to him, with the coffee and the Figaro, a batch of letters postmarked New York. Among them was one of blue paper, stamped with the Nevius crest, directed in his wife’s familiar hand. Oh, he had been awaiting it, calculating when it would arrive, devoured by impatience, hoping even that tide and weather favoring, it might reach him the day before. But now it had come, and letting the other letters lay where they were, he opened it, his eyes glad and eager.

“Dear Carol:

“I have bad news for you, or, at least what seems bad to me. Your whole affair with that woman has come out. My father has been told, and he says that if I do not come to him at once he will disinherit me. Precisely what course he will pursue I do not know; indeed since I first learned of your conduct I have been so dumb and crushed that the family have seen that I am incapable of acting for myself, and have taken the matter entirely out of my hands. But, independent of them, I know that you will agree with me, that it is best that we should part. For years we have led different lives; you never would take me anywhere; your pleasures were your own, not mine. But I will not reproach you. I know your nature, and how you resent interference. Hereafter there will be no one to bother you. A bachelor’s life, without ties or duties, is what you prefer. As for myself, I may tell you that a more wretched, brokenhearted woman does not exist. In separating myself from you, I say goodbye to so much—to my wasted years, to my ruined youth, to love, to happiness and to life. But it must be said, and in such grief as you would pity could you see, I say it. So soon as I am able I leave this empty and dishonored house; there are other women that will come to you in it, be truer to them than you have been to me. I can write no more, my eyes are blinded with my tears.

“Hilda.”

When Nevius finished this curious communication he neither changed color nor fainted away. But he did rumple it a little and then smoothed it out and read it again. It is a trick, he told himself, a forgery, a practical joke. But where was the trickster capable of perpetrating a jest such as that? “She must be mad,” he reflected. “What affair of mine has come out? Why must she go to her father. Why is she dumb and crushed? Why—why—why—?”

But ask questions of canary-colored furniture in a Paris hotel and see how communicative it is. Yet to the soul that is sinking Hope throws a straw. With the idea that something in the other letters might convey a clue to the mystery he ran them over. One was from the Canal Company. He threw it down. Another was from his broker; he tossed it aside. A third was from Chicago; he let it lie unopened. But the fourth was more promising; in one corner it bore the neat imprint of the Athenaeum Club and it was covered with the oblique scrawl with which Alphabet Jones was accustomed to distress his publishers and confuse his friends.

“Dear Reprobate:

“It is the way of this envious world to hate an adulterer. The brute has had such a confounded good time that the rest of us are jealous—an apothegm which you won’t have to read twice to understand that I have been interviewed by Mrs. Carol. Yesterday I was sent for and I at once precipitated myself to renew the expression of my homage. Your princess was looking remarkably well, but of you and of one who shall be nameless she did not speak as she looked, in fact, it would be hyperbole to say that she was complimentary. Of course I reasoned with her as best I could. I told her that accidents increased the best of families; that woman proposes and a poor devil accepts; that matrimony is paved with improper attentions. But my arguments were treated like cobwebs. I was told that you had gone abroad to avoid trouble, and though I intimated that I should do the same thing, and moreover that disappearances were deceptive, I was warmly urged to advise you to remain where you are. As a consequence I advise you to do nothing of the sort, though, between ourselves, it is always stupid to come back and explain things which need no explanation, and as for exoneration only sinners feel the need of that. Perhaps then your best course is to study the maxims of that Hindu philosopher whose name is I Dhont Kare; try not to be any more particular than you have been in the observance of the XI commandment; and, in any event, Tace et Memento. Divorces, as you may be aware, are quite modish this year. They are of all shades of green, cut low and behold, with or without frills as personal taste dictates, and are worn en train, sans pudeur et avec reproche.

“N. B.—Your wife would rather be dead than out of the fashion.

“With this for carte du pays, choose your own route. But which ever way you go, don’t talk back, it is middle-class to begin with, and besides an insult ignored insults the insulter more than the insulted.

“Yours in the bonds of Christian fellowship,

“A. B. Fenwick Chisholm-Jones.”

In a crescendo of bewilderment Nevius turned to the furniture again. “Am I asleep?” he asked. “Is this real, or a nightmare? Is it actual or am I insane? Who is it that shall be nameless? What is this rubbish about divorce? What is this obesity of the mind which Jones mistakes for wit? What does he mean by suggesting that I should remain where I am? Remain where I am! The steamer isn’t built that can carry me fast enough. One word with Hilda, only one, and this farce will end?”

Yet would it? Presently, with a remorse that was childish in its poignancy, one by one he recalled the numberless instances in which he had refused to take her to this function and to that, the embargo he had placed on certain of her associates, the mortification which she must have felt because of his attitude to her family, his surliness to her friends, the utter perversity with which he had thwarted the one poor little wish she had ever expressed, the natural, feminine desire to entertain and be entertained in turn.

Ah, indeed, if it were because of these things she was to leave him, he had no defence, not one. He could only raise his hat and speed her on her way. No doubt she would be happier, oh, much happier without him.

But was such a thing possible? Could it be that the one being in all the world whom he loved, whom he had loved for seven years with a seven times seven increasing love, whom he loved now with a prodigality of affection of which he had been previously unaware, could it be possible that she was to leave him because of this?

The accusation in regard to the woman perplexed, he knew it to be a delusion, one which he could rout with a word. That which presently affected him was the suffering Hilda must endure because of her belief in it. In similar circumstances what would his sufferings be! Why they would drive him mad. But apart from that the thing which moved him most was the fact that she could condemn him unheard, that she could go to others for her knowledge of him. It was not a thing he could have done to her. Of that he was quite sure. But on what, after all, had the condemnation been based? He was not a saint, far from it. In spite of his present perplexity, there had been moments when his deportment to others had not been licit. But never, as the phrase is used, had there been an affair, fancies merely which at best, or at worst, had not outlasted a week. What was it then that had come out? Why was she dumb and crushed?

And then, suddenly as intuitions visit us unaided by anything more tangible than that intangible operation which has been christened unconscious cerebration, a clue appeared and vanished.

“By the living God! I believe it is some nastiness of that Mrs. Anderson. If it is—”

He had sprung to his feet; his hand clenched menaced the gilding of the cornice, the filmy yellow of the curtains, the world that lay beyond.

But the sound of his voice must have startled him; he crossed the room, ashamed of the outburst, and presently, aided by the understanding that if ever calm were required of him it was then, he sat down again and strove to think.

This was Monday. There would be no ship from Havre till the end of the week, but on Wednesday there was a choice of boats that sailed from Southampton and Liverpool. It was now high noon. At three the Club-train left for London. By midnight he could be there. On the morrow he could engage passage. The day after he could sail. A week later he would be in New York, and one hour after he put foot on shore this nightmare would be dissipated and Hilda in his arms. Was he not sure of her, and how few the words that would serve to make her sure of him?

Closing his eyes he saw her again, as he had seen her the morning of his departure, her dark hair falling about the sweetness of her face, and in a voice that seemed tremulous with emotion, imploring him to remember his promise to return to her soon.

Yes surely, that promise he would keep, and with a lunge at a tasseled cord, presently he had Baptiste attending to his traps.

“Not the trouble to come to take oneself off so swift, is it not, my sir? But my sir will re-come, very sure. The America, it is far however. Beautiful land, eno says, and rich! Ah, how I wish my sir me would lead with him!”

Baptiste pottered away, mumbling to himself. But Nevius had gone. There was a trinket at the jeweler’s opposite which would look well on Hilda’s throat. Then, too, there was a telegram to be sent to the Canal Company. These things accomplished, he was able to eat an omelette, and get to the remote Gare du Nord in time to catch the train.

The next morning he awoke bewildered. What had happened to the Rue Castiglione? Why was it so hushed? Where were the birdlike trills of the hawkers? What had been done to the roar and rumble of Paris? And that sky of glittering tin, a pall had been stretched across it.

The Rue Castiglione no doubt was as noisy and as bright as ever. It was in Jermyn street that he had awaked, in a room which overlooked the ghostliness of mews that lay dumb and hidden beneath a fog of leprous brown.

It was by candle that he dressed, and when at last he was able to set out for the steamship office his teeth chattered with the rawness of the air. Hell is supposed to be hot, but fancy it cold, and there can not be a pin to choose between it and London in December.

The steamship office was in Cockspur street, the throw of a stone beyond, but Nevius felt too numb and depressed to get there unfortified. He went back to the hotel, ordered some drink, and in the gloom of the coffee-room sat a while, a copy of the Times before him. But since when had that serious sheet appeared in pink?

Before he could account for such levity, the paper disappeared, the room as well, and when, long after, he issued from a terrible struggle with rushing waters he was lying on a bed; at his side was a little man with white whiskers.

Nevius opened his eyes wider:

“I must have fainted, didn’t I?”

The little man nodded confidentially, with an air of approval.

“And a dom fine one it was altogether. Be easy a bit now, you’re not to get up this day.”

“But I’ve got to,” Nevius answered. “I’ve got to get my ticket.” Then he lost sight of the little man, and when the white whiskers again appeared it was after another combat with thunderclaps and torrential streams.

The little man was prophetic as a ballad. Nevius did not get up that day, nor on the morrow, either, though for a while he was permitted to look out at the dinginess of the empty mews. But he looked with little pleasure; he was weak and confused, and on his forehead above the left eye, a hot iron seemed to be scaring the bone.

“What is it?” he asked.

“We’ve been kicking over the traces, haven’t we?” the little man asserted with the same confidential approving air.

“Not a bit.”

“And dom stupid it would be if we couldn’t.”

“But I haven’t. I have been good as gold. I don’t know what fiend of a microbe has battened on me. I don’t know what can be the matter with my head.”

“And we’ve been angry, too. Anger is a poison. We didn’t know that, did we? Strychnine congests the brain, anger congests the liver.”

“I don’t see why you say that.”

“When we go gunning for a lady in our sleep, we know what has happened when we were awake, don’t we? We’ve got our system upset, we’ve got something on our mind, and as for that pain in our head, it’s a taste of neuralgia that will leave us with a bit of quinine.”

Nevius took the quinine, and to the burn in his forehead was added a roar in his ears. The night was white; barely did he close his eyes; to the agony of his temples was joined the agony of his thoughts. He tried to sleep, but the dual agony banished that benison, until at last he remembered the porter and through his aid succeeded in drugging himself with drink.

On the morrow, the little man changed the medicine; he ordered exalgine, and the burn in the forehead went. But not on that day was Nevius able to take ship, nor on the morrow, either. A week went by before he could go. Yet, meanwhile he had cabled to Hilda, telling her of his illness, imploring her from across the sea to remain where she was until he could reach her and show her that it was she he loved and none other.

This despatched he secured a prescription for a solution of opium, chloral and chloroform which did away with any further need of arousing the porter, and of which, when sleepless and in pain, he was to take one-half of one ounce.

It was on Thursday that he sailed. Eight days later, at six in the evening, he landed at Hoboken and drove to his house.

IX

The house was empty as a vacant bier, barred and bolted, unlighted, and to his repeated summons dumb. None the less, through that curious optimism which will visit even the condemned, Nevius told himself that he was but the victim of some accident, presently to be explained. He was disheartened indeed during the trip across he had done little but prefigure the almost instant reunion, which must occur when he stood once again face to face with his wife, yet in spite of the agony of the disappointment, as he descended the steps he affected, through that duality common to certain natures, to make light of the whole thing, and wondered what had become of Michette.

“Drive to the Brevoort,” he ordered.

But before the cab reached the avenue, the current of his thought had veered, and countermanding the first order, told the man to drive to the Snaiths. For it was there she must be. And, a cigarette between his lips, he threw himself back and resolutely dispossessed his mind of thought.

The cigarette done, he began on another. Before he had finished it, the carriage stopped at that corner of Madison avenue where, years before, he had sipped the brew whose effect was potent still. Through the glass above the door came a light from the hall beyond. The windows of the drawing-room, too, were lighted, and from the rooms on either side of the entrance there came also a filter of gas. Yes, she was there. And he rang the bell, not violently, but with a certain energy of his own.

“Where is Mrs. Nevius?”

The woman who had opened the door, started as at a malefactor, but immediately she recovered herself.

“I don’t know, sir. Would you wish to see Mrs. Snaith?”

Nevius nodded. For the life of him he could not question the servant further. He entered a reception room and stalked to and fro, though whether for one minute or fifty, he afterward forgot. The intermediate was submerged and forever lost when Mrs. Snaith appeared. But the cabman remembered, and for the purpose of these pages that may suffice.

“Where is Hilda?” he asked, and, prompted by the teachings of an earlier education, he raised her hand to his lips.

Mrs. Snaith withdrew the hand and for a moment eyed him strabismally, then in the deprecatory manner which was peculiar to her, addressed the floor.

“We thought—that is, we heard—Hilda said that—you were to remain abroad.”

“Where is she? I must see her.”

Mrs. Snaith fluttered her pallid hands.

“She is not well. She is not well at all. In fact, she is too ill to see you.”

“To ill to see me. What nonsense. I shall see her. Is she upstairs?”

As he spoke he turned. Mrs. Snaith made no attempt to detain him.

“Hilda is away,” she remarked. “Mr. Snaith is upstairs if you care to see him, but won’t the lawyers do?”

“Lawyers? What lawyers?”

Through sheer surprise Mrs. Snaith for the first time in her life looked him in the face.

“When did you get here?”

“An hour ago.”

“And don’t you know that the suit has been begun?”

Nevius had been standing, but at this statement he dropped into a chair and covered his eyes.

In a musing, contemplative way the lady gazed at him, and presently, with a sort inquiring defiance, she added—

“Of course you won’t contest it.”

Nevius looked up. There was such bewilderment in his expression that the lady grew bolder.

“The lawyers say that it is a clear case,” she announced a little loftily.

“A clear case of what? Do tell me what you mean.”

“Hilda wrote to you I am sure.”

“Hilda wrote nothing. She told me that an affair of mine had come out. That she was a brokenhearted woman because of it. The instant I got her letter I started to come here. If I have not got here sooner, it’s through no fault of mine. But I cabled her; didn’t she get it?”

Mrs. Snaith shrugged her shoulders.

“It’s all very well to send cablegrams from London. What you ought to have done was to have behaved yourself in New York. And it’s all very well for you to look at me that way. You know better than anyone. It took Hilda a long time before she could believe such a thing possible of either of you. But I knew what kind of a creature she was the first time I set eyes on her.”

“But can’t you tell me,” Nevius cried, “can’t you tell me whom you mean?”

Mrs. Snaith’s thin lips filled with abundant scorn.

“Why, your mistress, of course, that Adulam girl—”

Nevius was on his feet by this time, the expression in his face was not pleasant to behold, he was quite white beside; and when he confronted the lady, as he instantly did, his voice was not wholly assured.

“I have never contradicted a woman in my life, never to my knowledge have I been uncivil to one, but—”

He hesitated, and with a gasp which must have been the escape of rage compressed, abruptly he mastered himself.

“Nor will I begin with you.”

There was a bell on the table, he turned and touched it.

“But it is my duty to Miss Adulam to say—”

A servant appeared, and interrupting himself, he addressed her.

“Tell Mr. Snaith I wish to see him.” And as the servant disappeared he added:

“It is my duty to her to say that your accusation would be monstrous were it not absurd.”

The lady smiled stealthily. Such a remark could be treated with disdain. And, smiling, left the room.

Nevius neither saw nor heeded. He stood, his head bowed, his hands behind his back, till there came a shuffle of feet in the hall, and an obese dwarf with an erysipeliptic skin halted in the doorway.

“Well? What do you want? I’ll teach you to cut me in the street.”

Nevius reached for his hat and put it on.

“Your wife has charged Miss Adulam—”

“My wife? My wife isn’t in the habit of making charges—”

“Permit me, you are wrong, she is. It is not so long ago she hired a parcel of detectives to manufacture evidence against Montrion, and if Mrs. Montrion didn’t use it, it was only because, as she told me herself, she was afraid Montrion would shoot her.”

“It’s a lie.”

“What your wife says in regard to Miss Adulam may be so described. She knows it and so do you. What Hilda thinks I have yet to learn.”

“If you don’t know already, more fool you. If you have come here with any intention of contesting this suit, you might as well go back. The lawyers have daughters of their own and they say they’ll make an example of you.”

“Ah! you may tell them from me that I will contest it until the last armed court of appeal expires—which I suppose is just what they want.”

“By God then, if you do, I’ll ruin you.”

“And you may say, too, that I shall be at the Brevoort until I can get into my own house, and meanwhile whenever they take a fancy to serve the summons—”

“You’ve been served,” the dwarf shouted. “You’ve been served by publication. When I employ lawyers I get my money’s worth. The papers are full of it.”

Nevius ripped a glove in two.

“Do you mean that you have got Miss Adulam’s name in connection with mine?”

In his voice were such angers, in his bearing such threats, that the dwarf wheeled like a rat surprised.

“Then you ought to be trampled under foot,” Nevius gnashed, and striding after him cried, “In Hebrew there are four words for reptile, in my vocabulary there is but one—Snaith.”

The old man squirmed to the stairs, shrieking obscenities, fearful of attack.

But the front door opened and closed. Nevius had gone.

X

“Carol, this is the saddest thing that ever happened to me.”

On reaching the hotel, Nevius, after securing rooms, had sent for the papers. On the first page of the one he first examined was his name in leaded type, and beneath it, written in that reporter spirit which stops not even at a column, was an account of the last sensation, the petition of Mrs. Carol Nevius for divorce on the ground of her husband’s adultery with Janet Adulam and Gertrude Vührer. Though he had eaten nothing since noon, he sickened as he read, and was obliged to put the page down. The remainder of the article declared that after a painful scene at his house he had confessed his misconduct and fled abroad. The other papers contained articles of similar tenor, though one, more enterprising perhaps, stated that the correspondents were the housemaid and the cook.

An hour passed before Nevius could hold a pen, then he had sent a message to Jones, and now, as the novelist, cloaked in an Inverness, the white of his neckcloth just visible, entered the room, there was no cynicism in his voice, a sympathy merely, abiding and sincere.

“The saddest,” he repeated with just a glance at where the papers lay. “If there are words of consolation I do not know them.”

“It is hideous,” Nevius muttered. “I don’t wonder you advised me to remain where I was—”

“Did I suppose—could any one suppose such a thing possible? When I read that drivel I was in a rage beside which the anger of Achilles was a fleeting annoyance. Your wife ought to be tarred and feathered.”

Nevius raised a hand in protest. “It is not her fault. It’s that father-in-law of mine.”

“Father-at-law you mean. But that’s neither here nor there. The thing is done, and a more abominable iniquity never was committed. That your wife should wish a divorce, passe encore. But that in her effort to get it she should put a young girl into leaded type, a girl who was her intimate friend; a girl whose people were governors of New York at a time when the Snaiths, if they existed, were cleaning the streets; no, in the entire history of civilized life there is no parallel for it. And who is this other correspondent? Why didn’t she stick to her and let Miss Adulam out?”

“Hilda had nothing to do with it!” Nevius answered dejectedly. “Don’t say anything against her. I can’t and won’t permit it.”

“Bosh.”

But the novelist spoke in an undertone. From a box on the table he took a gold-tipped cigarette, at which article of London luxury he sniffed, and for a while there was silence in that room.

But presently Nevius, who had sat, his face in his hands, looked wearily up at his friend. “What do they say?”

“Who? People in general? Every one seems to be very well pleased. Some of the men are indignant at the publicity, knowing how, in similar circumstances, they would feel themselves. Others are indignant, too, but their indignation is partly envy, partly disgust, at having no such chances themselves. As for the women, that is a different guitar. You have got one of their sacred sex into trouble, and as a body they won’t forgive. Though individually, were you not rather compromising at present, you might toss monogrammed cambrics as before. On the whole, then, I may say that people in general are rather pleased than otherwise. There is a land where there is much joy over the sinner that repents. In the world we live in the joy is at his detection.”

Nevius leaned across the table.

“Do you mean to say that it is believed?”

“Well, you know—” And for a second the unembarrassable Jones actually hesitated. “You see, Carol, to be frank with you, more or less, don’t you know, for some time past people have connected Miss Adulam’s name with yours. And they say, you know, that there were times when she—well, when she came to see you.”

Nevius sank back.

“But even so,” he queried. “Even so—”

“Oh, if you put it in that light, in any light for that matter, I am with you. Of course it was sufficient for me to see it stated that you had made a confession, to know that you had done nothing of the sort. It is what we don’t do that gets into the papers, never what we have done, which after all,” the novelist added to himself, “is sufficient for most of us. The point is here, however, people had doubts, now they have none. Naturally you will declare Miss Adulam innocent, and the world will treat her as though you had never opened your head. But tell me, what sort of evidence have they?”

“Evidence! As God is my witness that girl is as straight as your sister.”

The reply came so abruptly, in a voice so indignant, and yet so earnest, that the novelist stared. Not for a moment had he doubted but that the facts were as Mrs. Nevius stated them.

His anger, his sympathy, too, were due to the knowledge that people of ordinary refinement do not permit certain forms of publicity. That Miss Adulam had taken a step aside, that Nevius had aided and abetted in the taking of that step, were matters which concerned him not in the least. To his thinking the wantonness of the whole affair consisted in the fact that Mrs. Nevius, in her desire for a divorce, had not gone about it in such a way that no one, not even the attorneys, could suspect that there was so much as a shred of linen which needed the services of a laundress. Men and women of decent breeding sunk their private grievances and separated with mutual delight, no doubt, but also with common courtesy. The act which Mrs. Nevius had committed was the act of a scullion, at best of a young person in Harlem. No matter how outraged she had felt, refinement should have inhibited her from disgracing a girl before the eyes of the multitude. It was that which had aroused his wrath, not once had the suspicion come to him that the charge might not be true.

But now as he stared at Nevius he saw that it was false. He was far too old a bird to be caught with chaff. He was far too good a critic of private theatricals not to know the true ring when he heard it, and as he saw in Nevius’ face, in his bearing and attitude, that transfiguring innocence which only the guiltless can display, he pounded the table with his fist.

“By George then, if that’s the case this whole matter is more damnable than it was before. Why, Carol, Bernhardt isn’t in it with your wife.”

“It isn’t my wife, I tell you, it’s her people. You know how they acted in regard to Montrion. They have done the same thing to me, with this difference, Fanny Montrion was behind the scenes, and Hilda knew nothing until they got their trumped charges in shape. It must have nearly killed her, though, puzzle as I may, I don’t see how they ever got her to believe them, and what’s more, I don’t believe they have. When I see her tomorrow it will take me just one minute to disabuse her mind. Her mother says she is ill, and God knows I am too.”

“You’ve seen the mother, have you?”

“Yes, she wouldn’t tell me where Hilda was, she kept repeating that she was too ill to see any one.”

“She was at the opera to night”; said Jones very quietly.

“Impossible!”

“You may well say that, but I saw her. She was with the Andersons in their box. I asked Anderson how she could show herself when the papers were dripping with the scandal she had made—”

“Well?”

“He laughed. ‘She has come to enjoy her revenge!’ he told me.”

Nevius got up, went to the sideboard and pouring out a glass of whisky drank it off.

Jones watched him. When he turned the novelist added:

“In the circumstances I wouldn’t try to see her. She has left you, it should be beneath your dignity to approach her in any way.”

Nevius shook his head helplessly.

“How dense you are! You don’t or won’t understand. She is a woman after all, and no matter how she may suffer she has too much pride to show it. I think she ought not to have gone to the opera tonight, whether she believed this thing or whether she didn’t, and I think too the Andersons alone could have had the bad taste to invite her. But none the less I make every excuse for her. Supposing our position reversed, what is there that I might not do?”

“He has the faith of a little child,” the novelist mused, “it’s pathetic.”

“But tell me, what did she say when you saw her?”

“Nothing very pleasant. To be candid, she doesn’t seem to have the same good opinion of you that you have of her.”

And Jones, knocking the ashes from his cigarette, added meditatively:

“But then you may be both in error.”

This little conclusion may not have reached Nevius; he was pacing the floor.

“I know I have been selfish,” he muttered. “Damn selfish. But I can’t understand—”

“See here, dear boy. I will go to her tomorrow. If she is to be argued with, I think I can handle her. But do you get to bed; it’s after two, and you look like the devil. Leave the matter in my hands.”

Nevius stopped short in his walk and gazed at his friend.

“Do you know I don’t realize it? I can’t realize it. But if by any chance I were convinced that she was not to return to me—”

A gesture completed the sentence.

“Bah!” And the novelist smiled complacently. “Suicide is out of fashion, dear boy, and vulgar too. Now listen to me. tomorrow the Snaiths will probably let you into your house. From what you said in your note I suppose you will want servants. I will attend to that. Now get to bed. I told you you looked like the devil, I should have said—you did. The devil is a very fascinating person, Carol, and unless you take some care of yourself you will entirely cease to resemble him.”

Oh, no doubt; and the novelist gone, the care which Nevius proceeded to take of himself consisted in more whisky, and on top of it a draught of the London drug.

XI

The morrow was charming, half spring, half autumn, with just that touch of frostiness which makes the blood beat fast. Nevius shivered, his eyes were heavy, his mind dull, his face yellow and blotched, the mouth drawn. He had looked at a mirror and had not looked again. Whisky bloats and opium disfigures. The ice water of a bath had brought a glow, but that had gone; he was trembling; it was a stimulant he needed, no doubt, and he called for absinthe.

With the drink a hall-boy came. There was a gentleman below with some keys and a message. Should he come up?

Nevius, his hand uncertain and vacillant, swallowed the absinthe before he spoke.

“Yes, he may come. And—what was it I wanted?—oh, fetch the morning papers.”

But the drink did him good. And presently, at a knock, he opened the door.

Before him stood a stout, young Jew, revolting as uncleanliness and vulgarity could make him. Yet, who vaguely, despite his nose and his youth resembled Mr. Snaith.

“Is your name C. Nevius? Well, here’s some keys and a summons.”

Nevius closed the door, the keys and summons in his hand. By whom could he hbe summoned now? But the mandate was perfectly legible. The complainant was Hilda Nevius, and did he not in twenty days appear or answer, judgment for relief demanded would be taken by default. Signed, Tooth and Tooth.

Tooth and Tooth? Ah, yes, the divorce sharks. Service by publication was not sufficient then. Apparently these gentlemen were in haste. And to think that Hilda could be capable—

The boy had come with the papers, but his coming and going passed unmarked. For an hour, that seemed a minute, Nevius sat wondering at his wife. A man who suffers is never bored.

But what did the hall-boy want now? Mr. Harding, of the Chronicle, was below, was he? And Mr. Robinson, of the Despatch, and Mr. McGrath, of the Evening Star? Well, below, deeper down even, for all of him they might remain. And yet, had he only Hilda to consider? Was there not Jenny, too?

“Show them up,” he ordered, and passing into the bedroom changed his dressing suit for morning garb. When he returned, the representatives of the press were there. Mr. Harding, who was sharpening a pencil, took the matter on himself.

“Mr. Nevius, I believe? Mr. Nevius, I have come to ask what you have to say in reply to the charges in yesterday’s papers? You have seen them, I suppose?”

“Yes, I have seen it stated that I made a confession, and then, to escape the consequences, fled abroad. I had no confession to make; I made none, and the fact that I am here should, I think, be evidence that consequences do not intimidate me. To this I have nothing to add, except that the charges brought against the young women named in the complaint are absolutely without foundation.”

“Shall you contest the suit?” inquired Mr. Robinson.

“If it is not withdrawn, as I am convinced it must be, I certainly shall.”

“What have you to say in regard to Mrs. Nevius?”

“Mrs. Nevius does not enter into the matter. There is no need for any mention of her name.”

“You think then,” began the representative of the Star, “that the suit was instigated by third parties?”

“I think nothing about it. I know. But this gentleman—” and Nevius indicated Mr. Harding, “—asked if I had any statement to make. I have made one. If you will publish that and nothing else you will oblige me.”

“But—”

“At this moment, I regret, I am occupied I must ask you to excuse me.”

The door behind him was open, and through it he retreated, angry with himself, angry with fate, angry with the world.

When he returned, there was the hall-boy again. This time with a note from Jones to the effect that he had secured servants and would look in later on.

“I send you the keys.” Nevius scribbled in reply. “Tell the servants to meet me at the house, and do come before midnight.”

The answer despatched, he sat down and tried to think, to forget rather and not to remember.

XII

Already the afternoon had taken itself off. A sun, red as ceiling-wax burned and subsided, leaving a sky of dead rose and water-green. Then shadows came, lapping the walls, devouring the furniture, creating abysses into which objects disappeared, mysteriously, one by one.

When night was wholly there, Nevius groped for his hat and gloves. Presently he was in the street, in a few minutes at his house. Yes. Jones had been as good as his word. There were lights in the windows and the outer door of the vestibule was open. With a latchkey he let himself in. The hall was chill, bleak too, sonorous beneath his tread. But where were the hangings and tapestries, where were the plants, the pedestalled lamps, the silken cushions, the candles with their yellow shades, all the attributes of ease that six weeks before had filled the drawing-room? Surely this was not his house, or else had the sheriffs passed that way. But it was his house, and why was it dismantelled? Where had the scent of the iris gone? Ah, yes; he remembered. These things were Hilda’s, all of them, even to the scent of the iris, and in leaving him, necessarily she had taken her chattels too.

And the floor above! Truly were it not for the chill he might have thought it summer time and Hilda off to the seashore, so properly had little familiar things been put away. But what was that on her bureau from which everything else had gone? Nothing, a picture of himself merely, overlooked, no doubt, and forgotten. Yet was it a picture of himself? At least if he had ever had the youth and alertness with which the picture credited him, never would he have them again.

The library which so long and well had separated her room from his had, out of gratitude, perhaps, been left untouched. There were the yellow shelves of law, the darker tomes of history, and here, in smooth maroon, stamped with the Nevius crest, were the classics of Greece and Rome. Beyond were the caryatides of literary France, Corneille, Racine, Moliére, dusty and undisturbed. But this empty space beneath? Surely Hilda never could have taken away the little gifts she had made him before she bestowed that great gift which was herself. The Owen Meredith from which in the gardens of Bronx she had repeated to him:

Since we parted yester eve,
I do love thee, love, believe,
Twelve times dearer, twelve times longer,
One dream deeper, one night stronger,
One sun surer, thus much more
Than I loved thee, love, before.

The Aldrich from which he had read to her:

But there will come a time, my love,
When if I read our stars aright
I shall not linger at your side
With my adieux. Till then, good-night.
You wish that time were now? And I!
You do not blush to wish it so?
You would have blushed yourself to death
To own as much a year ago.

And the Sonnets of Proteus:

What shall it matter, when our heads are gray,
Whether we loved, or did not love to-day?

And the Swinburne:

A little while and we die: shall life not thrive as it may?
For no man under the sky lives twice, outliving his day.

But though the rhymes returned unprompted, where were the books? Where was the Festus, the Rosetti, the Tennyson? Surely she could not have taken these gifts away. But then, what had she done with herself? And why did the gas burn so dimly? Or was it a mist that had got to his eyes?

“I beg pardon, sir—”

Nevius started. At the door a man stood, coatless, looking at him. “I am Patrick, sir; my wife is in the kitchen, would you—”

“Yes, of course. I know. Let me see—suppose you go to the Brevoort and get my tilings. Tell them to send the bill to my office. And what time is it? No, I can’t eat anything, but if there is any whisky lying about, you might bring it up.”

“Yes, sir; thank you, sir. Mr. Jones is in the parlor. Shall I ask him here?”

But before the novelist entered the room, Nevius lit a cigarette and hid his face in smoke.

“Well?”

“Well, I have seen your princess, and so far as I am concerned I can dispense with the honor of seeing her again. Calumny is to her what venom is to the adder, a sole defence. A harder, an unjuster woman I have never met, no not even in the masquerades of my own fiction. Her entire accusation has no other foundation than the tattle of the servants’ hall.”

“She is annoyed, Alphabet. So would I be. Don’t say anything against her. You don’t know her as I do. You don’t know the letter she wrote me. Her heart is breaking. But when I see her tomorrow—”

“See her! You’ll never see her till you meet in court. She is furious, not at all because of this thing, but because you have returned. Her attorney told her they would get a divorce in short order and here you are declaring you will contest it. You have upset her calculations. She fancied she could be free at once.”

“Yes, but then she didn’t understand. I assure you she will be very sorry when she learns the truth, very sorry indeed—”

“H’m,” the novelist sniffed and smiled. “When she is, I send my resignation to psychology. She knows the truth, she has always known it. Never for a second has she believed the charge she has made.”

“It is not Hilda; I have told you that. She wrote me that she was so dumb and crushed that her people took the matter entirely out of her hands.”

On the table at which Jones had seated himself, was a pile of bills and letters. On the topmost was the imprint of the District Messenger Service. Leisurely the novelist reached for it. In the envelope were the vouchers of the month before. Jones drew out one, then another.

“Tell me,” he presently asked, “when did you sail for Europe?”

“The second of December.”

“Your wife’s attorneys are Tooth and Tooth, are they not? So I thought. Will you look at this? It is dated 2nd of December and addressed to Tooth and Tooth, who you will see detained the messenger one hour and an answer which seems to have been received by somebody who signed herself H. Nevius. Is it your wife’s writing?”

The ticket he tossed across the table.

“Here is another, same date, same address. Here is another dated the 4th. Here is another dated the 5th. For a lady who was dumb and crushed, whose affairs had been taken entirely out of her hands, it seems to me that not only she was very agile with the pen but—”

Nevius sprang at him fiercely.

“But what? It is on evidence of that kind she has condemned me. Poor child, she knew no better. But you, who have accused her of listening to the tattle of the servants’ hall, do you expect me to descend the back stairs, too? Give me those tickets.”

Seizing and mutilating them he flung them at his feet, and in the same hot wrath blurted:

“If you have anything else to say against my wife, say it, but do you say it to me.”

Reflectively the novelist contemplated his fingertips, joined them, separated them, and joined them again.

“There is a little operation I must perform on you, Carol. One which will pain, but which is necessary and charitable.”

Mystified by this preamble, Nevius stared.

Jones stood up, closed the door, and whispered to his friend.

The latter shrank, his eyes dilated, his mouth agape.

“No, no, tell me; she never said that!”

“She has then, not to me alone, but to everyone. That sweet little friend of hers, Mrs. Anderson, with whom she is stopping, fairly revels in it. There isn’t a man in town, nor a woman either, that won’t hear it tomorrow.”

When Jones got the scalpel in his hand he knew where and how to cut. But then in this instance he was a trifle annoyed at the slur on his friend.

“When I heard it,” ’ he continued, “I did not see the object. I have since. Mrs. Carol understands what a mess she has made of it all, and she is trying to exculpate herself at any cost. If there is a single thing believable or unbelievable that she and Mrs. Anderson are capable of inventing to your discredit, invent it they will, and proclaim it too.”

Nevius bowed his head. The hot wrath must have gone.

“How sorry she will be,” he muttered. “How sorry, how sorry, how sorry she will be.”

What was there in that for Jones to laugh at? Yet laugh he did.

“My little Hilda!” Covering his face, Nevius leaned down and rested his arms on the table. When he again looked up his eyes may have been red, but they were steadfast still.

“Wait. Wait until I see her. For she must see me, or—”

“Yes, I told her your ultimatum of last night. Would you like to know what she said? It is not pleasant, but if it removes this cataract of yours I don’t mind. She said, and very affably, mind you, in that little voice which I have heard her affect when she wishes to impress: ‘Tell that man that nothing he might do could cause me greater pleasure, except to send him the pistol with which to do it.’ ”

As in pain which is acute, Nevius dug his nails into the palms of his hands, and for a while his face, tortured with the retroacting currents of conflicting thought, expressed only a suffering, sentient and visible. But gradually the hands relaxed, the expression modified, and you would have said that the cure which Jones had attempted was without effect.

“From what you say,” he ventured at last, “I must believe that Hilda’s condemnation of me is complete. But then I have been horribly selfish—”

“Her condemnation is so complete,” the novelist interrupted “that it absolves you from condemning her. In the total lack not only of justice but of decency which she displays, comfort yourself as you seem disposed to do, by being charitable to her and unjust to yourself. It is not nineteenth century, no, but by gad, its red-heel. Carol, I want you for a book.”

“—So selfish,” Nevius repeated, “that some day when you see her I want you to tell her that I regret it from the bottom of my heart.”

For a moment he looked down and away, but almost immediately, with a smile that was its own apology, he added:

“It’s best to take people as they find us, isn’t it, Alphabet? You have been very good to me, very considerate, and you have borne magnificently with my ill temper. I want to thank you, but I can’t. I am a trifle tired, perhaps—”

“Yes, you had better get to bed. But I want to thank you, and I can, for teaching me that phrase. It is best to take people as they find us. E vero ed é ben trovato. Trovato? E ben Trovatore!”

“What is that saying of Ingall’s?” he mused as he passed down the stair. “ ‘It is just as well to let dynamite alone, particularly when it happens to be intelligent and has a grievance.’ When Nevius understands what I do, he will kill that woman, and by George, when he does, for the first time in my life I shall want to be on the jury.”

“Patrick, is that you?” he interrupted himself to ask. “Patrick, do you keep an eye on Mr. Nevius, he is not at all well. Should he be ill during the night send for me at once, don’t call a messenger, ring up a cab, and tell the driver it’s a fiver if he gets me here in no time.”

With that, this serviceable writer of immoral fiction buttoned his Inverness and left the house.

“Patrick,” said Nevius a little later, “here is a prescription, take it to Asquith’s on the corner, get it filled and tell the druggist I want to speak to him. You found some whisky, did you? Very good, put it there.”

Pouring a little of the liquor out, he drank it off. Under its influence the stupor fell from him. He began a letter, which must have been difficult however: the right words would not always come and there was a blur in his eyes besides. But he got it done, and addressing it to his wife, immediately be began another to Miss Adulam, a third to Tredegar. In writing these also his pen often stopped, hesitant and perplexed, but when at last they were all finished, and on a fresh sheet he began the “Know all men by these presents”; his pen went rapidly enough, as he devised his property, real and personal, of whatever kind, nature and description, to Hilda Nevius, her heirs, executors and assigns forever.

“The druggist is below, sir.” At the door stood Patrick. “Shall I leave the prescription with you?”

“Yes, put it there. Ask him up. And, Patrick, do you wait.”

A moment, and Nevius rose in greeting of a meager man in a frock coat.

“Mr. Asquith, this is very kind of you. Here is my will. Will you witness it for me?”

“Certainly, anything to oblige.”

“I sign it then in your presence. Put your signature here, please, and your address. Patrick, I want you to witness it too. Thank you both very much.”

“Nothing else, Mr. Nevius, is there?”

No, there was nothing, and presently when he was alone again he repeated that word a little sadly to himself.

“What was that I once heard Jones say?” he queried. “We should prolong life, not death? That is it; and this is death. Well, let me not prolong it.”

Before him was the prescription; opening it he filled a goblet to the brim and tossed it off. How good it was! A little hot to the throat, a little cloying to the palate, but clean to the tongue, fragrant, too.

On the mantel lay his hat, he took it up and seating himself, his head covered, he drew on a glove and buttoned it. But why were the books, the yellow shelves of law, the darker tomes of history, retreating through that little space which he had noticed earlier in the night? Before he could account for anything so strange, the walls, too, had retreated, joy and fear, love and anguish, all had gone and in their stead was oblivion and rest for memory.

XIII

“Imbecile that you are! Don’t you know, Haven’t I told you, haven’t I arch-told you that nothing could cause her greater joy?”

“But what a reason! Am I to live merely because my death might gratify another?”

With an expression that was both furious and indulgent, Jones glowered in amicable rage.

“And truly,” Nevius added, “I don’t thank any of you.”

Long before he had awaked, conscious, if at all, only that people were leaving the room. Presently he had recognized Patrick; at once the episode of the previous night returned, and with it the perception of failure. Later he learned that Patrick, attracted by his breathing, alarmed at his attitude, had sent for a physician, for Jones as well. The physician had been the first to arrive, and after hours of labor, had gone, threatening to prosecute the druggist.

But now, three days later, clothed and in his right mind the resurrected sat talking with his friend.

“No,” Jones answered. “That would be medieval. I mean nothing so Hugoesque. But, dear boy, you have no right to leave the planet until you have shown this accusation to be as false as you and I know it to be. The bare bodkin may be simpler, but it is not at all chivalrous to leave Miss Adulam in the plight she is. Can’t you understand that if this effort had succeeded even her own mother would have believed that the story was true? No, you must live for the reporters, you must live for your wife, and meanwhile get a verdict. When you have got that kill yourself as often as you like. Yet there is just the eccentricity of the whole thing, man never commits suicide twice. If he recovers he has no desire to repeat the experiment, and if he doesn’t that is the end of that. But don’t you have anything to drink in this house?”

Oh, yes. Though little else had been discoverable drink there was in plenty, and presently, comforted by a Scotch and soda, the garrulous novelist ran on:

“But whatever possessed you to do a thing of that sort with your hat on? Do you know, that is what we call a document. I shall have a suicide in my next novel merely for that hat. I would give the whole story, for that matter, were it not so bald. It would not do for New York. Here the reporter can be as pornograph as the Marquess of Sade, if he knows how, and he usually does, but the novelist must be like Marguerite’s home, chaste and pure. We are willing enough to applaud Tristan and Isolde, when it is put to music and sung in a language which is not a court-tongue. But beyond that we won’t go. The unbribable Comstock won’t let us. But even apart from that, I couldn’t handle the thing. No one would think it probable, and to my reputation for realism a long farewell.”

The novelist looked into his glass. “It’s a good subject though. A deuced good subject. I might call it, let me see—I might call it Bagatelles, yes, Bagatelles or One of the Ten Commandments.

“Why not several of them while you are about it?”

“Several of the Ten Commandments? Why, that would be a tip-top title. Take in all classes of readers. Dear boy, if you don’t object I think I will.”

Nevius jumped from his seat.

“If you say one word,” he cried hotly, “one word that a microscopist could detect as referring to my wife, by the Lord Harry I’ll put daylight through you.”

“Dear me!” mumbled Jones, “how was I to suppose that you were in love with her still?”

At that you should have heard Nevius bluster. How he ranted, how he raved! In love with her? The idea! No indeed, not he. And when at last for sheer lack of breath he stopped, of the entire diatribe Jones believed actually not one word.

But, false friend that he was, he nodded as though he did.

“That’s right, that’s the way to talk, that’s the way you must talk to O’Donnell. We went over the whole matter today. He’ll be here now at any moment.”

And, vatic as usual, Mr. Jabez O’Donnell, a member of the bar, still young, yet already famous, a man with the face of a cherub and the guile of a fox, was promptly announced.

“This,” said Jones, as the lawyer entered, “this, my dear O’Donnell, is my friend and brother in Christ, Mr. Carol Nevius. His retainer will be large, his refreshers abundant. Let me earnestly commend him to your care.”

“Devil a bit of a retainer will I take;” the gentleman answered with great cordiality and a little brogue, “I am out for gore, not for coin.”

“Bravely said,” cried Jones, glass in hand, toasting the occasion, toasting everything, toasting illicit commerce. “You are pleased to meet Nevius, I know; and as for him, he radiates with delight.”

And at the way Nevius smiled, any one might have thought that really he was enjoying himself. Yet, how curious it was that this moment the smile visited his lips, a verse of Byron’s fluttered there too:

“And if I laugh at any mortal thing
’Tis that I may not weep: and if I weep
’Tis that our nature can not always bring
Itself to apathy.”

“Poseur!” sneered Jones, in an indignant aside.

Mr. O’Donnell seemed to appreciate, “I understand you, Mr. Nevius. I understand perfectly. It is a dreadful thing to have one’s name in the papers.”

“And still more dreadful not to.”

This interruption came, of course, from the novelist. No one paid any attention to him. The lawyer continued:

“The outrage in this instance is heightened by the fact that there need have been no publicity at all. Professional etiquette, if nothing else, should have prevented Tooth and Tooth from serving you by publication. They tell me that they did not know you were a member of the bar, and as their acquaintance is limited to those who practice in the General Sessions, that is a thing which I can believe. They also tell me that Mrs. Nevius represented that you would not return to this country. They pretend to be vexed at the mistake, but I have reasons for thinking that they regard the whole business as an excellent advertisement. Now permit me to ask a question. What sort of a man is your father-in-law? They seemed to have been employed by him before. One would hardly think such a thing possible, but is he at all of their class of life?”

“Between the man who pays to have a young girl defamed and the men who take the money and do the job,” Nevius promptly and grimly replied, “honors are easy.”

“That they are, Mr. Nevius, that goes without saying. But if I ask, it is because from what Tooth aud Tooth tell me he is not so dogmatic as he was before you returned. It appears that the night you landed he nearly gave up the ghost.”

“He could have had no interest in doing so, however.”

“No, precisely not, and perhaps for that reason he didn’t. But understand me; Jones says that the plaintiff is not to be argued with, and is determined to push the thing to the end. If such be the case, there is no use losing time with her. But if her father were properly approached, might not something be done?”

“Beyond asking him to play pendulum I see nothing.”

The lawyer laughed. “He hasn’t inspired you with much regard, has he?”

“Yes,” Nevius answered. “Yes, to such an extent even that I have put him in my will. Mr. Snaith is a member of the Society for the Protection of Animals, and in recognition of his affection for beasts, I have left him a mirror.”

Jones, rolled over in spasms of delight. “Oh! Carol! how I wish I had said that!”

In unconscious rememoration of the famous retort which in similar circumstances was fired point blank at another man of letters, Nevius turned to him and consolingly answered; “There, never mind, Alphabet. You will.”

Then with a deprecatory glance at the lawyer, who was laughing still, he prepared to return to facts.

“Forgive me, Mr. O’Donnell. My levity is out of place, in poor taste as well. This is tragedy, not farce. You will believe me when I say that nothing is further from my mind than a desire to jest.”

“I follow you there. I know quite how you feel. Years ago a man called on a physician; ‘I am terribly depressed,’ he said. ‘I want something to stir me up,’ ‘Go and see Grimaldi,’ the physician answered. ‘He will make you laugh.’ ‘I am Grimaldi,’ the patient replied. But to get down to business again. Tooth and Tooth have made a proposition, one however which they declare is made entirely on their own responsibility. It is this. They claim to have all the evidence they require against Miss Adulam, but the evidence against Miss Vührer, while equally plentiful, is not, to use their expression, so convenient. Now they offer to withdraw the charge against Miss Adulam, providing that you will supply them, through a third party of course, with a few additional facts concerning your acquaintance with Miss Vührer. This proposition, they wish me to assure you, is made solely out of deference to you. What shall I tell them?”

“What shall you tell them?” repeated Nevius wearily. “There is naturally no use in telling them that I am incapable of deserting the helpless, for they would not understand. But tell them I say they are shysters, that the suit may be withdrawn, that I have nothing to gain at their hands, and they will understand the message thoroughly.”

“Timeo Danaos et dona ferentes,” the uncrushable Jones threw in. “And by the way, Carol, Dona Ferentes! What a tip-top name for the plaintiff!”

The lawyer nodded to his client. “I might have expected such an answer. But look at it in this light, wouldn’t it be better—”

“There can be no better,” Nevius interrupted. “And no worse. Miss Adulam is a young gentlewoman whom I have known all my life. Could I in any way sacrifice myself for her I would do so, but I can not sacrifice an innocent girl, nor, presupposing I could, would Miss Adulam permit me. Of Miss Adulam’s justification there is no manner of doubt. If Tooth and Tooth, in saying that they have all the evidence against her which they require, speak truthfully, they have been imposed upon, precisely as Mrs. Nevius has been. There can be no evidence. Not a charge can they substantiate. They may have perjury at command, no doubt they have, in which case we shall know how to act when we get it in court. As for Miss Vührer, I did not know her first name, nor how her last was written until I saw it in the complaint. I have seen her but four times in my life. I never knew that she existed until Mrs. Nevius brought her into this room. Were I to act as Tooth and Tooth suggest, what would you think of me? And what should I think of myself?”

The lawyer took a long breath before he spoke.

“They have got something, make up your mind to that, though whether it be perjury or not I can’t say. But they intimate they are in a position to prove a confession made by you to Mrs. Nevius previous to your departure.”

For a moment Nevius fumbled in a drawer of the table.

“Yes, I know,” he answered. “I read something of the kind in the papers. But just look at this. When I sailed Mrs. Nevius gave me a list of things which she wanted me to get for her in Paris. This morning I sent them to her. Here is an acknowledgment from her mother. It is hardly supposable, is it, if I left Mrs. Nevius in the manner which Tooth and Tooth describe, that she should ask me the morning I sailed, to purchase corsets, gloves and lingerie?”

“The morning you sailed?”

“Certainly.”

“And this list is in her handwriting?”

“It is.”

“Why, then,” exclaimed the lawyer, “they can trot out all the perjury they like. That bit of paper stumps them. The alleged offences were condoned.”

To this Nevius assented absently. “There must be no such plea though. The denial of the allegations is all that is required. They can never prove one.”

“No doubt, no doubt.” And the lawyer rose to go. “But I do not need to tell you that the greatest mistake a man can make is to underrate his adversary’s abilities.”

“Unless it be,” laughed Jones, “to overrate his own.”

XIV

Like a lethargic snake disturbed, winter dragged itself away. April came, and with it an eager glitter, the surprise of violets, skies of silk, wadded with films of white cotton, all the caresses and surrenders of spring.

Upper Fifth avenue was well in the movement, alive with smart traps, Piccadilly accents, gems of bonnets, and grooms, the arms folded, impassible, correct. In all the world prettier women there are not than in that parade which circles through the Park, and descends again just in time to intercept the dusk. No, nor daintier either.

And pretty and dainty as the prettiest and daintiest, Mrs. Carol Nevius looked that spring. On her lips was the pink of the seashell, and in the depths of her sultry blue eyes the faintest petition for that sympathy which imaginary wrongs deserve. Ah, it was a pleasure to see her.

That pleasure was not enjoyed by her husband. But in those days his pleasures were few. Women, whom he had known all his life, forgot to remember him. Men, with whom he had lived on terms of offhand familiarity, had become punctiliously polite.

These things were nothing in comparison to others. The letter which he had sent rather blurred to his wife had been returned through Tooth and Tooth, with the intimation that he was persecuting her. The letter which he had sent to Miss Adulam had been answered by her mother; the girl was lying at the house of her uncle, Erastus Wilberforce, too ill to hold a pen. From Tredegar no answer came, a rumor merely that the boy was drinking himself to death.

Then, too, the divorce required in such haste that service by publication was necessary, languished, moribund and mute. And not at all because of the calendar. On motion it could have gone before a referee at once. But the Snaiths had other matters to attend to, though a girl was dying because of them, and a lad was throwing his life away.

Nevius ceased to be seen. His office was closed. The Canal Company, with perfect civility, dispensed with his services; other corporations for whom he had acted withdrew their business from his hands. That Mr. Snaith had been at work he understood, but it was long before he understood that that gentleman’s object was to attack the sinews of war, and thereby, the law’s delays continuing, to force him to capitulate. When the understanding did come to him, he reflected with some satisfaction that while skies were still fair he had cut that gentleman in the street.

Meanwhile, he stalked, uncompanioned, through the untellable loneliness of that ghastly house, seeking a clue to the mystery that was devastating three lives.

That Hilda had cared for him he had to believe, or else to regard her as an actress more consummate even than Rachel. For where was the actress who could assume a role and hold it, impeccably, not for a season alone, not so many nights a week, but every minute of seven years? That she knew her accusations to be false he was now convinced. With these for premises what conclusion could he draw? It could not be that after years of tenderness she had left him, because there were moments when he was irritable and perverse. No, surely that was not the cause. Nor could it be that she had left him because her father had threatened disinheritance. Judas, indeed, had been bribed, yet, while in the present instance the bribe was greater, still, though times had changed and living become more expensive, Nevius was unable to accept any solution such as that. Beside, not being a bit more heroic than the rest of us, a conclusion of that kind diminished him in his own esteem.

In the night of his perplexity a single ray had come. Jones had enjoyed a second conversation with this lady, in which Mrs. Nevius, after stating that the man whose name she had taken, was heedless beyond the power of words, that he had constantly borrowed her buttonhook, added, by way of summing up, that she had married him uniquely to go into society, and as he had refused to take her, he should bear the consequences without complaint.

That was the ray of light, tremulous and thin no doubt, but which, by reason of the darkness in which he groped, led him ultimately to what he regarded as the day. As stepping-stones he had two facts, one pathological, the other psychological. The pathological fact was this: Women who at recurrent intervals suffer greatly, are afflicted not only physically, but mentally as well. Their minds become the haunt of vagaries, of illusions, sometimes of madness, too. For these sufferings, for these vagaries and illusions, there is but one cure, one to which nature prompts—motherhood. The psychological fact hung like a corollary to the first. When a woman has lived seven years with a man and borne him no child, unintentionally it may be, yet instinctively that man she hates.

At the intervals alluded to, Hilda, he was aware, had suffered for days with an intensity of agony which was pitiful to behold. Moreover, as the years accumulated, the union had remained unblessed. Such maternal affection as she possessed had been given to him, to the cat; but Nature, who is not to be balked, was there and watching, and this was the revenge.

Such was the solution to which at last he arrived. The accusations which she had made had been hatched in the distemper of her brain, and the venomous hatred which she had abruptly displayed was but the working of a natural law.

Logical as it was, this solution did not by any means come at once. Winter had gone, spring was going, and still he groped until, aided by the ray which Jones had intercepted, suddenly he divined the truth. She is insane, he decided, and told himself that of that insanity he would cure her yet.

Thenceforth he had that for an aim. What loyalty, what gentleness, what divine courtesy and affection had not an English gentleman just displayed to a woman who had forever disgraced him, who stood, the whole world looking on, a convicted felon at the dock? And should he, Carol Nevius, be other than loyal, courteous and gentle too? The malady which had prompted that fair English girl to steal was the same, no doubt, as that which had prompted his wife to libel. And when at last the prison door reopened, was not that English gentleman there waiting to take his wife in his arms and carry her off to where health and sanity might be. And when this trial was at an end should not he, too, take his wife in his arms and carry her thence and nurse and guard her until reason returned and love as well? Ah, indeed he would. The cases were not parallel, but if it comforted him to think so, let that comfort be not begrudged.

In this wise months retreated, but with June, presto! a change. Enervated by the delay, possessed, perhaps, of a clearer understanding of resources and temperaments, Mrs. Nevius, in spite of her father and his policy, goaded her attorneys into asking that the matter be brought before a referee.

The day on which that motion was asked and granted, a curious episode occurred. Mr. O’Donnell was offered by an individual whom previously he had never seen, ten thousand dollars in current coin if he would agree to let the suit go against his client, ten thousand more if he carried out the agreement.

“It is not enough,” was O’Donnell’s reply.

On the morrow the offer was doubled, and on the morrow the reply was the same.

XV

The day was hot and humid. In Upper Fifth avenue green blinds were down, and grey doors were up. In the Park there were still carriages, but latterly smartness had been confined the traps of the cocottes, the ethers had livery stables without, the provinces within. Society had vanished to cool retreats, to country houses, and distant shores. In Wall street the chief change was the disappearance of the high hat, the frequency of straw. Men walked more leisurely, too, fanning themselves, choosing the shadows; some were unwaistcoated, and some wore handkerchiefs about the neck.

But that little lady with a waist that would fit in a garter, and who, merely in stepping from her carriage, pervaded the Nassau corner with aromas of the Rue de la Paix, she surely should be at Newport. And that obese little man with the look of one to whom Truth is always stranger than Fiction, what was he doing at her side? Surely he belonged on the box.

And who were these females in clothes not made for them who had just got from a cab? Surely they were detectives, and their duty to protect the little lady from the machinations of that unliveried lackey at her side.

And who, too, was this ponderous person that was now addressing them all. Why had he such a terrible twang? And why, as he spoke, did his words sound like wind escaping from a bladder inflated?

Mystery to all but one that passed that way. And he, though it was hot and humid, at sight of them grew cold. To the lady he raised his hat, and passing into the building before which this disparate group was assembled, had, himself, shot like a rocket five stories high and landed in the office of the Hon. John Metuchen, appointed by the court referee in the case of Nevius versus Nevius.

There was O’Donnell, and there, talking to him, was a white-haired gentleman with a patrician bearing to whom the intruder was introduced.

“Mr. Metuchen, permit me, this is my client, Mr. Nevius.”

“Your most obedient servant, sir,” murmured that courtly old man. Thereat lawyer and client passed into an inner room.

Nevius dropped in a chair. “They’re below,” he mumbled. “But what has she come for? She can’t testify.”

“To the fact of the marriage, she must, and that there has been no previous application. But that done, presumably she will go.”

“I did not expect—”

The sentence was never finished. Mrs. Carol had entered, and at sight of her the defendant grew mute. But he rose from his seat, reseating himself only when that ponderous person who followed had found her a chair. Immediately, Mr. Metuchen appeared. Then a man with paper and pencils, then two females, escorted by Mr. Snaith.

The room was large, high-ceiled, yet to Nevius it seemed very small. O’Donnell and he were at the end of a long table, at the other end of which Mr. Metuchen sat down. On the inner side was the stenographer. And beyond, at the window, the others had taken seat, all, in fact, save the ponderous person, who seemed inclined to stand and domineer.

He was saying something, but what? Nevius neither knew nor cared; he was watching his wife who presently, with that air and manner he loved so well, advanced a little and began to tell about one or two things which no one questioned. Then the business of the hearing seemed about to begin.

“Just bring your chair a little nearer, Becky.”

Becky? Who was Becky? But as one of the females tilted her seat, Nevius recognized the Rebecca of old. But to what was she to testify?

“Now Becky,” twanged the ponderous person, “what is your name? Rebecca Hawes? Very good. And how old are you, Becky? Very good. Have you ever seen this lady before? Oho! you’ve lived with her, have you? In what capacity? As waitress, eh? And have you ever seen that gentleman? Aha! He is Mr. Nevius, is he? Now Becky, what were your duties as waitress? To wait at table? To serve at meals? Very good, very good. And what else? You answered the door, did you? Aha! You answered the door! Now, Becky, in answering the door, in waiting on the table, did you ever see any one by the name of Janet Adulam? Oh, you have, have you? Often? Very often, eh? Very good, Becky, very good. Ever heard Mrs. Nevius say anything about her?”

“Ject,” snapped O’Donnell.

“Well, Counsellor,” the ponderous man with great affability retorted, “we won’t quarrel over a little thing like that; I’ll get at it in another way.”

“Now, Becky,” he continued, “Mrs. Nevius, so far as you could see, treated this Adulam girl like a friend, didn’t she—”

Nevius raised a hand.

“I submit, your Honor, that the attorney should not be permitted to refer to this young gentlewoman in the manner which he has done.”

The referee looked up.

“I think, Mr. Tooth, that Mr. Nevius is perhaps right—”

“Oh! oh!” the man protested, “that’s only my way.”

“The way of a cad,” muttered Nevius.

But the attorney, accustomed since boyhood to being so described, caught up the thread unruffled.

“Now, Becky, am I to understand that you regarded this Miss Adulam as a friend of Mrs. Nevius? I am, am I? And why am I? Because she was always coming there, eh? Well, coming where? Oho! to the Nevius house! I see, I see. But you say she was always coming there. You don’t mean that she liked it so much that she used to come when Mrs. Nevius wasn’t at home? Oho, you do, do you? Well, now, Becky, do you remember any particular occasion that she came when Mrs. Nevius was not at home? Lots of them? Why, what could she do there in Mrs. Nevius’ absence? Be kissed by Mr. Nevius! Do you mean to say that you saw Mr. Nevius kissing her? What, you have seen them in each other’s arms! You saw them? you positively swear that you saw them? Very good, Becky, very good. Now, what else did they do? Ate and drank, did they? Well, while they were eating and drinking what did they talk about? You don’t know? Don’t you remember? Oh, you didn’t understand, eh? And why not? Did they talk in whispers so that you couldn’t hear? Oho! They talked in Spanish, did they? Or in Italian! Any way they talked in some lingo you didn’t understand. Now, then, Becky, when Mrs. Nevius was at home, you have heard Mr. Nevius talking to her, haven’t you? Well tell us then what language he talked to her in? In English did he? No Italian folderols to his wife, eh? Only to Miss Adulam, eh? Very good, Becky, very good indeed. Now, when Mrs. Nevius was at home where did she sit at table? At the head of it, eh? And where did Mr. Nevius sit? At the foot, did he? Well, when this carousing was going on, where did Miss Adulam sit? At the head of the table, too? Took the wife’s place, eh? And where did Mr. Nevius sit? Right beside her! Why, I thought you said he sat at the foot of the table! Oho! he only sat at the foot of the table when his wife was there! I see. But when Miss Adulam came he moved his seat, eh? Sat close to her, I suppose. Well, how close? Close enough, you say. And while they were sitting as close as they could get, they talked in a language you couldn’t understand, did they? Now, when you had finished clearing up in the dining-room where did you go? Downstairs, eh? And when did you come up again? Two or three hours later, eh? Now, what had Miss Adulam and Mr. Nevius been doing in the meantime? You don’t know, you say, but when, at the end of two or three hours, you came upstairs again, you found them in each other’s arms. Is that what I am to understand? Very good. Now when did this occur? On the 10th of November, eh? And was anything of the kind repeated? On the 11th, eh? And on the 12th, and on the 14th? Did you tell any one of these goings on? Oh, you told Mrs. Nevius! What did she do? She accused her husband, did she? And what did he do? He confessed, eh? Confessed what? Confessed that he had been untrue, eh? Then what? Mr. Nevius went abroad did he? And what did Mrs. Nevius do? Packed up and left Mr. Nevius’ house, eh? Has she seen Mr. Nevius since? Hasn’t, eh? Very good, Becky; that will do for today.”

And with an air of satisfaction that would have been unpardonable in Napoleon at Marengo, Mr. Tooth caressed his chin with one hand and waved the other at O’Donnell.

“Brother O’D, if you have any questions—”

“I have,” O’Donnell answered shortly. “Hawes, look this way. Where are you living now?”

“At Mr. Snaith’s.”

“In what capacity?”

“Er—er—” The woman turned helplessly about, and suddenly spat, “Seamstress.”

“Mr. Referee,” said O’Donnell, “I beg you to remind Mrs. Nevius that she is not permitted to prompt the witness. Hawes,” he continued, “look at me. How do you remember the dates you have given?”

The witness made no answer.

“Come, out with it.”

“I—I—I wrote them down each time Miss Adulam came.”

“With what object?”

“Mrs. Snaith told me to.”

“When did she tell you?”

“I don’t remember.”

“Then you have got to remember. Did Mrs. Snaith tell you to keep a memorandum before Miss Adulam began to come to the house or afterward?”

“Afterward, sir.”

“Do you swear to that?”

“Yes, sir.”

“I thought you said you wrote the dates down each time Miss Adulam came.”

“So I did, sir.”

“Why did you?”

“Because Mrs. Snaith told me.”

“A moment ago you said that Mrs. Snaith did not tell you to do so until afterward. Now, look at me, which is it? Did she tell you before or after?”

“Before.”

“Do you swear to that?”

“Yes, sir.”

“Do you know what the penalty for perjury is?”

“I object,” threw in Mr. Tooth airily.

O’Donnell turned to Metuchen: “Here’s a witness, your Honor, who swears to two contradictory statements, and as they are material to—”

“They are not material,” retorted Mr. Tooth. “Mrs. Snaith has nothing to do with this suit. I have shown that Miss Adulam called on the defendant in the plaintiff’s absence. I have also shown what occurred. When Mrs. Snaith learned the facts is irrelevant—”

“But not obscure,” answered O’Donnell; “Mr. stenographer, when does witness swear Mrs. Snaith instructed her to take notes. Before Miss Adulam called? Thank you.”

“Now, Hawes,” he continued. “Besides keeping a memorandum for Mrs. Snaith, to whom did you mention these incidents?”

“To Mrs. Nevius, sir.”

“When?”

“When she returned home, sir.”

“When was that?”

“A few days later.”

“That must have been about the 16th or 17th of November, wasn’t it?”

“Yes, sir.”

“When did Mr. Nevius go abroad?”

“Some time in December.”

“Were you present when Mrs. Nevius accused her husband of being untrue?”

“No, but—”

“I want no buts. Answer yes or no. Did you hear him admit the accusation?”

“Well—he—”

“Answer my question. Did you or did not you?”

“No, sir, I didn’t, I—”

“That’s enough. Of what was the parlor floor composed?”

“Of the dining-room, parlor and butler’s pantry.”

“On the first occasion when Miss Adulam called do you know of her being in any other part of the house than on the parlor floor?”

“No, sir.”

“Can you on any of the subsequent occasions swear that she was in any other part of the house?”

“No, sir.”

“Very good, Becky, that will do for this afternoon.”

Mr. O’Donnell turned to his client, and with the air of one commenting on the weather remarked audibly yet indifferently: “Chops and tomato sauce!”

XVI

Day in, day out, the testimony continued. The cook testified. The waitress recalled, testified anew. The cook testified again, and a third time the waitress took the stand. By common consent objections ceased. Questions inane, idiotic, indecent, passed unchallenged, unrebuked.

Nevius ceased to attend. The coarseness was disgusting enough, but apart from that the presence of one who continued to come perplexed and tormented him. To those who have agreed to be bound by form, no law ever codified is rigider, and but for its shackles, at the first hearing he would have called to her, “Hilda, this is unworthy of you; let us go.” But no remonstrance being possible, it was easier to avoid that chamber where she listened exultingly to each fresh batch of scurrilities concerning himself.

For the exultation was there, one not dissimilar to that which that vestal must have displayed when her lover the gladiator fell and her delicate thumb reversed. It was this that unnerved him. He had fathomed the cause, but the effect he was unable to endure. But soon the exultation, the scurrilities must end, and then in what gentle ways would he woo her back to sanity and herself.

O’Donnell was not so sanguine. “They have got something,” he would insist, “or else Tooth is milking his client. He consumes hours over nothing. Yesterday we learned what you preferred for breakfast. The fact that you drank moselle for dinner was shown to the satisfaction of every one, the stenographer included. Metuchen went into the other room; I read a paper. No one listened except the plaintiff, and, by the way, did you tell me that she was pretty? Why, she is hideous; never in all my life hare I seen a woman with an expression as malignant as hers.”

“Souvent femme varie,” Nevius inconsequently replied.

“You are well rid of her. And the way she bullies Tooth! Were she a client of mine—however, that’s not the point. Tooth must have something else. Thus far the testimony of the servants has the value of a zero from which the periphery has been eliminated. But even otherwise the testimony of detectives is valueless unless corroborated. Tooth knows that, and he knows, too, that I can show the servants to have been in the pay of Mrs. Snaith. Now who is to corroborate them, for, mark my words, some corroboration there will be. Tooth is waiting for something, he is consuming time with no other object. Now what is it?”

“There is nothing. You have heard all you will ever hear.”

But O’Donnell was skeptical as a ragpicker, and with cause. When he next appeared in Tenth street the I-told-you-so was in his eye.

“We are sailing very close to the wind,” he announced. “What do you suppose happened today?”

Nevius was not good at conundrums and said so.

“Your friend Miss Vührer appeared,” the lawyer, with a great assumption of indifference, remarked, and then stopped to enjoy his client’s surprise.

“Did she?” that client answered, but with an apathy that was stagnant. “I had forgotten that she lived.”

“I had not, then. Though I admit I was not prepared for what occurred. Yesterday Tooth began with the waitress about her, showed that you were closeted with her for hours and exhibited a hairpin which was found on that sofa where you are sitting now. I had so little difficulty in putting that hairpin straight back into Mrs. Nevius’ hair that even Metuchen laughed.”

“Well?”

“Well, that was merely the prelude. This morning she appeared, as Jones would say, in impropriâ personâ. No, Nevius, she is worse than Becky, though, after all, she must get higher pay. With her was counsel, if you please, retained, of course, by Tooth. Pennell his name is, B. F. Pennell. When I saw him I knew that the surprise was at hand. He is a bad egg, but rottener than I had believed. Do you know, the plaintiff is very clever. It was she, I will take my oath, who put Tooth up to it.”

The apathy which Nevius had displayed was departing, he came nearer to O’Donnell and stood, looking at him, impatient of details and phrases. Was the diagnosis wrong, after all? Was there another explanation of this mystery? Only the day before he had asked himself that question. And now what was the cleverness over which O’Donnell seemed inclined to harp?

“Tooth is fly enough,” the lawyer was saying, “but unaided he would never have thought of this. Pennell got the young woman on the stand, and in no time at all had her white as snow. He had her take off her bonnet and show that in those blonde curls of hers there was not a hairpin to be found, he had her explain at some length that while her relations with you had been most friendly and pleasant, they had been also entirely innocent and that you had invariably treated her like what she called ‘a perfect gentleman.’ Then he turned her over to Tooth.”

“Well?”

“Tooth began very greasily; he asked her a few gentle little questions which gave her an opportunity to repeat all she had said, and finally brought out that a few months ago you had met her in the street and had assured her you were doing everything to serve her interests. Very nice as far it goes, isn’t it? Wait a bit. ‘And what did you say to Mr. Nevius?’ Tooth asked. ‘I asked Mr. Nevius,’ the little beast answered, ‘whether the other young lady was as innocent as I was?’ ‘And what was Mr. Nevius’ reply?’ Tooth inquired. ‘Mr. Nevius’ reply was that unfortunately she was not.’ ”

“That she was not?” gnashed Nevius.

“That is what she swore.”

“Then to the Tombs she goes.”

“There, it’s only your word against hers. You can do nothing.”

“But something must be done.”

“Precisely, and for that purpose I have got an adjournment. Now where is Miss Adulam? She must appear. There is no use in her standing on her dignity any longer. Where is she?”

“In Boston,” Nevius answered. “And she is ill.”

“Though she come on a shutter, come she must. Write her the facts, tell her the moment she arrives to communicate with me, but write to her at once.” With that the lawyer left.

For an hour Nevius sat, uncertain how to act. He tried to write and did, page after page, but the point he was unable to reach. No matter what circumlocutions he attempted, no matter how delicate the shadings, the fact stood out, bald and repugnant, that the accusation must stand unless rebutted by herself. And there had been his pride, could pride there be where only shamelessness was, that this young gentlewomen had answered the accusation in the only manner which it deserved, by making no answer at all. How was he to tell her to unseal her unsullied lips? Though he used arguments that might lure a saint from Paradise, the abomination would still be there, he was asking her to be cross-questioned in regard to her honor by a man such as his wife had employed. No, he could not. Better a thousand times the divorce than that ineffaceable indignity to her. Something else there must be. But what? As a child who plays a game, he felt that something burning yet still withheld. And suddenly it was his.

The letter which he presently wrote was not, however, for Miss Adulam, it was addressed to her uncle, Erastus Wilberforce. And as it lay signed and sealed before him, he covered his face with his hands. When he stood up, an illusion had unmasked, he had looked in his heart, it was empty.

The morrow was blank. Another day went by, during which he wandered through that dismal house from which even a ghost had fled. At noon, on the third day, a wire came:

Victory! Will be with you at nine.

“J. O’DONNELL.”

The message left him strangely unmoved, though one may wonder whether spring is sweeter than summer to a flower once dead. Punctual as a comet, the lawyer appeared. “Look at that!” he exclaimed. “You told me that Miss Adulam was a thoroughbred, but you didn’t tell me she was another Lady Flora Hastings too.”

At the paper he extended Nevius glanced and shuddered. It was a certificate, attested by two physicians that Miss Janet Adulam was virgo intacta.

“Why, Nevius, it is the Hastings affair over again. It will turn Tooth inside out. Outwitted, foiled, cornered, undone is that unholy shyster. Farewell to the Nevius divorce! And I may tell you Metuchen will be tickled to death. So far as he could he intimated he was with us every trip. I think I will take a drink. But what the devil are you looking so glum for? Nevius, listen to me, it was your duty to deny everything, but till I got that certificate, I’ll be shot if—”

Nevius checked him as with a bit. “What will Tooth do?” he asked, and so seriously that O’Donnell’s jubilance evaporated. “What will he do when you produce this thing?”

“Increase the charges on his bill. I suppose. What is there for him to do except to return to his Tombs practice?”

“Do you know,” added Nevius absently, “I would prefer it not to go on record.”

“Are you mad?” O’Donnell snarled. “This is the case. We have won it without calling a witness. Could I have foreseen it, do you suppose I would have bothered over those wenches your wife employed?”

Nevius shook his head, his eyes strange and weary.

“No, and could I have foreseen that my wife—O’Donnell, the point is here. If you show this privately to Tooth he will understand that he has lost. And yet he likes to win, does he not?

“Where is the attorney who don’t? I myself—”

“Yes, I know. You have been very kind, O’Donnell, but there is one thing more you can do. Show this to Tooth, tell him to withdraw the charge against Miss Adulam, to amend his complaint, and if he agrees, assure him that I will not further contest his efforts.”

“I don’t understand.”

“After this Vührer business, he is not above a trick or two, is he? Tell him to invent a corespondent, the servants he can coach to testify to what he wants, and—the divorce is his. I am tired of it all. O’Donnell, do this for me, won’t you?”

Sweet to the profession is the smell of an enemy’s corpse, and just as that fragrance was to be O’Donnell’s why should he be taken afar? He was not at all pleased and said so, but to the loss of the odors for which he had hungered, at last he became reconciled. A fortnight later a report was handed up recommending that divorce be granted to Hilda Nevius, plaintiff, on the ground of her husband’s illicit commerce with a woman unknown. Which report was promptly and properly confirmed.

A day or two and Nevius found his name again in leaded type. Beneath, augmented with new embroideries, was the old story retold. There was the initial accusation of the grief-stricken wife, his own admission of guilt and headlong flight. Then his return, denying everything but doing nothing to defend charges which had just been substantiated in full. According to the reporter the evidence was of such a character that it had to be heard in camera. Nevius had not even had the courage to appear. But every accusation had been proved, and now his poor, wounded wife, who had borne with his infidelities until forbearance had ceased to be a virtue, at last was free. In dissolving the miserable bands the court had granted her permission to assume her maiden name, a permission of which she would at once avail herself. She was the daughter of the wealthy banker, Thomas B. Snaith, and very prominent in society, as were also the corespondents, one of whom was a dashing western widow, the other, one of Saratoga’s reigning belles. And so on and so forth at the rate of eight dollars a column and a tenner for the “beat.” “The Lord loveth a cheerful liar,” Nevius reflected as he put the Chronicle down.

But O’Donnell had not been deprived of certain fragrances for nothing. He wrote a note, the substance of which—that Miss Adulam had been fully exonerated and her name withdrawn—appeared on the morrow in the Chronicle’s obscurest corner and in the Chronicle’s smallest type.

XVII

The paths to happiness are not many, but they are well defined. The finger-posts of the easiest are those which point to health and indifference.

But there are others that have a value, and between them the wayfarer has halted and will halt and conjecture. One leads to religion, and the pilgrim, if he be sorely depressed and temperamentally disposed will find it an excellent route. It may be tortuous, the goal may be remote, there may be ghosts at the crossings, but at least the traveller has that greatest of consolations—the belief that he is still a child, watched over and protected.

Another leads to that pure realm of ideas where individual preoccupations may not enter, where only the mysteries of beauty and of life endure.

But this route, rarely chosen, is adapted but to the student to whom solitude can offer the dual advantage of being with himself and of not being with others.

Nevius selected it. Health had ceased to interest him, temperamentally he was too nervous to acquire and preserve that suspension of judgment of which indifference is the fruit; and mentally he was too agile to accept dogmas unquestioned. He indeed tried to fatigue the mind in the fatigue of the body, but when, after hours of that sponge for thought which the saddle alone supplies, there was a question-mark in waiting. The why and wherefore of the divorce haunted him still. And as law was no longer possible, and his career at an end, he had a choice between drink and study. In the former he tried to drown that interrogation mark. But the interrogation mark knew how to swim. Then he plunged into history.

Between Caesar and Heliogabalus there was a moment when the gods no longer were, when Christ had not come, when man alone existed. In disgust of modernity it was to that epoch that he turned. The classics were at his elbow, and in the splendors which they evoked he reconstructed Rome. Presently the booksellers were at work and he had invoices of curious lore. Before the roses could fade he wreathed himself with them. He had adventures in the Subura, escapades with dazzling young empresses and relived the inimitable life. To the hum of harps he floated on a ship that had gardens, bowers, spangled sails and a jewelled prow. On painted elephants he quarried lions in their African fens. Throbbing through the rushes of the Nile there came to him the grave music of archaic hymns. Serapis whispered to him. Isis visited him unveiled. He sailed the Aegean, scaled Parnassus, lounged in the Academe. He prayed in temples that never heard an atheist’s voice, passed initiate into the mysteries of Eleusis, encountered divinities and monsters, curious superstitions and untenable creeds. He found grace and lust, deformity and magnificence, unimagined depravities, torturesome delights. He wandered from palace to lupanar, from prison to shrine, from forum to camp. There was not a sin nor an altar that he passed unexamined, not a secret that he left unprobed.

When antiquity was his, he rose from its study perplexed. Nowhere had he encountered hypocrisy. Therewith the Why returned.

XVIII

“Yes, I am off for Europe. For centuries I have been travelling on the map, now I am to try another tack. Come with me, Carol. You don’t know what a charming companion I am. No one does. I never open my head.”

Jones, a leg over the arm of a chair, a cigarette in his fingers, a smile of protracted amiability fluttering in and out his tawny beard, was discounting the pleasures of a trip abroad.

“In the autumn we could visit that city from which you have just returned. Mention Egypt and you see a priest, Persia, and you see a king, Greece—a goddess, but Rome was Might Triumphant. And to think that I have never been there—in this existence I mean, for I can swear I have jolted in chariots over those wide white roads. I can swear that I have supped with Lalage and thrown dice with Faustine. When I read history, memories return in floods. Let us go together and see what remains of the temples in which we have lived.”

He puffed at his cigarette. “And such good as it would do you. A change of scene and you would begin to forget. You need to forget. This accursed divorce is assuming the proportions of a pyramid. It is over a year since it ended, and still you brood. You will kill yourself as Tredegar has if you sit moping in this horror of a house. Not but what I appreciate the advantage of sorrow. Che non soffre, non vince—non Leonardo da Vinci. The tragedy of my life is that there has been no tragedy at all. If I have not written a great novel, there is the cause. An artist’s one value consists in his sorrows. They are all aspirations. The world is filled with people whose lives are so puerile, whose aims are so narrow that we should bless the misfortune which makes us nobler than they. Why, grief is a pleasure, it is a joy to weep. But—”

“Si je doute des larmes!” Nevius inconsequently objected. “C’est que je l’ai vu pleurer.”

“Ah, we have been reading de Musset have we? Fort bien, Monseigneur, fort bien, mais écoute:

“N’ es-tu pas jeune, heureux, partout le bien venu,
Et ces plaisirs légers qui font aimer la vie,
Si tu n’avais pleuré, quel cas en ferais-tu?
Lorsqu’au déclin du jour, assis sur la bruyère—
La bruyère c’est ton fauteuil—
Avec un vieil ami—le vieil ami, c’est moi—tu bois en liberté—
Oh, pour ca! Comme un Polonais même—
Dis moi, d’aussi bon coeur lèveras-tu ton verre
Si tu n’avais senti le prix de la gaieté?
Aimerais-tu les fleurs, les prés et la verdure
Les sonnets de Pétrarque et le chant des oiseaux,
Michel-Ange et les arts, Shakespeare et la nature
Si tu n’y retrouvais quelques anciens sanglots?
Comprendrais-tu des cieux l’ ineffable harmonie,
Le silence des nuits, le murmure des flots
Si quelque part, làbas, la fiévre et l’insomnie
Ne t’ avait fait songer a l’ éternel repos?
Plains la donc, plains la donc, cette belle infidèle—”

“Yes, had she been that,” Nevius interrupted, moved in spite of himself by the beauty of lines which he, too, knew by heart. “Had she been infidèle, I could see my way clearer. But though a year has gone by since she got the decree, still I am unable to understand why she asked for it. There was a moment when I thought her insane, when I thought, God forgive me, that this affair at an end I could win her back, reason with her, plead with her, love her again. But there was no insanity in her eyes when we met in court, a malignant exultation merely. And why? That Why is the first thing I find in the morning, the last that leaves me at night. For a year I have been haunted by interrogation marks, they are everywhere, they are in the food I eat. I close my eyes and still I see them. Even in sleep they pursue me, they fill my dreams.”

“It is of course supposable,” Jones, with singular acquiescence, replied, “that in asking for a divorce this lady had a motive. The malignity was due to your effort to thwart her. The exultation came of the prospect of showing that her lies were true.”

“But why drag herself through all that mud? I am a gentleman at least, am I not? If she wanted a divorce why in God’s name didn’t she tell me before I went to Paris. I am not a bit better than another, I have had my little hearts as well as anyone else, and I could have got it for her, without scandal, without disgrace, without the ruin of three lives—Well, Patrick, what is it?”

From the tray which the man held he took a pink card, gilt-edged.

“A lady, sir.”

Jones laughed loud and long. “En avant les amourettes. Va donc, farceur.”

“Blythe Sisseton,” Nevius repeated. “Never heard of her. Patrick, ask her what she wants.”

“That’s Ablaut’s Ex,” said Jones, as Patrick turned, but he bit his tongue as he did so.

“Ablaut’s Ex?”

“Oh, a little chorus girl whom he invited to dance the waltz in Faust. Man proposes you know, and chorus girls accept. But in accepting she meant Forever and he meant Tonight.”

“Well?”

“That’s all. What do you expect? A threevolume novel? He wrote Finis on a cheque ages ago. In the circumstances it would be foolish of you to see her.”

“Foolish of me? What in thunder do you mean? What have I got to do with her? Why should it be foolish of me to see her? But what are you staring at me for?”

“I’m not staring at you;” Jones snapped back. “I am merely giving you a little friendly advice. The girl is probably here out of curiosity, to have a look at the defendant in a cause célebre. If you are going to make a freak of yourself, run right down and show yourself off. But in your place I would send word that I was out, that I was dead. Now here’s Patrick—”

“She says she won’t detain you but a moment, sir, she—”

Nevius stood up and made for the door. Before he could reach it Jones had him by the arm.

“Carol, let me go.”

Without a word Nevius shook him off and left the room. But what was the meaning of that strange look he had?

“Does he suspect?” The novelist queried. “But when he knows!” He paused and looked about. “Anything would be better than to see the newspapers dripping again with his name. I must suggest something, but what?”

Ten minutes later the front door closed. When Nevius reentered the library Jones was reading Spinoza.

“You knew this!” Nevius blurted. The strange look had gone from his face, but a stranger one had come. He was livid, and the corners of his mouth had widened. “Why have I been gulled on every side? Why could you not tell me?”

“Dear boy, what omniscience is it that you attribute to me?” And Jones tossed aside the book he held and smiled. “The announcement of your lady’s engagement to Ablaut, if it is that to which you refer, was news to me until I read it in the Herald this morning.”

“Bah! Why didn’t you tell me she was his mistress? Why couldn’t you have told me? I committed suicide because of that woman. And look at these letters!”

But Jones had no need to look at those blue, iris-scented communications, each stamped with the Nevius crest, to divine what they contained.

“Look at them,” Nevius repeated. “Months before she began that suit, she was writing to him things like these.”

With a wrench he tore his collar apart.

“Why couldn’t you have told me,” he gasped, “why—why?”

“How could I, dear boy, I didn’t know,” the novelist with splendid mendacity replied. “But supposing, even that suspecting such a thing, I had so much as hinted at it, you would have held me up. ‘Your evidence or your life,’ you would have bawled. And I am not like you, Carol, alone in the world. I have my publishers to support. But now that the cat is out of the bag, the one thing for you to do is to say Schwamm darüber and pray that Ablaut may make an honest woman of her. Do sit down now and be quiet. Write to him, why don’t you? Paper is a splendid conductor for steam. Send him your congratulations. Say that you have just learned of the engagement, and that if the fair betrothed makes him half as happy as she has made you, he is the man of all others to be envied.”

“Yes,” Jones continued with a twist to his beard, but an eye on his host. “A little eighteenth-century politesse of that kind is far better than big words and short phrases. Anything, Carol, anything but a row. I don’t wonder though that you look as if a scrap would be a revel. Divorce is like matrimony, dear boy, a fellow has got to go through it three or four times before he knows how. By the time this lady gets done, what an expert she will be! It is true she is exceptionally gifted, facile principessa, as one might say, but—now give that to me, I am ashamed of you.”

“It is not loaded,” Nevius muttered from between his teeth.

“Even if it is not, it is capable of becoming so I suppose. Were Ablaut in this room and you shot him you would be acquitted—provided these letters were read. But would you permit them to go before a jury? I wouldn’t let the villain in a novel defend himself at the expense of a woman’s honor, and you, Carol, are a gentleman in flesh and blood. You remember that episode at Nice. There the lady showed even less foresight. The husband surprised the lover in her arms, but when he shot, civilization revolted at the medievalism of the act. Legally he was justified, but law and good breeding are not the same.”

Jones gave another twist to his beard and the douche of words continued.

“No, dear boy, you can’t shoot Ablaut. On the contrary, you should be very nice to him. He is in trouble. He has been led astray, and these are the wages of sin. From the announcement of the engagement I suppose he considers that this lady is in honor bound to make reparation, and while I can understand that, I can not understand what induced him to commit the error which makes the reparation needful. No, he deserves your sympathy. A more venomous, soulless little catin than she who is to lead him to the halter—altar, I mean—doesn’t exist, and never has, outside the walls of St. Lazare.”

“H’m—”

Nevius muttered something, but whether in agreement or rebuke, Jones did not care. He drawled on uninterruptedly in the leisurely fashion in which he had begun:

“This morning, when I read the announcement, it took me a moment before I understood why she waited as long as she has. Knowing her, as several of us do, it was quite on the cards that she should bring Ablaut to book the day the decree was signed. But remember on what grounds it was granted. The woman in the amended complaint existed only in Tooth’s imagination, and existed there only at your suggestion. It was the Frick case upside down. Tandems and tally-ho’s could have been driven straight through it—which was the reason, I fancy, when the newspapers were jubilating over your defeat that you held your tongue. And, by the way, do you know who it was that inspired that jubilee? This lady, dear boy, no one else. She had the articles written to order, and she had marked copies sent to every one she knew. Actually she sent one to me. She did not think it worth while, though, to send O’Donnell’s contradiction. Ah, mais non!” And Jones drew breath.

“But to return to the point, had she led Ablaut to the altar as precipitately as she led you to court, you, had you chosen, could have vitiated her decree, vitiated her marriage, and very neatly turned the tables by applying for a divorce from her. All that you could have done, dear boy, more too, had she been stupid enough to let you. But she wasn’t. The dear little thing knew a trick worth two of that. You had one year in which to appeal, yesterday the year expired; today the engagement is announced. And you can do nothing. Not a thing, dear boy. You can’t even shoot her; no, not any more than you can shoot Ablaut. Put any such idea as that out of your head. She has been malignant as syphilis, I admit; she has disgraced, corroded and destroyed; her conduct has been without parallel, without excuse; that she should be lapidated I admit also; I have nothing but contempt for her; she has unsexed herself, and if you struck her in the face with your glove, you would pay her an honor she does not deserve. But you can’t shoot her. To defend any such act these letters would have to be read. And though you may say now that they could be read, and not only that but all the secrets of this divorce be ventilated, yet when the time came you would permit nothing of the sort, and you would be electrocuted, dear boy, because of this fallatrix for whose sake a skunk is too good to die.”

The novelist paused and contemplated his fingertips. Presently, with a glance that noted the effects of the douche, he began anew:

“No, you are too young, life holds too many possibilities yet, for you to jeopardize it for her or for her maquereau either. Could you kill her, as I have killed many a culprit in my novels, without a suspicion resting on the executioner, I am rather inclined to think I would approve. But the difficulty is that she is not under your roof and not being a cracksman you can’t get under hers. Were she here in Tenth street, a bit of catgut tied across the head of the stairs, a slight shove, and there you are. The catgut vanishes and another accident in high life is recorded. Failing that, you could try a folding-bed; many a person has been smothered in them, you could imitate Incoul and turn on the gas when she was asleep, you could give her a vibrio in a mushroom, or squeeze a taste of cyanide of potassium into her champagne. Any one of these things, or of a hundred others, you could do if she were here, but luck is hers and she isn’t.

“Now, in view of all the circumstances, were this one of my novels, I would have the injured hero experiment in what will be one of the fine arts of the next century—Execution at a Distance. There are bunglers who send explosives by express, which is well enough in its way when it happens to be successful, but even then the intention is manifest and the police are running right and left. The art of Execution at a Distance, as practiced by the adept, will consist in projecting an agent in such a manner that it kills and leaves no trace either of its purpose or of its advent.

“For instance—by the way, I think I will take a little of that whisky—for instance, a young man is enamoured of a young woman. Difficulties ensue. Correspondence there must be, but how? By invisible ink, let us say, which becomes visible when breathed upon. For a year and a day the young man writes to his Dulcinea with ink of this description. Suddenly she wearies or lie does. What does he do, give her aconite pills? He gives a sheet of paper a bath of hydrocyanic, a coating of starch to protect it and drops it in a letter box. When the young woman receives it, she breathes on it to decipher what he has written, and falls dead, a piece of white paper in her hands. Coroner’s verdict: heart disease.

“On the other hand, supposing he has had no time or no need to train her to the advantages of invisible ink. As a love-token he sends her a box of flowers saturated with a similar preparation. She opens the box, the hydrocyanic escapes and she is dead. Verdict: heart failure.”

The novelist emptied his glass and looked at Nevius. But the latter had got his face in the shadow, a hand before it as well.

“All that,” Jones added thoughtfully, “all that is for the Year of our Lord 2001. Nowadays people have such prejudices, and yet if stupidity hurt how many would yell!”

For a while neither spoke, and to amuse himself perhaps, Jones took a sheet of paper and began to scribble. Presently he looked up.

“But what a rattling good story the whole thing would make. And what a lot I could do with you. I could begin with you from the cradle, carry you right through everything, put your hat on and kill you. Suicide is always a good climax. And I could call it—let me see, I should have to find something comprehensive, a title both neat and terse, one that would convey an entire existence.”

His eyes roamed to the ceiling, consulted the pencil, fell again on the paper on which he had written, and lighted sagaciously.

“I have it—From Womb to Tomb. Carol, dear boy, what do you say to that?”

As Nevius seemingly had nothing to say, Jones nodded complacently to himself and rose from his seat.

“I have accomplished my object, beau ténébreux. I have bored you so that your anger is gone. Thank me now and let me go also, but remember I sail on Saturday and you must sail, too.”

For a while longer Nevius sat, a hand before his face. But behind that hand were passing the incidents of the day: the coming of that little girl, the letters which she had found in her lover’s rooms, letters with which she had threatened the lover until threats were idle and his engagement was announced. And these letters, brought to him with the intelligence of that engagement, were written by one who had pretended to love him, whom he had defended, lauded and worshipped, who called herself Mrs. Nevius still and who had wrecked three lives. Back to him crowded the memories of the past. The scraps of the letter found in the basket. That was to Jenny, was it? How clever she had been that day. How cleverly black had been turned to white. How clever, too, had been her tactics in regard to that poor girl. And with what neatness and despatch had she not brought Vührer to the house. Yes, she had been very clever, but the cleverest thing of all was in declaring herself brokenhearted. And this was the little Hilda whom he thought would be so sorry when she learned the truth. The truth indeed! It had been for him to learn it. And now that he had—Madam Sapphira, be on your guard!

He repeated the menace; the echo perhaps aroused him. On the table were the letters, and near them a bit of paper embroidered with pencil-marks, the rough sketch of a tombstone, on which in neat characters was writ:

Here Lies Hilda Snaith,
And That is All She Ever Did.
Requies catin pace.

At this effort of the novelist’s he barely glanced; his eyes were fumbling the shelves. There was a book on chemistry that he wanted, and having got it he opened it, questioned it, and sitting down again interrogated the future and roamed through the past.

XIX

The Why had gone. He was no longer haunted, he knew. There are people to whom doubt is better than certainty and Nevius was one of them. The problem had occupied him; that gone he had nothing left—a duty merely—to which he presently turned his attention.

Of the incidents remote and dismissed which had suddenly returned was one he detained—the memory of a young girl examining her wedding gifts. Among these gifts were two vinaigrettes, and he could see her still, holding one, then the other to the mirror to judge which was the more becoming. The choice made, the rejected vinaigrette had been returned to Tiffany and some exchange effected.

It was the one incident of the old prenuptial days that had jarred, and it had particularly jarred in that the vinaigrette which had been exchanged, was the gift to his bride of one whose hand he had held and whose hand he had loved to hold. Apart, then, from any sentiment which he might have attached to the tribute, the commercial aspect with which it was regarded annoyed, and continued to annoy until, other incidents intervening, it was forgot.

But it had returned, and of an afternoon when the heat was such that man and beast fell dead in the streets he ventured out to shop. There was a scent-bottle, covered with gems, one which it would delight any woman to have and display, which, without any difficulty, he made his own. And there was also a phial of anhydrous prussic acid—but that he did not obtain until he had produced a jumble of Latin and hieroglyphics.

Later, in the quiet of the library, with mouth and nostrils bandaged, his eyes protected, his hands well gloved, he poured the contents of the phial into the jewelled toy, and re-stoppering both bottles, removed the bandage and breathed. It is not every neophite whose initial effort in laboratory work is attended with such success, and that fact he doubtless appreciated, for having breathed, he smiled. If all else failed, might he not turn chemist? The idea must have amused him, for, as he put the vinaigrette back in its case, the smile was still there, and as he wrapped up the case and directed it, he laughed. But then, chemistry is one of the most delightful pursuits imaginable, and he had been so long unoccupied that a possibility with even less perspective might have charmed.

Yet where, apart from Ceylon, is that prospect which always pleases? An hour had not passed before the vistas disclosed must have lost their allurement. The laughter, the smile had gone. In their place came a look perplexing and enervating, and through the quiet of the house pulsated a throbbing so loud, so loud, that to still it, perhaps, too, to rid his mind of chemistry and its charms, he drank.

It was the drink, no doubt, which on the morrow confined him to his room. But such a sedative is rest that on the succeeding day he was able to get to the floor below and breakfast too. Melon is not unpalatable at any hour, and when he had eaten a little he was quite in the humor to smoke a cigarette and learn the news of the day. It was the Times which he selected for the purpose, and after reading of the Homestead rebellion as he turned from the fourth page where the editorials are to the fifth where the advertisements such as death notices appear, the paper fell from him, the name Nevius had jumped out and stabbed him in the eyes.

He got to the window, the court was deluged with sunshine, and on the fence a piebald cat was enjoying a promenade.

But could it be possible that that package had been sent? Had he not hid it somewhere?

With a sidelong suspicious glance the cat continued its gingerly way.

Could it be possible? he repeated. But what had he done with it? Why could he not collect his thoughts? He went upstairs, and down once more, and up again. Patrick appeared, he fled away. He could not go out, he could not sit still, he could neither write nor speak, nor act nor think, and in his bedroom where he hid at last, he locked the door.

If rest be a sedative, suspense is not. And do what he might, suspense urged him from sofa to armchair, from armchair to sofa, and finally to the library, that he might see for himself if the package were there.

On the table was a telegram. It was from Bronx he knew. But not a bit.

“Touraine sails at noon tomorrow. Your berth retained. Have wired congratulations to Mrs. A.

“A. B. Fenwick Chisholm-Jones.”

Congratulations to Mrs. A! Who was Mrs. A? He put the telegram down and looked about. There was no one to reply. But who was Mrs. A? What had he to do with any Mrs. A?

Again he looked about. But still there was no one. Yet he must ask, he must speak, he must know. The bell was there, he rang it but could not wait and ran to the hall.

“Patrick,” he called. “Patrick.”

“Yes, sir, coming, sir.”

“Patrick,” he cried, while the man was yet below. “Patrick, what is there in the papers today?”

“In the papers, sir!”

“Tell me, can’t you. Don’t you see I am going mad. What was in the papers? Who is Mrs. A?”

Perplexed, astounded, the man halted midway on the stair.

“There’s a Mrs. Nevius who has been and married a gentleman whose name I disremember, sir, but—”

“Then why the devil couldn’t you say so before. Come up here. Don’t you hear me? Come up I tell you. I am going to Europe tomorrow and I want you to pack. And Patrick—”

“Yes, sir.”

“Here’s a hundred or more that you may find serviceable.” And as Nevius turned on his heel, gently if incorrectly, he repeated a verset from the Scriptures.

“Beautiful on the hill-slope are the feet of the bearer of glad news.”

But what he meant by that absurdity who shall say?

Beaumaris, August, London, October, 1892

Once Is Enough

Through the eager glitter of Fifth Avenue, Grace Waldron drove to her home. The landau, the liveries, the cherry-bays caught the eye, deflecting it to her. In the transverse stream of traps and motors, women smiled and nodded. On the sidewalk, men turned and stared.

Born a Varick, which is something; the wife of Christopher Waldron, which is something more; currently quoted “among those present”; young, rich, beautiful, intelligent—and, for good measure, not too intelligent—in her radiant landau she represented that which is everywhere phenomenal, an absolutely happy woman. The spiderous Fates who sit and spin are on the watch for such as she.

At the Amsterdams that afternoon, she had had with her Louie May, a young Philadelphian who, since they left Newport, had been stopping at her house. But, during the reception, in the sea of millinery that filled the rooms, the girl had been engulfed. Momentarily she had caught a glimpse of her, stranded at a gold and Sèvres heaped buffet and talking there with Nicholas Brevort—an old beau of her own—then, in the rising tides, she had been swept away. Vainly, for awhile, Grace had looked until, concluding that the girl would follow unless she had already preceded her, she had driven off alone.

That evening, Brevort was to dine with them and afterward they were all to go on to the opera, of which it was the opening night. It was yet early, barely five. In spite of the buffet at the Amsterdams, Grace had had nothing and, being healthy, as a beautiful woman must be, she felt she would like some tea, and rather hoped that on reaching home her husband would be in to have it with her.

Her marriage had been a love match. Christopher Waldron enjoyed the reputation of being the best dressed man in town, a reputation, which while perhaps formidable, is perhaps not much to boast of. But Waldron had other qualities. Behind an appearance politely peremptory, that air of being accustomed to instant obedience, he had a manner rarely seductive; the charm which certain New Yorkers used to have and which has gone with old New York. To Grace Varick, imbued by her people with the gentle traditions of gentler days, that charm was myrrh and cassia. Delightedly she had succumbed to it. Since then on her bed of roses not once had she found the crumpled leaf.

Now, as the radiant landau swung along the glittering street, she thought of what she would put on that evening and wondered what Louie would wear. The evening previous the girl had managed to present an appearance of such slim nakedness, that while, in view of that demon, the Mode, there was nothing you could put your finger on—metaphorically, that is—otherwise there was place and to spare. But that was the fault of Fashion. Louie was as nice a girl as ever lived. A bit too incandescently pretty perhaps, but that was not her fault either. On the morrow she was to return to Philadelphia. It could not be helped, though Chris had protested. He liked the girl, and what he liked was, well, hors concours. Nick Brevort probably also liked her. Yet one never knew. Concerning the girl he had been mum. But he was always that way. Had he been less non-committal, then, before the myrrh and cassia came, Grace might have been Mrs. Nick.

But now the landau, swinging into a side street, stopped. An automaton, suddenly alive, sprang from the box, bounded like a chamois up the steps, touched the bell, touched his hat, and Grace was in her home—one less spectacular than the Amsterdams, but almost as spacious and perhaps in better taste.

Abandoning her wraps to a footman, she entered a suite of rooms, at the end of which was a room much smaller than the others, consequently more intimate and in which, for that reason, she occasionally had tea. As though to accentuate its privacy, before the entrance draperies hung.

Lifting a portière, she was about to enter, when, with an intake of the breath, she dropped it and moved back.

It is impossible, she told herself. After the manner of those whom the incredible confronts and to whom it always seems unreal, she found but that. It is impossible, she repeated. To assure herself, she was about to raise the portière again when, intuitively, she desisted. Unbelievable as truth sometimes is, she had seen it. To shut it out, she closed her eyes, but, behind the lids, photographed on encephalic films, there they stood, Chris and Louie, his arms about her, in the attitude of a man to whom a girl has yielded, her mouth raised to his.

There is no mistaking that, and Grace misunderstood it so little that now, the sense of unreality gone, one of her selves—the least known to her, the wholly primitive, the animal that is in us all—was inciting her to tear the curtains aside, to rush in, to upbraid and denounce. But the relapse passed as rapidly as it had come. Another condition succeeded it. She felt sick at her stomach. With an effort she dominated that. Yet the effort, exerted on nerves already overstrung, created still another condition. She wanted to get away and hide.

To get anywhere she had to cross the hall, and there there were servants. Conscious of that, galvanised, too, by the instinct of form which enables a woman of the world to conceal any emotion, at once, with head erect, she went out. She ascended the stair, entered her bedroom, locked the door, and at last, securely alone, the instinct of form fell by, another, one more human, asserted itself, tears came, slowly at first, then torrentially.

It was not anger now that she felt, mere wretchedness, the despair which those only know who suddenly find themselves forsaken. Still she wept. Presently, ceasing to be a mere bag of pain and impulse, she re-became the normal woman.

In the first paroxysm she had thrown herself on her bed. Now, the feminine prompting, she stood up, looked in the mirror. The woman behind the cherry-bays, the beauty at whom men had turned and stared, where was she? Her eyes were bloodshot, the lids swollen, the face lined. That was no way to enter into a campaign, she told herself, for, as she had already decided, a campaign there must be.

She rang for her women. An hour later, bathed, massaged, dressed, she planned it.

But, already on the floor below, a counter plot had been organized. Unknown to Grace, Louie through half-closed eyes had seen her. At the sight, wholly momentary, those half-closed eyes had dilated. The girl tore herself from Waldron, indicated the curtains and beneath her breath, less with her voice than with her lips, threw it at him.

“Grace!”

That was all, but it was enough. Waldron straightened, turned, motioned at Louie to seat herself and took up a paper. But his eyes were on the curtains. A minute, another, yet another and still no movement, no sound, nothing.

He rustled the paper. “Aïda! I have supped on Aïda. Let’s have some tea.”

In speaking he went to the curtains, parted them. Beyond the rooms stretched ornate and vacant.

He turned to the girl. “You were dreaming.”

“Dreaming!” she repeated. She had left her seat. At the moment she hated him as only a girl can hate a man who has got her in a scrape. If this thing became known, socially she was dished. “Dreaming! I saw her!”

“I’ll ask,” said Waldron. He passed through the curtains. When he came back he nodded.

At the nod, she bridled. “You see I was right.”

Waldron looked at her. She was abominably pretty, but she was not worth it.

“We’ll have to get to work,” he announced.

“To work! At what?”

“At getting you out of this.”

“And yourself, too.”

“I was thinking of Grace.”

“What do you suppose she will do?”

“To you? Nothing. Grace is a gentlewoman.

“Well, then?”

But Waldron now was looking at the ceiling, from it he looked at the floor. Presently he approached the girl, and to make sure that no one but she should hear, he whispered.

At once the coral of her mouth contracted. Usually her voice was pitched in sol bémol, the tone of it caressed the ear, stirred the pulse. Now, when he had done and she answered, it grated.

“I won’t.”

Waldron’s eyes narrowed. “I am sorry, but we will have to face the music.”

She moved back. “Not to that tune then. Old, fat and, what’s worse, a pauper! I never heard anything so ridiculous. What would my people say?”

“Damn your people,” thought Waldron. But he did not tell her that. Instead, he parried.

“But, when it is all over, they will have nothing to say. Meanwhile you have yourself to consider—yourself and Grace. I said she would do nothing, nor will she, to you at least, except perhaps to cut you. That would be awkward.”

At the thrust, Louie, who had been standing, sat down, crossed her legs, tormented the tip of her delicate nose. It would be awkward, very. Perhaps the other way were best. For a moment she considered it, then, with youth’s mobility, agreed.

“Very good; though, if between us we muff it, why then—”

Waldron caught her up. “We must not muff it. Fortunately, my part is the hardest, you have but to follow the lead. Before dinner I will send you a box of roses. If, in the box, there is a card, then go ahead, tell her at once.”

At the program and the possibilities it evoked, Louie laughed.

“I say, Chris, not roses, lilies-of-the valley. They are more appropriate, more in the rôle, more jeune fille.”

But Waldron, sure now at least of her, was going. Five minutes later, in a Fifth Avenue club, he was talking at the hall porter.

“Have the operator telephone at once to Florley’s for a box of lilies-of-the-valley. Where is Mr. Brevort?”

“Yes, sir. Mr. Brevort is in there, sir.”

Squarely in a chair, Brevort sat, as, at this hour, he always sat, looking out on the avenue. He was getting on, moreover; that chair perhaps had made him stout, though less so than a man who was then talking very vigorously to him about nothing whatever.

Waldron approached, joined them. Presently the other man, sufficiently unburdened, got up.

Waldron turned. “Nick, you were at the Amsterdams to-day.”

Brevort turned also. “What of it?”

“You are a friend of Grace, aren’t you?”

Brevort turned again. It was his answer. Always he had spread openly before her the mantle of his devotion. There had been a time when she might have been his. But the estate of his father had come to him blanketed in mortgages. Instead of being rich, he had found himself relatively poor. Of that he had said nothing. But talking was not his forte, loyalty was.

“Grace needs your help,” Waldron resumed.

“Then it’s hers,” he said simply. But now a servant approached and addressed Waldron.

“The flowers are at the door, sir.”

“Bring them here.”

Adjacently other members were seated. They were not the kind that listen, but they might overhear. After the flowers had been brought, Waldron lowered his voice. What he had to say, he said quickly.

When he finished, Brevort turned on him. “What a damned blackguard you are.”

Waldron smiled, waved it away, let it pass. “The point is, will you?”

Meditatively Brevort drummed with his fingers. “It is a large order,” he said at last.

Again he drummed. “But not a life sentence, eh?”

Sure of him then, Waldron laughed. “And not hard labor either. My dear Nick, a month, less perhaps. Six weeks, at most. By the way, have you one of your cards, with you?”

Brevort fumbled and produced one. It never occurred to him to ask for what it was to be used. It did not occur to Waldron to tell him.

Waldron opened the box, put the card in it, retied the ribbons, scrawled the name and address, rang for a servant and dispatched it.

Brevort stood up. “I must dress.”

Waldron also got up. “I too. You won’t have something first?”

Brevort, without replying, stalked on. Waldron followed, left him at the door, entered a taxi and in it sailed home.

Grace meanwhile, regally gowned, roped with pearls, sat alone in her room, maturing her plans. Two hours, that were two eternities, had passed since this thing had battened on her. She was bruised, wounded almost to the death, almost but not quite. She had a rôle to perform and perform it she meant to, without a word, a reproach, a single recrimination.

At dinner presently, afterward at the opera, she would appear as always she had appeared, the portrait on foot of a woman without a care. On the morrow Louie’s visit terminated, and she would see her off, smile at her, kiss her good-by. The day after she, too, would go, but to Newport, where she could claim residence and where, without uncivil proceedings, they set you free.

Then Chris must marry the girl. Beyond that she could not see.

On a table beside her a clock struck silverly. She looked at it. It was time to go down. Leisurely, with every evidence of at least outward calm, down she went, entered the drawing-room, approached the fire and absently before it held a hand.

But someone else was entering, she turned. Slim, but less naked than the night before, in virginal white, a spray of lilies at the girdle, demure but incandescent, Louie appeared, and Grace smiled at her

For a second, but for a second only, the smile nearly bowled the girl over. At once she was up and at it.

“Grace,” she murmured in that sol bémol of hers, “Whatever became of you this afternoon? I hurried back here, found Chris, and he was so delighted that he kissed me.”

At the barefacedness of it, Grace flushed.

“What are you talking about?”

“Why, I’m engaged. Didn’t you know? Didn’t Chris tell you?”

But now in the doorway a footman was mumbling, and Brevort marched in.

With the bubbling laugh of a young faun, Louie, who was nearest, gave him her hand. Before he could address her, before even he could address his hostess, Waldron, entering at his heels, touched him on the back.

“I say, Nick, I do congratulate you. When I heard it I gave Louie a jolly good hug. You don’t mind, do you?”

“Did she?” Brevort rather cavalierly inquired, for he was looking at Grace who was looking at him. And what a look! Could bewilderment, uncertainty, then relief, then joy, the abrupt conviction that jealousy had blinded her, that it had all been a nightmare in daylight; could you fancy these things simultaneously expressed in one look; that is what hers expressed.

In the sudden emotion, one hand went to her throat, her lip trembled but she smiled. The other hand she stretched to him.

At once, the wonder of it about her, she asked: “Is it true, Nick?”

At which Brevort, bending deeply over that hand that she might not see he lied, and lied for her, gritted his teeth as he answered:

“When have you known me false?”

Beyond, in silent announcement of dinner, the butler appeared.

“Then come,” she cried, “and we will drink your health.” Gayly she turned to Waldron. “Chris, you take Louie.” In speaking she shook her finger. “But mind! Don’t kiss her again. Once is enough.”

Louie bubbled afresh, and Waldron smiled at her. They knew then that they had not muffed it.

The Bomb

A servant, entering the library of a Fifth Avenue club, approached me and said: “Mr. Converse telephones he will be here to see you in five minutes. Yes, sir.”

“At this hour!” I exclaimed.

It was three by the clock. But Converse had specious habits. He seldom appeared in the club before midnight. Hence my surprise. Though I little suspected it, I was in for another—for another one yet. But to Converse, so far, at least, as I am concerned, anything and everything was permissible.

I had always known him. We were in the same form at St. Paul’s, in the same corps at Heidelberg. In addition, I discreetly admired his sister, who had long lived abroad, and who but recently had returned here. Moreover, he had of late rather stirred me with inflammatory accounts of Margaret Dayce, a Philadelphia beauty, whom he was trying to win, in the face, too, of another chap, a man named Bundy, who also was in the running.

Naturally, my money was on Converse. But what did he want now, I wondered.

I looked about. The servant had gone. Save for the caryatides of the bookshelves, I was alone, and I took up a paper, an item of which had already absorbed me.

The item concerned Raritan, another old schoolmate. Though I would hardly have known him then, had I met him in a pantry, I could see him, as I first did, a slim, handsome lad, leaning against a table in my room in the upper school at Concord, and talking very agreeably about the Sicilian poets.

That day, when he had gone, I had missed my watch. But as I might have missed it earlier, I had omitted to suspect him. Subsequently, from other rooms, other things evaporated. Finally Raritan left St. Paul’s. For that matter, we all did. One cannot be a schoolboy forever, and more’s the pity. But I continued to hear about Raritan. What I heard was not ingratiating. Now here he was again, accused of forgery, and reported to be in hiding.

“Forgery!” I mentally exclaimed, and marveled a bit that he and I, who had been educated together, should have such different views on the proper use of pen and ink.

These meditations were interrupted. Converse, looking extremely red, and equally fit, was talking rapidly at me.

“Bundy’s got Margaret—or will have, unless I stop them, and I want you to help me. They came on from Philadelphia to-day, and have already secured the license.”

I jumped up. “Then you are done for. How did you hear?”

“Her mother wired. Bundy simply worked on the poor child’s jealousy.”

“A fruitful soil, was it?”

“Well, she saw me kissing a woman, saw me embracing her, saw her throw herself in my arms.”

I patted a smile. “Rather barefaced and luxurious of you, don’t you think? But how did she come to behold this idyl?”

“In a moving picture.”

Incredulously I stared. “But—”

Converse cut me short. “You remember when I went to meet the Lusitania? There the picture people got me and Sarah, too.”

“Your sister!”

“Yes, my sister.”

“But then—”

“Yes, of course. When Margaret learns the truth it will be rather a bomb. But meanwhile—”

I picked up my hat. “Meanwhile it is all too bad to be false.”

“It is worse. Margaret has never seen my sister. Bundy has. Bundy knows Sarah—however slightly. But he knows her. In spite of which, yesterday he took Margaret to see this confounded picture. There and then she threw me over, and he got her to promise to marry him here to-day.”

“I don’t wish him many happy returns of it, then.”

Absently, Converse nodded. “It is human to lose in death those for whom we care. It is inhuman to lose them in life.” He paused, looked grimly down, and determinedly up. “I can’t lose her, I shan’t, I won’t!”

“Bravo!” I cried. “The moving picture shows, and, having shown, moves on. Let’s be going. By the way, where is she?”

“Headed, her mother said, either for the Waldorf or the St. Regis. They got here at two. It is three now. It will have taken them an hour to get the license. We may be in time.”

“We have got to be,” I answered. “This club is midway between the two hotels. I will go to the one, you go to the other.”

In speaking I put my hat on, and made with Converse for the stair. “I think I know Bundy,” I added. “He was at St. Paul’s, wasn’t he? Apropos! That was an engaging tale about Raritan. Have you seen him lately?”

For a moment, Converse, occupied with other things, did not answer. Presently and indifferently he nodded. “The last time I saw the brute was in a Fifth Avenue bus. He was completely bald and presumed to complain to me about it. I told him it was unimportant what he had on his head, the important thing was what he had in it.”

But now we had reached the street, where, for club purposes, motors stood. “Take a cab,” Converse resumed. “I will take one, too.” As he spoke, he motioned to a chauffeur.

I motioned to another, and called at him: “If they are not at the St. Regis, join me at the Waldorf.”

From the taxi which he was then entering he called back at me: “If they are at the Waldorf, explode the bomb.”

“The bomb?” I queried mentally, as the car started, but at once I got it, and I fell to thinking, and rather platitudinously I fear, of the dynamic qualities of truth. At the Waldorf, though, I found new reflections.

The lobby, saturated with tobacco and electricity, full of people, of hurrying servants, of tourists eying one another hostilely, or with indifference, resounded with the call of pages, the click of the typewriter, the hum of talk.

Through the vibrations of it all, I approached the desk. Approaching it, also, was a man, rather tall, with Piccadilly clothes, a Delmonico manner, and an air of intense satisfaction. Beside him was a girl in a frock that suggested fresh almonds. From her arm swung a bag of Peking yellow, on which battened an argent monster with eyes of jade. Topping all was a hat that might have cost a thousand dollars. Doubtless it had cost less. I lack the huckster’s eye. But not, I hope, the eye for beauty. The girl was extraordinarily fair. Her hair rippled with gold. Yet in her face, in which there was all of youth’s courageous innocence, there was also, it seemed to me, the look of one who has taken what children call a dare, and who now rather wished that she had not.

This impression, wholly momentary, the girl’s companion jostled. He was addressing the clerk:

“My name is Bundy. I wired from Philadelphia for a suite, and forgot to ask for a clergyman, also.”

The clerk turned, examined some memoranda, turned again: “The suite will be ready shortly, Mr. Bundy.”

“And the clergyman?”

The clerk shook his head. “We don’t supply them.” He hesitated, and resourcefully added: “The Reverend Doctor Manlius is here. He registered last night.” A manicured finger shot out. “There he is now.”

Hat in hand, head bent, eyes lowered, a clergyman was crossing the hall. His abundant dark hair, upturned, as if curled, at the edges, glistened a little, but his close-cut beard was dull, as was also his severe black coat.

At once Bundy accosted him. I could not hear what he said, but I could see the clergyman stop, raise his eyes, and look uncertainly at Bundy. Worship has many forms, the devout have many attitudes, but perhaps the greatest grace that religion confers is serenity. Momentarily, this gentleman appeared to lack it. But momentarily only. Immediately he straightened, stroked his rich hair, and murmured something.

Bundy turned to the beauty. “Margaret, this is Doctor Manlius. Doctor Manlius is unprepared. He has no service with him.”

“I have one,” the girl announced. That wonderful hat of hers inclined itself, and a gloved hand, entering the bowels of the silver dragon, produced a prayer book, bound in tortoise shell, clamped with gold. “I was reading it in the train,” she continued. “I also read the burial service.” She paused and oddly added: “I think I like it best.”

But Bundy was in great good humor. “Everything in proper time,” he cheerfully retorted.

Doctor Manlius coughed: “Ahem! Yes. Quite so.”

“Well, then,” Bundy spaciously resumed. “We might—”

The rest of it was lost. I was about to intervene. Already I had taken aim. “Miss Dayce,” I had it on the tip of my tongue to say, “Converse bids me tell you that the woman you saw in his arms is his sister.”

But the thing missed fire. A different explosion occurred. Before me, a page in blue and brass was bawling my name.

I stopped the boy, questioned, learned that I was wanted at the telephone, divined who was at the other end, and, a bit relieved—for, if I may boast, I am a poor hand at projectiles—entered a booth, where at once Converse was talking at me.

“They are not here,” he huskily began. “Are they at the Waldorf?”

“Yes,” I shouted back. “In the hall—with a clergyman in tow.”

“What!”

“Some reverend rounder that Bundy has picked up here.”

With an oath, Converse cleared his throat: “Detain them then. Introduce yourself to Margaret. Throw the bomb. Say I am coming.”

I started to reply, but the connection was cut, and I could fancy Converse hastening mightily.

Meanwhile, there was work to be done, and, as I reëntered the foyer, mentally I again took aim. Yet at once I realized that, however effective the high projectile would prove, it was for the moment useless.

The girl, the man, the cleric, all three had vanished, and I told myself that somewhere in the vast hotel they were then actively collaborating in that ceremony which is the oldest of human rites.

I rushed at the desk. “Mr. Bundy—from Philadelphia. Where is he? I must see him.”

The clerk looked me over. “I hardly think he is disengaged at present.” Cautiously and bleakly he smiled. “We have given him a sitting room while his suite is being prepared.”

Impatiently I gestured. “It is life and death. I must see the young lady who is with him, and at once.”

Again the clerk surveyed me. The cautious smile had gone. “Well, I’ll send your name up.”

I whipped out a card. “Say it’s vital. Say—”

But the clerk had turned. In a moment, my card in his hand, I saw him directing an operator. Then, leisurely, behind a partition he disappeared. When I next saw him he was at the other end of the desk, talking confidentially to a fat man. Several minutes had already intervened. Several others had previously elapsed. Since I had last seen the girl, fully ten minutes must have gone. The marriage service, I told myself, is brief—but lasting, and, in my brain, words kept running confusedly over themselves: “To have and to scold, to—”

“Not in, sir.”

It was the clerk addressing me.

“Not in?” I amazedly repeated.

“Well, they don’t answer.” bleak smiled reappeared. “I guess they’re busy. Front!”

The clerk turned again. So far as he was concerned I had ceased to exist.

In sheer impotence, I also turned. Before me was the palm room, widely hospitable, enterable through many doors, but, at this hour, which was too early for tea, and too late for luncheon, untenanted.

Gloomily, I was contemplating the empty chairs and unoccupied tables, when, suddenly, Converse appeared.

He flew at me. “Where is she?”

I motioned at the ceiling. “In the bonds of matrimony.”

He strangled an oath. “You didn’t tell her?”

“I couldn’t. While you were telephoning they gave me the slip. But I will tell you something. There is nothing better for the emotions than caviare and champagne. Let’s have some.”

“You are ridiculous with your caviare and your emotions,” Converse snapped.

Appreciatively I nodded. “Let me offer you, then, some wisdom for food, some song for wine. The lady has left you. Let her go. There is wisdom. Here, now, is the wine. ‘The grave of all things has its violet.’ Quaff it.”

I was but trying to calm the poor devil; trying, however stupidly, to get him to accept the inevitable. I might as well have attempted to supply him with conjectures on the orbits of skylarking comets. He ignored me utterly. With something almost terrieresque in his eagerness, he was pointing.

Beyond, through a lateral entrance of the palm room, that trio, at this moment, appeared.

“Now we are in for it!” I told myself, and, from the spectacle, turned to Converse again.

With a grimace, he turned to me. “Is that your clergyman?”

“Not mine at all,” I was about to tell him, but he was so obviously preparing for action that, instead, I put a hand on his arm. “Don’t,” I admonished. “The greatest revenge is the disdain of any.”

He shook me off. “You are ridiculous with your revenge.”

As he spoke, he started, I following, toward the palm room, where already the three were seated, and where now a Greek omnibus was supplying them with great glasses of ice water.

The girl’s back was toward us. She did not see our approach. The Greek did not care. But Bundy said something, the clergyman looked deeply into.= his glass, and that wonderful hat half turned. I had no time to notice more. We had reached the table. In the air now were the vibrations of hostilities begun.

Immediately Converse let go. “Margaret—”

Bundy rose at the charge. Instantly, insolently, and invincibly, he fired. “I will thank you to address my wife as Mrs. Bundy.”

With that he had thought, perhaps, to bowl the foe over. Converse omitted to so much as blink. He was looking at the bride, who was looking at him. And what a look! Could eyes assassinate, hers would have killed. In their blight it occurred to me that for her to hate him to the death, she must also love him to distraction. But there was no love on exhibition then. Before her still was the affront of the moving picture.

That picture, with one lunge, Converse demolished. “Margaret, the woman you saw with me was my sister.” Another crash followed. “What’s more, Bundy knew it.”

“I!” Bundy cried. “I—” The explosion had staggered him. His protest rang false. But the field was his. The girl was his wife. He fired again: “Sister or no sister—”

If any one heard, no one heeded. Manlius stood up. The bride, too, was rising. She was looking from Converse to Bundy, from Bundy to Converse.

Converse helped her: “You can’t doubt me, but if you do, look at him.”

She was looking. She looked as if looking on some dreadful dream. But she looked, too, as if she saw Bundy for the first time.

“I appear to have been tricked.”

It was she who spoke. It was Manlius who answered: “Ahem! I think—really, I must be going.”

But now Bundy had got back at it. “Sister or no sister,” he was shouting, “you are married to me.”

Yes, but there are marriages that can be annulled, I told myself, and was about to say as much to Converse, but Bundy had turned to him:

“As for you—”

“Don’t run into excesses,” Converse threw at him. “Nor you, either,” he threw at Manlius. As he spoke, he looked the clergyman up and down. “The last time I saw you, sir, was in a Fifth Avenue bus. You were then quite bald.”

“Really,” Manlius expostulated, edging, as he spoke, away. “Really—”

Converse caught at him. “Now just tell this lady that she is not married.”

“What infernal nonsense is this?” Bundy noisily protested.

But Converse, who, with one hand, was holding the cleric, with the other abruptly tore from him an opulent wig, a false if pointed beard; and there, even in the prelate’s garb, even to me, perhaps, too, to Bundy, my old schoolmate. Raritan, who had talked so agreeably of the Sicilian poets, and whom the police were seeking, stood revealed. I nodded at him, but he failed to notice.

“Converse,” he was pleading, readjusting the while his disguise as best he could. “Converse, let me go.”

Converse nodded. “Then tell this lady you are not a clergyman.”

I turned to the girl. The Greek, open-mouthed, was staring. Bundy, his lips twisted with amazement and rage, was staring also. Suddenly, with an intake of the breath, he gulped and looked shiftily at Miss Dayce, who, limply, had sunk into a chair.

The fire had been a bit hot for her. Not one bomb only, but two, had exploded. There were ruins all about. In them an illusion had fainted, and jealousy lay dead. There were ruins all about, but in them there was light.

“Tell her—” Converse was saying.

She half raised a hand. Her eyes had filled. Her lip quivered. “No. I can see. Let him go. And, perhaps, you will ask him to take—to take—him with him.”

Her voice had broken, but it was bravely said, and, in the saying of it, she had drawn from a finger a ring which, her head averted, she extended behind her to where Bundy stood.

Bundy looked at her, at it. The ring fell, with a tinkle, on the floor. For a second his eyes followed it. But the tinkle must have sounded to him his finish. At once, with an uplift of the chin, he squared his shoulders, glanced at us, put his hat on, turned on his heel. But it was still all a bit too much. Margaret bowed her head. A sob shook her.

Converse busied himself immediately. Caressingly his arm went about her. “There! There!” he said, much as though she were a baby. “We will have some of that caviare and champagne that I have been hearing about, and then we’ll get a license of our own.

“Here,” he interrupted himself to inquire. “Where’s the waiter?” As he spoke, he turned to me. “Don’t stand dawdling there. You make me nervous. Sit down; give us a toast.”

“Gladly,” I answered. “What shall it be?”

Converse laughed. “Why,” he exclaimed, indicating the door through which his routed rival had gone. “What could it be except—Sic transit gloria Bundy!”

The Dear Departed

I

One by one the guests had gone, and with Trella now there was but a poet who had elevated rhyme to the dignity of a sport. His name was Villiers. In addition to rhyme and other gymnastics less violent, he cultivated paradox. At the moment, he was twisting his painted fingers, fumbling his hostess with his yellow eyes. Then, pontifically, he addressed her:

“There is but one enduring delight—certainty in love. Certainty that it exists, certainty that it is returned, certainty that it will never diminish.”

Trella looked at him so fixedly that he tacked.

“The idea suggests itself,” he hastened to add, “in connection with the Infanta of whom we were talking at dinner. Nobody seems to recognize that the one to blame for her conduct is her father. Don Carlos is a most ordinary person. He goes about talking, ‘God and my country,’ by day, wrecking households at night, as ignorant of Molière as my masseur. Evil exists only in the noise that it makes.

“ ‘Le scandale du monde est ce qui fait l’offense
Et ce n’est pas pécher que pécher en silence.”

“Have you been hearing things about me?” Trella interrupted.

Villiers promptly assumed the appearance of an idiot.

“Do you believe them?” she asked.

He waved his painted fingers. “Dear me!” he exclaimed. “I have heard so many lies concerning myself that how can you expect me to believe the stories I hear of others? No,” he continued, remotely, “had Don Carlos only known enough to cram Tartuffe down the girl’s throat she might not have carried on as she has. And then, again, she might have. Bad taste is in the Bourbon blood. The Princess Isabelle let herself down thirty feet out of a window, and ran off with a Polish mucker. They were caught and married by main strength.”

Trella patted a yawn.

“Tell me of yourself,” he agilely added. “What have you been doing? Or, rather, what have you not been doing? Do you know, I should love so to put my ideas of you in a poem. For private circulation, of course. It would have to be, wouldn’t it, unless it appeared in Latin?”

But, as for all reply she smiled indifferently; the poet stood up, and, balancing himself on his heels, smiled, too.

“ ‘Our Lady of the Immaculate Conversation,’ would, I think, be a very good title for that poem. Bonsoir, belle dame.”

Raising her wrist, he brushed it with his lips. In a moment he had gone.

As he passed from the room a servant entered. On a little tray he had a telegram which he brought her. Dated London and addressed to the Countess of Cloden, Avenue Marceau, Paris, it contained these words: “Will be with you to-night.”

With a gesture, she dismissed the man, and, leaning on a mantel, stared in a mirror, stared through it into the past, stared beyond it into the future, and then at herself, at her royal beauty, at the sunburst of flesh which she was.

In all our great Northwest, her grandfather, Commodore Verelst, had been accounted the richest and hardest of men. As a lad he tracked muskrats in the Michigan marshes. As a man, he constructed and commanded a fleet of lake steamers. As a corpse, he left millions. He had one son, who took them all, took them away to New York, and married. The result of the union was Trella. The original Verelst was a German, his wife was French. There was the gold of the Rhine in the glisten of Trella’s hair. In the faint umber of her skin, in the mobility and droop of her lips there was France. When Teuton and Latin combine there can be some very fetching results. Witness the Venetian. But when to these elements is added the magic of Manhattan the result not merely fetches, it astounds. Trella developed into an astounding young person.

As a girl, she reminded you of what the Argive Helen may have been in her teens. Her mouth seemed to promise more than any mortal mouth could give. Her voice was so insinuating that it conveyed the sensation of a kiss. She had glances as she had intonations, which dispensed a charm quite incandescent. Her eyes were particularly enthralling. They were large and blue, blue as the sea and bluer. Generally, she was prudent enough to keep them half closed. When she opened them they revealed a number of things—curiosity, restlessness and that je-m’en-ficheisme which is mistaken for frankness. When she chose, she could flood them with languors. She just lacked being tall.

In the process of the production and development of these witcheries her father concluded to leave for another world. After a proper period of regret, his widow left for another world, also. But it was Europe she selected. Though a New Yorker by birth, and inordinately rich, she had never succeeded in forcing certain portals. Such things annoy a woman. Hence the migration.

The migration effected, Mrs. Verelst discovered that to be decently lodged, two domiciles are obligatory. Mrs. Verelst took three. One in Paris, one on the Riviera, and one in Normandy. To these she added a fourth. The last was a cemetery. Her residence in that resort was not, however, immediate. She waited for certain things, primarily until her daughter was married.

It was on the Riviera that the preliminaries to this event occurred. Entrance to the penal colony, which is called Society there, is a matter of entire ease. Mrs. Verelst knocked and it was opened. There was a sesame in her dollars. There was another in Trella’s looks.

The particular section of the Riviera which she had selected is, geologically speaking, a Mediterranean cliff; descriptively, it is a sublimate of Paris in a tropic frame; pictorially, it is a fairyland in duodecimo; socially, it is striated with all the variegated hues of beautiful cosmopolitanism, and, familiarly, it is Monte Carlo. You may meet there kings, outlaws, demi-reps, professional beauties, cheap trippers, and Spanish grandees.

In the air is a smell of vitriol and violets, of vice, patented, prodigal, and perfumed. There is not an old-fashioned virtue in the place. There are tears, though, rivers of them, heightened by the click of the ball on the roulette table, the call of the dealers at trente-et-quarante, the music and monotony of Rien ne va plus. People go mad there. Others kill themselves. Some fall in love. Among the latter was Trella.

This extraordinary event occurred in a commonplace manner. At a rout given by the morganatic widow of an emperor the girl and her mother were present. During a pause in a dance, in a crash and subsidence of the orchestra, an Englishman caused himself to be presented. Before speech was possible there arose from beyond the voice of the world’s best tenor. It was an aria from the “Somnambula” that he was singing, the “Perche non posso odiarte,” which, for sheer beauty, is perhaps the most entrancing in all of Italy’s enchanting repertory.

The melting measures proceeded. The Englishman looked at the American girl and she at him. As they looked, the madness of the music seemed at first but the accompaniment of their thoughts, and then at once to transmit those thoughts from one to the other. Involuntarily, he moistened his lips. Into the perfection of the girl’s features a flush had come. To use a localism of the land, c’était le coup de foudre.

Trella let her long lashes fall. It was as though she had dropped a curtain. The man turned to her mother. That lady was whispering something. Yet what, he neither knew nor cared. The measures had swooned. The hush was broken by a ripple of applause.

“It is very warm,” Mrs. Verelst announced.

Before any one could engage with her in meteorological observations, the tenor, by way of encore, was distributing the enchantment of his notes anew.

Back of Trella a balconied window opened on the April night. Already she had investigated its possibilities, and raising those lashes again, she led the Englishman to the stars without. The aria followed them. He never forgot that song. Nor, perhaps, did she.

II

Life is packed with pleasures. One of the most delightful is to awake with the consciousness of being in love. On the morning succeeding the rout Shane Wyvill awoke to just that delight. He was turbulently intoxicated by a girl whom he had never seen before, and whose name he did not know.

But the morning was a replica of others. Moreover, it was a family trait to wake up with that sensation. So far back as the family went, and it went as far back as any of the other families which Mr. Burke has so diligently catalogued, the Shane Wyvills—the Shame Wyvills as custom had corrupted the name—had, in love, been freebooters. Titularly lords of Cloden, typically they were a bad lot.

The last earl, after filling the Continent with the uproar of his debauches, gave up the ghost with a shriek. What visions he beheld he lacked the time to relate. It may be assumed that they were not very cheerful. The youth of the existing incumbent had been what the French call stormy. After the storm, the calm. The past twenty years he had passed at Shane Towers, contemplating the landscape. That landscape had been so successfully postobited that it produced less than would suffice for a sweep.

The wants of the earl were many. But they were entirely spiritual. Pending their attainment he sat in a dressing-gown at peace with all the world, including his nephew, Shane Wyvill, who was incidentally his heir.

In the latter’s father, hereditary characteristics had been so in abeyance that he had been regarded as a nonentity. He had married one of the Villiers girls, and done nothing worse than lose a portion of her portion in the City. Then he had died, she, also, leaving this heir and what was left of her property. The amount was just enough to enable him to get along on.

Apart, then, from the advantage of being in line for an empty earldom and the further advantage of good teeth and good looks, Shane Wyvill had, from the point of view of the world at large, nothing whatever to boast of.

Even otherwise, he was not of a boastful nature. By way of compensation he enjoyed the formidable repute of being the best-dressed man in London. But the repute was unrighteous. He was too sensible to do more than put himself in the hands of the right people and then forget all about them—except their bills, which he paid, as he paid all such things, on presentation. It will be seen, therefore, that if not boastful, at any rate, he was proud. No one is perfect.

But the imperfections of Wyvill will be the better understood through a showing that this mid-April morning, on which he awoke with the consciousness of being in love, was but a return of sundry others. Fed, as every decently educated lad in England is, on the psalms of Aristophanes, he had also taken a course in Theocritus. In the green pastures of a long vacation he encountered a maiden whose studies had been less elaborate. Their defects he undertook to remedy. One noon he read to her an episode from an eclogue. At its close their eyes met. To quote Dante, they read no more that day. Subsequently, he encountered her, not in green pastures, but in Piccadilly, and at an hour nearer midnight than noon. In the interval she had convoluted into a chorus girl. Her salary was precisely twenty-five shillings a week. At no properly conducted London theatre is it permissible for a lady whose salary does not exceed thirty shillings to drive to the stage door in her brougham. The rule may seem arbitrary, but there it is, and in this case there it was. The young person who perhaps had grown luxurious, regarded it not merely as arbitrary, but awkward. For the sake of old times, Wyvill got her higher pay. Then for the sake of old times, also, she blackmailed him pretty nearly out of his boots. Such was his initiation into the charms of love and Leicester Square.

In politer spheres he presently discovered consolations. These consolations lasted until the lady’s husband began uncivil proceedings, from the result of which Wyvill was saved by a succession of events which converted him to a belief in miracles. The lady explained everything so satisfactorily to her husband that the proceedings were withdrawn, whereupon she eloped with another and a richer man. Such was his initiation into the horrors of matrimony and Mayfair.

It is said of those who beheld the mysteries at Eleusis that thereafter they ceased to smile. Wyvill’s experiences were quite as chastening. The pleasure in things that had pleased him waned. He tried hunting, and gave it up. It cost too much. He went forth to shoot in Canada, and returned disillusioned. Yet, in default of wealth, one must have a raison d’être. It was in the search for that raison that he encountered Trella. Her effect on him was instantaneous. Before he slept he was conscious of a new conception of beauty. When he awoke it was to the consciousness of a new conception of life. From the conjunction of these conceptions there mounted like a flame the delight of a dream of possessing the girl.

In fairyland you have but to ask and it is given. Since Perrault lived and labored, Monte Carlo is the nearest approach to that country. In its sorceries are solvents so surprising that you may land there a pauper and leave a plutocrat. You may also reverse the order of things. Where the enchanted rose is, there, too, is the disenchanting thorn.

But on the slopes which a syndicate in collaboration with nature has strewn with diaphanous days and electric lights, such thorns as grew Wyvill passed unheeding, and, in passing, promenaded straight into the domain of a beauty who, however, was not sleeping, but thoroughly wide-awake.

On the way, Wyvill gathered certain facts, which were so many flowers; the domain’s precise position, for instance, its name and the kilometers it took to get there. For even in fairyland, and perhaps particularly in fairyland, there are always mileposts in high hats and others in low neck to provide you with just such information.

In serving Prince Charming they also served the Wide-Awake Beauty. As a consequence, when, in due course, the two met again, had they been first cousins they could not have known more of each other. To Prince Charming the Wide-Awake Beauty was an American heiress, and to the Wide-Awake Beauty Prince Charming was heir to an earldom. What could be more succinct, what more satisfactory? Especially when it is remembered that it had required but one meeting, complicated by nothing more quotable than the melting measures of an aria, for the parties concerned to experience the coup de foudre.

To Trella the coup had all the charm of entire novelty. In New York she had flirted right and left. She liked men, liked admiration and a bold glance, and a squeeze of the hand she was none too shy to return. Apart from a liking for such things, they left her unaffected. After the boldest glance and the tightest squeeze her pulse registered normal. That, however, was less to her credit than to the discredit of the glancers and squeezers. Their seductions were limited to gymnastics.

In Paris and on the Riviera the liking for men continued, but men were scarce. One look at Wyvill had told her that he was of a different breed. Never before had she met any one with less manner and more ease. Never before had she beheld a human being so perfectly sent out. Never before had a presence impressed her so suddenly and so absolutely. For the first time, her pulse ceased to be normal. For the first time she saw a man, and in that man she saw, also, and for the first time, too—or thought she did—her master. At sight of him she flushed. Why, she did not know. But it seemed to her all very new and inexpressibly delightful.

In spite of which, or, perhaps, precisely on that account, when on the Casino’s esplanade, chance brought these two people face to face again, only an exchange of platitudes resulted. Yet, in circumstances not similar, perhaps, but cognate, people do not say what they think. As a rule, they do not think at all. They occupy themselves as best they may in sparring for wind. Such sparring as then occurred was rendered more vigorous than otherwise it might have been by the presence of the girl’s mother, who stuck to her, not with any un-American view to the observance of the proprieties, but simply because she had come out with her, and objected to being stranded.

The next day matters were more propitious. Wyvill dined with the Verelsts at their villa, took them afterward to the gambling rooms, and accompanied them home again, where he required no urging whatever to remain for a brandy and soda; no urging, either, to dispense with platitudes. After the good old American fashion, Mrs. Verelst made herself scarce, and the two were free to gaze at the Mediterranean moon and then at the avowals of each other’s eyes.

As weeds of the sea loosened by one current, stayed by another, mount slowly yet surely before achieving their gradual yet certain ascent, so did these avowals, arrested now by query, again by an objection, rise from the depths of their being and mount to their lips.

From avowals to action no appreciable time is required. In a moment they were in each other’s arms; in a week they were engaged; in a month they were married. In fairyland lovers don’t dilly-dally.

It was not, though, of course, at Monte Carlo that the marriage took place. Against its taking place at all Mrs. Verelst protested vehemently. She had an ardent desire to be the mother of a duchess, and the Duca di Cherella, a young Neapolitan, whom Trella treated as part of the landscape, had, in that desire, collaborated as ardently as she. Failing him, there were others. Besides, Mrs. Verelst, who, as the phrase is, had her police, knew that Wyvill’s uncle was capable of living forever. In accordance with a good old American custom, she wanted her money’s worth, and a title in futuro did not in the least satisfy her ideas of What’s What. As a consequence, she protested vehemently. She might just as well have held her tongue. Trella paid not the slightest attention to her. Seeing which, after another American fashion, Mrs. Verelst gave in. The marriage took place in Paris, and after the ceremony, through the scented streets, the bride and groom who had met in fairyland set out for paradise.

III

Love is a fever. Marriage is a febrifuge. That is the rule. This marriage was not an exception. Only its antipyretic effects were not immediately observable. At stations along the route the fever lifted them to chimerical altitudes, sank them to spaceless depths, lowered them deeper, lifted them vertiginously, caught and carried them beyond the earth, beyond the horizons of the known, beyond the confines of the real, disclosing through vistas undivined, those mysterious affinities that similarize the flesh and spirit. In fresh ascensions, the fair, illusory promises of love and life were uttered by them both. In new descents the vain, yet lovely vows, Forever, Never, were interchanged again. And so it went.

The duo is very archaic, but to them it seemed highly original, essentially unique, entirely their own composition. It seemed too capable of infinite variations. Through its interludes the memory of a murmur of other songs once filtered in on Wyvill, and jarred him as an oath will jar. Trella’s memories were less resonant. They were pages that girlhood had left quite blank, and at which along the route now and then she stopped and mused. With the refrain of that duo shaking constant stars in her ears it seemed inconceivable to her that such blankness there could be. Whereupon, after considering the past, she contemplated the future. The perspectives looked very spacious.

Meanwhile, impeded by nothing more than a maid and a valet, and delayed solely by a courier and a cargo of boxes, they journeyed circuitously from the scented Bois to the pink and crocus of Seville, and on through the ghosts and treasuries of Spain to its summer court at San Sebastian.

During the journey wherever Trella had shown herself admiration had been ambient. She had trailed it as a torch trails smoke. To that she had been always more or less accustomed. But in Seville, after the good old Andalusian custom, it was manifested vociferously, in open compliments of her mother’s handiwork, in shouts of Olle tu madre—hurrahs for that absent lady, which infuriated Wyvill, but which, through their fascinating indirection, delighted Trella, as, indeed, every novelty did.

In Castile, the admiration, while quite as fervent, became less noisy, and at San Sebastian so sedate that it would have been colorless had not chance—a function at the palace aiding—embodied it in the Duke of Thule.

The duke, who had an amiable, aimless way, made up in guile what he lacked in sense. Seen across the room, you would have taken him for Teuton; close to, for a fool. Trella saw but the royal. Barring the Regent to whom she had just been presented, she had never met one before. The encounter seemed to her uplifting. It heightened her in her own esteem.

It was at that juncture that she contemplated the future. The more she considered it the more spacious it grew. Then presently, little by little, one after another the delayed effects of the febrifuge appeared. The duo rang less starlike in her ears. The heights began to assume the aspect of the déjà vu, the ascensions to horizons beyond the known acquired the proportions of undertakings, and the affinities, similarizing sufficiently, had nothing more to say.

Everything being possible, it may be that, in the course of time, Wyvill also would have experienced the premonitory effects of the antipyretic, but Trella’s symptoms, at first unnoticed, then misinterpreted, subsequently evident, yet wholly enigmatic, left him perplexed.

Where is the Vandal that invented marriage? Wyvill put to himself some such question, but long after, when San Sebastian was but a halt in the trip and they were back in Paris again.

This occurred in the autumn. At that time, pending the termination of touches on a house which the girl’s mother had bought, Wyvill and Trella were lodged at the Bristol. There, one noon, the duke breakfasted with them. Afterward, Wyvill, with the purchase of some horses in view, joined their owner, the Vicomte de Chose, at a neighboring club, and, by virtue of a previous arrangement, drove with him, at three o’clock, to Saint Cloud, where the horses were stabled. On the way, Trella, looking nice enough to eat, whirled by in a brougham. Wyvill turned and kissed his hand to her. But the salute was unnoticed. She had not seen him, and continuing his way, he reached the stables, saw the horses, put them through their paces, and returned to the Bristol just in time to dress for dinner.

“What did you do this afternoon?” he asked, when the soup had gone. Without waiting for an answer, he told her about the horses. “Ce sont des alezans superbes,” he added—a phrase which he had caught from de Chose.

Trella did not know what alezans were. He explained. Then again he asked what she had done, but indifferently, as a husband may, not out of curiosity, but for the sake of talk.

“Nothing,” she answered. “After you went out my mother came and stayed here with me until nearly 5. Then I took a turn with her in the Bois.”

“Five is rather late nowadays for the Bois, is it not?” he asked, with the same air of indifference.

“The air does me good,” Trella replied, and let the subject drop.

Wyvill stared at her. Her hair made a garland of gold. Her eyes were sultry, her lips were scarlet. About her throat was a diamond collar. Her bodice was sewn with pearls. Between the diamonds and the pearls there glowed the silk of her skin. Never had she looked more beautiful. In the poise of her head, in her appearance and costume, she exhaled a charm almost intolerably aphrodisiac. She seemed created for love, for life at its fullest, and, as it now occurred to Wyvill, for lies.

The dinner proceeded. A maître d’hôtel after presenting a dish for inspection, superintended the serving of it by his underlings. Covers succeeded each other. Of what they consisted Wyvill did not notice. It had been arranged that he and Trella were to go that night to a première and afterward to the Embassy. This arrangement a remark of hers recalled.

Through the flowers and lights on the table he stared over at her again. When a man loves a woman, it is not an excess of ambition on his part to wish to trust her also. And suddenly a solution visited Wyvill. Might she not have accounted for her afternoon as she had, solely to save him and herself the boredom of the narration of some tiresome occurrence?

The solution was so stupid that it soothed. But even in the process of welcoming it there were incidents unconsciously recalled which trooped out and interfered. There was, for instance, a secretiveness which she had recently displayed in regard to such letters as were brought her. Recently, too, it had been obvious to him that she had preoccupations which she did not wish to disclose, thoughts to which he was a stranger. Moreover, there was that change in her, one that had filtered through such subtle gradations that only latterly the portent had perplexed.

Those who have suffered from jealousy know that it is physical, they know that it can no more be argued away than can any other distemper, and they know, too, to their own cost, perhaps, that its most torturesome form comes of thoughts that are hidden, and emotions they may not share.

To Wyvill the lie returned, but unvarnished now, and with it that determination to know which, in certain crises, is as imperious as famine. But of the inward tumult he gave no sign.

“What did your mother say?” he asked, leisurely.

By way of reply, Trella contented herself with shrugging her bare white shoulders.

“And you were here with her until nearly five?”

Trella nodded.

“Why not tell me the truth?”

At this she started. If he had struck her she could not have flushed more highly. But Wyvill omitted to pursue the advantage. At the sight of her confusion there came to him a sense not of anger, but of sorrow for himself and her.

The maître d’hôtel and his underlings had gone. Wyvill got from his chair and moved it nearer to her own.

“Distrust and affection don’t hit it off very well together, Trella. If you thought that I was deceiving you, you would think, too, that I was ceasing to care. It may be that you are ceasing to care for me. In that case, how shall I blame you? We cannot command affection. It commands us. Then, too, the quantity of it being limited, some day or other it must give out. When it does, love ends. No effort can prevent it. You have loved me now for a long time—almost six months. Unfortunately for us both, this is not a love affair, it is a marriage.”

He hesitated, hoping for an interruption, for some explanation or protest, but as she sat, tantalizingly beautiful and irritatingly dumb, he bent forward and, probing her with his eyes, very deliberately he asked:

“Where were you this afternoon?”

“I have told you.”

“No, forgive me, you are mistaken, you have not. You told me you were here until five. At three you passed me in the Rue Royale. Where were you going?”

Trella stood up, and with a little princess air which she could assume very well when she chose, she looked him in the face.

“You appear to be cross-questioning me.”

“Ah!” said Wyvill, rising, too. “Very good. I shall not presume to do so again. But I will presume to call your attention to the fact that you have lied to me. You have lied stupidly, wantonly. Whether the lie was meant to cover something equally stupid and wanton, I do not know. I do, though, know that while a wanton act may be shameful yet human, a wanton lie is shameless and vile.

“What is it, Harris?” he interrupted himself to ask. “No one rang.”

“No, sir, thank you, sir,” his valet, who had entered, answered, producing a dispatch which he had brought. “The carriage is at the door, sir.”

Wyvill opened the message. “Then you may dismiss it,” he ordered.

He turned to Trella. “You cannot go out, with my permission at least. My uncle is dead. I leave for London to-night.”

IV

Wyvill left Paris in a fury, determined to discover what Trella was up to if he had to employ a detective to do it. In the Channel the fury evaporated. When he reached Shane Towers he was glad he had probed no deeper. When the funeral was over he was glad that he had not questioned more.

As to that he was right. To expect some women to tell the truth is as naïf as to expect them to go about naked. They simply can’t. Then, too, there are mysteries concerning them which we may determine to solve, but which if time but intervene we prefer to ignore. Wyvill’s attitude was, therefore, perfectly natural. But in upbraiding the lady he had been absurd. There are complaints that are compliments, and reproaches which are testimonies of love.

Some inkling of this Trella probably intercepted. In any event, he was presently urged to return. But to return to what? He was still passionately in love with the girl who but a few months before had become his wife; the beauty and the charm of her were as dear to him as ever, dearer, even, by comparison; for in her place there seemed to have come a woman whom he had never known, and who, though her counterpart in charm, was otherwise a counterfeit.

Presently another letter came. He was urged again to return. But to whom? To Trella? Yes, and at once. The trains and the boats were not built that could take him to her fast enough. But with that stranger who had come in her place he had no concern whatever.

Then more letters came. Some were from his wife, offering to join him, and some were from Mrs. Verelst, whom Trella’s prompt elevation to the rank and attributes of peeress had entirely appeased.

It was then winter. But the winter passed and the spring came before he himself felt appeased. The appeasing was due to a note from the lady, in which she expressed a wish to explain.

As he read the note he could not but recall other explanations of which he had been cognizant. Yet, then, also, he could not but let them go. Time is a strange emollient. In its mysterious potency it softens without our knowledge. We are unaware that it has been acting on us, and suddenly a whisper, a breeze that passes, shows that it has done its work.

That night Trella received the telegram which was brought to her as Villiers was leaving her house.

Meanwhile she had found herself entertaining and being entertained by all that is best and worst in that curious cosmopolis which is called Tout-Paris. Yet there, even the worst have fits of propriety. Society abroad is very much the same as at home. It is not censorious. Provided a woman lives, outwardly, at least, on good terms with her husband; provided, as Villiers had noted, that there is an avoidance of open scandal, a lady is free to be as unladylike as she likes. With the men, at all times everything goes. Yet, now and then they do object to certain associations for their wives.

Of Lady Cloden stories began to be told. To begin with, she was not living with her husband, and it was rumored that, for reasons, which, however interesting, would not look well in print, he did not propose to live with her again. Such things dishearten. Moreover, it is not pleasant for a woman of position to see that position fade. Men acquire with her an easy form of address. They bow to her sometimes when they should not, and again omit to when they should. Matters had by no means come to that pass yet with Trella, but unless a halt were called social dégringolage was on the way.

And now on this particular night, as she stared in the mirror, at the sunburst of beauty which she was, it was of these things that she thought.

A step aroused her. She turned, glanced at the great, bare, brilliant room, then at the telegram which had been brought. Some one was approaching. She turned again. At the door her husband stood. With a little bleat which, if not of joy, was a very good imitation of it, she moved to meet and greet him, and at once, before he could speak, with a volubility to which she had not accustomed him, she acknowledged that she had been at fault, begging his forgiveness, relating things which he had never known, that she had a brother, that the latter had disgraced himself, that he had got into fresh difficulties, that that last afternoon at the Bristol she had gone to aid him, and that if she had hid the truth, it was out of delicacy, and the Lord knows what else, besides.

She paused, for lack of breath, perhaps. At the moment, from the avenue without, through the open window, came pouring the madness of a song of love. Wyvill had heard it somewhere, sometime, a long while ago, yet where or when he could not recall. Then suddenly he was back again in fairyland. The air was scented with flowers, he was speaking to some one, there was an aria that seemed to help his speech, that seemed to multiply the music of the replies. It was from the “Somnambula,” of course. He remembered now. Perhaps so, too, did she.

Pretty as a peach, and just as witty, savorous as a pineapple and with quite as much heart, commonplace in everything except in beauty, that aria in filtering through her pulp, must have stirred a memory, encountered a fiber, awakened an echo, for to her face she raised a hand and from her eyes there fell a tear.

Wyvill saw that tear. At once his arms were about her, his lips on hers. It seemed to him that they had parted only to reunite, that the past was a nightmare, that she loved him, that he loved her, better, even, than on the route to Paradise.

V

There are lakes which a breeze from the valley disturbs, but which the high winds from the summits leave unruffled. Then, for no appreciable reason, they reverse the order of things. There are natures that resemble those lakes. You never know where you are with them.

In attempting to display the cumulative incidents of this drama, no better analogy occurs by which to explain the opposite effects that circumstances, relatively identical, produced on Wyvill.

They were then at Deauville. Meanwhile, the stranger had gone, and with her every doubt of Trella. She was charmful, the more so, perhaps, because she had had what is called an experience with her husband, and it is said that experience teaches. Mrs. Verelst, who had had something in the nature of an experience also, tried to profit by it in offering to restore Shane Towers, and to maintain the place in proper fashion. At this Wyvill protested. It was, he declared, the gloomiest keep in England. Mrs. Verelst paid no attention to his nonsense. Trella, either. Paris had palled on her. For reasons of her own she was glad to evolve from it into what her mother termed her rightful sphere. All this was pleasant to Wyvill. The present was pleasant, also, and the future looked, as the future always does look, even pleasanter. And so the days fell by until, the Grand Prix over, they went down to Deauville.

There Mrs. Verelst contented herself with a suite in a hotel. But for Wyvill and Trella there was a house. This house, known, locally, because of its arrangements, as the Villa Portugaise, squats sumptuously before the sea. It is of two stories. The bedrooms are on the ground floor, the dining and reception-rooms adjoining. Between the two principal suites is a wide hall. One of these suites Trella selected for herself. Wyvill took the other. Both are splendid, and the villa itself is a gem.

It was early in July when they reached there. At that period Deauville is usually delightful. But in August it becomes infernal. The season is then at its height, and to its confluence surges a mob of viveurs and rastas.

Among others who appeared there that year was the Duke of Thule. Yet, owing to an attack of Anglophobia with which France is periodically afflicted, he came incog., as a private gentleman, merely. For the purposes of his sojourn he also had a villa. About it night and day men in plain clothes strolled unobtrusively. So are the mighty guarded.

The royal villa was next to the Villa Portugaise, and there, occasionally, as a friend and neighbor may, the duke dropped in, sometimes in beautiful flannels for a game of tennis, sometimes alarmingly begoggled for a flight in an auto, but always amiable and aimless.

And so the days fell by, punctuated by the diversions of Deauville—dips, drives, dinners, dances, polo matches, hurdle races and baccarat, but particularly by that general deviltry which, in an atmosphere dripping with ammonia and desire, scented with caprices and seaweed, those consorts of Society, wealth and idleness, inevitably produce.

Through the diversions and the deviltry of them the confidences apprehensible were truffled with a sans gêne quite idyllic. In the flow of these confidences there was, apparently, not an honest woman in the place. Everything being possible, such may have been the case.

One night the possibility occurred to Wyvill. That afternoon the Prix de Deauville had been run. He and Trella had been driven to the course by the duke. At the track he left them for a look in the paddock. On the way back his progress was momentarily impeded. Before him were two men. In a brief halt which a congestion of the crowd occasioned he garnered a snatch of their talk.

“C’est sa maîtresse,” one was saying.

“Ah! ah! Et le mari?”

“Il faut croire qu’il trouve ça charmant.”

But the congestion had diffused, Wyvill passed on, mounted to the tribune, where, looking down, he saw two men looking up. They were raising their hats. Their names he might have remembered, but he had forgotten their faces. He raised his own hat. The duke raised his. There was a clamor, a scurry, a clearing of the track, a careering of thoroughbreds, a riot of color, a shout, the horses were off, the Prix was being run, and the incident forgot.

Truth is an objective phenomenon. It acts in us and on us like a chemical precipitate. You may have given it no thought, and there it is revealed. That night, apropos to nothing, the incident returned to Wyvill. With it, from the depths of his being, there issued an obsession vague and obscure, something opaque and formless, but which, little by little, took shape and changed from an impossibility into a monstrous fact. Wyvill disowned it, disavowed it, would have none of it. But there it was. Presently the disavowals ceased. In certain conditions we get used to monsters. The soul makes itself at home with what it must.

Wyvill was seated in the library. An hour previous Trella, pretexting some one or other of those many malaises which women always have within beck and call, had disappeared for the night. Latterly these malaises and their coincidental disappearances had been frequent, and in considering them the dialogue overheard at the track returned, but freighted now with significance. The soul may accustom itself to what it must, but it will struggle first. We believe less what we should than what we wish.

For relief from the obsession Wyvill got up. He would have gone to Trella. But, presumably, she was asleep. In any event, he divined that her door was locked, and he knew that if she answered his knock at all, it would be but to reproach him with having disturbed her. Even otherwise, what could he say? He had suspected her before, and she had been good enough to overlook that suspicion. She had done more, she had produced a brother. There was nothing to prevent her now from producing a sister. With a lady so resourceful conversation was futile.

Wyvill looked at his watch. It was after two, much later than he had thought. Trella must have been asleep for hours. But the obsession had left him restless as a panther. Through the open window he stepped out to the lawn.

It was a perfect night, starful, silent, serene. From beyond, the recurrent hush and retreating wash of the waves accentuated the quiet, calming him unconsciously, allaying his restlessness, reducing the tension of his nerves. Under their influence he sauntered about the grounds a while, and then, turning back, reached Trella’s window.

Through the curtains a dim light filtered. As he looked at it, there was projected on the curtains a silhouette, faint but defined. If he hesitated, he never knew it. The window, undefended, opened at his grasp, and tearing the curtains aside, he sprang into the room, sprang at a man that was there, and, with a blow that would have felled a bullock, struck him between the eyes, hurling him backward against a mantel where, falling, his head struck. It cracked like a nut.

Satisfied but not satiated, he turned to Trella. Before he could reach her, the window had become a passageway. A cry, “Au secours!” had rent the night, and men in plain clothes that guard the mighty were tumbling into the room.

“Hors d’ici, canaille!” Wyvill shouted. “Out of here, or I’ll brain the lot of you!”

Raising a chair above his head, with all his force he flung it at them, but, deflected in flight, it went crashing against the wall; he was struggling with three men at once, while a fourth, falling at the foot of the mantel, was screaming, “My God! my God! he has killed his Royal Highness!”

“Tant mieux,” Wyvill, struggling still, threw back. But he was struggling with men who had no wish to struggle, who were seeking and uttering words of pacification.

“On ne veut pas faire du mal à Monsieur le Comte,” one kept repeating. “N’est ce pas, Paul? n’est ce pas, Jules? Seulement—”

With a manoevre which Wyvill had acquired in arguments with bargees on the Isis, Paul went spinning one way, Jules another, their mate rolling doubled in a corner.

“Hors d’ici!” he shouted again. “Hors d’ici, canaille, et enlevez votre crapule de prince.”

He turned in search of Trella. In the commotion she had vanished. But a door leading to the hall beyond was open, and leaving the men, in plain, and now tolerably tattered clothes, to their duty, through the door he passed to have a word with her.

Without, were scared and huddling servants. Scattering them to their quarters, Wyvill ransacked the house, searched the grounds. All he discovered was that an obsession had fled, and that Trella had got away through the night to her mother. Then, divining, perhaps, that she would regard any attempt to follow her as an excess of civility, he turned in and went to bed.

It was as well, perhaps. For what shall a man say to a woman who has ceased to care for him? That she has cared for him? It is better to let the subject drop. So, at least, Wyvill decided. Afterward he was glad that he had not tried to pursue the conversation further, glad that the dear departed had dispensed with the formality of farewell. And so, in the end, matters adjusted themselves, as, in the end, all matters do.

The next day the lady, chaperoned by her mother, journeyed from France, proceeded to this country and then to the land of the Dakotas, where, on the entirely justified plea of cruelty, complicated with desertion, she solicited and obtained a divorce.

The decree was received with general satisfaction. As a nation we do not approve of these matches. Moreover, through Mrs. Verelst, everybody knew that Wyvill was a sullen drunkard, with whom no self-respecting woman could live. Trella was more indulgent. She admitted that Wyvill was not, perhaps, all that he might have been, but she declared that she forgave him entirely. That certainly was very nice of her.

Of Thule she never spoke. The press of two worlds gave it out that he died of pneumonia, suddenly, as mortals do die, but decorously, as royals should. Trella never undeceived a soul on the subject. That certainly was nice of her, too.

The Elixir of Love

‘I am married to a woman who is not my wife.’

It was on a liner, after dinner. The big ship had lurched. Into the smoking-room where I sat Lord Silverbridge had lurched with it. He had dropped into a seat beside me. I had asked how he did. It was in answer to that question that he made this curious remark.

As he spoke he looked down and away and ran his long, thin fingers through his bright, thick hair.

‘What!’ I exclaimed.

‘And she is one of your compatriots, too.’

Lady Silverbridge—formerly Miss Fanny Bunker—was a Bostonian. Of that I was perfectly aware. At her wedding I had sent with my felicitations a fish-knife. I had not been previously honored with her acquaintance. But Silverbridge I had known through a series of tolerably orgiac semesters at Heidelberg, where his name was merely Jones.

Through what miracles of Death such processions of relatives were mown that from nobody he had become peer, it is idle to burden this narrative. Yet the fact that we had worn identical student caps and fought identical student duels had eluded time; it had eluded, too, transitions and still survived. It was to this survival that I attributed the rather intimate confidence of his curious remark.

Of the purport of it I had not so much as an idea. The day previous I had embarked at Cherbourg for New York and found Silverbridge on board. It was then early in August. His marriage had taken place in London late in May. At the time I was on the Continent. It was the fish-knife that represented me. Subsequently the press supplied me with accounts of the wedding, of the bride’s beauty as well. I never believe a word I read in the papers. But of the girl’s beauty I knew by repute. In her picture I had seen that she embodied the ideal, filled the heart, and stirred it, too—just as Austin Dobson said of Autonoë—with pulse of Spring.

These things take long in the telling. But when Silverbridge made his curious remark, memory promptly ladled them out. I throw them in here to get rid of them.

‘What!’ I repeated.

Silverbridge looked up. ‘Yes,’ he presently resumed, ‘it is beastly to boast, but I am up a bigger tree than any one you ever heard of. My wife is not my wife, and, though I am married to her, I am not her husband.’

At this, of course, possibilities of anterior entanglements suggested themselves. It occurred to me that when Silverbridge was Jones, he might, in some unhallowed moment, have gone and done it.

‘You are not beating about the bush to tell me that there is another of them, are you?’ I asked.

He turned to me quickly. ‘How did you hit on it? Is it common—in the States, I mean?’

‘Common! Common!’ I murmured. ‘I don’t know that I should quite call it that. It seems to me devilish awkward. I haven’t the Penal Code on the end of my fingers, but I fancy it must be ten years. How much do they give you in England?’

‘For what?’ he threw at me.

‘Why, for bigamy,’ I threw back.

He turned to me anew. ‘I am not talking about bigamy.’

‘Then what in thunder are you talking about?’

‘Something worse.’

Smoke is a sedative. I hailed a steward, got a cigar, and proceeded to light it. Before the process was completed he was at me again.

‘I have only one wife. That is to say, I have been married but once. But where my wife is I do not know.’

On the table before me was a passenger list. Already I had looked it over. Now I examined it once more. Among the S’s was the following entry: ‘Silverbridge, Graf und Gräfin mit Dienerschaft.’

‘Isn’t she on board?’ I asked.

‘No.’

‘Then, without indiscretion,’ I continued, handing him the list as I spoke, ‘who is the lady mentioned here?’

At this he nodded to me, ran his fingers again through his hair, and made answer: ‘There’s the point. I do not know.’

‘But,’ I gasped, ‘doesn’t she know?’

‘Yes, she knows.’

‘Well, then, who does she say she is?’

‘Miss Fanny Bunker.’

‘But, confound it,’ I cried, ‘Miss Fanny Bunker is the girl you married.’

‘Precisely,’ he replied, and nodded again as though it ought now to be all perfectly clear. ‘But then you see the Fanny Bunker whom I married and the Fanny Bunker who is on board are not the same.’

‘Of course not,’ I exclaimed. ‘How could she be since she is now Lady Silverbridge. Previously she was a young girl. Now she is a married woman. That is difference enough.’

‘The difference is wider than that,’ he rejoined. ‘Much wider. They are not the same person.’

I pitched my cigar away. ‘Then will you please tell me how things got so damnably mixed?’

‘Candidly, I can’t.’

At that, in mounting irritation, I would have left him. It seemed to me that he was cracked. I was about to say as much. But something in the melancholy of his eyes prevented.

‘No,’ he added, ‘I do not know how. But perhaps you can tell me. By the way, what was that stuff you used to stow at Heidelberg?’

‘Psychology?’

‘Yes, that’s it. I thought of it when I saw you getting aboard. I thought, too, that because of it I might ask your advice. I am not boring you, am I?’

‘Boring me! Give me the gist of this thing or you will drive me to drink.’

Silverbridge, however, was not to be hurried. He got a letter from his pocket, consulted it, consulted the ceiling, then, leaning forward, he made this extraordinary statement: ‘There are two of her.’

I looked at him, but said nothing. After all, what was there to say? Yet, in my silence, there must have been the encouragement which he sought, for he ran on at once, quite volubly.

‘It was in April we met. I cannot be sure, but I think between us it was love at first sight. I am sure, though, that I adored her at once. She exhaled all that is fetching in woman; simplicity, sympathy, sweetness, and strength. There was about her, too, an alertness, a vivacity, which I had never known. She went to my head. I think, too, I must have impressed her, for when I asked it was given. Our marriage was immediate. Somebody or other, a Frenchman I think, said that there are plenty of delightful marriages, but none that are delicious. The beggar was wrong. Ours was. But so appallingly brief! Four weeks, that is all. Yes, in four weeks she left me. One morning I awoke, aroused by a cry. At the other end of the room she was crouching and calling, “Where am I? Where am I?” And when I sprang up to go to her, she crouched yet further away, screaming, “Who are you? Who are you?” ’

‘The devil!’ I muttered.

‘You will understand in a moment what I did not. I assumed, of course—and it was horrible to assume it—that she had gone suddenly mad. But no, she was entirely rational, except in this, she denied any knowledge of or acquaintance with me. She denied that she was my wife. At first it was difficult to get her to believe even that she was in England. When I convinced her of that she accepted the fact, but not the marriage. She said she had had no part in it. Meanwhile, it was obvious that she herself was totally different. Her speech and manner had altered. In no way was she the same. I got Simpson in. Simpson you know is—’

‘Physician-in-ordinary,’ I interjected.

‘Yes, and he asked me concerning her antecedents. I could tell him but little. She had come to London for the season with some friends, and so soon after I met her as I could manage it we were married by special license. I told you it was love at first sight. I told him so, too. He advised me to write to her people.’

‘Well?’

‘I did. Here is a letter from her father. In it he says that had he had the time, had our marriage not been so precipitate, he would have told me—what do you suppose? That within her are two souls. Is such a thing possible?’

‘Goethe said it was. “Within me,” he declared, “two souls reside.” ’

‘But did they alternate? Her father says—’

‘That hers is a case of dual personality.’

‘Yes, those are his very words. But is there such a thing?’

‘No,’ I answered, after a moment. ‘It is a term serviceable merely for lack of a better one. You know, however, that the mind is dual. Ordinarily the two hemispheres of the brain work together. Now and again there is discord. The result is insanity. Less frequently while one of them is awake the other falls asleep, and vice versa. That, I suppose, is the case with Lady Silverbridge. What do you propose to do?’

‘I have no choice. At her insistence and at her father’s request I am taking her to Boston.’

‘As Lady Silverbridge?’

‘She won’t admit that she is that. She declares that she is Miss Bunker.’

‘Permit me. What is her attitude toward you?’

‘H’m. Civil, but chilly. I think she hates me.’

‘And you want my advice?’

To this question Silverbridge nodded hopelessly.

‘Then,’ I added, ‘take her back as you took her from church.’

With the same hopeless look Silverbridge nodded again. ‘Yes, it is easy to say, but nowadays there is no elixir of love.’

‘Indeed there is,’ I retorted. ‘Given tact, opportunity, propinquity, and the desire and any man—who is a man—can change frigidity into affection; hate into love. But the ingredients must be fused. They constitute the elixir.’

To this Silverbridge assented. ‘That’s of course. But, for the elixir to work, the girl must be normal. Fanny isn’t. She is abnormal.’

‘I am not so sure,’ I replied. ‘And yet, if you come to that, are any of us normal? How often it happens that we do or say things that we had no intention of doing or saying, things which afterward we are unable to account for. In the course of every life there are such changes of personality that, could each phase of our existence he incarnated into distinct individuals and those individuals got together, so dissimilar and antipathetic would they be, that it is only a question of time when they would come to blows.

‘No,’ I presently resumed. ‘We all change. It is a law of nature. But we change so gradually that the change is unperceived. Lady Silverbridge has changed, too, only the change in her instead of being gradual has been abrupt. But she is not, therefore, abnormal. For that matter nobody is. Every being, however constituted, has his or her raison d’être.’

‘Yes,’ said Silverbridge, after a moment. ‘That is probably true. Yet, even so, I don’t see how it helps me.’

‘Why, very greatly,’ I replied. ‘The moment you recognize that the condition of your wife is normal you may proceed to administer the elixir. Your wife is a young and sensitive woman. Barring a violin there is nothing more impressionable than a woman who is young and sensitive. Take, by the way, the violin for analogy. In the hands of an artist it is vibrant with harmony. In the hands of an artisan it is discordant. Of course, there are violins so wretched that no artist could draw from them quavers other than cracked and thin. But, given a virtuoso and a Cremona, and what duos, what trios even, the conjunction will produce! A young and sensitive woman is a Cremona in flesh and blood. The harmonies, the duos and trios of which she is capable depend on the maestria of the man by whom she is approached. Now you, I will assume, are a virtuoso and your wife a violin. If you wish her to go with you to Boston as she went with you from church, treat her as an artist should.’

Silverbridge beckoned a steward and ordered beer.

‘That is all very fine,’ he remarked, when I stopped to draw breath. ‘Very fine in theory, but in practice—’

‘In practice,’ I interrupted, ‘it is finer still. You know the ingredients of the elixir. These ingredients you have. You have but to compound them, feed her with them, and once more she is yours.’

The steward approached with the beer. Silverbridge swallowed it, student fashion, at a gulp.

‘Were not Lady Silverbridge already your wife,’ I resumed, the process which I am about to indicate would be perhaps inconvenient, certainly unconventional, but not impractical. As it is, it will appeal to you as being entirely proper, poetic to boot, and psychologic as well.’

Silverbridge looked at his empty glass and then inquiringly at me. But, though there was an inquiry in his eye, the melancholy and hopelessness in them abided.

‘Go to her stateroom to-night,’ I continued. ‘Go there when she is asleep. Go there when she is in her first sleep. Then whisper your name in her ear, whisper it again. Then again. Whisper to her that she loves you. But be careful not to awake her. In an hour return and whisper anew. Then leave her. The breathing of your name and the suggestion in her ear will make her dream of you, and in that dream it may be that the two hemispheres of her brain will begin to work in unison, or it may be that the one that knew you will be aroused and the other submerged. But in any event, whichever Fanny Bunker awakes tomorrow that Fanny Bunker will be yours. Then it will depend but on you to renew the harmonies you created.’

I stood up to go. For a moment yet he detained me. His face, previously drear, now was flushed. From his eyes the melancholy and hopelessness were departing.

‘Is—is this receipt one of your own manufacture or—or ⸺’

‘You will not find it in the pharmacopoeia,’ I answered. ‘But you will find it sovereign.’

‘It has been tried?’

‘Again and again.’

‘Successfully?’

‘Always.’

At this Silverbridge got also from his seat. ‘Thank you,’ he said very gravely. ‘Thank you. I, too, will try it.’

With that for the night we parted. The next day I looked for him. He did not seem to be about. On the morrow, on the promenade deck, I ran into him. At his side was a beauty.

‘Let me introduce you,’ he said.

As he spoke, he smiled. The beauty smiled also. That smile of his and of hers supplied me with obvious deductions.

An exchange of the usual platitudes ensued. But the deductions I was in haste to examine. I made them into a bundle which presently, after more platitudes, I took with me to the smoking-room. There, later, Silverbridge joined me.

‘The prescription worked all right, did it not?’ I asked.

‘Like an essence of bonbons,’ he answered. ‘I am married now to a woman who is my wife.’

‘But to which of them?’

‘To both,’ he luxuriously replied.

‘Lady Silverbridge is certainly a host in herself,’ I ventured to remark. ‘But then, so too is every Cremona. So is every impressionable woman. Should she get away again—’

‘If she should,’ Silverbridge, with hopeful and beautiful confidence, exclaimed, ‘if she should, have I not the psychologist’s stone in this lovely elixir!’

‘You have something better than that,’ I concluded. ‘You have love’s writ of habeas corpus.’

I

A YEAR or two ago Hugh Hyrtl was absolutely unknown; if it be different to-day, it is because of the following curious circumstances:

To begin with, he was an artist—a young artist, a good artist, a good-looking artist—but he was anything but a rich artist, and, as I have intimated, unknown. There were days when he was not certain whether he would dine or not, but, being young, he was hopeful, and, being hopeful, courageous. His atelier, which was also his bed-room and parlor, overlooked the courtyard of a great house on Tompkins Square.

Tompkins Square is not a locality over which Fashion presides, and Hugh, who was dainty in his ways, hated it as thoroughly as it is possible for an honest young fellow to hate anything. But Tompkins Square is perhaps the least expensive residential quarter of New York, and there Hugh was able to achieve the impossible—to dream of Fame and live on a dollar a day.

Meanwhile he was at work on that great picture which everyone has since seen—Heliogabalus smothering men with flowers. The picture had plenty of color, plenty of action, plenty of archæology, and Hugh was beginning to feel that it might be a success when one fine day, as he happened to be retouching the gold sigma on which the little emperor lounged and laughed, a window opposite his own was thrown open, and the initial incident of the accompanying drama occurred.

Across the court there came a trill, then a burst of song, a roulade of sheer joy such as is always pleasant to intercept, but particularly so when you happen to be in the youth of life and the youth of the year. Hugh looked up. In the opposite window was a girl—a pretty girl; yet when I say pretty I mean that prettiness which, when you see it, makes you want to jump straight down the possessor’s throat. It was the prettiness that comes with the eighteenth year to a girl who has blue eyes, kissable lips and a complexion of roses and cream.

When Hugh looked up the trill trembled and ceased. Four eyes had met. Hugh smiled, which was impertinent of him; the girl blushed, which was modest of her; then an old man appeared, one who neither blushed nor smiled, who looked exceeding cross and shut the window with a bang.

“Cæsar, what a beauty!” Hugh exclaimed, and turned to the sigma once more. In a moment he looked across the court. The window was blank. “I wonder,” he mused, and whistled softly to himself; “I wonder if I haven’t got too much ochre stuck on there.” He looked again at the window across the court. “Bah!” he continued, “as if I could have too much ochre. It’s the purple on the laticlave that jars.”

For a little space he painted away very determinedly, the muscles of his jaw close set; then he looked again at the window—there was no one, not even the cross old man.

“Oh, hang it all,” he cried. “I can’t work any more to-day!”

When an agile young fellow wants to, it doesn’t take him very long to get down six flights of stairs—no, nor seven, either, however steep those stairs may be—and presently Hugh entered a dingy den over which the janitress of the building presided.

The janitress was a fat person, with the voice of an ogre, and a great love for gossip and tenants who paid their way. Hugh never gossiped, but he had a smile which had won her heart, all ogress that she was. She laughed as he entered and flourished a broom.

“Mrs. O’Hassadam,” he began, “you are looking very handsome this morning. I—”

“Don’t be flattering an old lady like meself, Mr. Hyrtl, but say to me just plainly what you want, with no nonsense whatever.”

“Then, Mrs. O’Hassadam, as you love righteousness and abhor mammon, tell me who those people are that live up there on the other side of the court, yes, on the sixth story where the geranium is?”

“No great shakes, Mr. Hyrtl.”

“What!”

“No great shakes, Mr. Hyrtl.”

“But the girl?”

“No great shakes, I keep telling you; a gad-about, that’s what she is, with an ex-convict for a pa.”

“I don’t believe a word of it,” cried Hugh, indignantly, “no, not one word.”

“Question a lady’s veracity, Mr. Hyrtl? Where are your manners, Mr. Hyrtl. Mr. Hyrtl, mind what I am telling you. For ten years that old forger has been here, and, since I can remember, not a letter has come for him whatever, not a soul has come to see him and not once has he put his foot out of this door. Question a lady’s word!”

“But—”

“It’s a murderer he is, I am a-thinking, and as for that gal, she’s no better than she should be whatever at all, sitting there where anyone can see her, where I can see her, a-trying to make eyes at you.”

“But—”

“Oh, I know very well you’re forever in your paintbox and pay no attention to likes of her. It’s annoying you, she is, that’s what she’s doing, in a respectable house like this, besides.”

“But—”

“And what is it you want, whatever?” Mrs. O’Hassadam abruptly inquired of a little man, sadly shabby in appearance, who had loomed in the door. “There’s no old bottles to-day.”

“And if there were I wouldn’t want them,” the little man retorted, defiantly; “unless they were full. It’s lodgings I’m after.”

“It is, is it? Well, then, you’d better try and find them in some nice little place on Fifth avenue where they’ll only charge you five dollars if you ring the bell and ten dollars if you don’t. This establishment wouldn’t suit you at all.”

And Mrs. O’Hassadam made a skirmish with her broom.

“Lodgings, indeed,” she added, indignantly; “why not chambers, self-contained, with private entrance. Be off, or I’ll call the police. Mr. Hyrtl—”

Hugh had sidled out, pretending not to hear. Presently he was on the sidewalk. Beyond was the Square, deluged by the eager sunlight of a radiant noon; near at hand was a junkshop, and a step or two further on a window in which, temptingly arranged, were coils of sausages, red beefsteak, yellow fowl and a glistening ham. For a second, in sheer perplexity, Hugh stopped; yet, as he loitered there, he saw nothing of the contents of that window—it was what another had held that memory was reproducing, and, as the convolutions of fancy waned and subsided, he found himself staring at the individual whom Mrs. O’Hassadam had ordered to be off.

“Well, sir, do you take me for a freak?”

He was a stout, little man, with a long beard and the restless eyes of a ferret, distressingly shabby, the more so even that in his shabbiness was the unmistakable air of better days.

Hugh started from his reverie.

“Not a bit,” he answered, gently. “I am an artist, and if I stared at you it was because you look like a Roman Senator.”

“Why not a satyr? So you are an artist, eh? Well, where have I seen you before—in Lisbon, Liverpool or Leghorn?”

“Truly,” Hugh answered, “I have never been so far away.”

“You haven’t, haven’t you?” And the little man scrutinized the artist’s face. “All the same, I’ll be blowed if you don’t remind me of someone. Thundering guns, how cold it is!”

“Why, it must be seventy-five, at least.”

“Yes, I dare say—to those who have breakfasted, to those who dined last night and the night before; but when a man hasn’t eaten for forty-eight hours the rarest day of June is colder than Christmas Eve. Thundering guns!”

“You don’t mean to say—”

“Yes, I do mean to say. Now, tell me how I can earn a dollar at once—not to-morrow or to-night, but right now.”

And the little man, who had been looking very fiercely at Hugh, suddenly seemed about to collapse. Hugh caught him by the arm.

“Here, come with me,” he said.

In a moment both were seated at a table of the eating-shop within.

“Take some coffee first,” said Hugh, authoritatively, “and then—”

“Oh, you’re going to treat, are you? Well, now, my name is John Anderson—yes, sir, John Anderson, my Joe John—and it doesn’t rhyme with either beat or sponge. I won’t be treated. I may be indigent, but I am proud. Besides, if I had two-pence I could become a millionaire.”

“You will let me,” said Hugh, seductively, “make you a little loan. I have two dollars, here is one. Pay me when you are a millionaire.”

At the sight of the coin the little man turned purple.

“Thundering guns!” he muttered, “yesterday I passed an hour at the Metropolitan Museum looking at a gold piece in a case. Give me your name and address.”

Before the open door of the eating-house a slender figure passed. Hugh jumped from his seat. It was she, he could have sworn. The little man caught him by the arm.

“Your name and address,” he repeated.

Hugh shook himself loose. In a second he was in the street. The slender figure was just turning the corner, but Hugh was right behind. When at last he overtook that slender figure he discovered that it belonged to a sallow brunette.

At the table in the eating-house the little man was muttering:

“But where the deuce have I seen him before?”

II

THE next morning Hugh was hard at work gain. The painting before him was a wonder to behold. It represented a hall, similar to the interior of a temple—one in which fluted columns rose and met the dome; about it ran a gallery, and there, Heliogabalus, a painted boy of fifteen, lounged and laughed; near him were the magi come from afar to witness the nuptials of the Sun and Moon; opposite were musicians, and a little beyond a group of slaves were emptying huge baskets of lilies on the assembled guests beneath. Some of the latter, in flowers up to the waist, were trying to escape, but the door was barred. Others, aided by yellow couches, were trying to scale the wall and reach the gallery above, and on these a steady rain of red and white buds descended. In a corner, an avalanche of roses and violets had fallen, and from it men were struggling, their arms crooked, their eyes dilated. From the dome a glare of sunlight smote the purple draperies, danced on the sea of flowers and put a rainbow in the air. It was very gorgeous, a riot of splendid color, and to Hugh it meant nothing less than an encounter with that gracious lady whose name is Fame.

He was at work then on the sigma of gold on which the little emperor lounged, and that gold he was endeavoring to marry harmoniously with the brass of the trumpets and the crocus of the harps. The night before, on his return after a long tramp through Central Park, he had determined not to look again at the window across the court; for to look was to fall in love, and to fall in love meant Fame, farewell! and also Starvation, welcome!” In spite of which, however, no sooner was his light extinguished than he took a look. Save a single star that glowed and glimmered, there was not a thing to be seen. Thereupon, with all the strength of virtuous resolutions, he had wrapped himself in slumber and dreams of her. And now on this particular morning, he had not tried more than ten or a dozen times to see if she were there.

The sigma was done, its gold properly married with the crocus and brass, and Hugh was about to get to work on a heap of lilies and hyacinths when a fresh incident occurred. Someone was knocking at the door.

“Come in!” Hugh cried, without looking round. It was Mrs. O’Hassadam, he was sure.

But though he heard the door open, he heard nothing that indicated the presence of that lady; no rich, loud greeting and rustle of broom. He turned his head. On the threshold stood a man, very gaunt and sickly, a man who looked as though he had a bad digestion and a worse conscience; he seemed feeble, too, timorous and apologetic. His coat would not have caused envy in the heart of a backwoodsman, and his trousers were elaborately patched. One foot was shod with a slipper, the other with a shoe; both were rusty, and the man himself exhaled an indefinable odor of must and decay. At a glance Hugh recognized the cross old person who, the day before, had shut the opposite window with a bang.

“H’m!” he mused. “He’s going to call me to account for flirting with his daughter. Well, let him. Who’s afraid?”

“We are neighbors, sir,” the old man began, with a stealthy air and a covert look about him.

“Take a seat, I pray you,” said Hugh, politely.

“And being neighbors, I thought I would venture to call.”

“A compliment which does me much honor, and one which I trust you will permit me to repay,” Hugh answered, with a fine flourish. “Be seated, I beg of you.”

“You are a stranger here,” the old man added, thoughtfully; “but I have lived in this house for the past ten years.”

“Dear me!”

“Yes; ten years. I came here when my daughter Jenny was eight years old, and she is just eighteen to-day. She hasn’t always lived here, though. Until a few months ago she was away at school. She is a good girl, sir.”

To this statement Hugh nodded approvingly.

“It’s dull for her, very. She has no friends of her own age. I have not let her associate with the people hereabouts, and, as for myself, I am not much of a companion for a lass like her. Am I?”

Hugh tried his best to look complimentary. He failed, however, and said nothing. But the old man’s eyes were fixed on the floor and he ran on, unheeding:

“No, I am not, and she hasn’t any relatives, either. I am the last of my race. I am a Sisseton, and my brother Paul was killed at my side in the war. My wife, she died before I came here. So it’s dull for her, you see, very; and this being her birthday and you being a stranger, I just thought I might ask would you spend the evening with us?”

“Why, my dear Mr. Sisseton, nothing on earth, no, absolutely nothing could give me greater pleasure.”

“Well, then, that is settled. There will be some cake, and I don’t promise it, but there may be a glass of sweet wine.”

“I adore cake,” Hugh fairly shouted. “As for wine, I never touch it.”

“Don’t you, now?” And the old man looked up very sharply at Hugh. “Well, well, I have heard as much. I have heard—But there, never mind. It’s settled, then, is it? We may expect you at eight?”

“To the minute, Mr. Sisseton.”

But he spoke to the walls. The old man had disappeared as in a trap, closing the door noiselessly as he went, and Hugh returned to his lilies.

The work progressed slowly enough after that, for between the canvas and the brush every now and again a face would appear—one that was neither Roman nor Syrian, a bewilderment of yellow hair, blue eyes, kissable lips and a complexion of roses and cream.

“I am in luck,” Hugh decided. And had he not reached the austere age of three-and-twenty I promise you he would have danced for joy.

The afternoon took itself away. At six o’clock Hugh began touching up the dimmed splendor of a pair of patent-leather pumps which he found wrapped in an old newspaper at the bottom of his trunk. He got out his best coat and brushed it carefully; he got out a very large neckcloth, which he tied with the nicety of a geometrician; there was, he discovered, a crease still in his trousers, there was a pair of gloves that still could be worn, and—though you or I would have expected to be cut dead by our best beloved had we dared to wear such a hat as his—when he went out that evening for dinner no nicer, fresher, handsomer young fellow ever strode through Tompkins Square. Nevertheless, at one minute before eight precisely, when this hero of a midspring night rapped on an old man’s door his hand was trembling and he blushed like a girl.

It sounds like a phrase in a novel to say that the room into which he was then ushered was scrupulously neat, but it would take a maker of dainty ballads to describe its sweetness and simplicity. Barring the old man, who would have been a blur on a desert, there was not a thing in it that jarred. Two windows, which looked on the street, were hung with lace, which was imitation, of course, yet brilliantly white, and these curtains were looped to the wall with strips of canary silk that had probably come from a cigar-box. There were four chairs unconventionally arranged. There was one small table on which there was a large cake. There was another on which there was a lamp and a pink shade. On the walls were two colored lithographs, unframed, that were recognizedly supplements of a London weekly. In the air was the scent of innocence, and on one of the chairs, blushing like mad, sat the prettiest little girl in the world.

Hugh distinguished himself at once by tripping over a mat, and so confused was he that when his host mumbled some form of introduction he awkwardly stretched his hand and as awkwardly withdrew it.

“And are you very well, sir?” the young woman inquired, her head held a trifle to one side and in her eyes a manifest delight at finding him more embarrassed than herself.

Hugh declared that he had never felt better in his life. The young woman, in reply to a question which he then addressed, announced that her own health was perfect; the old man, duly interrogated, answered in the same strain, and then all three earnestly discussed the weather. Presently there was cake and lemonade, which Hugh lauded to the skies. Never had he eaten such ambrosia, never had he sipped such nectar; and, in the enthusiasm of the moment, he consented to play poker for imaginary stakes—a game at which, at the expiration of an hour, he had lost not a penny less than two million dollars. At one moment, however, during the progress of the play he had everything in his own favor. A rap had come on the door, and the old man had jumped as though a dog under the table had bitten him on the leg. “Don’t let anyone in,” he beseeched. “Say I have moved; say I am dead. Here, let me get into the other room.” And with that he had risen, his face contracted, shaking in every limb. But already Jenny had gone to the door. It was a mistake, she announced. A visitor for another tenant. Thus reassured, gradually the old man’s calm returned and the game continued. When it was done, there was more ambrosia, more nectar, more small-talk, and, finally, the inevitable good-night.

After Hugh had gone, father and daughter sat awhile in silence. Suddenly Jenny jumped to her feet and threw her arms about the old man’s neck.

“My darling papa, I love you!”

But what she meant by that absurd demonstration she did not wait to explain. She was out of the room and in her own in a second.

The old man heard her door close, and, taking the lamp, went to an anjoining chamber. It contained a bed, a chair, a bureau and a trunk. He put the lamp on the bureau and moved the bed. Then, kneeling down, he raised a plank from the floor and extracted a package wrapped in oilskin. This, with tender care, he opened, and drew out a bill of the nation of the value of one thousand dollars. Presently he drew out another of the game denomination, then a third, a fourth, until finally be had counted eighty-seven. And it would have been curious if he had not, for he had gone through the same operation almost seven thousand three hundred times—that is to say, twice a day for nearly ten years.

III

ONCE planted, the germ of friendship blooms apace. Barely a fortnight had gone, and here were these three people on the best of terms. In the discreetest manner, Hugh had managed to ingratiate himself with the old man; he was serviceable, and he asked no questions. The timidity, the shrinking fear of strangers, which was the peculiar characteristic of this curious individual, he treated as he would have one of those natural afflictions, such as rheumatism or baldness, to which advanced age is subject and for which there is no cure. Certainly he made no allusion to it, but then he had so much to occupy him that it maybe he gave it, if at all, little more than a passing thought.

Ah, yes! he had much to occupy him. Heliogabalus was indeed turned to the wall, but the atelier was bright with different studies of the same lead, luminous with blue eyes, yellow hair and complexions of roses and cream. Yet, for all his art, there was an intangible something in the original, a freshness, a vivacity, a charm that eluded him and escaped.

“I am too much in love to paint her properly,” he declared to himself; and as a matter of fact he was wholly, turbulently, absurdly in love with a girl whom he had known but a fortnight and of whose previous existence he had been absolutely unaware.

Of this state of affairs Jenny was seemingly ignorant. Now and again of an evening he sat with her and her father in that little sky-parlor where he had first tasted the food of the gods, and there, with a sentiment akin to reverence, listened to the sweet music of her words. Sometimes, when the evening happened to be clear, they took a stroll among the factory girls and mechanics in the Square, and sometimes they would sit awhile on one of the benches and discuss subjects in which—by comparison to one, the great one as yet unbroached—the interest was probably feigned; for there were times when their conversation, however animated, would subside and cease, and the wonder of love would be upon them. These silences, painfully awkward, indeed, Hugh would break with snatches of verse—lines of Owen Meredith, that poet of the nineteenth century who died the other day in his beloved France; quatrains of Browning, too; and once the ill-mannered young fellow recited a conceit of Leigh Hunt’s:

“Jenny kissed me when we met,
Jumping from the chair she sat in;
Time, you thief who love to get
Sweets upon your list, put that in—
Say I’m weary, say I’m sad,
Say that wealth and health have missed me,
Say I’m growing old; but add,
Jenny kissed me.”

At this impertinence, however, the girl’s face took on such mantling hues, that for very shame her companion was obliged to drop into sedater measures, and divert her attention with astronomical hypotheses in regard to the moon, which, at that moment, happened to be suspended above them, a slender sickle of gold.

In parishes like Tompkins Square, that pomp of Satan, which we have agreed to call Etiquette, is not always as punctiliously observed as it is in fairer precincts; and a day or two later when Hugh had related the disadvantages under which he labored, when trying, in the absence of the model, to get a certain face on canvas, not Miss Jenny Sisseton, no, nor her father, either, saw the slightest objection to her sitting in propria persona to this audacious young man. What need had they of our effete survival of the duenna of the past? Theirs was a solitude as harmless, yes, and as fragrant, as that of two flowers on separate stalks.

But one dazzling noon, it so happened, that this young woman, after sitting for at least ten minutes as quiet as a mouse, pouted her pretty lips, and looking straight at Hugh, who was painting them very determinedly, remarked with an air of sweet unconcern:

“Why don’t you tell me something of yourself?”

“Why?” Hugh echoed. “Because there is nothing to tell, I suppose. My life began—” he was about to say, “when I met you,” but he tacked adroitly—“the first time I saw an oil-painting. I was a child then, and ever since I have dreamed of being an artist.”

“But you are.”

“No, an apprentice, merely. And yet when I think of my first efforts, my one grief is that my poor mother could not have lived to see the progress I have made. She never believed much in art, but she did believe in me.”

“Is it long since—”

“Since she died? Yes, it is a long time ago. I was at school in Baltimore; a message came and they sent me to her at once. Our home was in Virginia, a little cottage not far from Richmond. There my mother lived with only an old negress to assist her. When I arrived, she was dead. Some excitement, the receipt of a letter, the old woman said, and she had sent for me, but she had sent too late. After the funeral I barred the windows, locked the door and went back to school. But they did not keep me long. I had no money. The little income which my mother enjoyed died with her, and the cottage could not be sold until I came of age.”

“Did you sell it then?”

“No, indeed. I shall never sell it. My mother was born there and it was there she died.”

“Tell me of her,” Jenny murmured. “Are you like her?”

“No, they used to say not. I take after my father, I believe. He was a sailor, the captain of a merchantman, and was lost at sea. It was a terrible blow for my mother; she was left alone with but myself for consolation. It was that she used to call me, and I—I loved her with all my heart.”

“I would have loved her, too,” Jenny sighed.

“If she could hear you, do you know what she would say?—do you know, Jenny? She would say: ‘My dear child, I love you, too. I love you because you are sweet and good, because you are tender-hearted, because you are the lovliest, best and dearest girl in all the world, because you have filled my boy’s life with living springs, because you are the future to him, and hope and fame.’ That is what she would say to you, Jenny, and she would add, I know: ‘Love him, Jenny, for my sake if you cannot love him for his own.’ ”

“But I do love you,” said the young woman, with great decision. “Didn’t you know it?”

At this unexpected avowal Hugh stood very still, his brush in the air; then the brush fell, and suddenly he was at her side, an arm about the the whiteness of her neck, his lips on hers.

“Here! Here! Stop that!”

The two culprits separated so quickly that neither were quite sure whether the kiss had been given or yet returned. Across the court, in the window opposite, Mr. Sisseton glowered, imposing and irate.

“Stop that, I say!” he repeated. “You have no right to do that. No right at all. As for you, young man, go back to your easel. Jenny, don’t you move until I am there.”

In their innocence, a thunderbolt from a clear sky could not have startled more. Jenny hid her face in her hands and Hugh bit his fingers. A minute passed, that seemed an hour long, then another, a third, a fourth; finally there came a shuffle in the hall and the old man entered, this time without the formality of a rap.

“Now, sir—” he began.

“Mr. Sisseton,” Hugh interrupted, “I swear to you it is the first time, and I swear to you, also, it would not have occurred if—if—”

“Well, sir, if what? If I hadn’t brought you together, perhaps. And do you suppose I didn’t do it on purpose?”

“What!”

“Precisely. Now will you be good enough to inform me what your intentions are?”

“My intentions are to marry your daughter, if she will do me the honor to become my wife.”

“Oh, they are, are they? And have you any reason to think that she will consent?”

“He knows that I will,” said that forward young woman.

“It’s come to that pass, has it?” muttered the tyrant. “Very good. Now, Mr. Hyrtl, perhaps you will answer a question. How do you propose to support her?”

Hugh’s answer was in the expression which he then assumed, one pathetic enough to have mollified a tiger. But Mr. Sisseton was either not to be mollified or else he demanded something more explicit than pantomime.

“Well, sir?” he growled.

“Well, sir,” Hugh at last made answer, “I am young, strong, ambitious, and it seems to me—”

“Fiddlesticks! So was I young, strong, ambitious, and it seemed to me that I was quite capable of supporting a wife on just those things for capital. The result was not satisfactory. I have had the experience, though, and on the day when my wife, outworn with privation and misery, died, I swore that my daughter should never marry a pauper.”

Hugh raised a hand in protest.

“Unless,” the old man continued, “unless my daughter happened to be an heiress.”

“Oh, papa, papa,” sobbed Jenny, “how can you be so cruel!”

Mr. Sisseton went to the door, opened it, peered out in the corridor, then closing it again, took a seat in the middle of the room and stared at Hugh as though he had never seen him before.

“What day of the month is it?” he asked, abruptly.

“Really—”

“Come now, a clever young fellow like you ought to tell me like a shot.”

“It’s the 10th,” said Hugh, morosely.

“The 10th of what?”

“The 10th of June,” sobbed Jenny.

“The 10th of June, is it?” the old man repeated, meditatively, “the 10th of June. Dear me, dear me, how time flies! Well, it being the 10th of June—You are quite sure, are you, that it is the 10th of June?”

“Yes, yes,” Hugh and Jenny answered in chorus.

“Well, it being the 10th of June, I may say, in confidence, of course, I may say that my daughter is an heiress.”

“An heiress!” the girl exclaimed.

“As if I cared,” said Hugh.

“Well, you might just as well care, then,” the old man retorted. “For if she were not, she would never be your wife. No, sir, never. However, in the circumstances, and in view of the fact that to-day is the 10th of June, I may congratulate you. Jenny will have eighty-seven thousand dollars.” And drawing from his pocket a package done up in oilskin, the old man displayed to the startled lovers a roll of banknotes of fabulous size.

“But where did you get them from?” Jenny gasped.

Up to this point the old man had conducted himself with the assurance and bravado of a stock-broker, but that simple little question seemed to have precisely the same effect on him that the prick of a pin has on a toy balloon. He collapsed.

“Why—why,” he stammered at last, “they belonged to your mother.”

“But only a moment ago you said she died of privation and want.”

“I saved them out of my pension, then.”

“Papa! Out of your pension! Fifty pensions like yours wouldn’t make that amount.”

The old man turned upon her, with recovered strength.

“Do you take me for a thief?” he gnashed.

“Perhaps you have a reason of your own,” said Hugh, “for not wishing to tell where the money came from.”

“I have. I have a dozen. I have a thousand.”

“Let us say no more about it, then. For my part, I regard you as above suspicion.”

“So do I,” said Jenny.

“And it’s lucky you do,” bawled the old man, all his former assurance and bravado returning. “It’s mighty lucky you do. You don’t know what a narrow squeeze you’ve had. You don’t either of you know of what I am capable when I’m vexed. But what do you mean, anyway, by asking me questions? Such impudence!”

“There, there, papa,” murmured Jenny.

“Yes, miss, such impudence! Now, you can accept what I choose to give you and accept it, too, with a devilish good grace or—or that’s the end of the marriage. I’ll pack you off to a convent, by gad, that’s just what I’ll do with you.”

And as he made these direful threats the fierce old man fairly chuckled.

“I’ll be good as gold,” said Jenny, seraphically.

“Well, you had better, and so had that lackadaisical simpleton there. Now, let us talk about the wedding. Good Heavens, what’s that?”

There had come on the door a knock that would have waked the dead. The old man jumped as though stung by a wasp.

“Don’t let anyone come in,” he entreated. “Barricade the door, hide me somewhere.”

His hands were trembling so that he could hardly get the oilskin package back in his pocket. His face was haggard and his eyes dilated, and suddenly he assumed the appearance of a hunted beast.

“Hide me,” he implored. “Don’t let anyone in!”

“But before either Hugh or Jenny could make even a pretense at obeying him, the door flew open and a little man with a long beard entered the room.

“Thundering guns!” he exclaimed, “I can’t congratulate you on your stairs.”

“Sir,” said Hugh, stepping forward, “to what do I owe the honor—”

“Do you mean to say that you don’t remember me?”

“I do not, sir; and as I happen to be discussing family matters—”

Mr. Sisseton beckoned frantically to Jenny, and slid like a shadow through the door.

“I will join you in a moment!” Hugh called after them. “Now, sir,” he continued; “what is it?”

“Nice gal, that,” said the stranger, appreciatively. “Why, there she is again, and again,” he added, pointing to the pictures that illuminated the room. “Is the old party her pa?”

“Sir, I am waiting—”

“Thundering guns! so you are, dear boy. Let’s sit down; those stairs of yours would tire a resurrectionist.”

IV

THE little man straddled a chair and gave a tug at his beard.

“A nice fellow, you are,” he muttered, with a fine show of indignation. “You save a man’s life and forget all about him. What kind of behavior is that? I was starving last month and you loaned me a dollar. Here it is.”

“Yes, indeed,” said Hugh, a trifle mollified; “I remember you now.”

“I should have repaid it before, but I didn’t have it.”

“Excellent reason; but then there was no hurry. I don’t see how you found me, though.”

“No trouble about that; all I had to do was to ask that fat harridan downstairs; the difficulty was to get the coin. After you bolted I had something to eat and invested the change in pencils, which I peddled at a profit, turned the proceeds into fancy notions; and, here I am, hale and hearty, with the future before me and a cool hundred in my pocket.”

“Bravo!” said Hugh. “I like your grit.”

“Bah! I’ll be a millionaire yet, and buy some of your pictures—that one, for instance; the pretty girl who is to be your wife.”

“And how the dickens did you know that?”

“I’m quick as a flash, that’s what I am. I can catch on quicker than any man you ever saw. But anyone would have known what was going on here. Bless your dear soul, I had only to catch a glimpse of her sweet face to know what was up. You’re not painting her picture for money, I’ll be bound.”

“Sir,” cried Hugh, irritated in spite of himself by the free and easy form of address, “I am very busy, and if—”

“Tut, tut. I have taken a fancy to you and you mustn’t be cross. Besides, it’s only my way. Let me tell you my story.”

“What for?”

“That you may know who I am, of course. I may look seedy, but I’m a man worth cultivating. You never heard of such an extraordinary fellow as I am. I have had a career that is simply marvelous. At twelve I was running a printing press in Toronto. The next year I made a fortune off a patent bit, and lost it in a night bucking the tiger. I have been an aëronaut, a telegraph operator, a nabob and a cook. I have followed a dozen trades—some honest, some not. I have engineered companies out of which millions have been made. I have been a miner in Arizona, in Cape Colony, in Peru I had the concession for lighting St. Petersburg with electricity and the charter for trams in Madras. I have handled cargoes of elephant tusks and smuggled opium in books. I have been a three-card-monté man on the Pacific slope and led revivals in Maine. The Wandering Jew is nothing to me. I have been everywhere, seen everything, and, though I am sixty years old, I am strong as an ox. With this hundred I shall open a cigar-shop. When I have a thousand to my credit I’ll take a hack at the Street.”

“With what?”

“With my brains, of course. What is there wonderful about speculating with the ready? Thundering guns! give me fifty thousand to-day and in a month I’ll quadruple it.”

“Or go broke.”

“Not a bit of it. What will you wager I don’t make a million? I am lucky, not a doubt of it, and I have ideas. My head is full of them. Anything suggests them—a tune from a barrel-organ, a sign in a window, a remark overheard and retained, the first paper I pick up; here, for instance—”

And the little man, leaning forward, picked up a newspaper which lay on the table. It was the one from which, a month before, Hugh had taken his pumps and which, with artistic indifference, he had suffered to remain where it fell.

“Thundering guns!”

With the agility of a clown the little man had sprung to his feet, his eyes glued to the paper. His face was always red, but suddenly it had grown bright purple.

“What is the number of this house?” he blurted.

“Seventeen.”

“Tompkins Square?”

Hugh nodded.

“Is there anyone here by the name of Sisseton?”

“Yes,” Hugh answered, blankly astonished. “But why do you ask?”

“Where does he live? Tell me at once.”

“Over there,” Hugh replied, with a gesture. “It was with him I was talking when you came in.”

“Thundering guns!”

With the bound of a panther the little man sprang at the door and vanished downstairs, crossed the court, mounted the other stairway, the paper still in his hand and Hugh at his heels.

“It is here, isn’t it?” he cried, over his shoulder, and burst into the Sisseton parlor.

Jenny was practicing on a type-writer and her father was beating a tattoo on the window, but at the sudden eruption both started and turned.

“Are you Mr. Rufus Sisseton?” the little man gasped. Mr. Sisseton seemed incapable of reply. He looked as though paralysis was claiming him as its own. It was Jenny who answered in his stead.

“In that case,” the little man announced, “my name is John Anderson and I am—”

He had no time to add more; Mr. Sisseton uttered one faint moan, raised his hands and fell into a chair.

Jenny made a dash at him. “Papa, papa!” she cried, “what is it?”

“The end,” he groaned. “Love, matrimony, everything you have dreamed is over.”

Under Jenny’s ministrations, presently he was again on his feet, and motioning to the little man he went with him into the adjoining room.

The two lovers stared for a second into each other’s eyes. On the floor the paper lay. Hugh caught it up, and after a glance at the headlines turned to the advertisements. One of them, which he read aloud, ran as follows:

“The next of kin of Humphery Anderson, who died the 10th of June, 1880, will learn something to their advantage by addressing Mr. Rufus Sisseton, 17 Tompkins Square.”

V

“WELL, sir,” said the little man, when Mr. Sisseton had closed the door. “What am I to learn to my advantage?”

At the moment Mr. Sisseton was enjoying the spectacle of that mental panorama in which the past unfolds and which is said to visit those about to drown. Ten years before, to a day, on a delightful June morning he had taken the express for Boston. Jenny was at school in a suburb of that city, and it was to see her that the excursion had been planned. He was not an accomplished traveler. Thus far his journeys—save that terrible one which we call the War—had been uneventful and few; as clerk in a wholesale grocery-shop his opportunities for travel had been slight; but a pension for which he had diligently petitioned to the Government had been granted, and to celebrate the occasion the firm he served had allowed him a holiday. On that morning he was therefore in the best of spirits, and as the train moved from the Grand Central Station he hummed very contendedly to himself. The distressing ugliness of the outlying districts were passed unmarked; it was the fragrance of Connecticut intervals that first attracted his attention; then he fell to musing about the possible existence of the people who dwelled in the roomy, white homesteads that appeared and vanished, the vocations of the loungers at the trim little stations that starred the route. A desire for life in the country beset him; he began to picture the pleasures he would enjoy on some little farm where Jenny could grow up in health and innocence, and presently his head nodded and he was asleep.

When he awoke, or perhaps it would be more exact to say when he recovered his senses, he was running like a deer across an empty field, fleeing from death and disaster. Then he had gone back, striving as best he could to aid the survivors of that collision, which, for its unparalleled horror, is cited still. There was a woman whom he had dragged from the burning wreck of a car; a child, for whose frail life he had struggled, and finally, by sheer strength, he had torn a man from a twisted seat that was holding him on a grill of flame.

The latter was dying, his face agonized, a leg broken, another charred to the bone, but even in his agony he retained his faculties.

“Take this,” he had said to his rescuer, “and give it yourself to my—”

At that the light had passed from his eyes; he was dead, and in Rufus Sisseton’s hand was a leather pocketbook on which the name Humphery Anderson shone in letters of gold.

When the old clerk reached New York his employers did not recognize him. He not only looked twenty years older, he seemed smitten with palsy. He took what money was due him, resigned his position and moved from the rooms he had occupied in St. Mark’s place to the less expensive region of Tompkins Square. He had but his pension now, and that pocketbook which contained absolutely nothing save a few memoranda and eighty-seven banknotes of the value of one thousand dollars each.

The memoranda related to the sale of a mine, but by whom or to whom there was not a word to indicate, and apart from them there was merely the name in gilt letters to show the ownership of the notes. Who was Humphery Anderson? Where had he come from? Where was he going? To whom had he wished this money to be given? These questions, and dozens of others which trod on their heels, Rufus Sisseton put ceaselessly and unavailingly to himself. The pockets of the man who had died before his eyes had been searched; there was a coarse handkerchief, two cigars, a handful of silver, a roll of small bills, a ticket to Boston, but not a clew to the identity of the deceased. His name, presumably, was Humphery Anderson, and that name Rufus Sisseton had given to the coroner and seen it chronicled in the list of the dead; but when a week went by, and no one claimed the body, the old clerk became uneasy. He put an advertisement in the Herald; there was no reply. He inserted another; the result was the same. It was then he resigned his position and moved to Tompkins Square.

Meanwhile he lived in a state of terror bordering on lunacy; death in the most terrible form had approached so close, the escape had been so narrow, that his nerves, never too strong at their best, had become unstrung. This his employers noticed, and were glad to have him go. But the thing which frightened him most, and of which no one save himself was aware, was the fear of being robbed. Behind every door he divined a possible thief; on every passer he scented a footpad; for as yet, in his uncertainty, he kept the pocketbook by him, sleeping on it at night, clutching it convulsively by day. But in Tompkins Square he felt easier; the idea of removing a plank occurred to him, and beneath his bed, in an oilskin wrapper, he placed the pocket-book. Another would have simplified everything by depositing the money in a bank, but Rufus Sisseton had grown timorous—banks had been known to fail. Therewith was the haunting memory of that agonized face and the words of the dying—“Give this, yourself.”

That “yourself” which the moribund had uttered the old clerk construed as constituting a sacred trust, and, to observe it as best he might, the advertisements continued. As time passed, and no reply came, his timorousness, instead of declining, increased. The eighty-seven thousand dollars submerged his faculties, he became the prey of fancies which banished both appetite and sleep; he kept to his room as much as possible, and finally so arranged that nothing could disturb his voluntary captivity. Nothing, indeed, except Jenny, who fluttered to him every year for awhile, and then took wing to the Massachusettsian school. When she had gone, he locked the door again and waited the coming of the Anderson heirs.

In this fashion seven years limped by, and Jenny, having received all the education which the school was competent to provide, returned definitely to her father. And it was as well, perhaps, that she did; for the latter, in his self-imposed seclusion, was becoming what Lombroso has recently christened a “mattoid”—a crank on the road to an asylum. Such signs of aberration as he was beginning to manifest the girl’s blithesomeness and beauty banished. She filled the little apartment with laughter, with song, sunshine and life; her winsomeness and beguiling ways awoke and entranced the old man, and in considering her future and its possibilities, the hour came in which he caught himself thinking of the advantages which would accrue if no heir of Humphery Anderson should appear.

That idea once in his head, declined to be dislodged. It was only an hypothesis, it is true; but an hypothesis that became a hope, and in that hope, little by little, the form of his timidity altered; he ceased to fear that the heir might not appear; he began to fear that he would; and abruptly the advertisements ceased.

At the expiration of nine years the old clerk commenced to regard the money as his own. There were little surprises that he planned—the purchase of a country home, trips with Jenny abroad. But the very first time that he counted the banknotes with the idea of appropriating a portion of them, they fell from his hand; he trembled from head to foot, and mentally he denounced himself as a thief. It may be that that same scrupulousness would forever have inhibited him from touching a penny of that trust, had he not discovered that Jenny was head over heels in love with a young artist to whom she had not addressed a single word. The discovery put an end to his hesitations. He made inquiries concerning Hugh, of which the result has been already conveyed; and, half in sorrow, half in joy, determined to give him Jenny, and the money, too.

It was these things that returned to him when the little man exclaimed:

“Well, sir, what am I to learn to my advantage?”

As he spoke, his eyes had the glitter of gems, and he tugged at his beard ferociously.

“I am Humphery Anderson’s next of kin, and in advertising for me I suppose it is because you had property of his in your possession.”

Mr. Sisseton hesitated. He thought of Jenny, of the happiness he had promised and of what must now ensue; but, to save the nation, he could not help being honest.

“Yes, sir,” he answered, dejectedly.

“Ha! ha!” laughed the little man. “I thought so. “Well, fire ahead, I’m listening.”

“It is for you to go on,” I think. “What relation are you to Humphery Anderson?”

At this question the little man turned the color of brick; for a second he lowered his eyes, but immediately he recovered his customary aplomb.

“Thundering guns! why, I am his brother, his last surviving relative!”

“How is it, then, that for ten years you have given no sign of existence?”

“For the best reason in the world—I have not been here. I have been in Mongolia, in Africa, in Peru; anywhere and everywhere except in the States. It is only six weeks ago that I landed. Even then I did not know of my brother’s death. I learned it only this moment.”

“How?”

“Through your advertisement, of course.”

“But I haven’t inserted one for over three years.”

“Then all I can say is that the paper in which I read it was over three years old and not very big for its age. But that is a side issue; how much did he leave?”

“Have you no idea?”

“H’m, let me see. My brother and I were owners of an Arizona claim. We sold out on the 15th of May, 1880. If he died on the 10th of June of that year he must have had somewhere between eighty and ninety thousand concealed on his person.”

“What became of you?”

“We parted at Tucson. I went to San Francisco, where I took ship for Hong Kong, without, of course, suspecting that Humphery was to turn in his chips in Boston.”

“Why do you speak of Boston?”

“It was there he intended to go.”

“Mr. Anderson, I must admit that your answers coincide with the papers in my possession. At the same time I must exact some tangible evidence of your identity.”

“Thundering guns!” the little man shouted, “so you shall. There,” he continued, drawing from his pocket a wallet similar to the one with which Mr. Sisseton had been intrusted. “Here is a Cuban passport, and here are two of Humphery’s letters. Do you know his writing?”

The old clerk glanced at the letters. They began “My dear Brother,” and were signed Humphery Anderson. The handwriting was identical with that on the memoranda. Incontestibly the heir had appeared.

“You have established your identity without a doubt,” he replied. “There remains to me now but one thing to do, and that is—”

“To fork over.”

“To tell you how your brother died—”

“What’s the use? I don’t care a rap. Whether it was paresis or the grip, what difference does it make? He’s dead, isn’t he? Well, that’s the end of it.”

“But,” protested Mr. Sisseton, a trifle scandalized at this manifestation of fraternal indifference. “I must explain how the money came in my possession.”

“All right, but cut it short.”

“He died in my arms,” said Mr. Sisseton, very gravely. “He was killed in a railway accident.”

“The deuce you say. Thundering guns! I thought you were going to tell me he was lynched. Though he was my brother, I am free to admit he was a confounded bad lot.”

“And now,” the old clerk continued, “I will give you what he intrusted to me.”

Therewith he handed out the roll of bills, which the heir carefully counted.

“Eighty-seven thousand!” he exclaimed. “In six months I’m a millionaire. As for you, I won’t insult you with any recompense, particularly as the interest would satisfy anyone.”

“The interest, sir? What do you mean by that? Those bills are the very same ones I received from your brother.”

“And you want me to believe that you kept them all this time in a cubby-hole! Stuff and nonsense!”

“Sir,” Mr. Sisseton, with great dignity, retorted, “Sir, you forget there was nothing to prevent me from keeping them always.”

“By George, that’s true enough! Here, help yourself.”

“I will take one of them, for you owe it me. It’s a trifle less than the amount I paid for advertising. But not another penny.”

“You won’t?”

No, sir, not a cent.”

In unfeigned astonishment the little man stared at his brother’s executor.

“You are an honest man,” he cried; “no, but hang me if you are not. I won’t forget you. I am going now to take a hack at the Street before the Board closes; but I won’t forget you, mind that.”

Followed by Mr. Sisseton, he opened the door and passed into the other room. Near the window Hugh and Jenny stood locked in each other’s arms. The little man turned and smiled.

“Makes one feel twenty years younger, doesn’t it?”

Already the lovers had separated. Hugh was scowling and the girl’s fair face was wet with tears.

“Mr. Hyrtl,” the old clerk began, “didn’t I tell you that everything was at an end. Didn’t—”

John Anderson, who had been tugging at his beard and grinning like a Cheshire cat, suddenly sprang back as though he trod on a serpent, his entire expression changed, and he grabbed Mr. Sisseton by the arm.

“What did you call that young man? Here,” he cried at Hugh, “is your name Hyrtl?”

“Certainly,” Hugh answered.

“Were you born near Richmond? Was your father a sailor? Was he lost at sea? Why don’t you answer? Thundering guns! are you dumb?”

“Not a bit; but I don’t understand your interest in my private affairs, nor yet your acquaintance with them. However, as I have no cause to make a mystery of my antecedents; I may say that I was born near Richmond, and that my father was lost at sea.”

“Torpedoes and dynamite! And whatever became of your mother? Did she—didn’t she—I mean—I mean what became of her?”

“She is dead,” Hugh answered. “Did you know her?”

“I? I never saw her in my life.”

“Well, then, what do you mean by—”

“What do I mean? What do I mean? I don’t know what I mean. I mean that in my travels I met a man named Hyrtl, and the name was so odd I never forgot it. That’s what I mean and nothing else, except that it’s infernally hot in here and I’m in a hurry.”

“No one is detaining you,” murmured Mr. Sisseton.

“I know that; but—but—see here, young man,” he continued, drawing from his pocket the roll of bills; “I have come into some money to-day that I didn’t expect, and, as you are going to be married, if three or four thousand are of any use to you, here they are.”

Hugh looked him from head to foot.

“Why do you make this offer?”

“Because I am your friend.”

“I have seen you but twice in my life.”

“Because I knew your father, then; because you did me a kindness; because—because—oh! hang it all, because I want to.”

“Thanks,” Hugh answered. “I am too poor to borrow and too proud to accept a gift. But I wish you would tell me why you spoke of my mother.”

“Will you take three or four thousand? Will you take five?”

“I will not.”

“Good-by, then; I’m off to my broker.”

With a bound, the little man shot through the door and disappeared as he had come—like the wind—leaving behind him the ruins of a castle in Spain and three people buried beneath them.

Mr. Sisseton was ashen; Jenny pale as a ghost re-arisen; Hugh alone a trifle flushed.

“That man,” he declared, “knew my people, I am convinced.”

“Perhaps so,” Mr. Sisseton muttered; “he appears to have been a great traveler.”

Then at once, without preamble, he told the whole story. Hugh and Jenny listened without interruption. The preceding incidents had made it all quite clear, and when the tale was ended, there was silence in that little room.

Hugh was the first to speak.

“How shall it matter after all? You have returned the money; it was your duty to do so, no one expected you to do anything else, and I am sure you must be convinced that had Jenny and I been married, and the money in our possession, we would have returned it as you have done.”

“I am sure of it,” Mr. Sisseton answered. “I know you to be honest as the day, and I wish, even now, you could be, as I had hoped, my son-in-law.”

“But I shall be.”

“You won’t,” the old man answered, and in his withered face and sunken eyes there was the obstinacy of a mule. “What I have said I have said. Jenny shall not marry a poor man. Would you take her into that rathole of yours and watch privation, sickness, fever and death visit her one by one. No, sir, not while I am alive.”

“If that be the case,” Hugh in fine fury retorted, “what did you come into my rathole for at all?”

“Because Jenny was in love with you.”

“And do you suppose she is going to stop now?”

“I don’t know, but you sha’n’t have her. You are poor and so is she.”

“But if love and matrimony were only permitted to the rich the earth would crumble.”

“Let her crumble. You sha’n’t have my daughter. She is as like her mother as two peas. I won’t have her die of want. You sha’n’t have her, I say.”

“But consider the difference. You were a clerk in a grocery-shop. However hard you may have worked, you couldn’t earn a dollar more than your salary. Whereas I am a painter, and my brush will bring me both fortune and fame.”

“I hope it may, but by that time Jenny will be gray-headed. No, sir, you sha’n’t have her.”

“I shall.”

“You shall not.”

“Mr. Sisseton, remember this: you can’t help yourself. Your daughter is of age, the law prevents you from interfering.”

“It does, does it? Well, what’s sauce for the goose is sauce for the gander. The law makes this my castle, and I order you hence. Begone!”

“Mr. Sisseton—”

“Begone, I say!”

“Very good, sir, I will go since you command it, but I will return with a summons. Jenny, my love, my chosen, but not mine, be brave.”

And therewith this hot-headed young fellow, his head erect, stalked from the room.

VI

IN high indignation at the old man’s mulish obstinacy Hugh strode out into the street and on and beyond into other regions of the city. He was vastly annoyed, and his annoyance was increased by the fact that he had permitted it to be apparent. He should have been calm, he told himself, calm, though authoritative, and he should have displayed, with cogent reasonings, the folly of supposing that at the tail-end of the nineteenth century a young woman could be sequestrated and kept apart from her lover. It was that he should have made manifest, and with it his ability to provide not only for Jenny, but for her father, her grandfather—for as many Sissetons as could be produced. And instead of that, instead of showing the slightest tact, the merest spark of common sense, he had threatened the old man with a summons and made him an enemy for life. There was now but one course left for him to pursue: to apologize as abjectly as he knew how, and that failing, to elope with Jenny on the spot. That she would go with him he did not doubt for an instant, and already he saw himself, another Lochinvar, bearing off the girl of his heart in a green car to the nearest parsonage available.

In dreams forecast he turned and retraced his steps. He would have it out with the old man at once, he determined; and on reaching Tompkins Square he marched straight up stairs and knocked, gently and deferentially at the Sisseton door. Save the beating of his own heart there was not a sound to be heard. He knocked again, a trifle more resolutely, yet still there was no reply. He peered through the keyhole. Not a glimmer of light was to be seen.

“It is I,” he called—“Hugh Hyrtl. Won’t you let me in, Mr. Sisseton? I am sorry for the way I spoke.”

But there was no answer to his appeal. Again he knocked, loudly, boisterously, calling to Jenny, calling to her father and calling in vain. From the floor below a voice mounted bidding him cease that racket. He tried the door; it was locked.

“You must let me in,” he insisted. “I shall stay here until you do.”

Again the protest mounted, with it the fall of a step that he knew, and Mrs. O’Hassadam, a broom in one hand, a candle in the other suddenly appeared.

“My! my!” that lady exclaimed, “if I didn’t think it was the police. They’re after him anyway, and good riddance it is.”

“After whom?”

“The ex-convict, to be sure; who would they be after? He was off like that! But they’re on his track, he can’t have got far at all whatever, he and his blooming daughter. It was wrong you were, Mr. Hyrtl, to consort with the likes of them.”

“What on earth do you mean?”

“What do I mean, Mr. Hyrtl? Indeed, and I mean what I say. An hour ago that old forger came downstairs dragging a trunk and his daughter after him. ‘I am going on a trip,’ said he, handing me his key. ‘To Sing Sing, I’ll wager,’ said I to myself. ‘I don’t know when I’ll be back,’ he continued. ‘Come, Jenny’; and, would you believe that though she was crying her eyes out, she tried to say something to me on the quiet like? But he grabbed her and whisked her off. At the rate he went it will take the cavalry to catch him. It’s a murder case, sure, Mr. Hyrtl, and a fine reputation whatever it will give to this house.”

“Gone,” Hugh murmured, dejectedly, “it can’t be possible.”

“Here is the key,” cried the janitress, triumphantly. “And if you were to unlock that door the Lord deliver us from the horrors you would find.”

With that statement for prelude, Mrs. O’Hassadam launched forth into voluble digressions and extravagant conjectures; but Hugh was not to be detained, he had no heart to listen further, and dumbly perplexed, he turned and sought his room.

For a fortnight thereafter Hugh ransacked the city, wandering like a lost dog through mazes of streets, interrogating windows, questioning lodging-house keepers, always on the alert and always disappointed. At the end of that period he learned that a second-hand furniture dealer had come, exhibited a bill of sale and carted off the Sisseton belongings. Where to? Ah! that Mrs. O’Hassadam did not know, but she took evident pleasure in losing herself in the wildest surmises.

Thereupon the Odyssey recommenced. The appalling ugliness of the suburbs, the terrors of Long Island, New Jersey wastes, one and all were visited and visited in vain. He had not a clew to work on and not a trace of the missing was to be had. Presently fatigue and disappointment had their way; a low fever overtook him and for a month he lay in bed. Mrs. O’Hassadam had a physician in for him, but Hugh was strong and young, and in spite of the physician the fever departed and the convslescent, very feeble but with clearer mind, rose to his feet. If Jenny had cared for him, he decided, at least she would have sent him a line.

Thereat he got at his easel again and painted with a grim energy which he had never displayed before. Work has the ability to dull the most ardent sorrow, and in that which Hugh undertook, though happiness had fallen by the wayside, art stood revealed. Moreover, chanced favored him. Being indifferent to both fame and fortune, he was necessarily the person whom fame and fortune elected to pursue. A dealer who heretofore had purchased his wares at prices that would have made a mad-dog blush, suddenly increased them. Not only that, he admitted that Hugh’s signature was beginning to acquire an appreciable commercial value, and as a commission for someone whose name he was not at liberty to mention, he took “Heliogabalus” in exchange for two thousand dollars in cash

Hugh paid the debts he had contracted during his illness and set to work harder than before. He could have taken a studio now in a pleasanter part of the city, or he could have set off on that tour through the ghosts and treasures of Italy of which every artist dreams. But invisible threads detained him, and he remained where he was, consuming his heart with regrets and his strength with fatigue.

Summer passed, the Autumn came, and with it an unstillable longing to get away—to be somewhere where there was youth and companionship, where there were smiles and flowers, the welcome of eyes and fields. His solitude was distressing to him. Week in, week out there was not a soul with whom he could exchange a word. He had not a friend, not a relative even, and his sweetheart he had lost. Wherever he looked was the desert, and in his heart was a blank despair. Had his mother been living, how quickly he would have gone to her. But she was dead, and he could no longer run to her side, as had been his wont, with the troubles of childhood’s years. He was alone, without a tie, a hope or an aim.

At the thought of his mother he recalled the hour when his dearest wish had been to erect a monument on her grave. He had money in plenty to do so now. Though he were forsaken by the living, why should be forsake the dead? The next day he arrived at Richmond, and by evening he was before the cottage which he loved.

Apparently nothing had happened to it. It had contented itself with continuing to be, and in the increasing darkness rose white and solitary as before. Hugh unlocked the door and entered. The shutters, he noticed, had disappeared, the broken windows were curtained with cobwebs, there was an odor and silence of the tomb, but practically it had weathered the years unchanged. Noiselessly, as though in fear of disturbing phantoms, he passed through the little hall to the kitchen beyond. It was chill and damp, but through the window the spire of the village church was just discernible, and nearby was a grave that he knew. For a minute, an hour perhaps, he loitered there, the guest of memories that came one by one and claimed him as their own—the sport he had had with Dinah and his mother’s tender care; episodes long forgotten returned to him, but in that curious fashion that episodes will at times assume, as though they had occurred not to him, but to some Hugh Hyrtl who had existed in an anterior life, one in which he personally had had no part and of which only a hearsay recollection endured. There, for instance, was his mother’s sudden illness and unexpected death. Try as he might, he could not reconstruct that scene. In the dimmest manner only he recalled that one day a cry was said to have rung through the cottage and that Dinah had found his mother fainting on the floor. But what had happened he had never known. The cause was obscure.

From these meditations a gust of wind aroused him. He shivered and turned. In a corner were a few pieces of wood, and with some stray papers in his pocket he determined to make a fire. But the task was not easy; a mass of ashes that for years had rested undisturbed filled the stove. In endeavoring to remove them, he struck a hard object, which, on examination, proved to be a key, curiously formed, long and narrow, that he could have sworn he had seen before. But where? In that anterior existence, perhaps, from which certain recollections come; and he was about to put it aside and continue his work, when abruptly, from the very core of memory, a picture floated—his mother standing at a table locking and unlocking a certain box. That box, he remembered, always stood on a shelf in her room; and at last, the ashes removed, he groped up the creaking stair to see if the box might be there still. The match he held went out. He lighted another and opened the door. On the shelf the box stood covered with immemorial dust. He raised it; it was so light he was sure there was nothing in it. Nevertheless he took it back to the kitchen and inserted and turned the key. Within, a letter lay, discolored and yellow. By the uncertain flicker of the fire, Hugh read from it as follows:

TUCSON, ARIZONA, 15th May, 1880.

MADAM—Although I am a stranger to you, I believe it to be my duty to place you in possession of certain information which otherwise you might never obtain.

Nine years ago it was reported that your husband, Humphery Hyrtl, was lost at sea. That report was false. When the ship which he commanded sank, I was with him. Of all on board he and I alone escaped. We were picked up by a passing vessel and taken to South America. On the boat he declared that he was my brother, and, on reaching Rio, caused it to be recorded at the United States Consulate that Humphery Hyrtl and his ship were lost. It did not take me long to discover that he had left in Virginia a wife and child, to whom, for reasons of his own, he did not wish to return. I became so indignant at his conduct that he finally promised to go back to you as soon as he had made enough to live on. Since then we have worked together, sometimes lucky, often the reverse. To-day our partnership is dissolved. His share amounts to ninety thousand dollars, and with it he should return to you; but, as he has told me to address his letters to Boston, I presume that it is his intention to dissipate the money which should rightfully go to your support and that of your son.”

I inform you of these facts in order that you may take such steps as seem advisable. He is to leave here to-morrow, and after making a short stop in St. Louis and in Chicago, should be in your neighborhood sometime during the first or second week of the coming month. If he does not appear, you will, by making inquiries concerning him, under his assumed name of Humphery Anderson, surely find him in Boston.

Yours truly,

JOHN ANDERSON.

When Hugh had read the letter, for the first time he understood the cause of his mother’s death. The knowledge that the man whom she had loved and mourned was not only alive, but preferred life under an assumed name to life with her, had broken her heart. Truly, he reflected, it was sufficient: the cup was full. And as he mused over the terrible tidings that the letter contained, he saw at once that it was his father who had been killed in the collision, that the money which had been intrusted to Sisseton was the money to which the letter referred; the remarkable chain of circumstances which had permitted John Anderson to represent himself as the brother of the deceased were clear to him and the unaccountable excitement which the little man had manifested when the name of Hyrtl was pronounced easily understood.

“The money was mine,” muttered Hugh. “He knew it, and, by heavens, I will make him disgorge!”

He passed out through the empty hall to the road beyond.

“Ah, Jenny,” he cried, to the stars, “let me but find you now and you shall be rich, indeed!”

VII

A DAY or two later, when Hugh awoke in his room in Tompkins Square it was with that sense of satisfaction which comes to a man who has done his duty. He had left orders in Richmond that a suitable monument be placed on his mother’s grave, and he had contracted to have the cottage refurnished and rebuilt, for it was there the coming honeymoon was to be passed.

The party essential to the proper passing of that honeymoon was indeed intangible and remote, but what difficulties shall impede a lover armed with courage and mailed in hope? He had absolutely nothing at all to do but to unearth John Anderson, and that accomplished, to find Jenny, and behold!—happiness, lifelong and uninterruptable, would crouch, a spaniel, at his feet.

The unearthing of such a person as John Anderson seemed to Hugh the easiest thing in the world. In the Stock Exchange and its purlieus an individual of such marked peculiarities must by this time have become well known. With Jenny it was different; but though that ruffian of a father of hers had hid her in the depths of a Japanese jungle or immured her behind convent walls, he would find and recover her yet. She should be his; she had promised it, and what shall separate those that love?

These anticipations were interrupted by a rap at the door. At the moment Hugh, in preparation of a visit to Wall Street, was meditatively brushing his hat, but at the rap he put the hat down and went to the door and opened it. There in the corridor’s dim penumbra was John Anderson in person.

Speechless with astonishment, Hugh started back.

“You!”

“Yes, dear boy,” the little man answered. “Whom did you expect? May I come in?”

With that he seized Hugh’s unresisting hand, and entering the room, straddled a chair.

“You’re well, I hope. So much the better. Thundering guns! but I am delighted to hear it.”

“How kind of you!”

“But I am delighted,” the little man insisted, for there was an irony in Hugh’s voice that would hardly have escaped a deaf-mute. “I am delighted, I assure you. Between ourselves, I was a trifle uneasy this morning when I set out for Tompkins Square.”

“And why so?”

“In the first place, because I have neglected you; it must be four months since I was here. Then, too, I have something on my conscience.”

“Ah?”

“Yes, my conscience may be elastic, but it is not gangrened. Hugh, dear boy, I haven’t acted right; no, thundering guns! I’ll be hanged if I have.”

Hugh nodded encouragingly. If he is going to own up, he reflected, I haven’t the heart to be angry.

“Go on,” he said, gently.

The little man pulled at his beard and tormented an ear.

“It’s hard work; if I had my choice I’d rather run for election, I give you my word I would.”

“Don’t, then.” And Hugh smiled benignly. “I know all.”

The little man jumped from his seat.

“Thundering guns!”

“It is about my eighty-seven thousand dollars, isn’t it?”

“ ‘Your’ eighty-seven—Fire and brimstone! You do know all. But how? Who on earth could have told you a thing that no one knew about save myself.”

“It was the one person who knew that told. It was you, Mr. Anderson, that told me. It was you yourself.”

“Torpedoes and dynamite! You’re a mind-reader, chiromancer and telepathist rolled into one.”

“No, nothing of that sort. Look at this.”

And Hugh displayed the letter which he had found in his Virginia home. The little man glanced at it and blushed.

“But four months ago, when I took that money—”

“My money.”

“Yes, your money, I admit. When I took it I can swear you hadn’t seen this letter then.”

“No, I had not,” Hugh answered, and thereupon related the circumstances connected with the finding of the key.

“This is fatality,” said the little man, with a solemn air. “In the long run everything comes out. And to think what a figure I should have cut if I had not been the first to speak!”

“There! It is not the money I regretted the most.”

“I know—I know, and that’s the worst of it. I made inquiries and learned what happened. If it were not for me you would have been married long since.”

“Oh, as to that,” said Hugh, gayly, “everything will go right enough now.”

“What a philosopher you are!” the little man, in manifest surprise, exclaimed. “A fellow annexes your property, prevents your marriage, and, instead of sand bagging him, you treat him as pleasantly as though he had done you a favor.”

At this speech Hugh laughed triumphantly. “I can promise you,” he said, “that if this morning I had run across you unexpectedly I might have taken the law into my own hands. But since of your own free will you come to make restitution. I—”

“Restitution! Thundering guns! we don’t understand each other at all.”

“We don’t?” cried Hugh, whom the wantonness of this reply had roused to sudden fury; “we don’t, eh? And do you mean to tell me—”

“Mean? I mean nothing. Thundering guns! haven’t you taken a look at me yet? Have I the air of a man who has come to restore eighty-seven thousand dollars, let alone ten cents? Why I haven’t a penny in the world. Look at these rags, look at my shoes; did you ever see such shoes? As for my shirt—”

The little man opened his tattered coat. His breast was bare.

Hugh sank into a chair and covered his face with his hands. The blow was too cruel.

“I don’t know,” the little man continued, when he saw that the pantomime had had its effect. “I don’t know how it all happened. For everyone this has been a bad year. It began on Friday, do you remember? and what it would have been if it begun on a thirteenth God only knows, and when I say God only I exaggerate. I started by making loads of money; I had enough to burn—it was a nuisance to me. Thundering guns! how I did bellow with the bulls, and suddenly it was the bears that caught me. Everything went, everything, everything. They didn’t even leave me my shirt.”

“My poor Jenny,” moaned Hugh. “My poor, dear Jenny.”

“Yes, indeed,” muttered the little man, with a vicious tug at his beard. “It’s that I should have foreseen. With the money I annexed you could have been happy and prosperous and made yourself a name, whereas now, oh, hang it all! it’s too tough. Why was I ever born? Why don’t you kick me? Why don’t you shoot me? Why don’t you send for the police?”

Hugh raised his eyes; there was a pathos in them, a sorrow for his lost love so great, so manifest, so abiding that John Anderson lowered his own.

“See here,” he added, after a moment, “see here; there’s no use taking on like that. I am down on my luck to-day, I admit, but to-morrow! Why, you have no idea of the inscrutable possibilities that the future contains. I’ll be on my feet again, I’ll be a millionaire yet. We’ll all be millionaires. Say the word and I’ll draw you a note, at sixty days, for a hundred thousand dollars.”

“It is enough that you have robbed me,” gnashed Hugh, re-overtaken by fury. “There is no need to insult me as well.”

“Insult you!” protested the little man. “Insult you, dear boy! Why I give you my word of honor—”

“Honor!” cried Hugh, a phrase from Dickens returning to him. “Honor, indeed! Bah! Give me something to take the taste out of my mouth.”

“I’ll swear by what you like, then,” the little man, in no wise disconcerted, replied. “I’ll swear that my dearest wish is to see you famous and happy.”

“And you have gone about it the right way, haven’t you?”

“No, you are right there, I haven’t. But just consider the circumstances. Before I knew of your existence the banknotes were in my pocket. Besides, if it hadn’t been for me your father never would have had them; as it was they kept crying to me—‘Carry us off, double us, triple us, quintuple us, repay later, but carry us off now.’ That’s what they kept crying to me, and, thundering guns! I was weak enough to obey. But as I said before, send for the police. State’s prison is too good for me; I ought to be hanged and have my ghost kicked.”

Hugh gave him a look that enveloped him from head to heel.

“I have but one request to make,” he said, measuredly; “and that is that you will go.”

At this, the little man got up and hobbled to the door. There, for a moment, he halted and tormented his beard; then, looking over his shoulder at Hugh, who had turned to the window where he had caught the first glimpse of Jenny’s face, he coughed. Hugh affected not to hear him.

“Mr. Hyrtl!”

Hugh still kept his back turned. The little man made a step toward him.

“Mr. Hyrtl, before I go let me tell you this; it may be a consolation to you. I am in more desperate straits than the day I met you. I had hope then; I have none left now. I am starving, and, as I cannot beg, I am going to throw myself into the river. Good-by.”

Hugh fumbled in his pocket, and, turning from the window, crossed the room. “Here, take that,” he said. “I give it to you because of the one good action of your life—in memory of my mother, whom you tried to aid.”

With that, he went back to the window, and the little man, his eyes very red and wet, opened the door and disappeared.

VIII

THE day passed somehow, the morrow as well; a week took flight, during which Hugh sat in his room, inert and listless, issuing, like a wolf from his den, only when hunger compelled.

On such occasions hunger seemed to vanish when food appeared; he had appetite for nothing; he had lost even zest in life. Another might have betaken himself to the caresses of that yellow fay who lurks in certain bottles; but to Hugh even that palliative was denied; he could not drink; it may be that he was too refined.

He could not work, either; he could not read. With that immobility noticeable in certain forms of dementia, he gazed at the untenanted window opposite hour after hour, until night loosed her draperies and the window was hid. At such times his mind was empty—inhabited, if at all, by spectral shadows, the phantoms of regret. Among our friends and acquaintances are always those who, to our knowledge, have sorrows of their own. But there are others that evolve a world, one that glows, subsides and dies away, unknown to any save themselves. The solitudes of space appall, the solitudes of the heart can be as endless as they. In those which Hugh concealed a universe had had its being and its subsistence—a universe with gem-like hopes for stars, one in which the sun had been so eager it had cast its rainbows in his eyes. But now it was all dispersed; there was nothing left—a desire merely, which, dumb at first, little by little had become articulate—a longing for the grave. Like many another young man who has suddenly found himself balked, Hugh had determined to take his life.

It was preoccupations of this description that a visitor one day interrupted. Hugh had not heard anyone enter, and was made aware of another’s presence only by the sound of his own name. He started with that spring a cat gives when suddenly aroused. Before him stood the picture-dealer who had taken Heliogabalus away. He was a man of noticeable gentility, a man with an acquired smile, a brilliant hat, fabulous trousers and a pea-green stick. At the moment he was diligently smoking a huge cigar.

“Nothing new, eh?” he inquired, with a glance at the empty easel.

Hugh shook his head.

“I have a commission for you,” he continued. “What’s the matter? You look out of sorts.”

To this Hugh made no reply.

“There’s a gentleman who has purchased an elegant house in Irving place; and he wants a high-toned artist to decorate it—he wants it done in first-rate style, and damn the expense. I told him of you, and he says you are to begin at once. His name is—h’m, what is his name? Thurlire, or something like that. However, I’ve got it written down. What do you say?”

“I say he can go to the devil.”

In amazement at this rebuff the dealer dropped the ashes from his cigar all over himself and flushed mightily.

“If that’s the message you expect one gentleman to take to another gentleman I guess you may—”

What in circumstances of that nature he thought Hugh might do will never be known to history. In a rich rustle of vocables and skirt, Mrs. O’Hassadam appeared at the open door, a letter in her hand, which, she announced, with much emphasis and a look of unmollifiable suspicion at the dealer, was for Mr. Hyrtl and for no one else whatever.

Hugh grasped the letter as the man in the legend grasped the straw. It was from Jenny, he was sure. But the handwriting was not of a maidenly description. It was in the bold, free hand of a clerk, and it intimated very tersely that the writer would be obliged for a check in payment of the monument which he had erected on Mrs. Hyrtl’s grave.

“And I haven’t a dollar,” mused Hugh. “One thing is certain: I can’t kill myself until that debt is paid.”

“Is that your answer?” asked the dealer, savagely.

Hugh blinked with the tremor of a somnambulist awaking from a trance. He had been so far away that he had forgot everything, even to the dealer’s presence.

“My answer? My answer to what? Oh, yes, about your friend’s house. Very good, I’ll do it.”

“Now that’s the talk I like. When will you begin? To-day? Good enough. Here’s the name and address. Do it up elegant, won’t you? So long.” And with that the dealer took his cigar and pea-green stick away.

Two hours later Hugh was at the house in Irving place. A man-servant opened the door, and on learning Hugh’s mission, laughed riotously.

“It’s a good one, isn’t it?” he roared.

And as Hugh only stared, dumbly perplexed, the servant suddenly subsided, and murmured, sepulchrally:

“I beg pardon, sir; I thought as how you were in it!”

“In what, you confounded idiot? Hang your impudence, what do you mean by laughing in my face? If you don’t know your place, your master shall teach you. Where is he?”

The muscles of the man’s face twitched, but he controlled the coming grin by a tight pressure of the lips.

“I beg pardon, sir,” he answered. “He isn’t here yet. I thought you knew he is to be married. If you will step this way, sir.” And fearing perhaps to explode, he drew a portiere aside and Hugh passed into the drawing-room.

It was large, high ceiled and furnished in very fair taste. Beyond, another room extended, before which curtains fell. The air was sweet with flowers, and presently, though dusk was approaching, and the light, as is usual in old New York houses, was not plentiful, Hugh perceived that he was not alone. The curtains had parted, and a lady was entering the room. She took a step or two in Hugh’s direction, apparently unconscious of his presence, and then, with a little bleat of surprise, she ran to where he stood.

“Hugh!”

The young man tottered like a drunkard.

“You, Jenny!” he exclaimed, in fine fervor. “Tell me I am not dreaming; tell me it is you.”

His answer was two arms thrown about his neck, two lips on his own, the murmur and gurgle of love and joy.

“Here! here! You’ve no right to do that.”

The curtains had parted again, and on the threshold of the room beyond an old man stood, very cross and disagreeable.

“Stop it, I say!”

And Hugh, more intoxicated than if he had drunk a dozen pints of champagne, looked from Jenny’s blue and sultry eyes into the glowering face of her father.

“Ah! I understand,” he exclaimed—“I understand all now. Thank you, dear Mr. Sisseton; thank you a million times.”

“You!” shrieked the old man. “You! What in the name of a wilderness of gorillas are you doing here?”

“Embracing your daughter.”

“Your conduct is infamous, sir. You lure me here by trick and pretense, and insult me to my face. Stand back, I say.”

“I lure you here? I? Why I didn’t know where you were. I would have given twenty years of my life to find you.”

“Oh, oh!” pouted Jenny. “What about my letters?”

“Letters? I haven’t had one,” answered Hugh, in a crescendo of bewilderment.

“I sent you a dozen at least, and you never took the trouble to answer one of them.”

“Twenty,” snapped the old man. “I have them all in my pocket.”

“Papa, papa!” sobbed the girl, “how could you be so cruel.”

“It must be evident to you,” said Hugh, persuasively, “it must be quite evident to you now, my dear Mr. Sisseton, that I was not the means of bringing you here.”

“Well, then, what in thunder did you come for?”

“Simply to fresco the walls.”

“As I did,” interjected Jenny, “in the hope of securing a position as type-writer.”

“What luck!” the old man growled.

“Luck!” Hugh cried, “It’s the hand of Providence that has led me to you, my dear, dear friend.”

“I forbid you to so address me, sir,” the old man fairly yelped. “You are insane, that’s what you are.”

“Haven’t I had enough to make me?”

“Tell me this, sir—do you still love my daughter?”

“With all my heart.”

“Will you agree not to ask her to marry you?”

“Never in the world.”

“In that case everything between us is at an end. Go to the devil.”

“But—”

“You sha’n’t have my daughter, that’s flat.”

“But—”

“You sha’n’t have my daughter—you sha’n’t have my daughter—you sha’n’t have my daughter—”

“Don’t be so sure,” said Hugh, with a great show of bluster. “Your daughter is of age and I’ll appeal to the law.”

“You will, will you? It seems to me you said that before. Come, Jenny, we must go at once.”

“Not yet,” called a shrill voice, and suddenly the room was inundated and entered by the glitter of electric lights, and an individual, superbly tailored and groomed, advanced majestically, his fingers in his waistcoat.

“What are you people quarreling about?” he inquired, haughtily. “Don’t you know how to behave? Thundering guns!”

And to the astonishment of those present John Anderson wheeled an armchair before the fire and began the delicate operation of toasting the veneered soles of a pair of patent-leather shoes.

“Draw up,” he said, “these October dusks are chill. Bring a chair for Miss Sisseton, Hugh; bring a chair for yourself.”

In his manner there was an ease, a serenity and self-sufficiency that was simply diabolic. Hugh stared like an oaf at a mountebank, and Mr. Sisseton, gaping with surprise, stood, his crumbling jaws half-parted.

John Anderson looked from one to the other and smiled at Jenny.

“That lover of yours doesn’t appear very grateful to a man who, in spite of wind and weather, has brought him to your side, does he, Miss Sisseton?”

“You don’t mean—” Hugh began and then hesitated, as though he were talking in a dream.

“Yes, I do,” John Anderson answered, encouragingly. “That’s precisely what I do mean.”

“In that case I forgive you.”

“You do, do you? Thundering guns! are we quits on those eighty-seven thousand dollars?”

“Yes,” said Hugh, with an entire absence of heartiness. “Yes, we are, although—”

“Although they would do you a jolly good service just at present, wouldn’t they? And you, Miss Sisseton,” he continued, turning to that young woman, who had approached the fire, her blue eyes filled with wonderment, “won’t you reward an old man, too?”

“Willingly,” she lisped, as she lowered the purity of her brow, “but the most grateful girl in the world—”

“Only offers what she can spare, and I am satisfied with it,” said the old ruffian between two kisses. “Thank you, my little beauty, I feel twenty years younger.”

“Here, here! You’ve no right to do that,” interposed Mr. Sisseton. “Stop it, I say!”

“Where did you get that jag?” John Anderson, in a tone of great interest, inquired. “Now, see here, pard; you, like myself, are a guest in this house, and it is very bad form of you to kick up a rumpus, dreadful bad form. I am surprised at you—”

“Stuff and nonsense!” growled the father.

“Yes, I am—I am surprised at you. A man of your age, too! But thundering guns! what’s that?”

And John Anderson leaned over and peered into the grate.

“Why, it’s a key,” Jenny exclaimed; “here let me get it.”

But Hugh was already at work, and in a moment he had extracted a key not at all dissimilar to one which he had seen before.

“What in the world was it doing there, I wonder?” John Anderson, with a superb assumption of surprise, remarked. Why, it looks as though it might belong to that box on the table, there. Hugh, suppose you try and see. That box, Hugh, must be like the one from which you disinterred the one good action of my life, isn’t it?”

Hugh nodded. The key fitted perfectly. The box opened without a creak.

“Look and see what’s in it, Miss Sisseton,” the little man continued. “Look and see. A key that falls down the chimney merits attention; it may have been your good fairy that let it fall. Look and see.”

“Here! here!” growled Jenny’s father. “You have no right to do that. What would Mr.—Mr. Whatever-his-name-is say if he saw you?”

“He would say she was doing quite right, partner. Rummage away, Miss Sisseton; rummage away.”

Thus encouraged, Jenny drew out a sheaf of bills.

“Banknotes!” she cried.

“There are eighty-seven of them,” said the little man. “Partner, they are the ones you were to give to your daughter, and, as no better use can be put to them, Mr. Thughlyrh returns them to you. Take them.”

“Take them?” Mr. Sisseton repeated, drawing himself up to his full height. “But what right do you—”

“Take them, I keep telling you; and you, Miss Sisseton, rummage away.”

“Diamonds and pearls!” the girl murmured, in ecstasy.

The little man hummed contentedly:

“ ‘Du hast Diamanten und Perlen,
Du hast—tra la la, tra la laire,
Du ha—hast die schönsten Augen,
Mein Liebling, was willst du noch mehr?’

Go on” he continued, “go on. Those diamonds and pearls are Mr. Thughlyrh’s wedding present to his bride.”

“But tell me, you shall tell me,” barked Mr. Sisseton, the perspiration streaming in the hollows of his cheek, “who is Mr. Thughlyrh? Is he—you, or is he the devil?”

“Neither. Do you wish to see him?”

“Of course, I do.”

“Well, then, the young and attractive Mr. Thughlyrh, who is to marry a beauty; the rich Mr. Thughlyrh, whose guests we are, is—”

“Who?” cried Jenny, while her lover pricked up his ears.

“—Is Hugh Hyrtl.”

“I!”

“Why, of course; I thought you had guessed it before. Thughlyrh is the anagram of your name, and, thundering guns! a hard one it was to make.”

“But the house?” said Hugh, beside himself with excitement.

“Rummage in the box, Miss Sisseton.”

In the box was a brief deed in Hugh’s name—signed, sealed and attested.

“It’s too much,” cried the young fellow, “I can’t accept it.”

John Anderson raised his hand, his face had become grave and serious.

“Dear boy,” he said, “let me, according to my lights, make amends for the past. No doubt I should have have done so sooner, but if I prolonged your sorrow, if I masqueraded in rags in your room, if I pretended to be more indigent than before, it was because I had not yet discovered Miss Sisseton. I wanted to restore her to you when I restored your money. From that test you issued as an angel might. Anyone else would have killed me; you gave me alms. Be generous to the end, Hugh. Don’t refuse what I am well able to give. Don’t leave me to my remorse.”

“So be it,” Hugh answered. “I accept the house on condition I may return it the next time you go broke.”

“Don’t count on that. I am forever cured of speculation. Hereafter I shall live on my income, and play whist with my partner here.”

“But for the love of heaven,” the old clerk implored, “tell me what all this means.”

“It means,” said the little man, rising as he spoke from his seat. “It means that I have encountered two things that I have never encountered before.”

“What are they?”

“Charity and forgiveness,” John Anderson answered, taking Hugh by one hand; “and absolute honesty,” he continued, stretching the other to Jenny’s papa.

“And now, dear lady and sweet sirs,” he added, with a large, old-fashioned bow, “do me the favor to step into the other room; a little feast has been prepared, the feast of betrothal, and from the wall where he laughs and lounges let Heliogabalus shower as many flowers as he may. There, do you hear the corks popping? Thundering guns! I shall drink deep to-night.”

CURTAIN.

When Baby was sick, we gave her Castoria.
When she was a Child, she cried for Castoria.
When she became Miss, she clung to Castoria.
When she had Children, she gave them Castoria.

The Falsehood Shop

The servant, opening the door, announced: “Miss Egon.”

I had not quite expected that. A moment previous I had been a thousand years away, among the young empresses of Byzance, whose brilliant lives I was trying and, what is worse for them, was succeeding in etching in dull prose. But, as the girl entered, the dead vanished, exorcised by the living, and I sprang forward to greet her.

“Where is Herbert, do you know?” she agitatedly asked.

To lie to a lady is never nice, yet tell the truth and sometimes it is not only the devil that you shame.

“No,” I answered with affected candor. With an equally assumed appearance of surprise, I added: “Don’t you?”

She stared at me and I at her. In her face was anxiety, uncertainty, constraint, a little panorama of emotions, but most noticeably charm. Ordinarily, not one of all the beauties of Byzance could have been as fair as she. But there were days when she was merely exquisite. This was one of them. She swallowed a sob, sank into a chair and, still looking at me, said, and simply enough: “He is dead.”

Well, yes, in a sense—that is to say, so far as she was concerned—Herbert Brook was dead. But I could not tell her so. I lacked the courage. Even otherwise I lacked the imagination to bury him decently—to bury him, for that matter, at all. In search of cover, I dropped into the vague.

“Nonsense!” I exclaimed. “Why do you say that?”

But, for the moment, I must have overdone it. For the moment, she must have caught, or thought she caught, a note that did not ring quite true, for at once, much as though she suspected that the brute might be somewhere concealed, she looked about, at the bookcases that lined the room, at the windows that gave on the Champs Elysées, at a portrait that hung on the wall—a portrait which displayed me in the resplendent costume of my Heidelberg corps, a great Dane crouching at my boots.

It was ten years ago that the thing was painted. Since then, my historical genuflections have bent me a bit. On the other hand, kneipes and their plenteous beer failing, I am less stout. Otherwise, barring of course the medieval accoutrements, the picture shows me much as I still am, with, moreover, what I shall always retain, the cicatrix of a student duel slashed across my face.

The girl’s eyes turned from the daub to me. Their promenade about the room had occupied but a moment, yet during it, whatever suspicion she may have had must have died. She looked as she had before, exquisite, anxious, constrained.

“Yes,” I reiterated, “why do you say that?”

Then the meager story of it limped forth to me, who knew it all and better, and in particular the key to it, which I was determined she should never get.

Herbert Brook was, confound him, my cousin. Relationship began and ended there. He was alarmingly good-looking and disgustingly rich, while I am but the scarred-faced historian of improbable queens. The role, passably obscure, had prevented me from ever more than tentatively approaching this girl, to whom Herbert had strummed another guitar. It was a way of his, a way which often had aroused in me the sin of envy, to carry everything by storm. But when he met Kate Egon, which he did entirely through my own stupidity, I had no fear of him, and that for the ridiculous reason that he was vehemently in love with a friend of hers, Jenny Price, who, however, as fate would have it, threw him over, whereat, in the rebound, and out of pique perhaps, he made up to Kate.

At the time we were all in New York. As soon as I learned how things were going, I saw that there was nothing for me to do except to be going also. A week later I was in Paris, where, among the Elysian Fields, on the corner of Boetia Street—beautiful and significant names!—I took the apartment which for the present my books and pictures adorn. “Lascia la donna e studia la matematica,” somebody said to someone who happened to be in circumstances such as mine, and it was in an effort to follow that sage advice and forget Kate that I turned, not indeed to mathematics, but to the problematic princesses of the past.

These people diverted me. On one occasion another person did also. This was a neighbor of mine, Madame de Trèfle, a prophetess much frequented by the superselect, whose apartment adjoined my own. A bagatelle of the door favoring, I made her acquaintance, as a result of which a sitting ensued, one that took place in a room furnished in cornflower and silver, filled with costly futilities, and which, like my library, overlooked the Elysian Fields. There, this lady, a tall, dark creature, dressed capriciously in champagne, yet with a face which in repose was strangely noble, looked me graciously over, closed her eyes and, apparently, fell asleep.

“Ah!” she presently exclaimed. “Your home is a city of pineapple cupolas covered with colors, a city in which the people wear painted gauze. But no. I am foolish. That is not your home; it is the home of your thoughts; yet there in the wide, white streets over which chariots roll, always you are looking for someone whom you do not see. No, you do not see her there, but here, in Paris, you will see her soon, and then—”

Madame de Trèfle gave a little convulsive start, opened her eyes, smiled and added: “The fee is fifty francs. You may pay my secretary at the door.”

It was worth it, though of the prophecy part I did not believe a word. In spite of which, or perhaps precisely on that account, the very next day, on the Champs Elysées, I ran into Kate. She and her mother had just come over, and pending Herbert’s arrival, were stopping at a hotel nearby. At tea that afternoon I told them about Madame de Trèfle, or as much, at least, as I judged advisable, and Kate, properly astounded, asked me to take her to her. I promised to do so, but before I could, all of a sudden this thing occurred; or rather and more exactly, one evening, a little later, when I was dressing, abruptly Herbert appeared.

I knew he was looked for that day, but his irruption in my rooms surprised me. By whomsoever else he may have been expected, it was certainly not by me. But I am, I hope, always civil, and, interrupting the tying of my tie to shake hands, I threw out: “Good trip?”

He dodged it, and with laughing eyes threw back: “You remember Jenny Price?”

In the mirror before me I nodded at him.

“She was on the ship. We have made it up.”

I turned on him. “What about Kate?”

Running his long, thin fingers through his thick hair, he gave me a queer little look. “That’s it. You’ll have to explain.”

I had finished with my tie and was putting on my coat, but at the outrageousness of that, I stopped.

“I’ll see you hanged first!”

From a gold case he got out a cigarette, and coolly offered me another. As he did so I looked him over. It is the misfortune of a historian that he is obliged to live the lives of other people, to participate in their vices and virtues—when they have any—and, at the moment, I realized that it is impossible for a man to get himself more into what is vulgarly termed a fix than in becoming engaged to two girls. But I realized also that the penalties for a polite felony of this kind are those which the conscience alone creates, and, as for conscience, I felt that Herbert had about as much as a weasel.

Then immediately I thought of Kate. I could fancy Joy bidding her farewell, Misery offering its arm, I could see her abrupt migration from noon into night. Yet, oddly enough, the picture evoked, instead of inciting me to assault, presented vistas which in some unaccountable manner restrained. I am surely not a hypocrite, and it annoyed me that they should.

At once, with a jerk, I got into my coat, and turning again on the brute, angrily I flung at him:

“It is a surgical operation you are asking me to perform.”

At the charge, his eyes lost none of their laughter. On the contrary, airily he retorted: “Yes, and you are just the chap to know how.”

He had been seated. Now springingly he stood up, looking as he did so quite as though he were dumping on the floor—and on me—any and every care.

At that I could indeed have kicked him. But my servant entered. In a moment Herbert had caught up his hat and gone.

I had planned that evening to dine out and then look in at the Opéra. The mood now for either excursion fell by. I told the servant to fetch whatever was easiest, a bit of chicken, a leaf or two of lettuce; and presently, these things consumed, I sat, an unlighted cigar between my teeth, considering in what manner without anodynes, without narcotics, without mortification morbus setting in, I could safely operate on Kate. Yet from no matter what angle I viewed it, the task of cutting into her the fact that the man of all others was not the man for her, and of cutting it, moreover, without making her wince, resolved itself into a high necromantic feat for which I entirely lacked the art. None the less, it had to be done. But how?

In this dilemma I lost myself until ultimately there surged the gleam of a plan of a falsehood shop, one which I would open and fill with mendacities so spacious and splendid that they would both assuage and console. Only—and here was the hitch—try as I might, I could not conjure one. Had this brute of a cousin of mine not been disgustingly rich, I might have invented some tale of financial turpitudes, though, if I did, any such story would only abase Kate in her self-esteem. Were he not then in Paris, I might have pretended that he had gone suddenly insane, though, if I did, she was just the girl to pack off to him. What then could I do? To open a falsehood shop is all very well, only, to open it profitably, one should be able to stock it, and the shelves of mine were bare. Yet, I told myself, there must be others, and immediately I knew that there were, and very convenient at that, just across the hall, in the apartment of my neighbor, Madame de Trèfle. Thereupon I determined to go to her on the morrow, to ransack her shelves and then to call on Kate.

But before I could, it was Kate who called on me.

Now, as she sat in my library, she told me what little she knew, which, summarily, was to the effect that Herbert had certainly arrived the day before and since then had as certainly disappeared.

“He is dead,” she repeated.

So he was, at least so far as she was concerned, but I had not yet got my wind, and in sparring for it, I again asked why she said that.

The dangers of Paris, she explained, the Apaches, the demon chauffeurs, the tiger bandits, adding that Herbert always had a lot of money with him and concluding with the perhaps natural suggestion that I accompany her to the police.

“I will do better than that,” I replied. “I will take you to Madame de Trèfle.”

She had been looking down and away, but at this she looked up. I could see she was rememorating what I had told her of the prophetess, and I could not but reflect that, coming from anyone but me, the story might have seemed a bit fantastic. But precisely as no grammarian ever wrote a line that was fit to read, so has no historian ever displayed a minimum of imagination. That reassuring fact was in my favor. Her face brightened. She rose to the bait.

Yet at once I realized that, however lacking in imagination I may be, I had been lacking also in forethought. I had neglected to dust the shop, and I asked Kate to be good enough to wait a second while I went and inquired whether Madame de Trèfle were free.

To this Kate assented, and presently I was again in the cornflower and silver salon where the prophetess received. It was a minute or two before she appeared, and meanwhile I looked out on the avenue which, on this high noon, was flooded with sunshine, filled with people, shuttled with fleeting cars.

But now a door was opening. I turned. Madame de Trèfle was before me, and I bowed over her jeweled hand.

“Madame,” I said as I straightened, “I have come to ask a favor. A girl has been thrown over for another. She is unaware of it. She thinks that the brute is dead. Will you let me bring her to you? And when I have, will you tell her—well—whatever you like: that he has tuberculosis, anything gentlemanly and contagious, and that for her own sake she must never see him again.”

As I spoke, I got out my cardcase. “Your usual fee is fifty francs. In this instance permit me to make it a hundred.”

Madamie de Trèfle half raised a finger. “Not for a thousand.”

“But,” I protested, “it is an act of charity that I ask.”

She sniffed at me. “Mistaken charity! Truth should never be withheld from those who are worthy to receive it.”

“No doubt,” I retorted. “But it is not a question of that. The girl could not be worthier. The point is, she isn’t fit.”

“Ta-ta-ta!” Madame de Trèfle, in mounting crescendo, replied. With an uplift of the chin she considered me. Her eyes narrowed. “Bring her here; I will judge of that.”

I did not like it—I did not like it in the least; but there was no way out of it. I went across the hall and brought Kate back.

“My child,” that woman said to her, “seat yourself in the chair here by the window and, for a little, while I am looking at you, I beg of you do not speak.”

I stationed myself behind Kate and for a moment stared out at the avenue. Then I turned to Madame de Trèfle, who was not looking at Kate at all. On the contrary, she was comfortably seated, her eyes closed, and appeared to be asleep. But presently and monotonously she began to speak.

“My dear, you are but recently come to Paris. Before coming you thought yourself interested in a man. But he is not good enough for you. You will not marry him. You will marry a man of mark.”

Whether Kate heard or not, certainly she did not heed. She half turned to me and indicated the window, through which, in the avenue below, suddenly I saw my cousin, seated in a heliotrope car, side by side with Jenny Price, whose hand he was holding and in whose face he was gazing with that cannibal expression which men cannot help displaying when they feel that they could eat the lady up.

There is no mistaking that expression—no one could mistake it; and as a congestion of traffic held the motor there, I saw that Kate had not mistaken it; that in spite of my precautions now, at last, she understood. Would she, I wondered, faint? But I should have known her better than to fancy she could do anything so inane. Besides, had her pride needed a moxa, instantly it was supplied. The traitorous pair, shelled by vibrations from the batteries of our eyes, simultaneously looked up. They saw us, flushed, turned and, the congestion relieved, shot on.

“Yes,” Madame de Trèfle was saying, “you will marry a marked man—a man with a scar.”

At that, with a little convulsive start, she blinked, considered us, then, rising, she smiled and added: “You may pay my secretary at the door.”

But, dear me, it was months and months before I was able to discern from Kate even the possibility that in that falsehood shop was truth. It took Kate longer, but, in the end, God bless her, she discerned it, too.

The Goblin Girl

“There’s Mr. Tams with that creature!”

Nelly Fay bit her bright lip, clenched her small hand, overturned her chair, and, abandoning her mother and the veranda, rushed into the house, not omitting to slam the door.

Beyond, on the road, a motor freighted with youth and beauty had shot like a comet. Mrs. Fay blinked at it. Then, rising, she sneezed and followed her daughter.

Nelly at the moment was staring unseeingly at a tall mirror which showed back her lemon-colored frock, her slim figure, and her face, which even in anger was delicious. It takes a very pretty girl to look appetizing when she is furious, yet in that, and without trying to in the least, she succeeded. She had the loveliest features, amber hair, and eyes big and blue, blue as the sea and bluer.

But now, conscious of her mother’s approach, she turned on her.

“I do wish you wouldn’t wear that ridiculous shawl! It gives me the fidgets!”

The hall, high and wide, gravely furnished, led to the dining room. Nelly, her mother in leash, went on and into this room, where already luncheon was ready, and where Fred, her brother, a good-looking lad in admirably cut clothes, presently followed.

Sarah, a maid, whom Mrs. Fay openly treasured, served them. The midday meal began. Fred ate with quiet ferocity, Mrs. Fay uncomplainingly, Nelly not at all. But she drank. She took a whole glass of water at a gulp.

Fred, eying her, interrupted himself and laughed.

“Did you see Tams and his secretary? A hummer from Hummersville, eh?”

Nelly gave him one look. Immediately, like a beautiful whirlwind, she had gone. Surprisedly, Fred turned to his patient mother.

“I say! What’s wrong now?”

If Mrs. Fay knew, she omitted to tell. As for Nelly, if she had tried, she would have failed. She herself did not know. That she was quivering with anger, she was aware. But as will sometimes happen to angered people, she did not know what she was angry at. The week previous, she had been subjected to a grave affront. The memory of it still rankled. But it was not that. Then what was it?

In her bedroom, to which she had flown, darkly she wondered. Then, precisely as you may have seen in a moving picture, before her stood Tams.

Tams was an inventor. He had discovered a process whereby you could—one of these days—telephone along a shaft of light. He had discovered tamsar, that explosive of which the dynamics exceed the potentialities of trinitrotoluol. He had in process of completion an aëroplane that would serve as a rocking-chair and on which you could fly out of the window. Recently he had been occupied with a theatrical device which Goldburg, the showman, intended to produce in “The Goblin Girl,” a musical comedy that was to delight Broadway.

For the rest, Tams was a virile, resolute man, with eyes that, while blue, were not the blue of the sea or of the sky, but of steel. They were very determined. So, too, was his jaw. He gave the impression of getting what he wanted. At the time when this drama began, he wanted two things, neither of which he ever mentioned. There was the theatrical device. He wanted it to be a go. But first and foremost and over and beyond everything else, he wanted Nellie Fay.

In the Long Island village where, during the summer and the better part of the autumn, the Fays resided, Tams had a bungalow and a workshop. In town he had an office and presumably a clerk. In any event, during the past week he had apparently acquired a secretary, a young woman with whom he motored about and with whom, through the bungalow’s wide-open windows, he was seen at table.

Previously, of an evening, he had looked in on the Fays. Fred liked him, Mrs. Fay liked him, so did Nelly. Moreover, of an afternoon, when he could get off early enough, he and Nelly had gone for a ride.

Nelly always looked well, but she looked best astride. Her togs were perfect and perhaps a bit heady. In these togs, one green afternoon, when riding through the woods with Tams, her cob picked a stone. The immediate limp had made that so obvious that both had stopped and dismounted. In the process of extracting the stone from the hoof, they had collided. A moment later, he had got a crack on the head.

Meanwhile, he had caught her, held her, kissed her, and would have kissed her again, but she had fought free and hit out, slashing him with her crop as hard as she could across the face. It had made quite a welt. Then, in a jiffy, she had been on and off.

Tams had rubbed his face, held a hand to it, jumped on, hurried after, overtaken the girl, and apologized.

Nelly, her cheeks aflame, her nose in the air, to all intents deaf and blind, had ridden on, first at a run, then at a gallop, then at a canter. The village had been reached. There, spotting a girl, she had waved at her, hopped off and, bridle in hand, walked along to the girl’s house, where she had tied the cob and entered.

At that, Tams, whose apologies had not ceased until she had dismounted, had gritted his teeth, wheeled, and vanished.

Since then, except with that creature, Nelly had not seen him nor had she wished to. The memory of his offense was too recent. It rankled, and not at all because she had not been kissed before, for she had been. Yet, after such kisses as she had previously received, her pulse had registered normal. That woodland kiss had been different. Unwarranted and unawaited, it had hurt and alarmed her.

The hurt had passed; the alarm had subsided; only anger remained, and its persistence perplexed, for she was angry in spite of herself, angry with an anger that was akin to a fever that you cannot shake off, but that does shake you. She was quivering with it. It parched her throat, flushed her face, and she wondered if she were going to die.

The possibility was not unwelcome. She had nothing to live for. She felt not only ill, but old, and not only old, but haggard. Hitherto, wherever she had gone, she had drawn the eyes of men. She had trailed admiration as a torch trails smoke. It had all been myrrh and cassia to her. But now its savor had gone, and this girl who had the charm and the caress of spring in her face, decided that she had nothing to live for.

Then, precisely as a moment before she had evoked Tams, now she evoked “that creature.”

She had had but one good look at her. That had been at the post office. He had tooted up, got out, and gone in just as Nelly had approached. He had not seen her nor, apparently, had his companion deigned to. The latter had sat in the car staring indifferently at nothing.

It was then that Nelly had had the one good look. It had frozen her. In none of the picture galleries of romance, in the museums of history, had she seen or imagined such a face. The quality of its beauty—coldly austere, as true beauty ever is—was unearthly. The eyes were stars, and in the carriage of the head, the cameo features, the glowing skin, the brilliantly invincible mouth, there were suggestions polar and dazzling. It was as if flesh and blood had achieved the impossible ability to detain and display some glory of the arctic aurora.

Before it Nelly had shrunk. In her own face was the loveliness of the lily, but before that other face she had felt it wither. A moment only. She had rallied at once.

“She isn’t a gentlewoman,” she had instantly and arrogantly decided. “And she’s common.”

The latter attenuation had been induced by the lady’s dress, which, though evidently a Fifth Avenue production, had been in coloring too pronounced for good taste and consequently unbecoming. Beauty, when fulgurant, should be soberly attired. This costume, the latest revival of a mid-Victorian mode, had been as gaudy as a peacock’s tail, and the gaudiness of it had dimmed her beauty, which had been otherwise diminished by a necklace of coral. But her face was supernal.

These details, however long in the telling, Nelly, with feminine ability, had summarized in that one good look, which had consumed hardly more than a second and amounted to but a glance.

Next to the post office was a shop, with that odor of having everything in it which village shops contrive to exhale. Nelly had turned and strolled in, turned and looked out.

Tams had issued from the post office, approached the car, said some word to the young woman, got in beside her, and they had driven off.

At that Nelly had vacated the shop. Then, in passing the post office, she had noticed a little crowd that had gathered, and, as she had moved on, she had overheard detached philosophies:

“Well, I never!” “And the airs of her!” “A ballet girl, I’ll bet.” “One of those Russians.”

Nelly knew better. Through her brother, she knew that, whatever the creature’s nationality might be, she was not a dancer, but Tams’ secretary and probably respectable, though certainly vulgar, and poignantly she wondered whether the awful costume had been his selection—which, she later discovered, it had.

But that afterward. At the time, dismissing the costume, she had wondered, and still more poignantly, whether Tams was to marry the person who wore it. The mere idea had made her sick.

Since then several days had intervened, days punctured by the spectacle of the creature shooting by, as she had on this high noon, like a comet. It was a little too much.

Now, in her bedroom which gave on the lawn and the road, Nelly seated herself at the window. There, as she sat, as sits Durer’s image of Melancholy—only much better dressed—something from without or within vibrated.

Before her the man again appeared, but not the one she had known. Another had come, a new one, composed of prowesses and powers hitherto ignored, and at once the form invisible and undefined that inevitably resides in the heart of a girl, and which is but the unincarnated soul of him who is destined to rule it, took substance. Then, as a weed of the sea, loosened and detached, rises slowly, stayed by one eddy, deflected by another, before achieving its gradual, yet assured ascent, a revelation, arrested by a tremor, again by a blush, from the depths of her being.

“But I love him!” she cried.

There is magic in those words. No sooner were they uttered than an exterior force seemed to lift from herself. Her mind became a rendezvous of apparitions. He appeared in countless phases—as she had seen him first, as she had seen him last, in all the changes of their acquaintance—and a shudder seized her at the knowledge of this love, of which she had been unconscious, and which had been tossed into existence by the sight of that creature.

That was it. She stood up and confronted it. That was the solution of the riddle of her anger. She was in love and she was jealous, and she could not be jealous unless she loved, and she could not love without being jealous.

Then immediately the exterior force that had lifted her from herself threw her back on that chair.

“I love him,” she stranglingly repeated, “and he is in love with another!”

Like a flying picture, torn from the cinematograph of memory, the wonder of that other’s face flashed by.

The picture fainted, succeeded by another—the green depths of the wood, the surprise, the kiss, the lash—that lash which now, consoled as he was, he never would forgive, and that kiss which now never would be repeated.

Despairingly she turned, threw a glance out of the window, and wished she could follow it.

Instead of anything so dramatic, she stared. Her hand clenched as it had on the veranda; her face flamed as it had when she had fled from the wood.

At the gate a motor had stopped and from it he and that creature were alighting.

Dumbfounded at the audacity, conscious that if he were capable of that he was capable of anything, and, through one of the sudden somersaults of the emotions, conscious also that it was no longer love that she had for him, but hate, she turned, hurried to the door, and locked it.

But it was impossible, she told herself. She had become the plaything of her own imagination and, to assure herself of the mistake, she hurried back from the door to the window.

Mistake indeed! There they were, actually walking up the path, she leaning on his arm and he talking lowly to her. It was more than flesh could bear. Nelly began to cry.

Her tears—tears of anger, of humiliation, of sheer helplessness—fell swiftly like the ripple of the rain. Not to stay them, for she could not, but in an effort to get away from herself, she flung herself face downward on the sofa.

What should she do, she plaintively wondered. What could she do? To whom could she turn? Long since her brother, as was his custom, must have gone to town, where he would remain until late, and her mother, as was her custom, was certainly asleep.

Well, there was comfort in that, she decided. There would be no one to receive them. In the consolation of it, she sat up and, reflecting, perhaps sagely, that there is no use in spoiling one’s looks, she dabbed at her slackening tears.

But now who was this? There was some one on the stair, some one at her door, some one who rapped, some one who spoke:

“Miss Nelly, Mr. Tams and a lady.”

The effrontery of that! Why, she wouldn’t even deign to answer!

“Miss Nelly, are you out?”

Tentatively a hand turned the resisting knob. Then presently she heard Sarah redescend the stair.

Now they would go, she told herself. They would have to, and when they had, she would put on her things and get her cob and have a good run. She did not care any more, not for anything or anybody.

At that reflection, finding herself crying again, she bit her lip. But to the soul that is sinking, hope throws always a straw. Perhaps, she told herself, some day, some time, her heart would be at peace. Perhaps. And fortified by the tolerably vague possibility, she stood up, went to the window again, and looked out.

There he was, strolling along to the motor, but alone.

Nelly craned a bit to see if that creature could be lagging behind. But no, he was really alone, and at once the partially appeasing idea occurred to her that, before presuming to get more than a bit beyond the gate, he had at least had the decency to pack that person off.

Yes, he must have, she decided, for now he was in the motor; now, with a toot, he had gone.

Assured of this, Nelly contemplated her lemon-colored frock, changed leisurely from it into her perfect togs, washed her face in sweet waters, took her crop and her gloves, unlocked the door, and went down.

But in the hall below, voices from the veranda arrested her. For a moment, her head drawn back in that attitude which a deer has when surprised, uncertainly she stood. Who could be out there? A sneeze informed her. That sneeze she recognized. Her mother was there. But, filled with wild surnise, she shook her crop. Could that creature be there, too?

Yet now, from the other end of the hall, a faint clatter of dishes came. A-tiptoe she went toward it. In the dining room Sarah was busying herself. At sight of the girl, she put down a tray.

“I thought you was out, miss.”

Nelly lifted a finger.

“Who is on the veranda?”

“Mr. Tams and a lady and your mother.”

“Mr. Tams! I saw him go.”

“Yes, miss, while your mother was dressing, he went to the post office. He came back a minute ago. The lady waited for him. She—”

Sarah took up the tray.

“Well?”

“Nothing, miss. I asked her would she have a cup of tea, and she just looked at me, like that!” Sarah bulged her eyes. “A foreigner, I’m thinking.”

Nelly, meditating escape by the back door, switched her crop and might have gone, but from the veranda a wave of laughter rolled richly like a flood of wine.

To her overwrought nerves, it was a bugle blast. With an uplift of the chin, she straightened. No back door, no cowardice for her! She would march out, her head in the air and good day to them, but civilly, for this was her house and, however insulted, she would not be betrayed into anything petty, though if that creature were a foreigner, perhaps she might be beneficently inspired to say to her something—well, something pleasant and acid, in French.

To that end a reconnaissance was needful—the lay of the land, the position of the enemy, the advantage or disadvantage of an abrupt sortie.

“Give me a drink of water, please,” she said to Sarah.

It was the stirrup cup, and, having drunk it, she went on, this time not in the hall where she might be seen, but into the sitting room, which gave on the veranda and through the latticed windows of which she could peer.

“Yes,” Tams was saying as, noiselessly, she approached. “But she limps.”

Mrs. Fay, in a shawl, had her back to the window. Opposite, leaning against the railing, was Tams. Beyond, in a chair, sat the creature.

“And, oddly enough, only in one leg—the left. There’s something wrong with it.”

Mrs. Fay sneezed.

“I hadn’t noticed it. But you say she sings?”

Tams nodded.

“Anything—duets, trios, a whole chorus—whatever you like.”

Mrs. Fay sneezed again.

“It does seem wonderful.”

Tams, leaning forward, took the young woman by the hand. At the touch, slowly she turned her head and covered him with her starlike eyes.

Nelly clutched at her crop. She could have struck them.

Mrs. Fay made a queer little noise—not a sneeze or a laugh, just a splutter—and, in reference evidently to something that had gone before, inquired:

“What do they say?”

Tams, releasing the girl’s hand, shifted.

“Well, you see the idea is so brand new that they don’t know whether they are in for rotten eggs or the biggest hit ever.”

“Dear me!”

“Yesterday, Goldburg, who is odjously familiar, clapped me on the back and said: ‘Make it dance, old boy, make it dance. That’s the stunt that’ll get ’em!’ ”

Patiently Mrs., Fay put in: “I should think so.”

“May I smoke?” Tams asked. “And somebody will,” he resumed as he got out a cigarette. “Somebody will do it, That’s inevitable. There’s barely an invention that hasn’t been bettered, There isn’t one that couldn’t be. Just now I’m ahead of this game, but though I can patent the process, I can’t patent the idea.”

Mrs. Fay, to whom that perhaps was Greek, exclaimed, “Oh, can’t you?”

Tams puffed.

“No, and moreover it’s all so simple. Not the machinery of course—that is a bit intricate—but the phonograph is mere a, b, c, and so is the rest of it.”

“Including the gown?”

“What gown?” thought Nelly. “What on earth are they talking about? And why does that creature sit there like a bump on a log? I could bite a tenpenny nail in two!”

Tams spilled his ashes.

“Don’t you like it? Why, I selected it myself. I saw it in a window.”

“Oh,” Mrs. Fay feebly protested, “I don’t mean but what it shows a great deal of taste—”

“And all of it bad,” Tams laughingly cut in. “Well, no doubt you are right. Whatever else I may be, I’m not a—what do you call him?—a Poiret. But that’s just it. I would have liked a suggestion or two from your daughter, whose taste is faultless, but, it appears, she isn’t in, and I have got to turn Gloria over tomorrow. She takes the title role.”

“Gloria?” Nelly indignantly repeated. “Is that that creature?”

Tams threw away his cigarette. “ ‘The Goblin Girl’ is billed for the tenth of next month.”

As he spoke, leaning forward once more, he again took the young woman’s hand.

“Come, my beauty, we must go.”

But his beauty made no reply, no movement even. Her head had not turned, as it previously had, slowly upward to him.

“Hello!” he exclaimed and dropped the hand, which fell limply. “She’s run down!”

“What does he mean?” thought Nelly. “What on earth is he doing?”

Tams, who had extracted a key from his pocket, was poking it at the peacock girdle. He was turning it there. Then he moved closer, masking the creature. But almost at once he turned, and Nelly saw the lips part, saw the teeth, the point of the tongue, and heard the opening sol bémol of a cavatina.

A moment only. Tams fumbled at her again. Abruptly the mouth closed, the aria ceased. It was as if he had bewitched her.

Mrs. Fay nodded applaudingly.

“It is certainly wonderful. I never could have believed that a doll could be made to go on like that. And you say they want it to dance?”

A doll! Amazedly Nelly wondered whether she were going mad or only becoming sane. She could have screamed and, lest scream she might, she clapped a hand to her mouth.

A doll! The bewilderment of it made her dizzy. Without conscious effort, she saw the creature as she had that noon, shooting by like a comet; she saw her as she had at the post office, looking as if the ground were not fit for her to tread on; and she saw her as she had in that fancy ball of the imagination, taking him away.

Then at once an overwhelming relief poured balm all over her.

But in complex emotions the first to assert itself is humiliation. The relief passed, ousted by a sense of shame that she had been tricked into betraying her feelings even to herself.

For it was a trick, she indignantly told herself, and, even otherwise, he ought to have known better. It was disgusting of him to have paraded that thing about like a joy forever and to have acted as if it were alive!

But she could act, too. She would show him and pretty quick!

Her crop under her arm, her head in the air, buttoning a glove as she went, out on the veranda she sailed.

“How do you do, Mr. Tams.” With a little nod, a nod remote and quite infinitesimal, she threw at him those five small words and caressingly, in her most sugary way, smiled at her mother. “Don’t catch more cold, dearest.”

Across the veranda she sailed, floated over, the steps, and on and up the path. There was a bit of wind, she noticed. She noticed, too, that the sun was going down. With her crop she decapitated a flower and, stooping, stuck it in her coat.

As she straightened, Tams was beside her.

“Nelly, I love you with all my heart and soul!”

Nelly looked up. The sky was a tent of various colors.

“Nelly, will you marry me?”

The wind sang about her like a flute.

A little later, when together they returned to the house, they found Mrs. Fay at the tea table.

Offering Tams a cup, the old lady said patiently:

“When you are quite ready, I hope you will take your beauty away. She’s uncanny.”

Tams smiled.

“There’s somebody else that I’m going to take away.”

Mrs. Fay, thinking, or affecting to think, of her treasure, started.

“Not Sarah?”

“Your daughter,” Tams with fitting gravity replied. “Your daughter has promised to be my wife.”

“Has she?” Mrs. Fay with amused, but affectionate interest, remarked.

“One lump or two? Well, I can’t honestly say that I didn’t suspect it. When is it to be?”

Nelly, contentedly helping herself to a caviar sandwich, answered for him:

“The day after the first production of ‘The Goblin Girl.’ ”

The Golden Chimera

“Janet Ferrol to the bar!”

At Oriol, before the war, in the dining-room of the Hôtel des Bains where I sat, memory had raised a latch and, from behind it, echoed that cry.

Without were the Côtes d’Or, the golden slopes of meridional France. Within was the simple comfort of the room, which was practically deserted at the time, and from which, a moment previous, a guest had gone.

At table he had sat opposite me. I could have sworn that I had seen him before. Yet where? For information I turned to the waiter.

“Léopold, who was that?”

Léopold rubbed his hands.

“A M. Bundy.” He paused and concisely added: “From the Americas.”

Bundy! That was it. At once a curtain had risen. The waiter, the dining-room, the Côtes d’Or, everything had vanished. In my quality of reporter, I was assisting again at the trial of Janet Ferrol, whom Bundy had defended.

That was in New York, four years ago. Previously Mrs. Ferrol had been currently quoted “among those present.” The fashion magazines supplied her picture. You saw her at Palm Beach, at Belmont Park, at Tuxedo. She was shown on the sands, on the ice, at the races. People who did not know better fancied her a widow. Of Ferrol there was no accompanying picture, no mention, and many must have concluded that if he were a man of the world, it was of a world other than this.

They would not have been far wrong, either. Hall Ferrol moved and had his being in the world of thought—a region perhaps unexplored by the lady who lived so palpably in the newspapers. Then presently her husband, whom they had ignored, created just a little ripple in them. He died, and you learned of his existence only through hearing that he was dead.

That was the ripple. It was followed by a lull, which was succeeded by a roar. Mrs. Ferrol was arrested, charged with his murder.

It was ridiculous, I told myself, for not long before I had interviewed this man, who was occupied—of all things!—with alchemy. Ordinarily I would have carefully avoided both him and it; but about that time an English scientist, Sir William Ramsay, had announced that with a certain combination of cathode rays and vacuum tubes the dream of the alchemists could be realized.

The subject was one on which the city editor had no erudition to conceal and none to display. But he felt that the man in the subway might relish a stick or two about it, and so, precisely as I was later told off to report the trial, I was then told off to get those sticks.

The task was not herculean. In the office encyclopedia I looked up “alchemy,” and found there that Hall Ferrol had written about it; looked up his address; went to Park Avenue, where, in a duplex apartment which for all I know to the contrary may have been triplex, I bearded him in his den. This was a great, bare room, totally devoid of any necromantic paraphernalia, in which he presented the melancholy spectacle of a rich man trying to be richer and, while he was at it, looking like a dentist.

I stated my errand. The tone in which I put it may have lacked seriousness, for he said, civilly enough, as if remarking about the weather:

“You don’t believe in alchemy.”

“Oh,” I answered, “I have three hundred and sixty-five beliefs, one for every day in the year. I am willing to add to them. In leap-year a belief in alchemy may come in handy.”

The inanity of that he ignored.

“You have practised it ever since you became a reporter. A wad of paper and an ounce of ink you transform into banknotes. What is that but alchemy? The transformation of metals is only a trifle more elaborate. As for Ramsay, it is infantile of him to say that it can be accomplished. It has been, and without any of his tubes or rays, either.”

I was amused at this attitude, which, however, all specialists exhibit to a trespasser in their vineyard, and I asked if he had accomplished it.

He nodded.

“Practically. Though I have nothing yet to show for it, I shall have, as others have before me.”

With that he gestured. A moment before he had suggested a dentist; it was a seer that he resembled then. Upon his face there came an expression rapt and vatic. Visibly he was astride, careering on his hobby.

In common, no doubt, with many others, I had ignorantly supposed that the easiest way to make money is to earn it. I was promptly undeceived.

He told me that there is a way easier still, a process for extracting something out of nothing, a solvent which turns lead into bullion, a secret called the alkahest—concerning which, by the way, Balzac wrote a novel that I never could read. Ferrol said that over it—over the secret, I mean, not the novel—the world went mad.

The madness seemed to me very rational. According to Ferrol, behind the process was mystery, about it romance, and above a golden chimera. That was the witchery of it. If you could snare and choke the chimera, she stammered the secret.

He admitted that all this happened a long time ago, and I thought that probably it never happened at all. In any event, the chimera flew away, as chimeras will. The secret went with it. But, as Ferrol put it, its fading memories still haunted the minds of men. They hallucinated the Middle Ages. They enthralled the Renaissance. They fascinated even Bacon.

Here I was on surer ground. Bacon, I was aware, knew all that was going and a lot that was not. He knew, for instance, that the world in which he lived was passing poor. He also knew that there had been an epoch when the world was just the reverse. He knew that the Babylonian satraps built at will cities fairer than the uplands of dream, palaces more luminous than the signs of the zodiac.

But Bacon’s knowledge was not universal. He did not know that the value of the treasure piled on the pyre of one of these satraps equaled eighty-four thousand millions of our money, which is a sum not much inferior to the total wealth of the United States.

Bacon did not know that, for the excellent reason that no one else did, until it was demonstrated by excavated and attesting tablets of imperishable brick. None the less, Bacon wondered what magic had created the magnificence that had been, and concluded, perhaps sagely, that a thread had been dropped from the scheme of things, that something, somewhere, was missing.

The deduction seems logical. At the beginning of the present era the total amount of money in circulation was less than that which in earlier days a single satrap—or even a married one—squandered. Moreover, poverty continued and increased until Columbus put down an idea, borrowed a boat on it, and brought back a world.

Things then began to look up. But, as Ferrol pointed out, just prior to the eruptions of gold from Mexico and Peru Europe was peopled with alchemists. Everywhere crucibles, alembics, and aludels were at work. Every one was chasing the chimera.

“Every one” is perhaps an exaggeration; but at least so many were at it that if there be a word of truth in history—which, in moments of faithlessness, I sometimes doubt—the game was actually quarried, the chimera was caught, the secret wrung from her. Kings and emperors had a finger in the pie. In the seventeenth century, with gold alchemistically obtained, Ferdinand III struck, not oil, but medals, some of which, attesting the miracle, were on view in the Vienna mint before the war. In the next generation the alchemistic successes of Augustus of Saxony were so much to his taste that, lightly, he gave a lady a supper-party that cost six millions.

Whatever the value of history may be, these instances and others like them are recorded in it. So also are mysterious stories of mysterious persons who provided the solvent by which the gold was obtained—the solvent, but not the secret; the alkahest, but not the process by which it was achieved.

That was the patent of the Rosicrucians, a society of adepts who got it from the Cabalists, a sect that originated among the Chaldean magicians, who in turn received it from no less a light than Azrael, angel of mysteries, and who, with it, taught the Babylonian monarchs what’s what.

That, of course, may not be true. Ferrol himself was a bit skeptical about it. But from indications which he supplied I afterward found the legend repeated and confirmed by all the great necromancers, by Paracelsus, Nostradamus, Albertus Magnus—and who am I to question them?

Besides, even if the story is not true, that does not detract from its charm; on the contrary, it adds to it. To sensible people, fairy tales are the most interesting of all. And anyway, and however the subject be regarded, it seemed probable that there had been a secret which now, by hook or by crook, Ramsay had nailed.

I said as much to Ferrol, who Johnsonianly addressed me.

“Sir, to recover that secret men invoked the aid of the planets, they invoked Satan himself, when it would have been simpler—” He hesitated, waved at something, and continued: “But when they got it they turned lead into bullion as readily as you turn paper into copy, as readily as I shall presently produce gold myself!” On a table before him he pounded. “Yes, sir, just as readily, and without any rubbish from Ramsay’s scrap-heap either. Vacuum tubes indeed! Cathode rays! Why not vaseline and a candle?”

II

Ferrol was mad as a hatter, I thought as I thanked him. Afterward I wondered whether it could have been in a lucid moment or in a fit of abstraction that he had married the woman who was charged with his death.

But the trial enlightened me, and now, in the dining-room at Oriol, the panorama of it returned. I was seated again at the press table and heard the ominous command:

“Janet Ferrol to the bar!”

Into court the woman limped and shrank, rather than sat, in a chair just beyond me.

Never have I seen a face so spectral. It was not guilt that it expressed, nor was it innocence. It was horror. Her skin was white as white paper, and that whiteness was accentuated by her weeds and by her eyes, which were black and burning. In the fashion magazines she had seemed very beautiful, slightly disdainful, sure of her charm. On that charm horror had dropped like a veil.

Beside her was Bundy, a large man, quite stout, with a face like a brandied cherry. Adjacently was another man with a gravely virile air and, for her, a look of extreme solicitude. His name, a brother reporter whispered, was Asher, and he had come up from Virginia to befriend her.

At the moment I had no time for further consideration of either of these men. Melvale, the district attorney, a dramatic person with the face of an elderly demon, was up and at it.

“May it please the court—Mr. Foreman and gentlemen of the jury!”

With three bows and this ritual he opened for the State, and began at once outlining the case for the people.

According to his account of it Ferrol was a wealthy recluse, and the defendant a woman insatiable of pleasure who, in pursuit of it, hesitated at nothing, not even at crime. Among her effects was a bottle containing muscarin, and with this poison she had rid herself of Ferrol and inherited his estate.

Melvale wheeled.

“This Brinvilliers killed her husband sordidly, for his money.” He paused and dramatically added: “And passionately, for another man!” As Melvale spoke, he pointed. “There he sits!”

He was pointing at Asher, who, with an air of contempt which seemed to me enormous, looked him up and down.

“Who was Brinvilliers, and how do you spell it?” a brother reporter asked.

But now Bundy was on his feet.

“I object to the district attorney prejudicing the jury against the lady, my client.”

The objection was not sustained.

“And I except to your honor’s ruling,” Bundy, with a bulldog look, threw up at the bench.

Melvale continued.

“There, gentlemen, is the crime; there, too, the motive. To finish the picture, evidence will be produced.”

As I sat in the dining-room I could see the picture, the frame as well—the court, vast, high-ceiled, close-packed, filled with spectators who had begged or badgered their way there; with men and women whom you would recognize as first-nighters, with others whom you would not recognize at all. For it is great sport to see a woman tried for her life. Yet when you have known her, or known of her, what more could you decently ask, except to have her convicted? That she would be, every one was convinced. The sight of her spectral face was enough.

But public opinion is a wave that thinks, changes its mind, thinks again. As the trial proceeded, no one was quite so sure. It is true, that spectral look had vanished.

On the stand, meanwhile, witnesses succeeded one another. Already the muscarin had been admitted in evidence and marked “Exhibit A.” “Exhibit B” was a certified copy of Ferrol’s will. “Exhibit C” was a bundle of Asher’s letters.

Concerning the muscarin, toxicologists for the State swore that it leaves no traces. In rebuttal, toxicologists for the defense swore that it does. The usual jest circulated. The mendacious were subdivided into liars, damned liars, and expert witnesses. Meanwhile it was shown that reagents employed at the autopsy had determined slight discolorations, which, it was also shown, might be attributed as well to natural causes as the reverse. Between the two you could pick and choose. It was a great privilege.

Ferrol’s will was different. It was very plain sailing. By it he devised all his property, of whatever kind, nature, and description, and wheresoever situated, to his wife and her heirs and legal representatives forever. Nothing could have been clearer.

As regards Asher’s letters, it was generally felt that no self-respecting woman should have preserved them. They were too alarmingly dull.

Additional testimony was supplied by servants, one of whom testified to having seen Ferrol in a state of great excitement two or three hours before his death, which, it was shown, had occurred shortly after midnight.

Where was the defendant at the time? It was Bundy who asked the question, it was the defendant who answered it. Bending to her, Bundy had requested her to take the stand.

It was then that the spectral look fell from her. Yet that was perhaps only natural. It is the fear of danger that affrights; but on the firing-line, while there may be death, fear and depression are gone.

Janet Ferrol displayed neither. Her face still was very pale; but to it, as the examination proceeded, gradually its former charm returned. Color diffused it, and once she smiled, very disdainfully and at Melvale, but the smile was there. It lighted her up for what she was—a rarely beautiful creature.

III

“Mrs. Ferrol,” Bundy began, extending one ample hand at her, the other at the jury, “will you be good enough to tell these gentlemen how Exhibit A, alleged to contain poison, came in your possession?”

With lifted eyes, in a clear, level voice, she answered:

“I removed it from Mr. Ferrol’s study.”

Bundy bowed.

“Thank you. Now the district attorney has given these gentlemen to understand that you benefited substantially by your husband’s death. Will you please tell them the value of the estate which you inherited from him?”

“Except for the furniture in our apartment and what money he had in the bank, I inherited nothing. There was no estate.”

Bundy started and stared.

“What? Nothing, you say? No estate?” Apparently he had never been so much surprised in all his life. “Then from what, may I ask, was his income derived?”

“From an annuity that died with him.”

In a crescendo of bewilderment which, though feigned, was well acted, Bundy lifted his hands.

“And did you know of this beforehand?” he asked.

“I knew of it before we were married,” the witness replied.

Bundy mopped his red face.

“Dear me! Dear me! Who would have supposed that my learned opponent, the district attorney, could be so grievously in error?”

Yet at once, in mitigation of that error, in obvious sympathy, too, he threw out:

“But there is Exhibit B, there is the will! Can you tell me why your late husband so elaborately devised to you nothing whatever?”

“Mr. Ferrol believed that through experiments in which he was engaged, he might at any moment become very wealthy.”

“Ah! And what was the nature of these experiments?”

“Alchemy.”

“Alchemy!” You would have thought that Bundy’s eyes were going to pop from his head. “So he was an alchemist! And was it the elixir of life that he was seeking?”

“No—the transmutation of metals.”

“O-ho! That was it, was it? And do you recall anything that he may have said on the subject?”

“He said that when the experiments were concluded he would project gold as a hose projects water; that we would wade in it.”

“And did Mr. Ferrol say what was necessary to bring about a result so—er—remarkable?”

“He said that the blood of a human being was indicated.”

“Ah! And did he tell you how he proposed to procure this—er—this ingredient?”

“He said he might carve up Sir William Ramsay.”

Blandly Bundy rubbed his hands and as blandly remarked:

“Mr. Ferrol being at the time in this city and Sir William in England?”

“Yes.”

“Did he say that there would be any preliminaries to the carving?”

“He said he would first dose him with muscarin.”

“And you feared that it was himself he might dose?”

“Precisely.”

“And it was for this reason that you removed it?”

“It was.”

“Thank you, Mrs. Ferrol. One question more—in regard to this gentleman, Mr. Asher. Is he a relative or connection of yours?”

“Mr. Asher is my second cousin.”

“Ah! Quite so. And prior to your husband’s death, did you see him often?”

“Since my marriage, I have seen him but twice—once yesterday, in the Tombs, and again to-day in court.”

Much as a nurse might look at an ill-treated child, Bundy cocked an eye.

“Did Mr. Ferrol object to your seeing him?”

The defendant, who thus far had held herself as if, in the vast room, she and Bundy were alone, seemed at the moment transiently aware that others were present.

“So far as I was concerned, Mr. Ferrol objected to nothing and insisted on but one thing.”

“And what was that?” asked Bundy, who at once clapped a hand to his mouth as if now he had put his foot in it.

“That I should have my way in everything.”

Bundy looked up at the ceiling. Where else could a nature so rare have gone? Then, leisurely returning to earth and his client, he shifted.

“Mrs. Ferrol, it has been shown that just before your husband’s death he was greatly excited. An alchemist is not supposed to be an excitable person. Can you tell these gentlemen what he was excited about?”

“He told me that after many disappointments he had recovered the alkahest, snared the chimera, got the secret of the transmutation of metals, and that with it he would make me the richest woman in the world.”

“And when you left him he was elated over that prospect?”

“Very much so indeed.”

“But you knew that until results were obtained there would be nothing but his annuity?”

“Yes.”

“Then you had nothing to gain by your husband’s death?”

The defendant, her eyes two disks of flame, bent forward.

“Say rather that I had everything to lose—perhaps even my life, which is now in jeopardy.”

Gravely Bundy considered it. Then, mopping his face, he smiled—smiled at the press table, smiled at the jury, smiled at her.

“Do not, I beg of you, Mrs. Ferrol, distress yourself on that account. The district attorney would have these gentlemen believe that you poisoned your husband, sordidly, for his money, and passionately, for another man.” Bundy coughed, gestured, and added: “I think I have very thoroughly disposed of my learned friend’s contentions. I—”

Severely the court interrupted:

“Reserve anything of that kind for your summing up!”

Bundy bowed. He had scored a point, and just when it would have the greatest effect. Conscious of which, he became a compound of irony and good humor, Falstaff and Mercutio in one.

“I am deeply grateful for your honor’s instructions.” He turned to his client. “Thank you, Mrs. Ferrol!” He turned to Melvale. “Your witness! And, by the way, let me beg of you, don’t go at this witness as you did at the last, like a common scold.” He turned to his client again. “I apologize in advance for any rudeness on the part of the district attorney.”

Meanwhile, from behind the bar, objections had exploded like shell from a rapidfire gun; but through the running fire of them Bundy held to his own, held to his trench, extracting bit by bit this curious story, which I could see interested even the judge. Benevolently over and down at the defendant he looked, and from the look I could divine the tenor of his coming charge.

Probably Melvale divined it also—if not then, at any rate after he had finished with the cross-examination, during which he fished but one item of reportable interest. It was to the effect that the defendant had been engaged to Asher, and that owing to a misunderstanding on her part the engagement had been broken; after which she had married Ferrol, who was old enough to be her father.

Melvale, smoothing what hair he had left as if it were some costly fur, threw out:

“Was your husband aware that you corresponded with Asher?”

Then it was that the defendant smiled. The smile lit her face, brought out its beauty.

“Mr. Ferrol was a gentleman.”

Melvale twisted.

“That is not an answer to my question!” he said sharply.

Again she smiled.

“To your question, yes, it is an answer, but not, perhaps, to your understanding. Mr. Ferrol did not concern himself with his wife’s correspondence. Some men do, I believe, and I dare say you are one of them; but they are not gentlemen.”

Fumingly the district attorney turned toward the judge.

“I ask that that be stricken out!” Then, fuming still, he got back at her. “You are in love with Asher now, are you not?”

She gave him one look, her fashion-magazine look, the look slightly disdainful. With that, and decently enough, it seemed to me, she answered:

“You are seeking to take my life, but my soul you cannot take, nor shall I reveal it to you.”

Then eventually, through the testimony of other experts, Bundy adduced their belief that Ferrol had died of heart failure, which his demonstrated neurosis and excitability had caused.

After the summing up, the charge followed, and the jury filed out. It was idle to wait, perilous as well—at any murder trial you run the risk of being talked to death, if nothing worse—and I went on to the office where I was employed, and where I later learned of Janet Ferrol’s acquittal.

IV

Now, as I sat in the dining-room of the Hotel des Bains, I wondered what had become of her. Long since her name had passed from the newspapers, and it seemed to me that I had heard—yet what does one not hear?—that Bundy had passed from the courts.

Then at once I realized why I had not immediately recognized him. In court his face had had the hue of a brandied cherry. That hue had gone, supplanted by pallor. In addition, he was very much thinner. In New York he had suggested Falstaff. It was Hamlet whom he resembled now.

“From the Americas,” Léopold, rubbing his hands, resumed. “The gentleman arrived to-day. Mme. Bundy is awaited shortly.”

The next morning I rather looked for him at the baths and in the gardens, but it was not until night that I spotted him, and then in the restaurant, where he appeared to have supped, and where he sat moodily, a glass of Pommard before him.

Seating myself, I threw out:

“Mr. Bundy, I believe. My name is Jones. Some years ago I reported the trial of Janet Ferrol, whom you so admirably defended.”

At the moment he was raising his glass. As I addressed him, he started, his hand shook, a little of the red contents spilled, he stared.

“Ah! You are a reporter, are you?” With that he abruptly got up and left the room.

Before the war people went to Marienbad for obesity, to Carlsbad for gastritis. These resorts were full of men without livers and of women without hearts. Oriol lacked that distinction. The pomps of fashion ignored it. Those who came to its woodland balms and baths were in search of relief from nerves overtaxed, of anodynes for neurasthenia. It was a little refuge for those whom Lombroso catalogued, and very inanely, as mattoids, for it were far simpler to have labeled them cranks.

Anywhere else Bundy’s conduct might have perplexed me; though, to be sure, the vocation of reporter is not always a source of welcomings. But at these baths to which, having stumbled in the newspaper harness, I had been shipped by my chief, I accepted Bundy’s abruptness as a matter of course. He, too, has been under some strain, I told myself. In the same breath I told Léopold that I also had no valid objection to Pommard.

Yet whether because Bundy and I were compatriots or, more reasonably perhaps, because we sat opposite each other at table, during the next day or two our acquaintance so far progressed that we exchanged platitudes and the time of day. Then it so happened that a patient committed suicide, as patients have sometimes done at Oriol, and that evening the subject swam up.

“Were you ever drawn that way?” he asked.

“Yes,” I answered; “but two things have always restrained me—a mad passion for political economy and a fear of getting hurt.”

At that his mouth twitched, it widened, he threw his head back and laughed very loudly, not at me or the stupidity of my antique jest, but at something else, something of which he alone could have been aware.

And still he laughed. Then, abruptly, on a high note, the laughter ceased. It was as if it had been suddenly nipped. His Hamlet air returned. Gravely he considered me.

“What were you saying?”

“Nothing. But you were speaking of assassination driven in, which suicide is.”

“Yes, yes, to be sure. Well, Janet had it in reserve.”

“And that’s the best place for it.”

Bundy sketched an unheeding gesture.

“From what appeared in court, you will appreciate that she counted on Ferrol’s experiments. None the less, she had planned to leave him.”

“Because of Asher?” I inquired. Impatiently Bundy shifted.

“Asher? No! She had conceived another love, a love that is unique, one which, when evolved, transcends every other, which saps the veins of youth, drains the heart of age, which has made fathers destroy their sons and daughters betray their mothers, that love which never relents and never releases, that love which once was worshiped as a god, which to-day rules New York, that love, her master—and perhaps yours—was—”

“Gold!” I threw at him.

Bundy nodded.

“It was because of it that she married Ferrol. He had told her that he would make her the richest woman in the world. Ostensibly to encourage him, but privately for another reason, she assisted at every one of his experiments. It was in the course of them that, believing he would not succeed, she planned to leave him. Then, one day, suddenly, before her eyes, he turned the trick; he had snared the chimera; he had got it!” Bundy paused, contemplated his fingers, and added: “That night he died.”

“Yes,” I broke in. “The gist of it all appeared at the trial.”

Bundy nodded again.

“You have been good enough to commend my part in it; but at the time I believed absolutely in her innocence.”

I stared at him.

“You don’t mean that she actually killed that lunatic?”

Bundy blinked and winced. The simple words I had uttered seemed to choke him. For a moment he struggled with them. Then, rallying, he coughed.

“Ferrol was not a lunatic. No man with a creative mind ever is. The genius is normal. It is the ordinary individual, with his stupid thoughts and uncreative mind, that is abnormal. Ferrol was a genius. He had hit on a process by which electricity can turn lead into gold. You may doubt it; but if with carbon and an electric furnace—that is to say, with heat equal to four thousand degrees centigrade, which must be the temperature of the throne of Satan—if with that you can manufacture diamonds, as Moissan did, why not gold? The matrix of both is heat.”

“But,” I got in, “at the trial it was not electricity which your client testified about. It was blood; the blood of a human being—Ramsay’s, for choice.”

“She made it all up.”

“The carving process and the preliminary poison?”

“Every word of it.”

I sat back.

“And you knew of this?”

Bundy twisted.

“Were you in court when the verdict was rendered? You were not? Then you missed an instructive moment. Janet crumpled and fell. She had fainted. Innocent people don’t faint when they are acquitted. They expect acquittal. It is relief at the unexpected that crumples the guilty up. Only a moment before she had determined to kill herself. It was afterward that I learned of it.”

I did not know of all this. I told him so, and looked about for Léopold and more Pommard; but the waiter was nowhere visible.

“Well,” Bundy was saying, “it was long before she recovered—I don’t mean consciousness, but health, her charm, and that beauty of hers which had been under an eclipse. The Tombs, the preliminaries, the trial, yet chiefly, perhaps, a vision of the chair—these things had prostrated her; but finally, not alone because of her youth, but also because of the golden chimera and its secret, which Ferrol had revealed to her—finally, issuing from that prostration, she put her hand in mine.”

“What?” I had been awaiting almost any climax but that; yet, though I did not then suspect it, there was another and a more surprising one in store. “What?” I repeated.

Bundy emptied his glass.

“I knew, and she knew that I knew. It was for protection that she put her hand in mine, and we were married.”

“I never heard of that,” I interrupted.

Indifferently he shrugged a shoulder.

“Oh, very quickly, without any publicity. Meanwhile I had abandoned my profession, and she had nothing. For a time we suffered atrociously. Inasmuch as Janet had the alkahest, you may wonder why; but, believe me, a vision of the electric chair can be very obliterating. During the trial, and the terror of it, she had forgotten one of the main factors of the process. The golden chimera had again escaped. It was a year before she recovered it. That year put its mark on her and on me, Both of us suffered atrociously. But that is always the way—to get to paradise there is always a desert to cross!”

“Yes?” I proddingly put in, for he had stopped and looked absently away.

Presently, as if returning from some inordinate distance, he got back to it.

“The Czar, I understand, is rather well off. He has a million a day, though whether the million is in dollars or rubles I have forgotten. In any event, it is improbable that he has to count the copecks. Janet and I won’t have to, either. We will be richer than he, rich as the satraps of Babylon!”

He had been speaking quietly in a colorless monotone, but with that he sprang up. I thought he was going to say good night, but he shouted:

“Yes, rich as the satraps of Babylon! Not Azrael, angel of mysteries, not the arcanum of the Cabalists, not the abracadabra of the alchemists, not Ramsay’s tubes and rays, not these, or any of them, but the riddle of the ages, which Ferrol solved, will put us on a plane with the great figures that Sardanapalus and Semiramis were—eh?”

“Pardon, monsieur!”

I turned. Bundy wheeled. Unobserved by either of us, Léopold had approached and was rubbing his hands at him.

“Madame desires to speak to monsieur,” the waiter said.

At that, without a word, without a look, Bundy, as if hypnotized, stalked from the room.

I watched him go. A dozen questions had occurred to me—a story as well. I took it for granted that Janet had arrived during the day, and I wondered whether he might not return with her. The privilege of sitting at table with a young, beautiful, and mythologically opulent murderess was one that I had never experienced. It would, I thought, be not dissimilar to that of contemplating some fabulous monster conveniently displayed.

Yet somehow the picture of her which he had silhouetted did not in the least correspond with my idea of the woman whom I had admired in court. I wondered if, like him, she also had changed. But it was late, fully ten o’clock. I, too, had come to Oriol for my nerves; and reflecting that, for the night at least, they had sufficiently supped on surprises, I postponed until the morrow any additional adventures in criminal plutocracy, and ambled off to bed.

V

The next day Bundy was not in his accustomed seat. It was occupied by a woman with a worn, patient face, who glanced at me as I sat down before her.

Motioning to Léopold, I asked after Bundy. In a whisper he told me that M. Bundy was not very well. Bending a little as he poured me a glass of wine, he added that Mme. Bundy was seated opposite.

“Nonsense!” I mentally retorted.

Janet was young; this woman was old. Moreover, Janet’s hair was black as a truffle, and hers was gray as November. It might possibly be a wig, I thought; but even so—

“You were inquiring about my son, I believe,” she was saying in a low, gentle voice.

I wondered whom she had addressed, until I saw that her eyes, which seemed very pathetic, were fixed on me.

“Excuse me,” I answered. “Except the waiter and the doctor, the only human being that I know here is a man named Bundy.”

“That is my son,” she replied.

“Oh!” I exclaimed. “I beg your pardon. From something the waiter said, I knew that a Mrs. Bundy was expected, but I supposed it was his wife.”

She shook her gray head.

“My son is not married. He never has been.”

Thoroughly flabbergasted, I sat back.

“Not married! But—but only last evening he was telling me about a Mrs. Ferrol, whom he once defended. I thought—but perhaps you knew her?”

Sadly, with her pathetic eyes, she considered me—considered, too, perhaps something else. Then she sighed.

“Yes; I used to go to her in the Tombs.”

“Did you?” I lamely got out. “And how did she impress you?”

“Like an angel in a cell.”

Dazed and uncertain, I took it up.

“You believed in her innocence?”

For a moment, as if picturing it, she closed her eyes. They opened, and in her low voice she answered:

“It was hardly a question of belief. No one could see her in that prison and not be convinced. Friendless, alone, charged with a crime at which her young soul revolted, the sight of her would have been heartrending had it not been sublime. She accepted everything not only without a murmur, but with the air of that great lady who, during the Terror, went to the guillotine smelling a rose. Did you know Mrs. Ferrol?”

“No,” I hesitatingly answered. “No; I merely reported her trial.” Again I hesitated and then got down to it. “But, afterward, did she not marry?”

Wanly, over that worn face, passed the wraith of a smile.

“Yes, after the year of widowhood she married her second cousin, Paul Asher, a Virginian who had been in love with her ever since he was a boy. They are very happy, I believe. Well, she deserved to be happy.”

“Oh!” I exclaimed in mounting bewilderment, through the apogee of which, however, a gleam of understanding shot. “Oh, indeed! Your son, I regret to hear, is not very well.”

“Ah! If he were,” she pathetically answered, “what would he be doing at Oriol? But you do not seem to be very well yourself. Forgive me for asking, but do you, too, imagine things? The doctor says—”

Whatever it may have been that the doctor said, I did not hear. I was lost in what I had heard. Another curtain had risen. I saw that in the course of this lady’s remarks I had been assisting at a second trial, at which Janet had again been acquitted.

Then, as that curtain fell, at once another parted. The significance of Bundy’s irrational laughter, of his shouts, of his fantastic tale, was clear. With a smile at my own stupidity—a smile which his mother must have construed into a leer as lunatic as any that he could display—I decided that my nerves had got all they could out of Oriol.

But food was before me, so also was wine.

“Sic transit gloria Bundy!” I mumbled as I drank it.

Yet in that obituary of the living, while there was immense pity for him, there was relief, too, and as great, at Janet’s second acquittal.

Presently, the meal finished, after bowing to the poor wretch’s mother, I left the room to pack my things, realizing that once more the chimera had escaped, and this time doubtless forever.

The Grand Duke’s Rubies

There is in New York a club called the Balmoral, which has two peculiarities—no one ever goes there much before midnight, and it is the only place in town where you can get anything fit to eat at four o’clock in the morning. The members are politicians of the higher grade, men about town, and a sprinkle of nondescripts. In the unhallowed inspiration of a moment, Alphabet Jones, the novelist—in polite society Mr. A. B. Fenwick Chisholm-Jones—baptized it the Smallpox, a name which has stuck tenaciously, the before-mentioned members being usually pitted—against each other. Of the many rooms of the club, one, it should be explained, is the most enticing. It is situated on an upper floor, and the siren that presides therein is a long table dressed in green. Her name is Baccarat.

One night last February, Alphabet Jones rattled up to the door in a vagabond hansom. He was thirsty, impecunious, and a trifle tired. He had been to a cotillon, where he had partaken of champagne, and he wanted to get the taste of it out of his throat. He needed five hundred dollars, and in his card-case there were only two hundred and fifty. The bar of the Athenaeum Club he knew at that hour was closed, possible moneylenders were in bed, and it was with the idea of killing the two birds of the legend that he sought the Balmoral.

He encountered there no difficulty in slaking his thirst; and when, in one draught, which brought to his tonsils a suggestion of art, science, and Wagner combined, he swallowed a brandy-and-soda, he felt better, and looked about to see who might be present. The room which he had entered was on what is called the parlor floor. It was long, high-ceiled, comfortably furnished, and somewhat dim. At the furthermost end three men were seated, two of whom he recognized, the one as Sumpter Leigh, the other as Colonel Barker; but the third he did not remember to have seen before. Some Westerner, he thought; for Jones prided himself on knowing everyone worth knowing in New York, and, it may be added, in several other cities as well.

He took out his card-case and thumbed the roll of bills reflectively. If he went upstairs, he told himself, he might double the amount in two minutes. But then, again, he might lose it. Yet, if he did, might not five hundred be as easily borrowed as two hundred and fifty?

“It’s brutal to be so hard up,” he mused. “Literature doesn’t pay. I might better set up as publisher, open a drug-shop, turn grocer, do anything, in fact, which is brainless and remunerative, than attempt to earn a living by the sweat of my pen. There’s that Interstate Magazine: the editor sent me a note by a messenger this morning, asking for a story, adding that the messenger would wait while I wrote it. Evidently he thinks me three parts stenographer and the rest kaleidoscope. What is a good synonym for an editor, anyway?”

And as Jones asked himself this question he glared fiercely in a mirror that extended from cornice to floor. Then, mollified, possibly, by his own appearance, for he was a handsome man, tall, fair, and clear of skin, he threw himself on a sofa, and fell to thinking about the incidents of the ball.

For some time past he had been as discreetly attentive as circumstances permitted to a young girl, the only child of a potent financier, and on that particular evening he had sat out the cotillon with her at an assembly. She was very pretty and, unusual as it may seem in a débutante, rather coy. But when, a half-hour before, he had wished her sweet dreams in that seductive manner for which he was famous, she had allowed the tips of her fingers to rest in his own just one fleeting second longer than was necessary, and, what is more to the point, had looked into his eyes something which now, under the influence of the brandy-and-soda, seemed almost a promise. “Dear little soul!” he muttered; “if she marries me I will refuse her nothing. It will be the devil’s own job, though, to get her any sort of an engagement ring. Tiffany, perhaps, might give me one on credit, but it will have to be something very handsome, something new; not that tiresome solitaire. Those stones I saw the other day—H’m! I wonder what that fellow is staring at me for?”

He lounged forward to where the men were seated, and, being asked to draw a chair, graciously accepted the invitation and another brandy-and-soda as well.

“It was this way,” the stranger exclaimed, excitedly, when he and Jones had been introduced. “I was telling these gentlemen when you came in that you looked like the Grand Duke Sergius—”

“Thank you,” the novelist answered, affably. “The same to you.”

“I never saw him though,” the stranger continued.

“No more have I.”

“Only his picture.”

“Your remark, then, was doubly flattering.”

“But the picture to which I allude was that of a chimerical grand duke.”

“Really, sir, really you are overwhelming.”

“But wait a minute, do wait a minute. Mr. Jones, I don’t know whether you caught my name: it is Fairbanks—David Fairbanks.”

“Delighted! I remember it perfectly. My old friend, Nicholas Manhattan, bought a ruby of you once, and a beauty it was. I heard at the time that you made a specialty of them.”

“So did the grand duke. He came here, you know, on that man-of-war.”

“Yes, I know. Mrs. Wainwaring gave him a reception. It was just my luck: I was down with the measles at the time.”

“Oh, you were, were you? You were down with the measles, eh? Well, I wish I had been. Gentlemen, listen to this; you must listen. I was in my office in Maiden Lane one day, when a young man came in. He wore the most magnificent fur coat I have ever seen in my life. No, that coat was something that only Russia could have produced. He handed me a card on which was engraved

PCE Michel Zaraguine,
Aide-de-camp de S. A. I. le grand-duc Serge de Russie.

“And then, of all things in the world, he offered me a pinch of snuff, and when I refused he helped himself out of a beautiful box and flicked the grains which had fallen on his lapel with a nimbleness of finger such as it was a pleasure to behold. I ought to tell you that he spoke English with great precision, though his accent was not pleasant—sort of grizzled, as it were. Well, gentlemen, he said that his prince, as he called him, the grand duke, wanted some rubies; they were intended for a present; and, though my visitor did not imply anything either by word or gesture, I suspected at once that they were for a lady. The grand duke at that time had been here a fortnight, and it was said—However, there is no use in going into that. So I showed him a few; but, if you will believe me, he wanted enough to make a tiara. I told him that a tiara of stones of that quality would come anywhere from sixty to eighty thousand dollars. If I had said a peck of groats he could not have appeared more indifferent. ‘It is a great deal of money,’ I said. He smiled a little at that, as though he were thinking, ‘Poor devil of an American, it may seem a great deal of money to you, but to a grand duke—!’ Then I brought out all I had. He looked them over with the pincers very carefully, and asked how much I valued them at. I told him a hundred and ten thousand dollars. He didn’t turn a hair.”

“Was he bald?” Jones asked.

“No, sir, he was not; and your jest is ill-timed. Gentlemen, I appeal to you. I insist on Mr. Jones’s attention—”

“Why, the man is crazy,” Jones mused. “What does he mean by saying that my jest is ill-timed? But why does he insist on my attention? He’s drunk—that’s what he is; he’s drunk and quarrelsome. Well, let him be. What do I care?” And Alphabet Jones looked complacently at his white waistcoat and then over at his excitable vis-à-vis. Mr. Fairbanks was a little man of the Cruikshank pattern, very red and rotund, and as he talked he gesticulated.

“So I said to him, ‘There’s been a corner in rubies, but it broke, and that is the reason why I can give them at that price.’ He didn’t know what a corner was, and when I explained he took a notebook out of his pocket and wrote something in it. ‘I am making a collection of Americanisms for the Czarina,’ he said. ‘By the way,’ he added, ‘what is a Sam Ward!’ I told him. He laughed, and put it down—”

“His throat?”

Mr. Fairbanks glanced at Jones with unconcealed irritation: “Dr. Hammond, sir, says that punning is a form of paresis.”

“Be careful about that epsilon; it’s short.”

“Well, Mr. Jones, you ought to know how to pronounce the word better than I, for you have the disease and I haven’t. Gentlemen, I insist—”

But Jones had begun to muse again. “That fat little brute is a type,” he told himself. “I must work him in somewhere. I wonder, though, if I had not better leave him and go up to the baccarat. It might be more remunerative. It would be amusing,” and Alphabet smiled at the fantasy of his own thought, “it would be amusing indeed if he tried to prevent me.” He put his hand over his eyes and let Mr. Fairbanks ramble on.

“You see,” he heard him say, in connection with something that had gone before, “a man in my business has to be careful. Now, there are rubies and rubies. I only handle the Oriental stones, which are a variety of the hyaline corindus. They are found in Ceylon, in Tibet, and in Burma among the crumblings of primordial rock. But I have seen beauties that were picked from waste lands in China from which the granite had presumably disappeared. They are the most brilliant and largest of all. There is another kind, which looks like a burned topaz: it is found in Brazil and Massachusetts. Then there is the Bohemian ruby, which is nothing but quartz reddened by the action of manganese; and there are also imitations so well made that only an expert can tell them from the real. I keep a few of the latter on hand so as to be able to gauge a customer. Well, gentlemen, the Russian picked up two of them, which I placed before him, and put them to one side. He knew the false article at a glance. Your friend, Jones, that simpleton Nicholas Manhattan, would have taken one of the imitation if I had not prevented him, but this fellow was so clever about it that he won my immediate respect.”

“Jones, indeed!” Alphabet muttered. “Why, the brute is as familiar as a haberdasher’s advertisement!” He looked at him again: his face was like a brandied peach that had fallen into the fire, and his head was set on his shoulders like an obus on a cannon. “Bah!” he continued, “what is the use in being irritated at a beggar who is as ugly as a high hat at the seashore?”—“When you do me the honor to address me, sir,” he said, aloud, “I shall be obliged if you will call me Mr. Jones.”

“Tut, tut!” the little man answered, and then, without further attention to Alphabet, he continued his tiresome tale:

“When the Russian had examined the rubies very carefully a second time, he said, half to me and half to himself, ‘I think they will do.’ Then, looking up at me, he added, ‘Mr. Fairbanks, you do not make a hundred-thousand-dollar sale every day, do you?’ ‘No, your Excellency,’ I answered—you see, I made a dash at Excellency; Prince seemed sort of abrupt, don’t you think?’—‘No, your Excellency, it does not happen over once a week.’ He smiled at that, and well he might, for the biggest sale I had previously made amounted to but nine thousand dollars. ‘Mr. Fairbanks,’ he continued, ‘the grand duke is rich, as you well know. I am not. You will understand me the better when I tell you that at present, unless cholera has visited Russia since I left (and I hope it has), there are exactly twenty-nine people in Petersburg who bear the same name and title as myself. Now, if the grand duke purchases these rubies, what will my commission be?’ ‘That is squarely put, your Excellency,’ I answered—‘squarely put. Will his Imperial Highness pay cash for the rubies?’ ”

“You might have asked him if his Imperial Highness would pay rubis sur l’ongle. But I remember you don’t approve of wit.”

This interjection came, of course, from Jones. Mr. Fairbanks, however, let it pass unnoticed. It may be that he did not understand.

“ ‘Necessarily,’ he replied. ‘A recent ukase of the Czar’s inhibits any member of the Imperial family from purchasing so much as a brass samovar on credit.’ I bowed. ‘A very proper and wise ukase that is, your Excellency. Under such circumstances I think I see my way to giving you one percent.’ He laughed at that, as though I had made a remark of great brilliance.”

“I like that,” Jones exclaimed, in spite of himself. “Why, you wouldn’t be brilliant in a calcium light.”

But this remark, like the former, passed unheeded. For the first time since his memory ran not to the contrary it seemed to Jones that he was being ignored; and to ignore Jones! Allons donc!

“ ‘Look at me,’ said the Russian,” Mr. Fairbanks continued. “ ‘The grand duke will not buy these rubies except on my recommendation, and I value that recommendation at not a kopeck less than ten thousand dollars. It is to take or to leave. Choose, sir, choose.’ And with that he picked up his hat. ‘I cannot, your Excellency, I cannot.’ He turned away and made for the door. ‘Excellency,’ I cried, ‘I will give you five.’ He wheeled about. ‘If,’ he said, ‘you offer one percent when you can give five and three-fifths, you are just as well able to give nine and two-thirds.”

“He was a lightning calculator, wasn’t he?”

“ ‘On my conscience,’ I answered, ‘I cannot give more than seven.’ ‘Ah!’ he replied, ‘I do not know how to haggle.’ He reflected a moment. ‘It is well,’ he said; ‘I accept.’ Gentlemen, when he said that, I felt that I had done a good day’s work. Apart from the commission I had a clean profit of eighteen thousand dollars; and eighteen thousand dollars is a tidy sum—not to you, gentlemen, nor to Jones there, but to me.”

“Ged, the little cad is getting sarcastic.” And Jones laughed quietly to himself and finished his brandy-and-soda.

Mr. Fairbanks waved his arms and pounded the table so excitedly that he roused a waiter from a nap.

“Yes, bring the same,” he cried. “Now, gentlemen, I am coming to the point. I insist on your attention. Mr. Jones, I will thank you not to interrupt—unless it happens that you care to aid me with the details. Yes, sir, I said details—d-e-t-a-i-l-s. Now wait a minute, will you? Gentlemen, I appeal to you. He shall wait. Beat it into his head—can’t you?—that I am coming to the point, and very interesting, I promise, you will all find it to be.”

“Tu te vantes, mon bonhomme, tu te vantes. Here’s to you.”

“Here’s to you. Well, gentlemen, it was then one o’clock. I always lunch at that hour, and I asked the Russian if he would let me offer him a bite. ‘I would very much like to try a Sam Ward,’ he said, ‘and I might take some tea and a bit of toast.’ ‘That,’ I replied, ‘would be tasty with a little caviar.’ I wanted to show him that, though a dealer in precious stones, I was first and foremost a man of the world.”

Alphabet Jones rolled over in spasms of delight. “Divinities of Pindar,” he shouted, “listen to that!”

“Gentlemen, gag that man—gag him: I will be listened to. There, now, will you be quiet? You make me lose the thread. Where was I? Oh, yes: the Russian seemed to reflect a moment, and looked at his watch. ‘I think,’ he said, ‘it would be better to go straight to the Brevoort House.’ (The grand duke, I knew, was stopping there.) ‘My prince is to go out this afternoon between two and three, and if you do not see him today it may be hard to manage it tomorrow.’ ‘I am at your orders, Excellency,’ I answered; ‘business before pleasure.’ ‘Good, then,’ he returned; ‘we will take a droschky, or, better even, your railway that is in the air.’ ‘The elevated, you mean,’ I said—‘the elevated. Yes, of course.’ Inwardly I was well pleased that the suggestion should have come from him, for I am not overfond of riding in a cab with a hundred and ten thousand dollars’ worth of rubies in my pocket and a stranger for sole companion. For he was a stranger—wasn’t he?—and, by his own account, not well-to-do. But that Russian had a knack of disarming suspicion. And, besides, how was it possible for me to have any doubts about a man who fought as he had over the percentage? It would have been nonsensical. So I did the rubies up in cotton, put them in a box, and off we went. On the way to the elevated you ought to have seen how the people stared at that coat. All the time he kept up a delightful flow of conversation. He told me any number of interesting things about his country, and when I asked if he had read ‘The Journey Due North’ he told me that he had, and that when Sala was in Russia his father had entertained him at his country-house a few versts from Moscow. Think of that, now! Altogether, he made himself most agreeable. I asked him on the way if he thought that inasmuch as I was to have the honor of seeing the grand duke it would not be more in accordance with etiquette for me to put on a dress-coat. But he laughed, and said, no, the grand duke would never notice. Then he told me some very curious anecdotes about him—how, for instance, he fainted dead away at the sight of an apple, and yet kept a balloon and an aeronaut, just as Jones there might keep a dogcart and a groom. He told me, among other things, that at Petersburg the grand duke had a pet tiger, which would accept food from no one but him, and on my asking how the tiger got along when the grand duke was away, he said that the grand duke had him stuffed. Oh, he was very entertaining, and spoke English better than you would have imagined. We walked over from Eighth Street to the hotel, and when we reached it he took me straight upstairs to his own room. ‘If you will sit a minute,’ he said, ‘I will see if his Highness can receive you.’ He went away, and I looked about me. The room into which I had been shown was a sitting-room with a bedroom opening from it. There was a writing-table standing against the door which led to the adjoining apartment, and while I was waiting I just glanced at the things with which the table was littered. There were a number of foreign newspapers, but in what language they were printed I could not make out; there was a package of official-looking documents tied with a string, a great blue envelope addressed in French to the Prince Michel Zaroguine and postmarked Washington, and back of all, in a frame, the photograph of a man.”

For some minutes previous Mr. Fairbanks had been speaking quite composedly, though Jones, with the observant eye of his class, had noticed that near the ears his cheeks and his forehead as well were wet with perspiration. But now abruptly he grew unaccountably excited, and his speech displayed a feverish animation. His face had lost its scarlet; it had grown very white; and it seemed to the novelist that in some manner which he could not explain to himself it had taken on a not unfamiliar aspect. “H’m!” he reflected, “it’s odd. I know I never saw the man before, and I am sure that I do not particularly care ever to see him again. Leigh ought to have more sense than to bring an orangutan even into such a club as the Smallpox. Besides, what does he mean by boring everyone to death? By gad, I believe he has put Leigh to sleep. It’s worse than a play.” But still he made no effort to move. In spite of himself, he felt vaguely fascinated, and, though he declined to admit it, a trifle ill at ease.

“I took up the photograph,” Mr. Fairbanks continued, “and while I was examining it, the Russian came back. In his hand he held a checkbook. ‘That’s the grand duke himself,’ he said. ‘He will stop in here presently on his way out. There will be two or three members of the suite with him; and, that you may recognize his Highness at once, take a good look at the picture. When he comes in you must do this way: button your coat, please; thanks: now stand anywhere you like and make a low bow. Let me see you make one. Bravo! that is splendid. Only—how shall I say?—do not let your arms hang in that fashion. The grand duke might think you had dropped something and were stooping to pick it up. However, that is a minor matter. It may be that he won’t see you at all. But of all things remember this: under no circumstances must you speak to him unless he first addresses you, and then you must merely answer his question. In other words, do not, I pray you, try to engage him in conversation.’ ‘Does he speak English?’ I asked. I couldn’t help it. I was getting nervous. ‘Now let us have the rubies,’ he said. I took the box out of my breast-pocket and handed it to him. He opened it, drew the cotton aside, and ran his fingers lovingly over the gems. ‘Yes,’ he said, ‘they will do.’ Then he closed the box again, and put it in the drawer of the table at which he had taken a seat. ‘If,’ he continued, ‘his Highness is satisfied, I will draw a draft for you, and Count Béziatnikoff will sign it. The count,’ he went on to say, ‘is the keeper of the Privy Purse. The draft itself is on the London Rothschilds, but they will cash it at Belmont’s.’ I did not quite like that arrangement: it did not seem entirely businesslike. ‘Your Excellency,’ I said, ‘it is the custom here to have checks for large amounts certified before they are offered in payment.’ But I had to explain what certification meant before he understood me. ‘That is nothing,’ he said, ‘that is nothing. If his Highness is pleased, we will go to Belmont’s together, or, if you prefer, we will sit here over a Sam Ward and let one of the hotel-clerks go to the bank in our stead.’ There seemed to me nothing objectionable in that suggestion; for, after all, I could not exact of any one, however grand-ducal he might be, to go about with a hundred and ten thousand dollars in his waistcoat.”

“Or in his trousers either.”

“Or in his trousers either, as you very properly put it. Now, Mr. Jones—Mr. Leigh, look at me; Colonel Barker—colonel—I am coming to the point. Where’s that waiter? Gentlemen, see here; watch that man there—watch Jones. Don’t take your eyes off Mr. Jones, but listen, all of you, to what I say. Mr. Leigh, you are looking at me: look at your friend, colonel, I insist. Mr. Jones, you, if you care to, can look at me. Now, gentlemen, now—”

“Have you got a camera concealed about your person?”

“No, I have not, but I have something that came from one. You wait a minute, and I’ll show it to you. I’ll show it to you all. Where did I leave off?”

“In his waistcoat-pocket.”

“Thank you: so I did. Well, gentlemen, we sat there talking as pleasantly as you please. The Russian joked a bit, and said that he wanted a certified check from me—the check for his commission, you remember—and presently he got up and said he would see what was delaying his Highness. So I sat awhile, twirling my thumbs. Five minutes passed, ten minutes passed. I looked at my watch: it was almost half-past two. That draft, I told myself, won’t be cashed today. I went to the window and looked out. I went to the door: there was no one in the hall but a chambermaid. I went back to my seat, and then, moved by my own uneasiness, I opened the drawer of the table. The box was gone! I took the drawer out. It was one that extended the entire width of the table: the further end of it had been cut off. I looked down and in through the place from which I had taken it. I could see into the next room! I pulled the table to one side, and there, just where the drawer had touched the door against which it had stood, was an oblong opening cut through the woodwork of the door itself. I was downstairs in an instant. Gentlemen, the grand duke had gone to Philadelphia that very morning. No such person as Prince Zaroguine lodged in the hotel. The clerk came upstairs with me. ‘That room,’ he said, ‘is occupied by a Frenchman, and the adjoining room belongs to a man who registered from Boston. Why, that’s his picture there!’ he exclaimed, pointing to the picture of the grand duke. ‘I did not even know that they were acquainted. But they will be back; they have left their things; they haven’t even paid their bills.’ I did not wait for their return: if I had I might be waiting still. But I took the photograph, and down to Inspector Byrnes I posted. ‘That,’ said he, ‘that is the picture of one of the ’cutest rogues in the land. He has as many names as the Czar of Russia himself.’ And the original of that picture—Gentlemen, here—Mr. Leigh, here—colonel, here is the picture itself. I have kept it with me ever since. The original of that picture sits before you. Hold on to him, colonel. Jones, if you move I’ll put a bullet through you. Mr. Leigh, do you ring for the police. Hold him, colonel. Disgorge, you scoundrel, disgorge! I have got you at last!” And then, before the astonished gaze of Alphabet Jones, Colonel Barker faded in a mist, Mr. Fairbanks lost his rotundity, his black coat changed to a blue swallowtail with brass buttons, he grew twenty years younger, and, so far from being violent, he seemed rather apologetic than otherwise.

“It’s six o’clock, sir,” he said. “Will you order anything before the bar closes?”

Alphabet blinked his eyes. He was lying in a cramped position on the sofa. He was uncomfortable and very hot. He pulled himself together and looked around. Save for the waiter and himself, the room was deserted.

“Is there any baccarat going on upstairs?” he asked.

“No, sir; the gentlemen are just going away.”

“Well, well,” he mused, “that was vivid. H’m! I’ll work it up as an actual occurrence and send it on to the Interstate: it will be good for the two hundred and fifty which I meant to make at baccarat.—I say, waiter, get me a Remsen cooler, please.”